1 Samuel 21

1 Then David came to Nob to Ahimelech the priest. Ahimelech came to meet David trembling, and said to him, “Why are you alone, and no man with you?” 2 David said to Ahimelech the priest, “The king has commanded me to do something, and has said to me, ‘Let no one know anything about the business about which I send you, and what I have commanded you. I have sent the young men to a certain place.’ 3 Now therefore what is under your hand? Please give me five loaves of bread in my hand, or whatever is available.”

4 The priest answered David, and said, “I have no common bread, but there is holy bread; if only the young men have kept themselves from women.”

5 David answered the priest, and said to him, “Truly, women have been kept from us as usual these three days. When I came out, the vessels of the young men were holy, though it was only a common journey. How much more then today shall their vessels be holy?” 6 So the priest gave him holy bread; for there was no bread there but the show bread that was taken from before Yahweh, to put hot bread in the day when it was taken away.

7 Now a certain man of the servants of Saul was there that day, detained before Yahweh; and his name was Doeg the Edomite, the best of the herdsmen who belonged to Saul. 8 David said to Ahimelech, “Isn’t there here under your hand spear or sword? For I have neither brought my sword nor my weapons with me, because the king’s business required haste.”

9 The priest said, “Behold, the sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom you killed in the valley of Elah, is here wrapped in a cloth behind the ephod. If you would like to take that, take it; for there is no other except that here.”

David said, “There is none like that. Give it to me.”

10 David arose, and fled that day for fear of Saul, and went to Achish the king of Gath. 11 The servants of Achish said to him, “Isn’t this David the king of the land? Didn’t they sing to one another about him in dances, saying,

‘Saul has slain his thousands,

and David his ten thousands?’”

12 David laid up these words in his heart, and was very afraid of Achish the king of Gath. 13 He changed his behavior before them, and pretended to be insane in their hands, and scribbled on the doors of the gate, and let his spittle fall down on his beard. 14 Then Achish said to his servants, “Look, you see the man is insane. Why then have you brought him to me? 15 Do I lack madmen, that you have brought this fellow to play the madman in my presence? Should this fellow come into my house?”

1 Samuel 22

1 David therefore departed from there, and escaped to the cave of Adullam. When his brothers and all his father’s house heard it, they went down there to him. 2 Everyone who was in distress, everyone who was in debt, and everyone who was discontented, gathered themselves to him; and he became captain over them. There were with him about four hundred men. 3 David went from there to Mizpeh of Moab, and he said to the king of Moab, “Please let my father and my mother come out with you, until I know what God will do for me.” 4 He brought them before the king of Moab; and they lived with him all the time that David was in the stronghold. 5 The prophet Gad said to David, “Don’t stay in the stronghold. Depart, and go into the land of Judah.”

Then David departed, and came into the forest of Hereth. 6 Saul heard that David was discovered, with the men who were with him. Now Saul was sitting in Gibeah, under the tamarisk tree in Ramah, with his spear in his hand, and all his servants were standing around him. 7 Saul said to his servants who stood around him, “Hear now, you Benjamites! Will the son of Jesse give everyone of you fields and vineyards? Will he make you all captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, 8 that all of you have conspired against me, and there is no one who discloses to me when my son makes a treaty with the son of Jesse, and there is none of you who is sorry for me, or discloses to me that my son has stirred up my servant against me, to lie in wait, as it is today?”

9 Then Doeg the Edomite, who stood by the servants of Saul, answered and said, “I saw the son of Jesse coming to Nob, to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub. 10 He inquired of Yahweh for him, gave him food, and gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine.”

11 Then the king sent to call Ahimelech the priest, the son of Ahitub, and all his father’s house, the priests who were in Nob; and they all came to the king. 12 Saul said, “Hear now, you son of Ahitub.”

He answered, “Here I am, my lord.”

13 Saul said to him, “Why have you conspired against me, you and the son of Jesse, in that you have given him bread, and a sword, and have inquired of God for him, that he should rise against me, to lie in wait, as it is today?”

14 Then Ahimelech answered the king, and said, “Who among all your servants is so faithful as David, who is the king’s son-in-law, and is taken into your council, and is honorable in your house? 15 Have I today begun to inquire of God for him? Be it far from me! Don’t let the king impute anything to his servant, nor to all the house of my father; for your servant knows nothing of all this, less or more.”

16 The king said, “You shall surely die, Ahimelech, you, and all your father’s house.” 17 The king said to the guard who stood about him, “Turn, and kill the priests of Yahweh; because their hand also is with David, and because they knew that he fled, and didn’t disclose it to me.” But the servants of the king wouldn’t put out their hand to fall on the priests of Yahweh.

18 The king said to Doeg, “Turn and attack the priests!”

Doeg the Edomite turned, and he attacked the priests, and he killed on that day eighty-five people who wore a linen ephod. 19 He struck Nob, the city of the priests, with the edge of the sword, both men and women, children and nursing babies, and cattle and donkeys and sheep, with the edge of the sword. 20 One of the sons of Ahimelech, the son of Ahitub, named Abiathar, escaped, and fled after David. 21 Abiathar told David that Saul had slain Yahweh’s priests.

22 David said to Abiathar, “I knew on that day, when Doeg the Edomite was there, that he would surely tell Saul. I am responsible for the death of all the persons of your father’s house. 23 Stay with me. Don’t be afraid, for he who seeks my life seeks your life. For you will be safe with me.”

1 Samuel 23

1 David was told, “Behold, the Philistines are fighting against Keilah, and are robbing the threshing floors.”

2 Therefore David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Shall I go and strike these Philistines?”

Yahweh said to David, “Go strike the Philistines, and save Keilah.”

3 David’s men said to him, “Behold, we are afraid here in Judah. How much more then if we go to Keilah against the armies of the Philistines?”

4 Then David inquired of Yahweh yet again. Yahweh answered him, and said, “Arise, go down to Keilah; for I will deliver the Philistines into your hand.”

5 David and his men went to Keilah, and fought with the Philistines, and brought away their livestock, and killed them with a great slaughter. So David saved the inhabitants of Keilah. 6 When Abiathar the son of Ahimelech fled to David to Keilah, he came down with an ephod in his hand.

7 Saul was told that David had come to Keilah. Saul said, “God has delivered him into my hand; for he is shut in by entering into a town that has gates and bars.” 8 Saul summoned all the people to war, to go down to Keilah, to besiege David and his men. 9 David knew that Saul was devising mischief against him; and he said to Abiathar the priest, “Bring the ephod here.” 10 Then David said, “O Yahweh, the God of Israel, your servant has surely heard that Saul seeks to come to Keilah, to destroy the city for my sake. 11 Will the men of Keilah deliver me up into his hand? Will Saul come down, as your servant has heard? Yahweh, the God of Israel, I beg you, tell your servant.”

Yahweh said, “He will come down.”

12 Then David said, “Will the men of Keilah deliver me and my men into the hand of Saul?”

Yahweh said, “They will deliver you up.”

13 Then David and his men, who were about six hundred, arose and departed out of Keilah, and went wherever they could go. Saul was told that David was escaped from Keilah; and he gave up going there. 14 David stayed in the wilderness in the strongholds, and remained in the hill country in the wilderness of Ziph. Saul sought him every day, but God didn’t deliver him into his hand. 15 David saw that Saul had come out to seek his life. David was in the wilderness of Ziph in the wood.

16 Jonathan, Saul’s son, arose, and went to David into the woods, and strengthened his hand in God. 17 He said to him, “Don’t be afraid; for the hand of Saul my father won’t find you; and you will be king over Israel, and I will be next to you; and Saul my father knows that also.” 18 They both made a covenant before Yahweh. Then David stayed in the woods, and Jonathan went to his house.

19 Then the Ziphites came up to Saul to Gibeah, saying, “Doesn’t David hide himself with us in the strongholds in the woods, in the hill of Hachilah, which is on the south of the desert? 20 Now therefore, O king, come down. According to all the desire of your soul to come down; and our part will be to deliver him up into the king’s hand.”

21 Saul said, “You are blessed by Yahweh; for you have had compassion on me. 22 Please go make yet more sure, and know and see his place where his haunt is, and who has seen him there; for I have been told that he deals very crafty. 23 See therefore, and take knowledge of all the lurking places where he hides himself, and come again to me with certainty, and I will go with you. It shall happen, if he is in the land, that I will search him out among all the thousands of Judah.”

24 They arose, and went to Ziph before Saul: but David and his men were in the wilderness of Maon, in the Arabah on the south of the desert. 25 Saul and his men went to seek him. When David was told, he went down to the rock, and stayed in the wilderness of Maon. When Saul heard that, he pursued David in the wilderness of Maon. 26 Saul went on this side of the mountain, and David and his men on that side of the mountain; and David hurried to get away for fear of Saul; for Saul and his men surrounded David and his men to take them. 27 But a messenger came to Saul, saying, “Hurry and come; for the Philistines have made a raid on the land!” 28 So Saul returned from pursuing David, and went against the Philistines. Therefore they called that place Sela Hammahlekoth.[*]

29 David went up from there, and lived in the strongholds of En Gedi.

“Sela Hammahlekoth” means “rock of parting”.

1 Samuel 24

1 When Saul had returned from following the Philistines, he was told, “Behold, David is in the wilderness of En Gedi.” 2 Then Saul took three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and went to seek David and his men on the rocks of the wild goats. 3 He came to the sheep pens by the way, where there was a cave; and Saul went in to relieve himself. Now David and his men were staying in the innermost parts of the cave. 4 David’s men said to him, “Behold, the day of which Yahweh said to you, ‘Behold, I will deliver your enemy into your hand, and you shall do to him as it shall seem good to you.’” Then David arose, and cut off the skirt of Saul’s robe secretly. 5 Afterward, David’s heart struck him, because he had cut off Saul’s skirt. 6 He said to his men, “Yahweh forbid that I should do this thing to my lord, Yahweh’s anointed, to stretch out my hand against him, since he is Yahweh’s anointed.” 7 So David checked his men with these words, and didn’t allow them to rise against Saul. Saul rose up out of the cave, and went on his way. 8 David also arose afterward, and went out of the cave, and cried after Saul, saying, “My lord the king!”

When Saul looked behind him, David bowed with his face to the earth, and showed respect. 9 David said to Saul, “Why do you listen to men’s words, saying, ‘Behold, David seeks to harm you?’ 10 Behold, today your eyes have seen how Yahweh had delivered you today into my hand in the cave. Some urged me to kill you; but I spared you; and I said, I will not stretch out my hand against my lord; for he is Yahweh’s anointed. 11 Moreover, my father, behold, yes, see the skirt of your robe in my hand; for in that I cut off the skirt of your robe, and didn’t kill you, know and see that there is neither evil nor disobedience in my hand, and I have not sinned against you, though you hunt for my life to take it. 12 May Yahweh judge between me and you, and may Yahweh avenge me of you; but my hand will not be on you. 13 As the proverb of the ancients says, ‘Out of the wicked comes wickedness;’ but my hand will not be on you. 14 Against whom has the king of Israel come out? Whom do you pursue? A dead dog? A flea? 15 May Yahweh therefore be judge, and give sentence between me and you, and see, and plead my cause, and deliver me out of your hand.”

16 It came to pass, when David had finished speaking these words to Saul, that Saul said, “Is that your voice, my son David?” Saul lifted up his voice, and wept. 17 He said to David, “You are more righteous than I; for you have done good to me, whereas I have done evil to you. 18 You have declared today how you have dealt well with me, because when Yahweh had delivered me up into your hand, you didn’t kill me. 19 For if a man finds his enemy, will he let him go away unharmed? Therefore may Yahweh reward you good for that which you have done to me today. 20 Now, behold, I know that you will surely be king, and that the kingdom of Israel will be established in your hand. 21 Swear now therefore to me by Yahweh, that you will not cut off my offspring[*] after me, and that you will not destroy my name out of my father’s house.”

22 David swore to Saul. Saul went home, but David and his men went up to the stronghold.

or, seed

1 Samuel 25

1 Samuel died; and all Israel gathered themselves together, and mourned for him, and buried him at his house at Ramah.

Then David arose, and went down to the wilderness of Paran. 2 There was a man in Maon, whose possessions were in Carmel; and the man was very great. He had three thousand sheep and a thousand goats; and he was shearing his sheep in Carmel. 3 Now the name of the man was Nabal; and the name of his wife Abigail. This woman was intelligent and had a beautiful face; but the man was surly and evil in his doings. He was of the house of Caleb. 4 David heard in the wilderness that Nabal was shearing his sheep. 5 David sent ten young men, and David said to the young men, “Go up to Carmel, and go to Nabal, and greet him in my name. 6 Tell him, ‘Long life to you! Peace be to you, and peace be to your house, and peace be to all that you have. 7 Now I have heard that you have shearers. Your shepherds have now been with us, and we didn’t harm them, neither was there anything missing from them, all the while they were in Carmel. 8 Ask your young men, and they will tell you. Therefore let the young men find favor in your eyes; for we come on a good day. Please give whatever comes to your hand, to your servants, and to your son David.’”

9 When David’s young men came, they spoke to Nabal all those words in the name of David, and waited.

10 Nabal answered David’s servants, and said, “Who is David? Who is the son of Jesse? There are many servants who break away from their masters these days. 11 Shall I then take my bread, my water, and my meat that I have killed for my shearers, and give it to men who I don’t know where they come from?”

12 So David’s young men turned on their way, and went back, and came and told him all these words.

13 David said to his men, “Every man put on his sword!”

Every man put on his sword. David also put on his sword. About four hundred men followed David, and two hundred stayed by the baggage. 14 But one of the young men told Abigail, Nabal’s wife, saying, “Behold, David sent messengers out of the wilderness to Greet our master; and he insulted them. 15 But the men were very good to us, and we were not harmed, and we didn’t miss anything, as long as we went with them, when we were in the fields. 16 They were a wall to us both by night and by day, all the while we were with them keeping the sheep. 17 Now therefore know and consider what you will do; for evil is determined against our master, and against all his house; for he is such a worthless fellow that one can’t speak to him.”

18 Then Abigail hurried and took two hundred loaves of bread, two bottles of wine, five sheep ready dressed, five seahs[*] of parched grain, one hundred clusters of raisins, and two hundred cakes of figs, and laid them on donkeys. 19 She said to her young men, “Go on before me. Behold, I am coming after you.” But she didn’t tell her husband, Nabal. 20 As she rode on her donkey, and came down by the covert of the mountain, that behold, David and his men came down toward her, and she met them.

21 Now David had said, “Surely in vain I have kept all that this fellow has in the wilderness, so that nothing was missed of all that pertained to him. He has returned me evil for good. 22 God do so to the enemies of David, and more also, if I leave of all that belongs to him by the morning light so much as one who urinates on a wall.”[*]

23 When Abigail saw David, she hurried and got off of her donkey, and fell before David on her face, and bowed herself to the ground. 24 She fell at his feet, and said, “On me, my lord, on me be the blame! Please let your servant speak in your ears. Hear the words of your servant. 25 Please don’t let my lord pay attention to this worthless fellow, Nabal; for as his name is, so is he. Nabal[*] is his name, and folly is with him; but I, your servant, didn’t see my lord’s young men, whom you sent. 26 Now therefore, my lord, as Yahweh lives, and as your soul lives, since Yahweh has withheld you from blood guiltiness, and from avenging yourself with your own hand, now therefore let your enemies, and those who seek evil to my lord, be as Nabal. 27 Now this present which your servant has brought to my lord, let it be given to the young men who follow my lord. 28 Please forgive the trespass of your servant. For Yahweh will certainly make my lord a sure house, because my lord fights Yahweh’s battles. Evil will not be found in you all your days. 29 Though men may rise up to pursue you, and to seek your soul, yet the soul of my lord will be bound in the bundle of life with Yahweh your God. He will sling out the souls of your enemies, as from the hollow of a sling. 30 It will come to pass, when Yahweh has done to my lord according to all the good that he has spoken concerning you, and has appointed you prince over Israel, 31 that this shall be no grief to you, nor offense of heart to my lord, either that you have shed blood without cause, or that my lord has avenged himself. When Yahweh has dealt well with my lord, then remember your servant.”

32 David said to Abigail, “Blessed is Yahweh, the God of Israel, who sent you today to meet me! 33 Blessed is your discretion, and blessed are you, who have kept me today from blood guiltiness, and from avenging myself with my own hand. 34 For indeed, as Yahweh, the God of Israel, lives, who has withheld me from harming you, unless you had hurried and come to meet me, surely there wouldn’t have been left to Nabal by the morning light so much as one who urinates on a wall.”[*]

35 So David received from her hand that which she had brought him. Then he said to her, “Go up in peace to your house. Behold, I have listened to your voice, and have granted your request.”

36 Abigail came to Nabal; and behold, he held a feast in his house, like the feast of a king. Nabal’s heart was merry within him, for he was very drunk. Therefore she told him nothing, until the morning light. 37 In the morning, when the wine had gone out of Nabal, his wife told him these things, and his heart died within him, and he became as a stone. 38 About ten days later, Yahweh struck Nabal, so that he died. 39 When David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, “Blessed is Yahweh, who has pleaded the cause of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and has kept back his servant from evil. Yahweh has returned the evildoing of Nabal on his own head.” David sent and spoke concerning Abigail, to take her to himself as wife. 40 When David’s servants had come to Abigail to Carmel, they spoke to her, saying, “David has sent us to you, to take you to him as wife.”

41 She arose, and bowed herself with her face to the earth, and said, “Behold, your servant is a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord.” 42 Abigail hurried, and arose, and rode on a donkey, with five ladies of hers who followed her; and she went after the messengers of David, and became his wife. 43 David also took Ahinoam of Jezreel; and they both became his wives. 44 Now Saul had given Michal his daughter, David’s wife, to Palti the son of Laish, who was of Gallim.

1 seah is about 7 liters or 1.9 gallons or 0.8 pecks

or, male.

“Nabal” means “foolish”.

or, one male.

1 Samuel 26

1 The Ziphites came to Saul to Gibeah, saying, “Doesn’t David hide himself in the hill of Hachilah, which is before the desert?” 2 Then Saul arose, and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, having three thousand chosen men of Israel with him, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph. 3 Saul encamped in the hill of Hachilah, which is before the desert, by the way. But David stayed in the wilderness, and he saw that Saul came after him into the wilderness. 4 David therefore sent out spies, and understood that Saul had certainly come. 5 Then David arose, and came to the place where Saul had encamped; and David saw the place where Saul lay, with Abner the son of Ner, the captain of his army. Saul lay within the place of the wagons, and the people were encamped around him.

6 Then David answered and said to Ahimelech the Hittite, and to Abishai the son of Zeruiah, brother of Joab, saying, “Who will go down with me to Saul to the camp?”

Abishai said, “I will go down with you.” 7 So David and Abishai came to the people by night: and, behold, Saul lay sleeping within the place of the wagons, with his spear stuck in the ground at his head; and Abner and the people lay around him. 8 Then Abishai said to David, “God has delivered up your enemy into your hand today. Now therefore please let me strike him with the spear to the earth at one stroke, and I will not strike him the second time.”

9 David said to Abishai, “Don’t destroy him; for who can stretch out his hand against Yahweh’s anointed, and be guiltless?” 10 David said, “As Yahweh lives, Yahweh will strike him; or his day shall come to die; or he shall go down into battle and perish. 11 Yahweh forbid that I should stretch out my hand against Yahweh’s anointed; but now please take the spear that is at his head, and the jar of water, and let us go.”

12 So David took the spear and the jar of water from Saul’s head; and they went away: and no man saw it, or knew it, nor did any awake; for they were all asleep, because a deep sleep from Yahweh was fallen on them. 13 Then David went over to the other side, and stood on the top of the mountain afar off; a great space being between them; 14 and David cried to the people, and to Abner the son of Ner, saying, “Don’t you answer, Abner?”

Then Abner answered, “Who are you who cries to the king?”

15 David said to Abner, “Aren’t you a man? Who is like you in Israel? Why then have you not kept watch over your lord, the king? For one of the people came in to destroy the king your lord. 16 This thing isn’t good that you have done. As Yahweh lives, you are worthy to die, because you have not kept watch over your lord, Yahweh’s anointed. Now see where the king’s spear is, and the jar of water that was at his head.”

17 Saul knew David’s voice, and said, “Is this your voice, my son David?”

David said, “It is my voice, my lord, O king.” 18 He said, “Why does my lord pursue his servant? For what have I done? What evil is in my hand? 19 Now therefore, please let my lord the king hear the words of his servant. If it is so that Yahweh has stirred you up against me, let him accept an offering. But if it is the children of men, they are cursed before Yahweh; for they have driven me out today that I shouldn’t cling to Yahweh’s inheritance, saying, ‘Go, serve other gods!’ 20 Now therefore, don’t let my blood fall to the earth away from the presence of Yahweh; for the king of Israel has come out to seek a flea, as when one hunts a partridge in the mountains.”

21 Then Saul said, “I have sinned. Return, my son David; for I will no more do you harm, because my life was precious in your eyes today. Behold, I have played the fool, and have erred exceedingly.”

22 David answered, “Behold the spear, O king! Then let one of the young men come over and get it. 23 Yahweh will render to every man his righteousness and his faithfulness; because Yahweh delivered you into my hand today, and I wouldn’t stretch out my hand against Yahweh’s anointed. 24 Behold, as your life was respected today in my eyes, so let my life be respected in Yahweh’s eyes, and let him deliver me out of all oppression.”

25 Then Saul said to David, “You are blessed, my son David. You will both do mightily, and will surely prevail.” So David went his way, and Saul returned to his place.

1 Samuel 27

1 David said in his heart, “I will now perish one day by the hand of Saul. There is nothing better for me than that I should escape into the land of the Philistines; and Saul will despair of me, to seek me any more in all the borders of Israel. So shall I escape out of his hand.” 2 David arose, and passed over, he and the six hundred men who were with him, to Achish the son of Maoch, king of Gath. 3 David lived with Achish at Gath, he and his men, every man with his household, even David with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the Carmelitess, Nabal’s wife. 4 Saul was told that David had fled to Gath: and he sought no more again for him. 5 David said to Achish, “If now I have found favor in your eyes, let them give me a place in one of the cities in the country, that I may dwell there. For why should your servant dwell in the royal city with you?” 6 Then Achish gave him Ziklag that day: therefore Ziklag belongs to the kings of Judah to this day. 7 The number of the days that David lived in the country of the Philistines was a full year and four months. 8 David and his men went up and raided the Geshurites, the Girzites, and the Amalekites; for those were the inhabitants of the land, who were of old, on the way to Shur, even to the land of Egypt. 9 David struck the land, and saved no man or woman alive, and took away the sheep, the cattle, the donkeys, the camels, and the clothing. Then he returned, and came to Achish.

10 Achish said, “Against whom have you made a raid today?”

David said, “Against the South of Judah, against the South of the Jerahmeelites, and against the South of the Kenites.” 11 David saved neither man nor woman alive, to bring them to Gath, saying, “Lest they should tell about us, saying, ‘David did this, and this has been his way all the time he has lived in the country of the Philistines.’”

12 Achish believed David, saying, “He has made his people Israel utterly to abhor him. Therefore he will be my servant forever.”

1 Samuel 28

1 In those days, the Philistines gathered their armies together for warfare, to fight with Israel. Achish said to David, “Know assuredly that you will go out with me in the army, you and your men.”

2 David said to Achish, “Therefore you will know what your servant can do.”

Achish said to David, “Therefore I will make you my bodyguard forever.”

3 Now Samuel was dead, and all Israel had mourned for him, and buried him in Ramah, even in his own city. Saul had put away those who had familiar spirits the wizards, out of the land. 4 The Philistines gathered themselves together, and came and encamped in Shunem; and Saul gathered all Israel together, and they encamped in Gilboa. 5 When Saul saw the army of the Philistines, he was afraid, and his heart trembled greatly. 6 When Saul inquired of Yahweh, Yahweh didn’t answer him by dreams, by Urim, or by prophets. 7 Then Saul said to his servants, “Seek for me a woman who has a familiar spirit, that I may go to her, and inquire of her.”

His servants said to him, “Behold, there is a woman who has a familiar spirit at Endor.”

8 Saul disguised himself and put on other clothing, and went, he and two men with him, and they came to the woman by night. Then he said, “Please consult for me by the familiar spirit, and bring me up whomever I shall name to you.”

9 The woman said to him, “Behold, you know what Saul has done, how he has cut off those who have familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land. Why then do you lay a snare for my life, to cause me to die?”

10 Saul swore to her by Yahweh, saying, “As Yahweh lives, no punishment will happen to you for this thing.”

11 Then the woman said, “Whom shall I bring up to you?”

He said, “Bring Samuel up for me.”

12 When the woman saw Samuel, she cried with a loud voice; and the woman spoke to Saul, saying, “Why have you deceived me? For you are Saul!”

13 The king said to her, “Don’t be afraid! What do you see?”

The woman said to Saul, “I see a god coming up out of the earth.”

14 He said to her, “What does he look like?”

She said, “An old man comes up. He is covered with a robe.” Saul perceived that it was Samuel, and he bowed with his face to the ground, and showed respect.

15 Samuel said to Saul, “Why have you disturbed me, to bring me up?”

Saul answered, “I am very distressed; for the Philistines make war against me, and God has departed from me, and answers me no more, by prophets, or by dreams. Therefore I have called you, that you may make known to me what I shall do.”

16 Samuel said, “Why then do you ask me, since Yahweh has departed from you and has become your adversary? 17 Yahweh has done to you as he spoke by me. Yahweh has torn the kingdom out of your hand, and given it to your neighbor, even to David. 18 Because you didn’t obey Yahweh’s voice, and didn’t execute his fierce wrath on Amalek, therefore Yahweh has done this thing to you today. 19 Moreover Yahweh will deliver Israel also with you into the hand of the Philistines; and tomorrow you and your sons will be with me. Yahweh will deliver the army of Israel also into the hand of the Philistines.”

20 Then Saul fell immediately his full length on the earth, and was terrified, because of Samuel’s words. There was no strength in him; for he had eaten no bread all day long or all night long.

21 The woman came to Saul, and saw that he was very troubled, and said to him, “Behold, your servant has listened to your voice, and I have put my life in my hand, and have listened to your words which you spoke to me. 22 Now therefore, please listen also to the voice of your servant, and let me set a morsel of bread before you. Eat, that you may have strength, when you go on your way.”

23 But he refused, and said, “I will not eat.” But his servants, together with the woman, constrained him; and he listened to their voice. So he arose from the earth and sat on the bed. 24 The woman had a fattened calf in the house. She hurried and killed it; and she took flour, and kneaded it, and baked unleavened bread of it. 25 She brought it before Saul, and before his servants; and they ate. Then they rose up, and went away that night.

1 Samuel 29

1 Now the Philistines gathered together all their armies to Aphek; and the Israelites encamped by the spring which is in Jezreel. 2 The lords of the Philistines passed on by hundreds and by thousands; and David and his men passed on in the rear with Achish.

3 Then the princes of the Philistines said, “What about these Hebrews?”

Achish said to the princes of the Philistines, “Isn’t this David, the servant of Saul the king of Israel, who has been with me these days, or rather these years, and I have found no fault in him since he fell away to today?”

4 But the princes of the Philistines were angry with him; and the princes of the Philistines said to him, “Make the man return, that he may go back to his place where you have appointed him, and let him not go down with us to battle, lest in the battle he become an adversary to us. For with what should this fellow reconcile himself to his lord? Should it not be with the heads of these men? 5 Isn’t this David, of whom people sang to one another in dances, saying,

‘Saul has slain his thousands,

and David his ten thousands?’”

6 Then Achish called David, and said to him, “As Yahweh lives, you have been upright, and your going out and your coming in with me in the army is good in my sight; for I have not found evil in you since the day of your coming to me to this day. Nevertheless, the lords don’t favor you. 7 Therefore now return, and go in peace, that you not displease the lords of the Philistines.”

8 David said to Achish, “But what have I done? What have you found in your servant so long as I have been before you to this day, that I may not go and fight against the enemies of my lord the king?”

9 Achish answered David, “I know that you are good in my sight, as an angel of God. Notwithstanding the princes of the Philistines have said, ‘He shall not go up with us to the battle.’ 10 Therefore now rise up early in the morning with the servants of your lord who have come with you; and as soon as you are up early in the morning, and have light, depart.”

11 So David rose up early, he and his men, to depart in the morning, to return into the land of the Philistines, and the Philistines went up to Jezreel.

1 Samuel 30

1 When David and his men had come to Ziklag on the third day, the Amalekites had made a raid on the South, and on Ziklag, and had struck Ziklag, and burned it with fire, 2 and had taken captive the women and all who were in it, both small and great. They didn’t kill any, but carried them off, and went their way. 3 When David and his men came to the city, behold, it was burned with fire; and their wives, their sons, and their daughters were taken captive. 4 Then David and the people who were with him lifted up their voice and wept until they had no more power to weep. 5 David’s two wives were taken captive, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. 6 David was greatly distressed; for the people spoke of stoning him, because the souls of all the people were grieved, every man for his sons and for his daughters; but David strengthened himself in Yahweh his God. 7 David said to Abiathar the priest, the son of Ahimelech, “Please bring the ephod here to me.”

Abiathar brought the ephod to David. 8 David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “If I pursue after this troop, will I overtake them?”

He answered him, “Pursue; for you will surely overtake them, and will without fail recover all.”

9 So David went, he and the six hundred men who were with him, and came to the brook Besor, where those who were left behind stayed. 10 But David pursued, he and four hundred men; for two hundred stayed behind, who were so faint that they couldn’t go over the brook Besor. 11 They found an Egyptian in the field, and brought him to David, and gave him bread, and he ate; and they gave him water to drink. 12 They gave him a piece of a cake of figs, and two clusters of raisins. When he had eaten, his spirit came again to him; for he had eaten no bread, and drank no water for three days and three nights. 13 David asked him, “To whom do you belong? Where are you from?”

He said, “I am a young man of Egypt, servant to an Amalekite; and my master left me, because three days ago I got sick. 14 We made a raid on the South of the Cherethites, and on that which belongs to Judah, and on the South of Caleb; and we burned Ziklag with fire.”

15 David said to him, “Will you bring me down to this troop?”

He said, “Swear to me by God that you will not kill me and not deliver me up into the hands of my master, and I will bring you down to this troop.”

16 When he had brought him down, behold, they were spread around over all the ground, eating, drinking, and dancing, because of all the great plunder that they had taken out of the land of the Philistines, and out of the land of Judah. 17 David struck them from the twilight even to the evening of the next day. Not a man of them escaped from there, except four hundred young men, who rode on camels and fled. 18 David recovered all that the Amalekites had taken; and David rescued his two wives. 19 There was nothing lacking to them, neither small nor great, neither sons nor daughters, neither plunder, nor anything that they had taken to them. David brought back all. 20 David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drove before those other livestock, and said, “This is David’s plunder.”

21 David came to the two hundred men, who were so faint that they could not follow David, whom also they had made to stay at the brook Besor; and they went out to meet David, and to meet the people who were with him. When David came near to the people, he greeted them. 22 Then all the wicked men and base fellows, of those who went with David, answered and said, “Because they didn’t go with us, we will not give them anything of the plunder that we have recovered, except to every man his wife and his children, that he may lead them away, and depart.”

23 Then David said, “Do not do so, my brothers, with that which Yahweh has given to us, who has preserved us, and delivered the troop that came against us into our hand. 24 Who will listen to you in this matter? For as his share is who goes down to the battle, so shall his share be who stays with the baggage. They shall share alike.” 25 It was so from that day forward, that he made it a statute and an ordinance for Israel to this day. 26 When David came to Ziklag, he sent some of the plunder to the elders of Judah, even to his friends, saying, “Behold, a present for you from the plunder of Yahweh’s enemies.” 27 He sent it to those who were in Bethel, to those who were in Ramoth of the South, to those who were in Jattir, 28 to those who were in Aroer, to those who were in Siphmoth, to those who were in Eshtemoa, 29 to those who were in Racal, to those who were in the cities of the Jerahmeelites, to those who were in the cities of the Kenites, 30 to those who were in Hormah, to those who were in Borashan, to those who were in Athach, 31 to those who were in Hebron, and to all the places where David himself and his men used to stay.

1 Samuel 31

1 Now the Philistines fought against Israel; and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain on Mount Gilboa. 2 The Philistines overtook Saul and on his sons; and the Philistines killed Jonathan, Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul. 3 The battle went hard against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was greatly distressed by reason of the archers. 4 Then Saul said to his armor bearer, “Draw your sword, and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and thrust me through, and abuse me!” But his armor bearer would not; for he was terrified. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell on it. 5 When his armor bearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell on his sword, and died with him. 6 So Saul died, and his three sons, and his armor bearer, and all his men, that same day together.

7 When the men of Israel who were on the other side of the valley, and those who were beyond the Jordan, saw that the men of Israel fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they abandoned the cities and fled; and the Philistines came and lived in them. 8 On the next day, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, they found Saul and his three sons fallen on Mount Gilboa. 9 They cut off his head, stripped off his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines all around, to carry the news to the house of their idols, and to the people. 10 They put his armor in the house of the Ashtaroth, and they fastened his body to the wall of Beth Shan. 11 When the inhabitants of Jabesh Gilead heard what the Philistines had done to Saul, 12 all the valiant men arose, went all night, and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons from the wall of Beth Shan; and they came to Jabesh, and burned them there. 13 They took their bones and buried them under the tamarisk[*] tree in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.

or, salt cedar

2 Samuel 1

1 After the death of Saul, when David had returned from the slaughter of the Amalekites, and David had stayed two days in Ziklag; 2 on the third day, behold,[*] a man came out of the camp from Saul, with his clothes torn, and earth on his head. When he came to David, he fell to the earth, and showed respect.

3 David said to him, “Where do you come from?”

He said to him, “I have escaped out of the camp of Israel.”

4 David said to him, “How did it go? Please tell me.”

He answered, “The people have fled from the battle, and many of the people also have fallen and are dead. Saul and Jonathan his son are dead also.”

5 David said to the young man who told him, “How do you know that Saul and Jonathan his son are dead?”

6 The young man who told him said, “As I happened by chance on Mount Gilboa, behold, Saul was leaning on his spear; and behold, the chariots and the horsemen followed close behind him. 7 When he looked behind him, he saw me, and called to me. I answered, ‘Here I am.’ 8 He said to me, ‘Who are you?’ I answered him, ‘I am an Amalekite.’ 9 He said to me, ‘Please stand beside me, and kill me; for anguish has taken hold of me, because my life lingers in me.’ 10 So I stood beside him and killed him, because I was sure that he could not live after that he had fallen. I took the crown that was on his head and the bracelet that was on his arm, and have brought them here to my lord.”

11 Then David took hold on his clothes, and tore them; and all the men who were with him did likewise. 12 They mourned, wept, and fasted until evening, for Saul, and for Jonathan his son, and for the people of Yahweh,[*] and for the house of Israel; because they had fallen by the sword. 13 David said to the young man who told him, “Where are you from?”

He answered, “I am the son of a foreigner, an Amalekite.”

14 David said to him, “Why were you not afraid to stretch out your hand to destroy Yahweh’s anointed?” 15 David called one of the young men, and said, “Go near, and cut him down!” He struck him so that he died. 16 David said to him, “Your blood be on your head; for your mouth has testified against you, saying, ‘I have slain Yahweh’s anointed.’”

17 David lamented with this lamentation over Saul and over Jonathan his son 18 (and he commanded them to teach the children of Judah the song of the bow; behold, it is written in the book of Jashar):

19 “Your glory, Israel, was slain on your high places!

How the mighty have fallen!

20 Don’t tell it in Gath.

Don’t publish it in the streets of Ashkelon,

lest the daughters of the Philistines rejoice,

lest the daughters of the uncircumcised triumph.

21 You mountains of Gilboa,

let there be no dew or rain on you, and no fields of offerings;

For there the shield of the mighty was defiled and cast away,

The shield of Saul was not anointed with oil.

22 From the blood of the slain,

from the fat of the mighty,

Jonathan’s bow didn’t turn back.

Saul’s sword didn’t return empty.

23 Saul and Jonathan were lovely and pleasant in their lives.

In their death, they were not divided.

They were swifter than eagles.

They were stronger than lions.

24 You daughters of Israel, weep over Saul,

who clothed you delicately in scarlet,

who put ornaments of gold on your clothing.

25 How the mighty have fallen in the middle of the battle!

Jonathan was slain on your high places.

26 I am distressed for you, my brother Jonathan.

You have been very pleasant to me.

Your love to me was wonderful,

passing the love of women.

27 How the mighty have fallen,

and the weapons of war have perished!”

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

2 Samuel 2

1 After this, David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Shall I go up into any of the cities of Judah?”

Yahweh said to him, “Go up.”

David said, “Where shall I go up?”

He said, “To Hebron.”

2 So David went up there with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. 3 David brought up his men who were with him, every man with his household. They lived in the cities of Hebron. 4 The men of Judah came, and there they anointed David king over the house of Judah. They told David, “The men of Jabesh Gilead were those who buried Saul.” 5 David sent messengers to the men of Jabesh Gilead, and said to them, “Blessed are you by Yahweh, that you have shown this kindness to your lord, even to Saul, and have buried him. 6 Now may Yahweh show loving kindness and truth to you. I also will reward you for this kindness, because you have done this thing. 7 Now therefore let your hands be strong, and be valiant; for Saul your lord is dead, and also the house of Judah have anointed me king over them.”

8 Now Abner the son of Ner, captain of Saul’s army, had taken Ishbosheth the son of Saul, and brought him over to Mahanaim; 9 and he made him king over Gilead, and over the Ashurites, and over Jezreel, and over Ephraim, and over Benjamin, and over all Israel. 10 Ishbosheth, Saul’s son, was forty years old when he began to reign over Israel, and he reigned two years. But the house of Judah followed David. 11 The time that David was king in Hebron over the house of Judah was seven years and six months. 12 Abner the son of Ner, and the servants of Ishbosheth the son of Saul, went out from Mahanaim to Gibeon. 13 Joab the son of Zeruiah and David’s servants went out, and met them by the pool of Gibeon; and they sat down, the one on the one side of the pool, and the other on the other side of the pool. 14 Abner said to Joab, “Please let the young men arise and play before us!”

Joab said, “Let them arise!” 15 Then they arose and went over by number: twelve for Benjamin and for Ishbosheth the son of Saul, and twelve of David’s servants. 16 They each caught his opponent by the head, and thrust his sword in his fellow’s side; so they fell down together: therefore that place in Gibeon was called Helkath Hazzurim.[*] 17 The battle was very severe that day; and Abner was beaten, and the men of Israel, before David’s servants. 18 The three sons of Zeruiah were there, Joab, and Abishai, and Asahel: and Asahel was as light of foot as a wild gazelle. 19 Asahel pursued Abner; and in going he didn’t turn to the right hand or to the left from following Abner. 20 Then Abner looked behind him, and said, “Is that you, Asahel?”

He answered, “It is.”

21 Abner said to him, “Turn aside to your right hand or to your left, and grab one of the young men, and take his armor.” But Asahel would not turn aside from following him. 22 Abner said again to Asahel, “Turn aside from following me. Why should I strike you to the ground? How then could I look Joab your brother in the face?” 23 However he refused to turn aside. Therefore Abner with the back end of the spear struck him in the body, so that the spear came out behind him; and he fell down there, and died in the same place. As many as came to the place where Asahel fell down and died stood still. 24 But Joab and Abishai pursued Abner. The sun went down when they had come to the hill of Ammah, that lies before Giah by the way of the wilderness of Gibeon. 25 The children of Benjamin gathered themselves together after Abner, and became one band, and stood on the top of a hill. 26 Then Abner called to Joab, and said, “Shall the sword devour forever? Don’t you know that it will be bitterness in the latter end? How long will it be then, before you ask the people to return from following their brothers?”

27 Joab said, “As God[*] lives, if you had not spoken, surely then in the morning the people would have gone away, and not each followed his brother.” 28 So Joab blew the trumpet; and all the people stood still, and pursued Israel no more, and they fought no more. 29 Abner and his men went all that night through the Arabah; and they passed over the Jordan, and went through all Bithron, and came to Mahanaim. 30 Joab returned from following Abner; and when he had gathered all the people together, nineteen men of David’s and Asahel were missing. 31 But David’s servants had struck Benjamin and of Abner’s men so that three hundred sixty men died. 32 They took up Asahel, and buried him in the tomb of his father, which was in Bethlehem. Joab and his men went all night, and the day broke on them at Hebron.

“Helkath Hazzurim” means “field of daggers”.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

2 Samuel 3

1 Now there was long war between Saul’s house and David’s house. David grew stronger and stronger, but Saul’s house grew weaker and weaker. 2 Sons were born to David in Hebron. His firstborn was Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; 3 and his second, Chileab, of Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite; and the third, Absalom the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur; 4 and the fourth, Adonijah the son of Haggith; and the fifth, Shephatiah the son of Abital; 5 and the sixth, Ithream, of Eglah, David’s wife. These were born to David in Hebron.

6 While there was war between Saul’s house and David’s house, Abner made himself strong in Saul’s house. 7 Now Saul had a concubine, whose name was Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah; and Ishbosheth said to Abner, “Why have you gone in to my father’s concubine?”

8 Then Abner was very angry about Ishbosheth’s words, and said, “Am I a dog’s head that belongs to Judah? Today I show kindness to Saul’s house your father, to his brothers, and to his friends, and have not delivered you into the hand of David; and yet you charge me today with a fault concerning this woman! 9 God do so to Abner, and more also, if, as Yahweh has sworn to David, I don’t do even so to him; 10 to transfer the kingdom from Saul’s house, and to set up David’s throne over Israel and over Judah, from Dan even to Beersheba.”

11 He could not answer Abner another word, because he was afraid of him.

12 Abner sent messengers to David on his behalf, saying, “Whose is the land?” and saying, “Make your alliance with me, and behold, my hand will be with you, to bring all Israel around to you.”

13 He said, “Good. I will make a treaty with you, but one thing I require of you. That is, you will not see my face unless you first bring Michal, Saul’s daughter, when you come to see my face.”

14 David sent messengers to Ishbosheth, Saul’s son, saying, “Deliver me my wife Michal, whom I was given to marry for one hundred foreskins of the Philistines.”

15 Ishbosheth sent and took her from her husband, even from Paltiel the son of Laish. 16 Her husband went with her, weeping as he went, and followed her to Bahurim. Then Abner said to him, “Go! Return!” and he returned. 17 Abner had communication with the elders of Israel, saying, “In times past, you sought for David to be king over you. 18 Now then do it; for Yahweh has spoken of David, saying, ‘By the hand of my servant David, I will save my people Israel out of the hand of the Philistines, and out of the hand of all their enemies.’”

19 Abner also spoke in the ears of Benjamin: and Abner went also to speak in the ears of David in Hebron all that seemed good to Israel, and to the whole house of Benjamin. 20 So Abner came to David to Hebron, and twenty men with him. David made Abner and the men who were with him a feast. 21 Abner said to David, “I will arise and go, and will gather all Israel to my lord the king, that they may make a covenant with you, and that you may reign over all that your soul desires.” David sent Abner away; and he went in peace.

22 Behold, David’s servants and Joab came from a raid, and brought in a great plunder with them; but Abner was not with David in Hebron; for he had sent him away, and he had gone in peace. 23 When Joab and all the army who was with him had come, they told Joab, “Abner the son of Ner came to the king, and he has sent him away, and he has gone in peace.”

24 Then Joab came to the king, and said, “What have you done? Behold, Abner came to you. Why is it that you have sent him away, and he is already gone? 25 You know Abner the son of Ner. He came to deceive you, and to know your going out and your coming in, and to know all that you do.”

26 When Joab had come out from David, he sent messengers after Abner, and they brought him back from the well of Sirah; but David didn’t know it. 27 When Abner was returned to Hebron, Joab took him aside into the middle of the gate to speak with him quietly, and struck him there in the body, so that he died, for the blood of Asahel his brother. 28 Afterward, when David heard it, he said, “I and my kingdom are guiltless before Yahweh forever of the blood of Abner the son of Ner. 29 Let it fall on the head of Joab, and on all his father’s house. Let there not fail from the house of Joab one who has an issue, or who is a leper, or who leans on a staff, or who falls by the sword, or who lacks bread.” 30 So Joab and Abishai his brother killed Abner, because he had killed their brother Asahel at Gibeon in the battle. 31 David said to Joab, and to all the people who were with him, “Tear your clothes, and clothe yourselves with sackcloth, and mourn in front of Abner.” King David followed the bier. 32 They buried Abner in Hebron; and the king lifted up his voice, and wept at Abner’s grave; and all the people wept. 33 The king lamented for Abner, and said, “Should Abner die as a fool dies? 34 Your hands weren’t bound, and your feet weren’t put into fetters. As a man falls before the children of iniquity, so you fell.”

All the people wept again over him. 35 All the people came to urge David to eat bread while it was yet day; but David swore, saying, “God do so to me, and more also, if I taste bread, or anything else, until the sun goes down.”

36 All the people took notice of it, and it pleased them; as whatever the king did pleased all the people. 37 So all the people and all Israel understood that day that it was not of the king to kill Abner the son of Ner. 38 The king said to his servants, “Don’t you know that there a prince and a great man has fallen today in Israel? 39 I am weak today, though anointed king. These men, the sons of Zeruiah are too hard for me. May Yahweh reward the evildoer according to his wickedness.”

2 Samuel 4

1 When Saul’s son heard that Abner was dead in Hebron, his hands became feeble, and all the Israelites were troubled. 2 Saul’s son had two men who were captains of raiding bands. The name of one was Baanah, and the name of the other Rechab, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, of the children of Benjamin (for Beeroth also is considered a part of Benjamin: 3 and the Beerothites fled to Gittaim, and have lived as foreigners there until today). 4 Now Jonathan, Saul’s son, had a son who was lame in his feet. He was five years old when the news came about Saul and Jonathan out of Jezreel; and his nurse picked him up and fled. As she hurried to flee, he fell and became lame. His name was Mephibosheth. 5 The sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, Rechab and Baanah, went and came at about the heat of the day to the house of Ishbosheth, as he took his rest at noon. 6 They came there into the middle of the house, as though they would have fetched wheat; and they struck him in the body: and Rechab and Baanah his brother escaped. 7 Now when they came into the house, as he lay on his bed in his bedroom, they struck him, killed him, beheaded him, and took his head, and went by the way of the Arabah all night. 8 They brought the head of Ishbosheth to David to Hebron, and said to the king, “Behold, the head of Ishbosheth, the son of Saul, your enemy, who sought your life! Yahweh has avenged my lord the king today of Saul, and of his offspring.[*] ”

9 David answered Rechab and Baanah his brother, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, and said to them, “As Yahweh lives, who has redeemed my soul out of all adversity, 10 when someone told me, ‘Behold, Saul is dead,’ thinking that he brought good news, I seized him and killed him in Ziklag, which was the reward I gave him for his news. 11 How much more, when wicked men have slain a righteous person in his own house on his bed, should I not now require his blood from your hand, and rid the earth of you?” 12 David commanded his young men, and they killed them, cut off their hands and their feet, and hanged them up beside the pool in Hebron. But they took the head of Ishbosheth, and buried it in Abner’s grave in Hebron.

or, seed

2 Samuel 5

1 Then all the tribes of Israel came to David at Hebron, and spoke, saying, “Behold, we are your bone and your flesh. 2 In times past, when Saul was king over us, it was you who led Israel out and in. Yahweh said to you, ‘You will be shepherd of my people Israel, and you will be prince over Israel.’” 3 So all the elders of Israel came to the king to Hebron, and king David made a covenant with them in Hebron before Yahweh; and they anointed David king over Israel.

4 David was thirty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned forty years. 5 In Hebron he reigned over Judah seven years and six months; and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty-three years over all Israel and Judah. 6 The king and his men went to Jerusalem against the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, who spoke to David, saying, “The blind and the lame will keep you out of here”; thinking, “David can’t come in here.” 7 Nevertheless David took the stronghold of Zion. This is David’s city. 8 David said on that day, “Whoever strikes the Jebusites, let him go up to the watercourse and strike the lame and the blind, who are hated by David’s soul.” Therefore they say, “The blind and the lame can’t come into the house.”

9 David lived in the stronghold, and called it David’s city. David built around from Millo and inward. 10 David grew greater and greater; for Yahweh, the God of Armies, was with him. 11 Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, with cedar trees, carpenters, and masons; and they built David a house. 12 David perceived that Yahweh had established him king over Israel, and that he had exalted his kingdom for his people Israel’s sake. 13 David took more concubines and wives for himself out of Jerusalem, after he had come from Hebron; and more sons and daughters were born to David. 14 These are the names of those who were born to him in Jerusalem: Shammua, Shobab, Nathan, Solomon, 15 Ibhar, Elishua, Nepheg, Japhia, 16 Elishama, Eliada, and Eliphelet.

17 When the Philistines heard that they had anointed David king over Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David, but David heard about it and went down to the stronghold. 18 Now the Philistines had come and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim. 19 David inquired of Yahweh, saying, “Shall I go up against the Philistines? Will you deliver them into my hand?”

Yahweh said to David, “Go up; for I will certainly deliver the Philistines into your hand.”

20 David came to Baal Perazim, and David struck them there. Then he said, “Yahweh has broken my enemies before me, like the breach of waters.” Therefore he called the name of that place Baal Perazim.[*] 21 They left their images there; and David and his men took them away.

22 The Philistines came up yet again, and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim. 23 When David inquired of Yahweh, he said, “You shall not go up. Circle around behind them, and attack them in front of the mulberry trees. 24 When you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry trees, then stir yourself up; for then Yahweh has gone out before you to strike the army of the Philistines.”

25 David did so, as Yahweh commanded him, and struck the Philistines all the way from Geba to Gezer.

“Baal Perazim” means “Lord who breaks out”.

2 Samuel 7

1 When the king lived in his house, and Yahweh had given him rest from all his enemies all around, 2 the king said to Nathan the prophet, “See now, I dwell in a house of cedar, but God’s ark dwells within curtains.”

3 Nathan said to the king, “Go, do all that is in your heart; for Yahweh is with you.”

4 That same night, Yahweh’s word came to Nathan, saying, 5 “Go and tell my servant David, ‘Yahweh says, “Should you build me a house for me to dwell in? 6 For I have not lived in a house since the day that I brought the children of Israel up out of Egypt, even to this day, but have moved around in a tent and in a tabernacle. 7 In all places in which I have walked with all the children of Israel, did I say a word to any of the tribes of Israel, whom I commanded to be shepherd of my people Israel, saying, ‘Why have you not built me a house of cedar?’”’ 8 Now therefore tell my servant David this, ‘Yahweh of Armies says, “I took you from the sheep pen, from following the sheep, to be prince over my people, over Israel. 9 I have been with you wherever you went, and have cut off all your enemies from before you. I will make you a great name, like the name of the great ones who are in the earth. 10 I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that they may dwell in their own place, and be moved no more. The children of wickedness will not afflict them any more, as at the first, 11 and as from the day that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel. I will cause you to rest from all your enemies. Moreover Yahweh tells you that Yahweh will make you a house. 12 When your days are fulfilled, and you sleep with your fathers, I will set up your offspring[*] after you, who will proceed out of your body, and I will establish his kingdom. 13 He will build a house for my name, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever. 14 I will be his father, and he will be my son. If he commits iniquity, I will chasten him with the rod of men, and with the stripes of the children of men; 15 but my loving kindness will not depart from him, as I took it from Saul, whom I put away before you. 16 Your house and your kingdom will be made sure forever before you. Your throne will be established forever.”’” 17 Nathan spoke to David all these words, and according to all this vision.

18 Then David the king went in, and sat before Yahweh; and he said, “Who am I, Lord[*] Yahweh, and what is my house, that you have brought me this far? 19 This was yet a small thing in your eyes, Lord Yahweh; but you have spoken also of your servant’s house for a great while to come; and this among men, Lord Yahweh! 20 What more can David say to you? For you know your servant, Lord Yahweh. 21 For your word’s sake, and according to your own heart, you have worked all this greatness, to make your servant know it. 22 Therefore you are great, Yahweh God. For there is no one like you, neither is there any God besides you, according to all that we have heard with our ears. 23 What one nation in the earth is like your people, even like Israel, whom God went to redeem to himself for a people, and to make himself a name, and to do great things for you, and awesome things for your land, before your people, whom you redeemed to yourself out of Egypt, from the nations and their gods? 24 You established for yourself your people Israel to be your people forever; and you, Yahweh, became their God. 25 Now, Yahweh God, the word that you have spoken concerning your servant, and concerning his house, confirm it forever, and do as you have spoken. 26 Let your name be magnified forever, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies is God over Israel; and the house of your servant David will be established before you.’ 27 For you, Yahweh of Armies, the God of Israel, have revealed to your servant, saying, ‘I will build you a house.’ Therefore your servant has found in his heart to pray this prayer to you.

28 “Now, O Lord Yahweh, you are God, and your words are truth, and you have promised this good thing to your servant. 29 Now therefore let it please you to bless the house of your servant, that it may continue forever before you; for you, Lord Yahweh, have spoken it. Let the house of your servant be blessed forever with your blessing.”

or, seed

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

2 Samuel 8

1 After this, David struck the Philistines and subdued them; and David took the bridle of the mother city out of the hand of the Philistines. 2 He struck Moab, and measured them with the line, making them to lie down on the ground; and he measured two lines to put to death, and one full line to keep alive. The Moabites became servants to David, and brought tribute. 3 David struck also Hadadezer the son of Rehob, king of Zobah, as he went to recover his dominion at the River. 4 David took from him one thousand seven hundred horsemen and twenty thousand footmen. David hamstrung all the chariot horses, but reserved of them for one hundred chariots. 5 When the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadadezer king of Zobah, David struck twenty two thousand men of the Syrians. 6 Then David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus; and the Syrians became servants to David, and brought tribute. Yahweh gave victory to David wherever he went. 7 David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadadezer, and brought them to Jerusalem. 8 From Betah and from Berothai, cities of Hadadezer, king David took a great quantity of brass. 9 When Toi king of Hamath heard that David had struck all the army of Hadadezer, 10 then Toi sent Joram his son to king David, to greet him, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadadezer and struck him; for Hadadezer had wars with Toi. Joram brought with him vessels of silver, vessels of gold, and vessels of brass: 11 King David also dedicated these to Yahweh, with the silver and gold that he dedicated of all the nations which he subdued; 12 of Syria, of Moab, of the children of Ammon, of the Philistines, of Amalek, and of the plunder of Hadadezer, son of Rehob, king of Zobah.

13 David earned a reputation when he returned from striking down eighteen thousand men of the Syrians in the Valley of Salt. 14 He put garrisons in Edom. Throughout all Edom put he garrisons, and all the Edomites became servants to David. Yahweh gave victory to David wherever he went. 15 David reigned over all Israel; and David executed justice and righteousness for all his people. 16 Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the army, Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was recorder, 17 Zadok the son of Ahitub and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar were priests, Seraiah was scribe, 18 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites, David’s sons were chief ministers.

2 Samuel 9

1 David said, “Is there yet any who is left of Saul’s house, that I may show him kindness for Jonathan’s sake?” 2 There was of Saul’s house a servant whose name was Ziba, and they called him to David; and the king said to him, “Are you Ziba?”

He said, “I am your servant.”

3 The king said, “Is there not yet any of Saul’s house, that I may show the kindness of God to him?”

Ziba said to the king, “Jonathan still has a son, who is lame in his feet.”

4 The king said to him, “Where is he?”

Ziba said to the king, “Behold, he is in the house of Machir the son of Ammiel, in Lo Debar.”

5 Then king David sent, and brought him out of the house of Machir the son of Ammiel, from Lo Debar. 6 Mephibosheth, the son of Jonathan, the son of Saul, came to David, and fell on his face, and showed respect. David said, “Mephibosheth.”

He answered, “Behold, your servant!”

7 David said to him, “Don’t be afraid of him; for I will surely show you kindness for Jonathan your father’s sake, and will restore to you all the land of Saul your father. You will eat bread at my table continually.”

8 He bowed down, and said, “What is your servant, that you should look at such a dead dog as I am?” 9 Then the king called to Ziba, Saul’s servant, and said to him, “All that belonged to Saul and to all his house I have given to your master’s son. 10 Till the land for him, you, your sons, and your servants. Bring in the harvest, that your master’s son may have bread to eat; but Mephibosheth your master’s son will always eat bread at my table.”

Now Ziba had fifteen sons and twenty servants. 11 Then Ziba said to the king, “According to all that my lord the king commands his servant, so your servant will do.” So Mephibosheth ate at the king’s table, like one of the king’s sons. 12 Mephibosheth had a young son, whose name was Mica. All that lived in Ziba’s house were servants to Mephibosheth. 13 So Mephibosheth lived in Jerusalem; for he ate continually at the king’s table. He was lame in both his feet.

2 Samuel 10

1 After this, the king of the children of Ammon died, and Hanun his son reigned in his place. 2 David said, “I will show kindness to Hanun the son of Nahash, as his father showed kindness to me.” So David sent by his servants to comfort him concerning his father. David’s servants came into the land of the children of Ammon.

3 But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun their lord, “Do you think that David honors your father, in that he has sent comforters to you? Hasn’t David sent his servants to you to search the city, to spy it out, and to overthrow it?”

4 So Hanun took David’s servants, shaved off one half of their beards, and cut off their garments in the middle, even to their buttocks, and sent them away. 5 When they told David this, he sent to meet them, for the men were greatly ashamed. The king said, “Wait at Jericho until your beards have grown, and then return.”

6 When the children of Ammon saw that they had become odious to David, the children of Ammon sent and hired the Syrians of Beth Rehob, and the Syrians of Zobah, twenty thousand footmen, and the king of Maacah with one thousand men, and the men of Tob twelve thousand men. 7 When David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the army of the mighty men. 8 The children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array at the entrance of the gate. The Syrians of Zobah and of Rehob, and the men of Tob and Maacah, were by themselves in the field. 9 Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose of all the choice men of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians. 10 The rest of the people he committed into the hand of Abishai his brother; and he put them in array against the children of Ammon. 11 He said, “If the Syrians are too strong for me, then you shall help me; but if the children of Ammon are too strong for you, then I will come and help you. 12 Be courageous, and let us be strong for our people, and for the cities of our God; and may Yahweh do what seems good to him.” 13 So Joab and the people who were with him came near to the battle against the Syrians, and they fled before him. 14 When the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians had fled, they likewise fled before Abishai, and entered into the city. Then Joab returned from the children of Ammon, and came to Jerusalem. 15 When the Syrians saw that they were defeated by Israel, they gathered themselves together. 16 Hadadezer sent, and brought out the Syrians who were beyond the River: and they came to Helam, with Shobach the captain of the army of Hadadezer at their head. 17 David was told that; and he gathered all Israel together, passed over the Jordan, and came to Helam. The Syrians set themselves in array against David, and fought with him. 18 The Syrians fled before Israel; and David killed seven hundred charioteers of the Syrians, and forty thousand horsemen, and struck Shobach the captain of their army, so that he died there. 19 When all the kings who were servants to Hadadezer saw that they were defeated before Israel, they made peace with Israel, and served them. So the Syrians were afraid to help the children of Ammon any more.

2 Samuel 11

1 At the return of the year, at the time when kings go out, David sent Joab, and his servants with him, and all Israel; and they destroyed the children of Ammon, and besieged Rabbah. But David stayed at Jerusalem. 2 At evening, David arose from his bed and walked on the roof of the king’s house. From the roof, he saw a woman bathing, and the woman was very beautiful to look at. 3 David sent and inquired after the woman. One said, “Isn’t this Bathsheba, the daughter of Eliam, Uriah the Hittite’s wife?”

4 David sent messengers, and took her; and she came in to him, and he lay with her (for she was purified from her uncleanness); and she returned to her house. 5 The woman conceived; and she sent and told David, and said, “I am with child.”

6 David sent to Joab, “Send me Uriah the Hittite.” Joab sent Uriah to David. 7 When Uriah had come to him, David asked him how Joab did, and how the people fared, and how the war prospered. 8 David said to Uriah, “Go down to your house and wash your feet.” Uriah departed out of the king’s house, and a gift from the king was sent after him. 9 But Uriah slept at the door of the king’s house with all the servants of his lord, and didn’t go down to his house. 10 When they had told David, saying, “Uriah didn’t go down to his house,” David said to Uriah, “Haven’t you come from a journey? Why didn’t you go down to your house?”

11 Uriah said to David, “The ark, Israel, and Judah, are staying in tents; and my lord Joab and the servants of my lord, are encamped in the open field. Shall I then go into my house to eat and to drink, and to lie with my wife? As you live, and as your soul lives, I will not do this thing!”

12 David said to Uriah, “Stay here today also, and tomorrow I will let you depart.” So Uriah stayed in Jerusalem that day, and the next day. 13 When David had called him, he ate and drink before him; and he made him drunk. At evening, he went out to lie on his bed with the servants of his lord, but didn’t go down to his house. 14 In the morning, David wrote a letter to Joab, and sent it by the hand of Uriah. 15 He wrote in the letter, saying, “Send Uriah to the forefront of the hottest battle, and retreat from him, that he may be struck, and die.”

16 When Joab kept watch on the city, he assigned Uriah to the place where he knew that valiant men were. 17 The men of the city went out, and fought with Joab. Some of the people fell, even of David’s servants; and Uriah the Hittite died also. 18 Then Joab sent and told David all the things concerning the war; 19 and he commanded the messenger, saying, “When you have finished telling all the things concerning the war to the king, 20 it shall be that, if the king’s wrath arise, and he asks you, ‘Why did you go so near to the city to fight? Didn’t you know that they would shoot from the wall? 21 Who struck Abimelech the son of Jerubbesheth? Didn’t a woman cast an upper millstone on him from the wall, so that he died at Thebez? Why did you go so near the wall?’ then you shall say, ‘Your servant Uriah the Hittite is also dead.’”

22 So the messenger went, and came and showed David all that Joab had sent him for. 23 The messenger said to David, “The men prevailed against us, and came out to us into the field, and we were on them even to the entrance of the gate. 24 The shooters shot at your servants from off the wall; and some of the king’s servants are dead, and your servant Uriah the Hittite is also dead.”

25 Then David said to the messenger, “Tell Joab, ‘Don’t let this thing displease you, for the sword devours one as well as another. Make your battle stronger against the city, and overthrow it.’ Encourage him.”

26 When Uriah’s wife heard that Uriah her husband was dead, she mourned for her husband. 27 When the mourning was past, David sent and took her home to his house, and she became his wife, and bore him a son. But the thing that David had done displeased Yahweh.

2 Samuel 12

1 Yahweh sent Nathan to David. He came to him, and said to him, “There were two men in one city; the one rich, and the other poor. 2 The rich man had very many flocks and herds, 3 but the poor man had nothing, except one little ewe lamb, which he had bought and raised. It grew up together with him, and with his children. It ate of his own food, drank of his own cup, and lay in his bosom, and was like a daughter to him. 4 A traveler came to the rich man, and he spared to take of his own flock and of his own herd, to prepare for the wayfaring man who had come to him, but took the poor man’s lamb, and prepared it for the man who had come to him.”

5 David’s anger burned hot against the man, and he said to Nathan, “As Yahweh lives, the man who has done this deserves to die! 6 He must restore the lamb fourfold, because he did this thing, and because he had no pity!”

7 Nathan said to David, “You are the man. This is what Yahweh, the God of Israel, says: ‘I anointed you king over Israel, and I delivered you out of the hand of Saul. 8 I gave you your master’s house, and your master’s wives into your bosom, and gave you the house of Israel and of Judah; and if that would have been too little, I would have added to you many more such things. 9 Why have you despised Yahweh’s word, to do that which is evil in his sight? You have struck Uriah the Hittite with the sword, and have taken his wife to be your wife, and have slain him with the sword of the children of Ammon. 10 Now therefore the sword will never depart from your house, because you have despised me, and have taken Uriah the Hittite’s wife to be your wife.’

11 “This is what Yahweh says: ‘Behold, I will raise up evil against you out of your own house; and I will take your wives before your eyes, and give them to your neighbor, and he will lie with your wives in the sight of this sun. 12 For you did this secretly, but I will do this thing before all Israel, and before the sun.’”

13 David said to Nathan, “I have sinned against Yahweh.”

Nathan said to David, “Yahweh also has put away your sin. You will not die. 14 However, because by this deed you have given great occasion to Yahweh’s enemies to blaspheme, the child also who is born to you will surely die.” 15 Nathan departed to his house.

Yahweh struck the child that Uriah’s wife bore to David, and it was very sick. 16 David therefore begged God for the child; and David fasted, and went in, and lay all night on the ground. 17 The elders of his house arose beside him, to raise him up from the earth: but he would not, and he didn’t eat bread with them. 18 On the seventh day, the child died. David’s servants were afraid to tell him that the child was dead, for they said, “Behold, while the child was yet alive, we spoke to him, and he didn’t listen to our voice. How will he then harm himself, if we tell him that the child is dead?”

19 But when David saw that his servants were whispering together, David perceived that the child was dead; and David said to his servants, “Is the child dead?”

They said, “He is dead.”

20 Then David arose from the earth, and washed, and anointed himself, and changed his clothing; and he came into Yahweh’s house, and worshiped. Then he came to his own house; and when he requested, they set bread before him, and he ate. 21 Then his servants said to him, “What is this that you have done? You fasted and wept for the child while he was alive, but when the child was dead, you rose up and ate bread.”

22 He said, “While the child was yet alive, I fasted and wept; for I said, ‘Who knows whether Yahweh will not be gracious to me, that the child may live?’ 23 But now he is dead, why should I fast? Can I bring him back again? I will go to him, but he will not return to me.”

24 David comforted Bathsheba his wife, and went in to her, and lay with her. She bore a son, and he called his name Solomon. Yahweh loved him; 25 and he sent by the hand of Nathan the prophet, and he named him Jedidiah,[*] for Yahweh’s sake.

26 Now Joab fought against Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and took the royal city. 27 Joab sent messengers to David, and said, “I have fought against Rabbah. Yes, I have taken the city of waters. 28 Now therefore gather the rest of the people together, and encamp against the city, and take it; lest I take the city, and it be called by my name.”

29 David gathered all the people together, and went to Rabbah, and fought against it, and took it. 30 He took the crown of their king from off his head; and its weight was a talent[*] of gold, and in it were precious stones; and it was set on David’s head. He brought a great quantity of plunder out of the city. 31 He brought out the people who were in it, and put them under saws, under iron picks, under axes of iron, and made them pass through the brick kiln; and he did so to all the cities of the children of Ammon. Then David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.

“Jedidiah” means “loved by Yahweh”.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

2 Samuel 13

1 After this, Absalom the son of David had a beautiful sister, whose name was Tamar; and Amnon the son of David loved her. 2 Amnon was so troubled that he became sick because of his sister Tamar; for she was a virgin; and it seemed hard to Amnon to do anything to her. 3 But Amnon had a friend, whose name was Jonadab, the son of Shimeah, David’s brother; and Jonadab was a very subtle man. 4 He said to him, “Why, son of the king, are you so sad from day to day? Won’t you tell me?”

Amnon said to him, “I love Tamar, my brother Absalom’s sister.”

5 Jonadab said to him, “Lay down on your bed, and pretend to be sick. When your father comes to see you, tell him, ‘Please let my sister Tamar come and give me bread to eat, and prepare the food in my sight, that I may see it, and eat it from her hand.’”

6 So Amnon lay down and faked being sick. When the king came to see him, Amnon said to the king, “Please let my sister Tamar come, and make me a couple of cakes in my sight, that I may eat from her hand.”

7 Then David sent home to Tamar, saying, “Go now to your brother Amnon’s house, and prepare food for him.” 8 So Tamar went to her brother Amnon’s house; and he was lying down. She took dough, and kneaded it, made cakes in his sight, and baked the cakes. 9 She took the pan, and poured them out before him; but he refused to eat. Amnon said, “Have all men leave me.” Then every man went out from him. 10 Amnon said to Tamar, “Bring the food into the room, that I may eat from your hand.” Tamar took the cakes which she had made, and brought them into the room to Amnon her brother. 11 When she had brought them near to him to eat, he took hold of her, and said to her, “Come, lie with me, my sister!”

12 She answered him, “No, my brother, do not force me! For no such thing ought to be done in Israel. Don’t you do this folly. 13 As for me, where would I carry my shame? And as for you, you will be as one of the fools in Israel. Now therefore, please speak to the king; for he will not withhold me from you.”

14 However he would not listen to her voice; but being stronger than she, he forced her, and lay with her. 15 Then Amnon hated her with exceedingly great hatred; for the hatred with which he hated her was greater than the love with which he had loved her. Amnon said to her, “Arise, be gone!”

16 She said to him, “Not so, because this great wrong in sending me away is worse than the other that you did to me!”

But he would not listen to her. 17 Then he called his servant who ministered to him, and said, “Now put this woman out from me, and bolt the door after her.”

18 She had a garment of various colors on her; for the king’s daughters who were virgins dressed in such robes. Then his servant brought her out and bolted the door after her. 19 Tamar put ashes on her head, and tore her garment of various colors that was on her; and she laid her hand on her head, and went her way, crying aloud as she went. 20 Absalom her brother said to her, “Has Amnon your brother been with you? But now hold your peace, my sister. He is your brother. Don’t take this thing to heart.”

So Tamar remained desolate in her brother Absalom’s house. 21 But when king David heard of all these things, he was very angry. 22 Absalom spoke to Amnon neither good nor bad; for Absalom hated Amnon, because he had forced his sister Tamar. 23 After two full years, Absalom had sheep shearers in Baal Hazor, which is beside Ephraim: and Absalom invited all the king’s sons. 24 Absalom came to the king, and said, “See now, your servant has sheep shearers. Please let the king and his servants go with your servant.”

25 The king said to Absalom, “No, my son, let us not all go, lest we be burdensome to you.” He pressed him; however he would not go, but blessed him.

26 Then Absalom said, “If not, please let my brother Amnon go with us.”

The king said to him, “Why should he go with you?”

27 But Absalom pressed him, and he let Amnon and all the king’s sons go with him. 28 Absalom commanded his servants, saying, “Mark now, when Amnon’s heart is merry with wine; and when I tell you, ‘Strike Amnon,’ then kill him. Don’t be afraid. Haven’t I commanded you? Be courageous, and be valiant!”

29 The servants of Absalom did to Amnon as Absalom had commanded. Then all the king’s sons arose, and every man got up on his mule, and fled. 30 While they were on the way, the news came to David, saying, “Absalom has slain all the king’s sons, and there is not one of them left!”

31 Then the king arose, and tore his garments, and lay on the earth; and all his servants stood by with their clothes torn. 32 Jonadab, the son of Shimeah, David’s brother, answered, “Don’t let my lord suppose that they have killed all the young men the king’s sons; for Amnon only is dead; for by the appointment of Absalom this has been determined from the day that he forced his sister Tamar. 33 Now therefore don’t let my lord the king take the thing to his heart, to think that all the king’s sons are dead; for only Amnon is dead.” 34 But Absalom fled. The young man who kept the watch lifted up his eyes, and looked, and behold, many people were coming by way of the hillside behind him. 35 Jonadab said to the king, “Behold, the king’s sons are coming! It is as your servant said.” 36 As soon as he had finished speaking, behold, the king’s sons came, and lifted up their voice, and wept. The king also and all his servants wept bitterly. 37 But Absalom fled, and went to Talmai the son of Ammihur, king of Geshur. David mourned for his son every day. 38 So Absalom fled, and went to Geshur, and was there three years. 39 King David longed to go out to Absalom; for he was comforted concerning Amnon, since he was dead.

2 Samuel 14

1 Now Joab the son of Zeruiah perceived that the king’s heart was toward Absalom. 2 Joab sent to Tekoa, and brought a wise woman from there, and said to her, “Please act like a mourner, and put on mourning clothing, please, and don’t anoint yourself with oil, but be as a woman who has mourned a long time for the dead. 3 Go in to the king, and speak like this to him.” So Joab put the words in her mouth.

4 When the woman of Tekoa spoke to the king, she fell on her face to the ground, showed respect, and said, “Help, O king!”

5 The king said to her, “What ails you?”

She answered, “Truly I am a widow, and my husband is dead. 6 Your servant had two sons, and they both fought together in the field, and there was no one to part them, but the one struck the other, and killed him. 7 Behold, the whole family has risen against your servant, and they say, ‘Deliver him who struck his brother, that we may kill him for the life of his brother whom he killed, and so destroy the heir also.’ Thus they would quench my coal which is left, and would leave to my husband neither name nor remainder on the surface of the earth.”

8 The king said to the woman, “Go to your house, and I will give a command concerning you.”

9 The woman of Tekoa said to the king, “My lord, O king, may the iniquity be on me, and on my father’s house; and may the king and his throne be guiltless.”

10 The king said, “Whoever says anything to you, bring him to me, and he will not bother you any more.”

11 Then she said, “Please let the king remember Yahweh your God, that the avenger of blood destroy not any more, lest they destroy my son.”

He said, “As Yahweh lives, not one hair of your son shall fall to the earth.”

12 Then the woman said, “Please let your servant speak a word to my lord the king.”

He said, “Say on.”

13 The woman said, “Why then have you devised such a thing against the people of God? For in speaking this word the king is as one who is guilty, in that the king does not bring home again his banished one. 14 For we must die, and are like water spilled on the ground, which can’t be gathered up again; neither does God take away life, but devises means, that he who is banished not be an outcast from him. 15 Now therefore seeing that I have come to speak this word to my lord the king, it is because the people have made me afraid. Your servant said, ‘I will now speak to the king; it may be that the king will perform the request of his servant.’ 16 For the king will hear, to deliver his servant out of the hand of the man who would destroy me and my son together out of the inheritance of God. 17 Then your servant said, ‘Please let the word of my lord the king bring rest; for as an angel of God, so is my lord the king to discern good and bad. May Yahweh, your God, be with you.’”

18 Then the king answered the woman, “Please don’t hide anything from me that I ask you.”

The woman said, “Let my lord the king now speak.”

19 The king said, “Is the hand of Joab with you in all this?”

The woman answered, “As your soul lives, my lord the king, no one can turn to the right hand or to the left from anything that my lord the king has spoken; for your servant Joab urged me, and he put all these words in the mouth of your servant; 20 to change the face of the matter has your servant Joab done this thing. My lord is wise, according to the wisdom of an angel of God, to know all things that are in the earth.”

21 The king said to Joab, “Behold now, I have done this thing. Go therefore, and bring the young man Absalom back.”

22 Joab fell to the ground on his face, showed respect, and blessed the king. Joab said, “Today your servant knows that I have found favor in your sight, my lord, king, in that the king has performed the request of his servant.”

23 So Joab arose and went to Geshur, and brought Absalom to Jerusalem. 24 The king said, “Let him return to his own house, but let him not see my face.” So Absalom returned to his own house, and didn’t see the king’s face. 25 Now in all Israel there was no one to be so much praised as Absalom for his beauty. From the sole of his foot even to the crown of his head there was no defect in him. 26 When he cut the hair of his head (now it was at every year’s end that he cut it; because it was heavy on him, therefore he cut it); he weighed the hair of his head at two hundred shekels,[*] after the king’s weight. 27 Three sons were born to Absalom, and one daughter, whose name was Tamar. She was a woman with a beautiful face. 28 Absalom lived two full years in Jerusalem, and he didn’t see the king’s face. 29 Then Absalom sent for Joab, to send him to the king, but he would not come to him. Then he sent again a second time, but he would not come. 30 Therefore he said to his servants, “Behold, Joab’s field is near mine, and he has barley there. Go and set it on fire.” So Absalom’s servants set the field on fire.

31 Then Joab arose, and came to Absalom to his house, and said to him, “Why have your servants set my field on fire?”

32 Absalom answered Joab, “Behold, I sent to you, saying, ‘Come here, that I may send you to the king, to say, “Why have I come from Geshur? It would be better for me to be there still. Now therefore let me see the king’s face, and if there is iniquity in me, let him kill me.”’”

33 So Joab came to the king, and told him; and when he had called for Absalom, he came to the king, and bowed himself on his face to the ground before the king; and the king kissed Absalom.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 200 shekels is about 2 kilograms or about 4.4 pounds.

2 Samuel 15

1 After this, Absalom prepared a chariot and horses for himself, and fifty men to run before him. 2 Absalom rose up early, and stood beside the way of the gate. When any man had a suit which should come to the king for judgment, then Absalom called to him, and said, “What city are you from?”

He said, “Your servant is of one of the tribes of Israel.”

3 Absalom said to him, “Behold, your matters are good and right; but there is no man deputized by the king to hear you.” 4 Absalom said moreover, “Oh that I were made judge in the land, that every man who has any suit or cause might come to me, and I would do him justice!” 5 It was so, that when any man came near to do him obeisance, he stretched out his hand, and took hold of him, and kissed him. 6 Absalom did this sort of thing to all Israel who came to the king for judgment. So Absalom stole the hearts of the men of Israel. 7 At the end of forty years, Absalom said to the king, “Please let me go and pay my vow, which I have vowed to Yahweh, in Hebron. 8 For your servant vowed a vow while I stayed at Geshur in Syria, saying, ‘If Yahweh shall indeed bring me again to Jerusalem, then I will serve Yahweh.’”

9 The king said to him, “Go in peace.”

So he arose, and went to Hebron. 10 But Absalom sent spies throughout all the tribes of Israel, saying, “As soon as you hear the sound of the trumpet, then you shall say, ‘Absalom is king in Hebron!’”

11 Two hundred men went with Absalom out of Jerusalem, who were invited, and went in their simplicity; and they didn’t know anything. 12 Absalom sent for Ahithophel the Gilonite, David’s counselor, from his city, even from Giloh, while he was offering the sacrifices. The conspiracy was strong; for the people increased continually with Absalom. 13 A messenger came to David, saying, “The hearts of the men of Israel are after Absalom.”

14 David said to all his servants who were with him at Jerusalem, “Arise, and let us flee; or else none of us will escape from Absalom. Hurry to depart, lest he overtake us quickly, and bring down evil on us, and strike the city with the edge of the sword.”

15 The king’s servants said to the king, “Behold, your servants are ready to do whatever my lord the king chooses.”

16 The king went out, and all his household after him. The king left ten women, who were concubines, to keep the house. 17 The king went out, and all the people after him; and they stayed in Beth Merhak. 18 All his servants passed on beside him; and all the Cherethites, and all the Pelethites, and all the Gittites, six hundred men who came after him from Gath, passed on before the king. 19 Then the king said to Ittai the Gittite, “Why do you also go with us? Return, and stay with the king; for you are a foreigner, and also an exile. Return to your own place. 20 Whereas you came but yesterday, should I today make you go up and down with us, since I go where I may? Return, and take back your brothers. Mercy and truth be with you.”

21 Ittai answered the king, and said, “As Yahweh lives, and as my lord the king lives, surely in what place my lord the king is, whether for death or for life, your servant will be there also.”

22 David said to Ittai, “Go and pass over.” Ittai the Gittite passed over, and all his men, and all the little ones who were with him. 23 All the country wept with a loud voice, and all the people passed over. The king also himself passed over the brook Kidron, and all the people passed over, toward the way of the wilderness. 24 Behold, Zadok also came, and all the Levites with him, bearing the ark of the covenant of God; and they set down God’s ark; and Abiathar went up, until all the people finished passing out of the city. 25 The king said to Zadok, “Carry God’s ark back into the city. If I find favor in Yahweh’s eyes, he will bring me again, and show me both it, and his habitation; 26 but if he says, ‘I have no delight in you;’ behold, here am I. Let him do to me as seems good to him.” 27 The king said also to Zadok the priest, “Aren’t you a seer? Return into the city in peace, and your two sons with you, Ahimaaz your son, and Jonathan the son of Abiathar. 28 Behold, I will stay at the fords of the wilderness, until word comes from you to inform me.” 29 Zadok therefore and Abiathar carried God’s ark to Jerusalem again; and they stayed there. 30 David went up by the ascent of the Mount of Olives, and wept as he went up; and he had his head covered, and went barefoot: and all the people who were with him each covered his head, and they went up, weeping as they went up.

31 Someone told David, saying, “Ahithophel is among the conspirators with Absalom.”

David said, “Yahweh, please turn the counsel of Ahithophel into foolishness.”

32 When David had come to the top, where God was worshiped, behold, Hushai the Archite came to meet him with his coat torn, and earth on his head. 33 David said to him, “If you pass on with me, then you will be a burden to me; 34 but if you return to the city, and tell Absalom, ‘I will be your servant, O king. As I have been your father’s servant in time past, so will I now be your servant; then will you defeat for me the counsel of Ahithophel.’ 35 Don’t you have Zadok and Abiathar the priests there with you? Therefore whatever you hear out of the king’s house, tell it to Zadok and Abiathar the priests. 36 Behold, they have there with them their two sons, Ahimaaz, Zadok’s son, and Jonathan, Abiathar’s son. Send to me everything that you shall hear by them.”

37 So Hushai, David’s friend, came into the city; and Absalom came into Jerusalem.

2 Samuel 16

1 When David was a little past the top, behold, Ziba the servant of Mephibosheth met him with a couple of donkeys saddled, and on them two hundred loaves of bread, and one hundred clusters of raisins, and one hundred summer fruits, and a bottle of wine. 2 The king said to Ziba, “What do you mean by these?”

Ziba said, “The donkeys are for the king’s household to ride on; and the bread and summer fruit for the young men to eat; and the wine, that those who are faint in the wilderness may drink.”

3 The king said, “Where is your master’s son?”

Ziba said to the king, “Behold, he is staying in Jerusalem; for he said, ‘Today the house of Israel will restore me the kingdom of my father.’”

4 Then the king said to Ziba, “Behold, all that belongs to Mephibosheth is yours.”

Ziba said, “I bow down. Let me find favor in your sight, my lord, O king.”

5 When king David came to Bahurim, behold, a man of the family of Saul’s house came out, whose name was Shimei, the son of Gera. He came out and cursed as he came. 6 He cast stones at David, and at all the servants of king David, and all the people and all the mighty men were on his right hand and on his left. 7 Shimei said when he cursed, “Be gone, be gone, you man of blood, and base fellow! 8 Yahweh has returned on you all the blood of Saul’s house, in whose place you have reigned! Yahweh has delivered the kingdom into the hand of Absalom your son! Behold, you are caught by your own mischief, because you are a man of blood!”

9 Then Abishai the son of Zeruiah said to the king, “Why should this dead dog curse my lord the king? Please let me go over and take off his head.” 10 The king said, “What have I to do with you, you sons of Zeruiah? Because he curses, and because Yahweh has said to him, ‘Curse David;’ who then shall say, ‘Why have you done so?’”

11 David said to Abishai, and to all his servants, “Behold, my son, who came out of my bowels, seeks my life. How much more this Benjamite, now? Leave him alone, and let him curse; for Yahweh has invited him. 12 It may be that Yahweh will look on the wrong done to me, and that Yahweh will repay me good for the cursing of me today.” 13 So David and his men went by the way; and Shimei went along on the hillside opposite him, and cursed as he went, threw stones at him, and threw dust. 14 The king, and all the people who were with him, came weary; and he refreshed himself there.

15 Absalom and all the people, the men of Israel, came to Jerusalem, and Ahithophel with him. 16 When Hushai the Archite, David’s friend, had come to Absalom, Hushai said to Absalom, “Long live the king! Long live the king!”

17 Absalom said to Hushai, “Is this your kindness to your friend? Why didn’t you go with your friend?”

18 Hushai said to Absalom, “No; but whomever Yahweh, and this people, and all the men of Israel have chosen, his will I be, and with him I will stay. 19 Again, whom should I serve? Shouldn’t I serve in the presence of his son? As I have served in your father’s presence, so will I be in your presence.”

20 Then Absalom said to Ahithophel, “Give your counsel what we shall do.”

21 Ahithophel said to Absalom, “Go in to your father’s concubines that he has left to keep the house. Then all Israel will hear that you are abhorred by your father. Then the hands of all who are with you will be strong.”

22 So they spread a tent for Absalom on the top of the house, and Absalom went in to his father’s concubines in the sight of all Israel. 23 The counsel of Ahithophel, which he gave in those days, was as if a man inquired at the inner sanctuary of God. So was all the counsel of Ahithophel both with David and with Absalom.

2 Samuel 17

1 Moreover Ahithophel said to Absalom, “Let me now choose twelve thousand men, and I will arise and pursue after David tonight. 2 I will come on him while he is weary and exhausted, and will make him afraid. All the people who are with him will flee. I will strike the king only, 3 and I will bring back all the people to you. The man whom you seek is as if all returned. All the people shall be in peace.”

4 The saying pleased Absalom well, and all the elders of Israel. 5 Then Absalom said, “Now call Hushai the Archite also, and let us hear likewise what he says.”

6 When Hushai had come to Absalom, Absalom spoke to him, saying, “Ahithophel has spoken like this. Shall we do what he says? If not, speak up.”

7 Hushai said to Absalom, “The counsel that Ahithophel has given this time is not good.” 8 Hushai said moreover, “You know your father and his men, that they are mighty men, and they are fierce in their minds, like a bear robbed of her cubs in the field. Your father is a man of war, and will not lodge with the people. 9 Behold, he is now hidden in some pit, or in some other place. It will happen, when some of them have fallen at the first, that whoever hears it will say, ‘There is a slaughter among the people who follow Absalom!’ 10 Even he who is valiant, whose heart is as the heart of a lion, will utterly melt; for all Israel knows that your father is a mighty man, and those who are with him are valiant men. 11 But I counsel that all Israel be gathered together to you, from Dan even to Beersheba, as the sand that is by the sea for multitude; and that you go to battle in your own person. 12 So shall we come on him in some place where he shall be found, and we will light on him as the dew falls on the ground; and of him and of all the men who are with him we will not leave so much as one. 13 Moreover, if he has gone into a city, then shall all Israel bring ropes to that city, and we will draw it into the river, until there isn’t one small stone found there.”

14 Absalom and all the men of Israel said, “The counsel of Hushai the Archite is better than the counsel of Ahithophel.” For Yahweh had ordained to defeat the good counsel of Ahithophel, to the intent that Yahweh might bring evil on Absalom. 15 Then Hushai said to Zadok and to Abiathar the priests, “Ahithophel counseled Absalom and the elders of Israel that way; and I have counseled this way. 16 Now therefore send quickly, and tell David, saying, ‘Don’t lodge tonight at the fords of the wilderness, but by all means pass over; lest the king be swallowed up, and all the people who are with him.’”

17 Now Jonathan and Ahimaaz were staying by En Rogel; and a female servant used to go and tell them; and they went and told king David. For they might not be seen to come into the city. 18 But a boy saw them, and told Absalom. Then they both went away quickly, and came to the house of a man in Bahurim, who had a well in his court; and they went down there. 19 The woman took and spread the covering over the well’s mouth, and spread out bruised grain on it; and nothing was known. 20 Absalom’s servants came to the woman to the house; and they said, “Where are Ahimaaz and Jonathan?”

The woman said to them, “They have gone over the brook of water.”

When they had sought and could not find them, they returned to Jerusalem. 21 After they had departed, they came up out of the well, and went and told king David; and they said to David, “Arise and pass quickly over the water; for thus has Ahithophel counseled against you.”

22 Then David arose, and all the people who were with him, and they passed over the Jordan. By the morning light there lacked not one of them who had not gone over the Jordan. 23 When Ahithophel saw that his counsel was not followed, he saddled his donkey, arose, and went home, to his city, and set his house in order, and hanged himself; and he died, and was buried in the tomb of his father. 24 Then David came to Mahanaim. Absalom passed over the Jordan, he and all the men of Israel with him. 25 Absalom set Amasa over the army instead of Joab. Now Amasa was the son of a man whose name was Ithra the Israelite, who went in to Abigail the daughter of Nahash, sister to Zeruiah, Joab’s mother. 26 Israel and Absalom encamped in the land of Gilead. 27 When David had come to Mahanaim, Shobi the son of Nahash of Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and Machir the son of Ammiel of Lodebar, and Barzillai the Gileadite of Rogelim, 28 brought beds, basins, earthen vessels, wheat, barley, meal, parched grain, beans, lentils, roasted grain, 29 honey, butter, sheep, and cheese of the herd, for David, and for the people who were with him, to eat; for they said, “The people are hungry, and weary, and thirsty in the wilderness.”

2 Samuel 18

1 David counted the people who were with him, and set captains of thousands and captains of hundreds over them. 2 David sent the people out, a third part under the hand of Joab, and a third part under the hand of Abishai the son of Zeruiah, Joab’s brother, and a third part under the hand of Ittai the Gittite. The king said to the people, “I will also surely go out with you myself.”

3 But the people said, “You shall not go out; for if we flee away, they will not care for us; neither if half of us die, will they care for us. But you are worth ten thousand of us. Therefore now it is better that you are ready to help us out of the city.”

4 The king said to them, “I will do what seems best to you.”

The king stood beside the gate, and all the people went out by hundreds and by thousands. 5 The king commanded Joab and Abishai and Ittai, saying, “Deal gently for my sake with the young man, even with Absalom.” All the people heard when the king commanded all the captains concerning Absalom.

6 So the people went out into the field against Israel; and the battle was in the forest of Ephraim. 7 The people of Israel were struck there before David’s servants, and there was a great slaughter there that day of twenty thousand men. 8 For the battle was there spread over the surface of all the country, and the forest devoured more people that day than the sword devoured. 9 Absalom happened to meet David’s servants. Absalom was riding on his mule, and the mule went under the thick boughs of a great oak, and his head caught hold of the oak, and he was taken up between the sky and earth; and the mule that was under him went on. 10 A certain man saw it, and told Joab, and said, “Behold, I saw Absalom hanging in an oak.”

11 Joab said to the man who told him, “Behold, you saw it, and why didn’t you strike him there to the ground? I would have given you ten pieces of silver, and a sash.”

12 The man said to Joab, “Though I should receive a thousand pieces of silver in my hand, I still wouldn’t stretch out my hand against the king’s son; for in our hearing the king commanded you and Abishai and Ittai, saying, ‘Beware that no one touch the young man Absalom.’ 13 Otherwise if I had dealt falsely against his life (and there is no matter hidden from the king), then you yourself would have set yourself against me.”

14 Then Joab said, “I’m not going to wait like this with you.” He took three darts in his hand, and thrust them through the heart of Absalom, while he was yet alive in the middle of the oak. 15 Ten young men who bore Joab’s armor surrounded and struck Absalom, and killed him. 16 Joab blew the trumpet, and the people returned from pursuing after Israel; for Joab held the people back. 17 They took Absalom and cast him into the great pit in the forest, and raised over him a very great heap of stones. Then all Israel fled, each to his own tent. 18 Now Absalom in his lifetime had taken and reared up for himself the pillar which is in the king’s valley, for he said, “I have no son to keep my name in memory.” He called the pillar after his own name. It is called Absalom’s monument, to this day.

19 Then Ahimaaz the son of Zadok said, “Let me now run, and carry the king news, how Yahweh has avenged him of his enemies.”

20 Joab said to him, “You must not be the bearer of news today, but you must carry news another day. But today you must carry no news, because the king’s son is dead.”

21 Then Joab said to the Cushite, “Go, tell the king what you have seen!” The Cushite bowed himself to Joab, and ran.

22 Then Ahimaaz the son of Zadok said yet again to Joab, “But come what may, please let me also run after the Cushite.”

Joab said, “Why do you want to run, my son, since that you will have no reward for the news?”

23 “But come what may,” he said, “I will run.”

He said to him, “Run!” Then Ahimaaz ran by the way of the Plain, and outran the Cushite.

24 Now David was sitting between the two gates; and the watchman went up to the roof of the gate to the wall, and lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, a man running alone. 25 The watchman cried, and told the king. The king said, “If he is alone, there is news in his mouth.” He came closer and closer.

26 The watchman saw another man running; and the watchman called to the porter, and said, “Behold, a man running alone!”

The king said, “He also brings news.”

27 The watchman said, “I think the running of the first one is like the running of Ahimaaz the son of Zadok.”

The king said, “He is a good man, and comes with good news.”

28 Ahimaaz called, and said to the king, “All is well.” He bowed himself before the king with his face to the earth, and said, “Blessed is Yahweh your God, who has delivered up the men who lifted up their hand against my lord the king!”

29 The king said, “Is it well with the young man Absalom?”

Ahimaaz answered, “When Joab sent the king’s servant, even me your servant, I saw a great tumult, but I don’t know what it was.”

30 The king said, “Turn aside, and stand here.” He turned aside, and stood still.

31 Behold, the Cushite came. The Cushite said, “News for my lord the king, for Yahweh has avenged you today of all those who rose up against you.”

32 The king said to the Cushite, “Is it well with the young man Absalom?”

The Cushite answered, “May the enemies of my lord the king, and all who rise up against you to do you harm, be as that young man is.”

33 The king was much moved, and went up to the room over the gate, and wept. As he went, he said, “My son Absalom! My son, my son Absalom! I wish I had died for you, Absalom, my son, my son!”

2 Samuel 20

1 There happened to be there a base fellow, whose name was Sheba, the son of Bichri, a Benjamite; and he blew the trumpet, and said, “We have no portion in David, neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse. Every man to his tents, Israel!”

2 So all the men of Israel went up from following David, and followed Sheba the son of Bichri; but the men of Judah joined with their king, from the Jordan even to Jerusalem. 3 David came to his house at Jerusalem; and the king took the ten women his concubines, whom he had left to keep the house, and put them in custody, and provided them with sustenance, but didn’t go in to them. So they were shut up to the day of their death, living in widowhood.

4 Then the king said to Amasa, “Call me the men of Judah together within three days, and be here present.”

5 So Amasa went to call the men of Judah together; but he stayed longer than the set time which he had appointed him. 6 David said to Abishai, “Now Sheba the son of Bichri will do us more harm than Absalom did. Take your lord’s servants, and pursue after him, lest he get himself fortified cities, and escape out of our sight.”

7 Joab’s men went out after him, and the Cherethites and the Pelethites, and all the mighty men; and they went out of Jerusalem, to pursue Sheba the son of Bichri. 8 When they were at the great stone which is in Gibeon, Amasa came to meet them. Joab was clothed in his apparel of war that he had put on, and on it was a sash with a sword fastened on his waist in its sheath; and as he went along it fell out. 9 Joab said to Amasa, “Is it well with you, my brother?” Joab took Amasa by the beard with his right hand to kiss him. 10 But Amasa took no heed to the sword that was in Joab’s hand. So he struck him with it in the body, and shed out his bowels to the ground, and didn’t strike him again; and he died. Joab and Abishai his brother pursued Sheba the son of Bichri. 11 One of Joab’s young men stood by him, and said, “He who favors Joab, and he who is for David, let him follow Joab!”

12 Amasa lay wallowing in his blood in the middle of the highway. When the man saw that all the people stood still, he carried Amasa out of the highway into the field, and cast a garment over him, when he saw that everyone who came by him stood still. 13 When he was removed out of the highway, all the people went on after Joab, to pursue Sheba the son of Bichri. 14 He went through all the tribes of Israel to Abel, and to Beth Maacah, and all the Berites. They were gathered together, and went also after him. 15 They came and besieged him in Abel of Beth Maacah, and they cast up a mound against the city, and it stood against the rampart; and all the people who were with Joab battered the wall, to throw it down. 16 Then a wise woman cried out of the city, “Hear, hear! Please say to Joab, ‘Come near here, that I may speak with you.’” 17 He came near to her; and the woman said, “Are you Joab?”

He answered, “I am.”

Then she said to him, “Hear the words of your servant.”

He answered, “I’m listening.”

18 Then she spoke, saying, “They used to say in old times, ‘They shall surely ask counsel at Abel;’ and so they settled a matter. 19 I am among those who are peaceable and faithful in Israel. You seek to destroy a city and a mother in Israel. Why will you swallow up Yahweh’s inheritance?”

20 Joab answered, “Far be it, far be it from me, that I should swallow up or destroy. 21 The matter is not so. But a man of the hill country of Ephraim, Sheba the son of Bichri by name, has lifted up his hand against the king, even against David. Just deliver him, and I will depart from the city.”

The woman said to Joab, “Behold, his head will be thrown to you over the wall.”

22 Then the woman went to all the people in her wisdom. They cut off the head of Sheba the son of Bichri, and threw it out to Joab. He blew the trumpet, and they were dispersed from the city, every man to his tent. Then Joab returned to Jerusalem to the king. 23 Now Joab was over all the army of Israel, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and over the Pelethites, 24 Adoram was over the men subject to forced labor, Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was the recorder, 25 Sheva was scribe, and Zadok and Abiathar were priests, 26 and Ira the Jairite was chief minister to David.

2 Samuel 21

1 There was a famine in the days of David for three years, year after year; and David sought the face of Yahweh. Yahweh said, “It is for Saul, and for his bloody house, because he put the Gibeonites to death.”

2 The king called the Gibeonites, and said to them (now the Gibeonites were not of the children of Israel, but of the remnant of the Amorites, and the children of Israel had sworn to them; and Saul sought to kill them in his zeal for the children of Israel and Judah); 3 and David said to the Gibeonites, “What should I do for you? And with what should I make atonement, that you may bless Yahweh’s inheritance?”

4 The Gibeonites said to him, “It is no matter of silver or gold between us and Saul, or his house; neither is it for us to put any man to death in Israel.”

He said, “Whatever you say, that I will do for you.”

5 They said to the king, “The man who consumed us, and who devised against us, that we should be destroyed from remaining in any of the borders of Israel, 6 let seven men of his sons be delivered to us, and we will hang them up to Yahweh in Gibeah of Saul, the chosen of Yahweh.”

The king said, “I will give them.”

7 But the king spared Mephibosheth, the son of Jonathan the son of Saul, because of Yahweh’s oath that was between them, between David and Jonathan the son of Saul. 8 But the king took the two sons of Rizpah the daughter of Aiah, whom she bore to Saul, Armoni and Mephibosheth; and the five sons of Michal the daughter of Saul, whom she bore to Adriel the son of Barzillai the Meholathite. 9 He delivered them into the hands of the Gibeonites, and they hanged them on the mountain before Yahweh, and all seven of them fell together. They were put to death in the days of harvest, in the first days, at the beginning of barley harvest. 10 Rizpah the daughter of Aiah took sackcloth, and spread it for herself on the rock, from the beginning of harvest until water poured on them from the sky. She allowed neither the birds of the sky to rest on them by day, nor the animals of the field by night. 11 David was told what Rizpah the daughter of Aiah, the concubine of Saul, had done. 12 So David went and took the bones of Saul and the bones of Jonathan his son from the men of Jabesh Gilead, who had stolen them from the street of Beth Shan, where the Philistines had hanged them, in the day that the Philistines killed Saul in Gilboa; 13 and he brought up from there the bones of Saul and the bones of Jonathan his son. They also gathered the bones of those who were hanged. 14 They buried the bones of Saul and Jonathan his son in the country of Benjamin in Zela, in the tomb of Kish his father: and they performed all that the king commanded. After that, God answered prayer for the land.

15 The Philistines had war again with Israel; and David went down, and his servants with him, and fought against the Philistines. David grew faint; 16 and Ishbibenob, who was of the sons of the giant, the weight of whose spear was three hundred shekels of brass in weight, he being armed with a new sword, thought he would kill David. 17 But Abishai the son of Zeruiah helped him, and struck the Philistine, and killed him. Then the men of David swore to him, saying, “Don’t go out with us to battle any more, so that you don’t quench the lamp of Israel.”

18 After this, that there was again war with the Philistines at Gob. Then Sibbecai the Hushathite killed Saph, who was of the sons of the giant. 19 There was again war with the Philistines at Gob; and Elhanan the son of Jaare-Oregim the Bethlehemite killed Goliath the Gittite’s brother, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver’s beam. 20 There was again war at Gath, where there was a man of great stature, who had six fingers on every hand, and six toes on every foot, twenty four in count; and he also was born to the giant. 21 When he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimei, David’s brother, killed him. 22 These four were born to the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.

2 Samuel 22

1 David spoke to Yahweh the words of this song in the day that Yahweh delivered him out of the hand of all his enemies, and out of the hand of Saul, 2 and he said:

“Yahweh is my rock,

my fortress,

and my deliverer, even mine;

3 God is my rock in whom I take refuge;

my shield, and the horn of my salvation,

my high tower, and my refuge.

My savior, you save me from violence.

4 I call on Yahweh, who is worthy to be praised;

So shall I be saved from my enemies.

5 For the waves of death surrounded me.

The floods of ungodliness made me afraid.

6 The cords of Sheol[*] were around me.

The snares of death caught me.

7 In my distress, I called on Yahweh.

Yes, I called to my God.

He heard my voice out of his temple.

My cry came into his ears.

8 Then the earth shook and trembled.

The foundations of heaven quaked and were shaken,

because he was angry.

9 Smoke went up out of his nostrils.

Consuming fire came out of his mouth.

Coals were kindled by it.

10 He bowed the heavens also, and came down.

Thick darkness was under his feet.

11 He rode on a cherub, and flew.

Yes, he was seen on the wings of the wind.

12 He made darkness a shelter around himself:

gathering of waters, and thick clouds of the skies.

13 At the brightness before him,

coals of fire were kindled.

14 Yahweh thundered from heaven.

The Most High uttered his voice.

15 He sent out arrows, and scattered them;

lightning, and confused them.

16 Then the channels of the sea appeared.

The foundations of the world were laid bare by Yahweh’s rebuke,

at the blast of the breath of his nostrils.

17 He sent from on high and he took me.

He drew me out of many waters.

18 He delivered me from my strong enemy,

from those who hated me, for they were too mighty for me.

19 They came on me in the day of my calamity,

but Yahweh was my support.

20 He also brought me out into a large place.

He delivered me, because he delighted in me.

21 Yahweh rewarded me according to my righteousness.

He rewarded me according to the cleanness of my hands.

22 For I have kept Yahweh’s ways,

and have not wickedly departed from my God.

23 For all his ordinances were before me.

As for his statutes, I did not depart from them.

24 I was also perfect toward him.

I kept myself from my iniquity.

25 Therefore Yahweh has rewarded me according to my righteousness,

According to my cleanness in his eyesight.

26 With the merciful you will show yourself merciful.

With the perfect man you will show yourself perfect.

27 With the pure you will show yourself pure.

With the crooked you will show yourself shrewd.

28 You will save the afflicted people,

But your eyes are on the haughty, that you may bring them down.

29 For you are my lamp, Yahweh.

Yahweh will light up my darkness.

30 For by you, I run against a troop.

By my God, I leap over a wall.

31 As for God, his way is perfect.

Yahweh’s word is tested.

He is a shield to all those who take refuge in him.

32 For who is God, besides Yahweh?

Who is a rock, besides our God?

33 God is my strong fortress.

He makes my way perfect.

34 He makes his feet like hinds’ feet,

and sets me on my high places.

35 He teaches my hands to war,

so that my arms bend a bow of brass.

36 You have also given me the shield of your salvation.

Your gentleness has made me great.

37 You have enlarged my steps under me.

My feet have not slipped.

38 I have pursued my enemies and destroyed them.

I didn’t turn again until they were consumed.

39 I have consumed them,

and struck them through,

so that they can’t arise.

Yes, they have fallen under my feet.

40 For you have armed me with strength for the battle.

You have subdued under me those who rose up against me.

41 You have also made my enemies turn their backs to me,

that I might cut off those who hate me.

42 They looked, but there was no one to save;

even to Yahweh, but he didn’t answer them.

43 Then I beat them as small as the dust of the earth.

I crushed them as the mire of the streets, and spread them abroad.

44 You also have delivered me from the strivings of my people.

You have kept me to be the head of the nations.

A people whom I have not known will serve me.

45 The foreigners will submit themselves to me.

As soon as they hear of me, they will obey me.

46 The foreigners will fade away,

and will come trembling out of their close places.

47 Yahweh lives!

Blessed be my rock!

Exalted be God, the rock of my salvation,

48 even the God who executes vengeance for me,

who brings down peoples under me,

49 who brings me away from my enemies.

Yes, you lift me up above those who rise up against me.

You deliver me from the violent man.

50 Therefore I will give thanks to you, Yahweh, among the nations,

and will sing praises to your name.

51 He gives great deliverance to his king,

and shows loving kindness to his anointed,

to David and to his offspring,[*] forever more.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

or, seed

2 Samuel 23

1 Now these are the last words of David.

David the son of Jesse says,

the man who was raised on high says,

the anointed of the God of Jacob,

the sweet psalmist of Israel:

2 “Yahweh’s Spirit spoke by me.

His word was on my tongue.

3 The God of Israel said,

the Rock of Israel spoke to me,

‘One who rules over men righteously,

who rules in the fear of God,

4 shall be as the light of the morning, when the sun rises,

a morning without clouds,

when the tender grass springs out of the earth,

through clear shining after rain.’

5 Most certainly my house is not so with God,

yet he has made with me an everlasting covenant,

ordered in all things, and sure,

for it is all my salvation, and all my desire,

although he doesn’t make it grow.

6 But all the ungodly will be as thorns to be thrust away,

because they can’t be taken with the hand,

7 But the man who touches them must be armed with iron and the staff of a spear.

They will be utterly burned with fire in their place.”

8 These are the names of the mighty men whom David had: Josheb Basshebeth a Tahchemonite, chief of the captains; the same was Adino the Eznite, against eight hundred slain at one time. 9 After him was Eleazar the son of Dodai the son of an Ahohite, one of the three mighty men with David, when they defied the Philistines who were there gathered together to battle, and the men of Israel had gone away. 10 He arose and struck the Philistines until his hand was weary, and his hand froze to the sword; and Yahweh worked a great victory that day; and the people returned after him only to take plunder. 11 After him was Shammah the son of Agee a Hararite. The Philistines had gathered together into a troop, where there was a plot of ground full of lentils; and the people fled from the Philistines. 12 But he stood in the middle of the plot and defended it, and killed the Philistines; and Yahweh worked a great victory. 13 Three of the thirty chief men went down, and came to David in the harvest time to the cave of Adullam; and the troop of the Philistines was encamped in the valley of Rephaim. 14 David was then in the stronghold; and the garrison of the Philistines was then in Bethlehem. 15 David longed, and said, “Oh that someone would give me water to drink from the well of Bethlehem, which is by the gate!”

16 The three mighty men broke through the army of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Bethlehem that was by the gate, and took it and brought it to David; but he would not drink of it, but poured it out to Yahweh. 17 He said, “Be it far from me, Yahweh, that I should do this! Isn’t this the blood of the men who risked their lives to go?” Therefore he would not drink it. The three mighty men did these things.

18 Abishai, the brother of Joab, the son of Zeruiah, was chief of the three. He lifted up his spear against three hundred and killed them, and had a name among the three. 19 Wasn’t he most honorable of the three? therefore he was made their captain. However he wasn’t included as one of the three. 20 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done mighty deeds, killed the two sons of Ariel of Moab. He also went down and killed a lion in the middle of a pit in a time of snow. 21 He killed a huge Egyptian, and the Egyptian had a spear in his hand; but he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian’s hand, and killed him with his own spear. 22 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada did these things, and had a name among the three mighty men. 23 He was more honorable than the thirty, but he didn’t attain to the three. David set him over his guard. 24 Asahel the brother of Joab was one of the thirty: Elhanan the son of Dodo of Bethlehem, 25 Shammah the Harodite, Elika the Harodite, 26 Helez the Paltite, Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, 27 Abiezer the Anathothite, Mebunnai the Hushathite, 28 Zalmon the Ahohite, Maharai the Netophathite, 29 Heleb the son of Baanah the Netophathite, Ittai the son of Ribai of Gibeah of the children of Benjamin, 30 Benaiah a Pirathonite, Hiddai of the brooks of Gaash. 31 Abialbon the Arbathite, Azmaveth the Barhumite, 32 Eliahba the Shaalbonite, the sons of Jashen, Jonathan, 33 Shammah the Hararite, Ahiam the son of Sharar the Ararite, 34 Eliphelet the son of Ahasbai, the son of the Maacathite, Eliam the son of Ahithophel the Gilonite, 35 Hezro the Carmelite, Paarai the Arbite, 36 Igal the son of Nathan of Zobah, Bani the Gadite, 37 Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Beerothite, armor bearers to Joab the son of Zeruiah, 38 Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, 39 and Uriah the Hittite: thirty-seven in all.

2 Samuel 24

1 Again Yahweh’s anger burned against Israel, and he moved David against them, saying, “Go, count Israel and Judah.” 2 The king said to Joab the captain of the army, who was with him, “Now go back and forth through all the tribes of Israel, from Dan even to Beersheba, and count the people, that I may know the sum of the people.”

3 Joab said to the king, “Now may Yahweh your God add to the people, however many they may be, one hundred times; and may the eyes of my lord the king see it. But why does my lord the king delight in this thing?”

4 Notwithstanding, the king’s word prevailed against Joab, and against the captains of the army. Joab and the captains of the army went out from the presence of the king to count the people of Israel. 5 They passed over the Jordan, and encamped in Aroer, on the right side of the city that is in the middle of the valley of Gad, and to Jazer; 6 then they came to Gilead, and to the land of Tahtim Hodshi; and they came to Dan Jaan, and around to Sidon, 7 and came to the stronghold of Tyre, and to all the cities of the Hivites, and of the Canaanites; and they went out to the south of Judah, at Beersheba. 8 So when they had gone back and forth through all the land, they came to Jerusalem at the end of nine months and twenty days. 9 Joab gave up the sum of the counting of the people to the king: and there were in Israel eight hundred thousand valiant men who drew the sword; and the men of Judah were five hundred thousand men. 10 David’s heart struck him after he had counted the people. David said to Yahweh, “I have sinned greatly in that which I have done. But now, Yahweh, put away, I beg you, the iniquity of your servant; for I have done very foolishly.”

11 When David rose up in the morning, Yahweh’s word came to the prophet Gad, David’s seer, saying, 12 “Go and speak to David, ‘Yahweh says, “I offer you three things. Choose one of them, that I may do it to you.”’”

13 So Gad came to David, and told him, and said to him, “Shall seven years of famine come to you in your land? Or will you flee three months before your foes while they pursue you? Or shall there be three days’ pestilence in your land? Now answer, and consider what answer I shall return to him who sent me.”

14 David said to Gad, “I am in distress. Let us fall now into Yahweh’s hand; for his mercies are great. Let me not fall into man’s hand.”

15 So Yahweh sent a pestilence on Israel from the morning even to the appointed time; and seventy thousand men died of the people from Dan even to Beersheba. 16 When the angel stretched out his hand toward Jerusalem to destroy it, Yahweh relented of the disaster, and said to the angel who destroyed the people, “It is enough. Now withdraw your hand.” Yahweh’s angel was by the threshing floor of Araunah the Jebusite.

17 David spoke to Yahweh when he saw the angel who struck the people, and said, “Behold, I have sinned, and I have done perversely; but these sheep, what have they done? Please let your hand be against me, and against my father’s house.”

18 Gad came that day to David, and said to him, “Go up, build an altar to Yahweh on the threshing floor of Araunah the Jebusite.”

19 David went up according to the saying of Gad, as Yahweh commanded. 20 Araunah looked out, and saw the king and his servants coming on toward him. Then Araunah went out, and bowed himself before the king with his face to the ground. 21 Araunah said, “Why has my lord the king come to his servant?”

David said, “To buy your threshing floor, to build an altar to Yahweh, that the plague may be stopped from afflicting the people.”

22 Araunah said to David, “Let my lord the king take and offer up what seems good to him. Behold, the cattle for the burnt offering, and the threshing instruments and the yokes of the oxen for the wood. 23 All this, O king, does Araunah give to the king.” Araunah said to the king, “May Yahweh your God accept you.”

24 The king said to Araunah, “No; but I will most certainly buy it from you for a price. I will not offer burnt offerings to Yahweh my God which cost me nothing.” So David bought the threshing floor and the oxen for fifty shekels[*] of silver. 25 David built an altar to Yahweh there, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings. So Yahweh was entreated for the land, and the plague was removed from Israel.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces, so 50 shekels is about 0.5 kilograms or 1.1 pounds.

1 Kings 1

1 Now king David was old and advanced in years; and they covered him with clothes, but he couldn’t keep warm. 2 Therefore his servants said to him, “Let a young virgin be sought for my lord the king. Let her stand before the king, and cherish him; and let her lie in your bosom, that my lord the king may keep warm.” 3 So they sought for a beautiful young lady throughout all the borders of Israel, and found Abishag the Shunammite, and brought her to the king. 4 The young lady was very beautiful; and she cherished the king, and served him; but the king didn’t know her intimately.

5 Then Adonijah the son of Haggith exalted himself, saying, “I will be king.” Then he prepared him chariots and horsemen, and fifty men to run before him. 6 His father had not displeased him at any time in saying, “Why have you done so?” and he was also a very handsome man; and he was born after Absalom. 7 He conferred with Joab the son of Zeruiah, and with Abiathar the priest; and they followed Adonijah and helped him. 8 But Zadok the priest, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, Nathan the prophet, Shimei, Rei, and the mighty men who belonged to David, were not with Adonijah. 9 Adonijah killed sheep, cattle, and fatlings by the stone of Zoheleth, which is beside En Rogel; and he called all his brothers, the king’s sons, and all the men of Judah, the king’s servants; 10 but he didn’t call Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah, and the mighty men, and Solomon his brother. 11 Then Nathan spoke to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon, saying, “Haven’t you heard that Adonijah the son of Haggith reigns, and David our lord doesn’t know it? 12 Now therefore come, please let me give you counsel, that you may save your own life, and your son Solomon’s life. 13 Go in to king David, and tell him, ‘Didn’t you, my lord, king, swear to your servant, saying, “Assuredly Solomon your son shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne?” Why then does Adonijah reign?’ 14 Behold,[*] while you are still talking there with the king, I will also come in after you and confirm your words.”

15 Bathsheba went in to the king in his room. The king was very old; and Abishag the Shunammite was serving the king. 16 Bathsheba bowed, and showed respect to the king. The king said, “What would you like?”

17 She said to him, “My lord, you swore by Yahweh[*] your God[*] to your servant, ‘Assuredly Solomon your son shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne.’ 18 Now, behold, Adonijah reigns; and you, my lord the king, don’t know it. 19 He has slain cattle and fatlings and sheep in abundance, and has called all the sons of the king, Abiathar the priest, and Joab the captain of the army; but he hasn’t called Solomon your servant. 20 You, my lord the king, the eyes of all Israel are on you, that you should tell them who will sit on the throne of my lord the king after him. 21 Otherwise it will happen, when my lord the king sleeps with his fathers, that I and my son Solomon will be considered criminals.”

22 Behold, while she was still talking with the king, Nathan the prophet came in. 23 They told the king, saying, “Behold, Nathan the prophet!”

When he had come in before the king, he bowed himself before the king with his face to the ground. 24 Nathan said, “My lord, king, have you said, ‘Adonijah shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne?’ 25 For he has gone down today, and has slain cattle, fatlings, and sheep in abundance, and has called all the king’s sons, the captains of the army, and Abiathar the priest. Behold, they are eating and drinking before him, and saying, ‘Long live king Adonijah!’ 26 But he hasn’t called me, even me your servant, Zadok the priest, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and your servant Solomon. 27 Was this thing done by my lord the king, and you haven’t shown to your servants who should sit on the throne of my lord the king after him?”

28 Then king David answered, “Call Bathsheba in to me.” She came into the king’s presence and stood before the king. 29 The king swore, and said, “As Yahweh lives, who has redeemed my soul out of all adversity, 30 most certainly as I swore to you by Yahweh, the God of Israel, saying, ‘Assuredly Solomon your son shall reign after me, and he shall sit on my throne in my place;’ I will most certainly do this today.”

31 Then Bathsheba bowed with her face to the earth, and showed respect to the king, and said, “Let my lord king David live forever!”

32 King David said, “Call to me Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada.” They came before the king. 33 The king said to them, “Take with you the servants of your lord, and cause Solomon my son to ride on my own mule, and bring him down to Gihon. 34 Let Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anoint him there king over Israel. Blow the trumpet, and say, ‘Long live king Solomon!’ 35 Then come up after him, and he shall come and sit on my throne; for he shall be king in my place. I have appointed him to be prince over Israel and over Judah.”

36 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada answered the king, and said, “Amen. May Yahweh, the God of my lord the king, say so. 37 As Yahweh has been with my lord the king, even so may he be with Solomon, and make his throne greater than the throne of my lord king David.”

38 So Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the Cherethites and the Pelethites went down and had Solomon ride on king David’s mule, and brought him to Gihon. 39 Zadok the priest took the horn of oil from the Tent, and anointed Solomon. They blew the trumpet; and all the people said, “Long live king Solomon!”

40 All the people came up after him, and the people piped with pipes, and rejoiced with great joy, so that the earth shook with their sound. 41 Adonijah and all the guests who were with him heard it as they had finished eating. When Joab heard the sound of the trumpet, he said, “Why is this noise of the city being in an uproar?”

42 While he yet spoke, behold, Jonathan the son of Abiathar the priest came; and Adonijah said, “Come in; for you are a worthy man, and bring good news.”

43 Jonathan answered Adonijah, “Most certainly our lord king David has made Solomon king. 44 The king has sent with him Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and they have caused him to ride on the king’s mule. 45 Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet have anointed him king in Gihon. They have come up from there rejoicing, so that the city rang again. This is the noise that you have heard. 46 Also, Solomon sits on the throne of the kingdom. 47 Moreover the king’s servants came to bless our lord king David, saying, ‘May your God make the name of Solomon better than your name, and make his throne greater than your throne;’ and the king bowed himself on the bed. 48 Also thus said the king, ‘Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, who has given one to sit on my throne today, my eyes even seeing it.’”

49 All the guests of Adonijah were afraid, and rose up, and each man went his way. 50 Adonijah was afraid because of Solomon; and he arose, and went, and hung onto the horns of the altar. 51 Solomon was told, “Behold, Adonijah fears king Solomon; for, behold, he is hanging onto the horns of the altar, saying, ‘Let king Solomon swear to me first that he will not kill his servant with the sword.’”

52 Solomon said, “If he shows himself a worthy man, not a hair of his shall fall to the earth; but if wickedness is found in him, he shall die.”

53 So king Solomon sent, and they brought him down from the altar. He came and bowed down to king Solomon; and Solomon said to him, “Go to your house.”

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

1 Kings 2

1 Now the days of David came near that he should die; and he commanded Solomon his son, saying, 2 “I am going the way of all the earth. You be strong therefore, and show yourself a man; 3 and keep the instruction of Yahweh your God, to walk in his ways, to keep his statutes, his commandments, his ordinances, and his testimonies, according to that which is written in the law of Moses, that you may prosper in all that you do, and wherever you turn yourself. 4 Then Yahweh may establish his word which he spoke concerning me, saying, ‘If your children are careful of their way, to walk before me in truth with all their heart and with all their soul, there shall not fail you,’ he said, ‘a man on the throne of Israel.’

5 “Moreover you know also what Joab the son of Zeruiah did to me, even what he did to the two captains of the armies of Israel, to Abner the son of Ner, and to Amasa the son of Jether, whom he killed, and shed the blood of war in peace, and put the blood of war on his sash that was around his waist, and in his shoes that were on his feet. 6 Do therefore according to your wisdom, and don’t let his gray head go down to Sheol[*] in peace. 7 But show kindness to the sons of Barzillai the Gileadite, and let them be among those who eat at your table; for so they came to me when I fled from Absalom your brother.

8 “Behold, there is with you Shimei the son of Gera, the Benjamite, of Bahurim, who cursed me with a grievous curse in the day when I went to Mahanaim; but he came down to meet me at the Jordan, and I swore to him by Yahweh, saying, ‘I will not put you to death with the sword.’ 9 Now therefore don’t hold him guiltless, for you are a wise man; and you will know what you ought to do to him, and you shall bring his gray head down to Sheol[*] with blood.”

10 David slept with his fathers, and was buried in David’s city. 11 The days that David reigned over Israel were forty years; he reigned seven years in Hebron, and he reigned thirty-three years in Jerusalem. 12 Solomon sat on David his father’s throne; and his kingdom was firmly established.

13 Then Adonijah the son of Haggith came to Bathsheba the mother of Solomon. She said, “Do you come peaceably?”

He said, “Peaceably. 14 He said moreover, I have something to tell you.”

She said, “Say on.”

15 He said, “You know that the kingdom was mine, and that all Israel set their faces on me, that I should reign. However the kingdom is turned around, and has become my brother’s; for it was his from Yahweh. 16 Now I ask one petition of you. Don’t deny me.”

She said to him, “Say on.” 17 He said, “Please speak to Solomon the king (for he will not tell you ‘no’), that he give me Abishag the Shunammite as wife.”

18 Bathsheba said, “Alright. I will speak for you to the king.”

19 Bathsheba therefore went to king Solomon, to speak to him for Adonijah. The king rose up to meet her, and bowed himself to her, and sat down on his throne, and caused a throne to be set for the king’s mother; and she sat on his right hand. 20 Then she said, “I ask one small petition of you; don’t deny me.”

The king said to her, “Ask on, my mother; for I will not deny you.”

21 She said, “Let Abishag the Shunammite be given to Adonijah your brother as wife.”

22 King Solomon answered his mother, “Why do you ask Abishag the Shunammite for Adonijah? Ask for him the kingdom also; for he is my elder brother; even for him, and for Abiathar the priest, and for Joab the son of Zeruiah.” 23 Then king Solomon swore by Yahweh, saying, “God do so to me, and more also, if Adonijah has not spoken this word against his own life. 24 Now therefore as Yahweh lives, who has established me, and set me on my father David’s throne, and who has made me a house as he promised, surely Adonijah shall be put to death today.”

25 King Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he fell on him, so that he died. 26 To Abiathar the priest the king said, “Go to Anathoth, to your own fields; for you are worthy of death. But I will not at this time put you to death, because you bore the Lord[*] Yahweh’s ark before David my father, and because you were afflicted in all in which my father was afflicted.” 27 So Solomon thrust Abiathar out from being priest to Yahweh, that he might fulfill Yahweh’s word, which he spoke concerning the house of Eli in Shiloh.

28 This news came to Joab; for Joab had followed Adonijah, although he didn’t follow Absalom. Joab fled to Yahweh’s Tent, and held onto the horns of the altar. 29 King Solomon was told, “Joab has fled to Yahweh’s Tent, and behold, he is by the altar.” Then Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, saying, “Go, fall on him.”

30 Benaiah came to Yahweh’s Tent, and said to him, “Thus says the king, ‘Come out!’”

He said, “No; but I will die here.”

Benaiah brought the king word again, saying, “Thus said Joab, and thus he answered me.”

31 The king said to him, “Do as he has said, and fall on him, and bury him; that you may take away the blood, which Joab shed without cause, from me and from my father’s house. 32 Yahweh will return his blood on his own head, because he fell on two men more righteous and better than he, and killed them with the sword, and my father David didn’t know it: Abner the son of Ner, captain of the army of Israel, and Amasa the son of Jether, captain of the army of Judah. 33 So their blood will return on the head of Joab, and on the head of his offspring[*] forever. But for David, for his offspring,[*] for his house, and for his throne, there will be peace forever from Yahweh.”

34 Then Benaiah the son of Jehoiada went up and fell on him, and killed him; and he was buried in his own house in the wilderness. 35 The king put Benaiah the son of Jehoiada in his place over the army; and the king put Zadok the priest in the place of Abiathar. 36 The king sent and called for Shimei, and said to him, “Build yourself a house in Jerusalem, and live there, and don’t go anywhere else. 37 For on the day you go out and pass over the brook Kidron, know for certain that you will surely die. Your blood will be on your own head.”

38 Shimei said to the king, “What you say is good. As my lord the king has said, so will your servant do.” Shimei lived in Jerusalem many days.

39 At the end of three years, two of Shimei’s slaves ran away to Achish, son of Maacah, king of Gath. They told Shimei, saying, “Behold, your slaves are in Gath.”

40 Shimei arose, saddled his donkey, and went to Gath to Achish, to seek his slaves; and Shimei went, and brought his slaves from Gath. 41 Solomon was told that Shimei had gone from Jerusalem to Gath, and had come again.

42 The king sent and called for Shimei, and said to him, “Didn’t I adjure you by Yahweh, and warn you, saying, ‘Know for certain, that on the day you go out, and walk anywhere else, you shall surely die?’ You said to me, ‘The saying that I have heard is good.’ 43 Why then have you not kept the oath of Yahweh, and the commandment that I have instructed you with?” 44 The king said moreover to Shimei, “You know in your heart all the wickedness that you did to David my father. Therefore Yahweh will return your wickedness on your own head. 45 But king Solomon will be blessed, and David’s throne will be established before Yahweh forever.” 46 So the king commanded Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he went out, and fell on him, so that he died. The kingdom was established in the hand of Solomon.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

or, seed

or, seed

1 Kings 3

1 Solomon made an alliance with Pharaoh king of Egypt, and took Pharaoh’s daughter, and brought her into David’s city, until he had finished building his own house, Yahweh’s house, and the wall around Jerusalem. 2 However the people sacrificed in the high places, because there was not yet a house built for Yahweh’s name. 3 Solomon loved Yahweh, walking in the statutes of David his father; except that he sacrificed and burned incense in the high places. 4 The king went to Gibeon to sacrifice there; for that was the great high place. Solomon offered a thousand burnt offerings on that altar. 5 In Gibeon, Yahweh appeared to Solomon in a dream by night; and God said, “Ask for what I should give you.”

6 Solomon said, “You have shown to your servant David my father great loving kindness, because he walked before you in truth, in righteousness, and in uprightness of heart with you. You have kept for him this great loving kindness, that you have given him a son to sit on his throne, as it is today. 7 Now, Yahweh my God, you have made your servant king instead of David my father. I am just a little child. I don’t know how to go out or come in. 8 Your servant is among your people which you have chosen, a great people, that can’t be numbered or counted for multitude. 9 Give your servant therefore an understanding heart to judge your people, that I may discern between good and evil; for who is able to judge this great people of yours?”

10 This request pleased the Lord, that Solomon had asked this thing. 11 God said to him, “Because you have asked this thing, and have not asked for yourself long life, nor have you asked for riches for yourself, nor have you asked for the life of your enemies, but have asked for yourself understanding to discern justice; 12 behold, I have done according to your word. Behold, I have given you a wise and understanding heart; so that there has been no one like you before you, and after you none will arise like you. 13 I have also given you that which you have not asked, both riches and honor, so that there will not be any among the kings like you for all your days. 14 If you will walk in my ways, to keep my statutes and my commandments, as your father David walked, then I will lengthen your days.”

15 Solomon awoke; and behold, it was a dream. Then he came to Jerusalem, and stood before the ark of Yahweh’s covenant, and offered up burnt offerings, offered peace offerings, and made a feast for all his servants.

16 Then two women who were prostitutes came to the king, and stood before him. 17 The one woman said, “Oh, my lord, I and this woman dwell in one house. I delivered a child with her in the house. 18 The third day after I delivered, this woman delivered also. We were together. There was no stranger with us in the house, just us two in the house. 19 This woman’s child died in the night, because she lay on it. 20 She arose at midnight, and took my son from beside me, while your servant slept, and laid it in her bosom, and laid her dead child in my bosom. 21 When I rose in the morning to nurse my child, behold, it was dead; but when I had looked at it in the morning, behold, it was not my son, whom I bore.”

22 The other woman said, “No; but the living one is my son, and the dead one is your son.”

The first one said, “No; but the dead one is your son, and the living one is my son.” Thus they spoke before the king.

23 Then the king said, “One says, ‘This is my son who lives, and your son is the dead;’ and the other says, ‘No; but your son is the dead one, and my son is the living one.’”

24 The king said, “Get me a sword.” So they brought a sword before the king.

25 The king said, “Divide the living child in two, and give half to the one, and half to the other.”

26 Then the woman whose the living child was spoke to the king, for her heart yearned over her son, and she said, “Oh, my lord, give her the living child, and in no way kill him!”

But the other said, “He shall be neither mine nor yours. Divide him.”

27 Then the king answered, “Give her the living child, and definitely do not kill him. She is his mother.”

28 All Israel heard of the judgment which the king had judged; and they feared the king; for they saw that the wisdom of God was in him, to do justice.

1 Kings 4

1 King Solomon was king over all Israel. 2 These were the princes whom he had: Azariah the son of Zadok, the priest; 3 Elihoreph and Ahijah, the sons of Shisha, scribes; Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, the recorder; 4 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the army; Zadok and Abiathar were priests; 5 Azariah the son of Nathan was over the officers; Zabud the son of Nathan was chief minister, the king’s friend; 6 Ahishar was over the household; and Adoniram the son of Abda was over the men subject to forced labor.

7 Solomon had twelve officers over all Israel, who provided food for the king and his household. Each man had to make provision for a month in the year. 8 These are their names: Ben Hur, in the hill country of Ephraim; 9 Ben Deker, in Makaz, in Shaalbim, Beth Shemesh, and Elon Beth Hanan; 10 Ben Hesed, in Arubboth (Socoh and all the land of Hepher belonged to him); 11 Ben Abinadab, in all the height of Dor (he had Taphath, Solomon’s daughter, as wife); 12 Baana the son of Ahilud, in Taanach and Megiddo, and all Beth Shean which is beside Zarethan, beneath Jezreel, from Beth Shean to Abel Meholah, as far as beyond Jokmeam; 13 Ben Geber, in Ramoth Gilead (the towns of Jair the son of Manasseh, which are in Gilead, belonged to him; and the region of Argob, which is in Bashan, sixty great cities with walls and bronze bars, belonged to him); 14 Ahinadab the son of Iddo, in Mahanaim; 15 Ahimaaz, in Naphtali (he also took Basemath the daughter of Solomon as wife); 16 Baana the son of Hushai, in Asher and Bealoth; 17 Jehoshaphat the son of Paruah, in Issachar; 18 Shimei the son of Ela, in Benjamin; 19 Geber the son of Uri, in the land of Gilead, the country of Sihon king of the Amorites and of Og king of Bashan; and he was the only officer who was in the land.

20 Judah and Israel were numerous as the sand which is by the sea in multitude, eating and drinking and making merry. 21 Solomon ruled over all the kingdoms from the River to the land of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt. They brought tribute and served Solomon all the days of his life. 22 Solomon’s provision for one day was thirty cors[*] of fine flour, sixty measures of meal, 23 ten head of fat cattle, twenty head of cattle out of the pastures, and one hundred sheep, besides deer, and gazelles, and roebucks, and fattened fowl. 24 For he had dominion over all on this side the River, from Tiphsah even to Gaza, over all the kings on this side the River: and he had peace on all sides around him. 25 Judah and Israel lived safely, every man under his vine and under his fig tree, from Dan even to Beersheba, all the days of Solomon. 26 Solomon had forty thousand stalls of horses for his chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen. 27 Those officers provided food for king Solomon, and for all who came to king Solomon’s table, every man in his month. They let nothing be lacking. 28 They also brought Barley and straw for the horses and swift steeds to the place where the officers were, each man according to his duty. 29 God gave Solomon abundant wisdom and understanding, and very great understanding, even as the sand that is on the seashore. 30 Solomon’s wisdom excelled the wisdom of all the children of the east and all the wisdom of Egypt. 31 For he was wiser than all men; than Ethan the Ezrahite, Heman, Calcol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol: and his fame was in all the nations all around. 32 He spoke three thousand proverbs; and his songs numbered one thousand five. 33 He spoke of trees, from the cedar that is in Lebanon even to the hyssop that grows out of the wall; he also spoke of animals, of birds, of creeping things, and of fish. 34 People of all nations came to hear the wisdom of Solomon, sent by all kings of the earth, who had heard of his wisdom.

1 cor is the same as a homer, or about 55.9 U. S. gallons (liquid) or 211 liters or 6 bushels

1 Kings 5

1 Hiram king of Tyre sent his servants to Solomon; for he had heard that they had anointed him king in the place of his father, and Hiram had always loved David. 2 Solomon sent to Hiram, saying, 3 “You know that David my father could not build a house for the name of Yahweh his God because of the wars which were around him on every side, until Yahweh put his enemies under the soles of his feet. 4 But now Yahweh my God has given me rest on every side. There is no enemy and no evil occurrence. 5 Behold, I intend to build a house for the name of Yahweh my God, as Yahweh spoke to David my father, saying, ‘Your son, whom I will set on your throne in your place shall build the house for my name.’ 6 Now therefore command that cedar trees be cut for me out of Lebanon. My servants will be with your servants; and I will give you wages for your servants according to all that you say. For you know that there is nobody among us who knows how to cut timber like the Sidonians.”

7 When Hiram heard the words of Solomon, he rejoiced greatly, and said, “Blessed is Yahweh today, who has given to David a wise son to rule over this great people.” 8 Hiram sent to Solomon, saying, “I have heard the message which you have sent to me. I will do all your desire concerning timber of cedar, and concerning cypress timber. 9 My servants will bring them down from Lebanon to the sea. I will make them into rafts to go by sea to the place that you specify to me, and will cause them to be broken up there, and you will receive them. You will accomplish my desire, in giving food for my household.”

10 So Hiram gave Solomon cedar timber and cypress timber according to all his desire. 11 Solomon gave Hiram twenty thousand cors[*] of wheat for food to his household, and twenty cors[*] of pure oil. Solomon gave this to Hiram year by year. 12 Yahweh gave Solomon wisdom, as he promised him. There was peace between Hiram and Solomon, and the two of them made a treaty together. 13 King Solomon raised a levy out of all Israel; and the levy was thirty thousand men. 14 He sent them to Lebanon, ten thousand a month by courses; for a month they were in Lebanon, and two months at home; and Adoniram was over the men subject to forced labor. 15 Solomon had seventy thousand who bore burdens, and eighty thousand who were stone cutters in the mountains; 16 besides Solomon’s chief officers who were over the work, three thousand and three hundred, who ruled over the people who labored in the work. 17 The king commanded, and they cut out large stones, costly stones, to lay the foundation of the house with worked stone. 18 Solomon’s builders and Hiram’s builders and the Gebalites cut them, and prepared the timber and the stones to build the house.

20,000 cors would be about 120,000 bushels or about 4.2 megaliters of wheat, which would weigh about 3,270 metric tons.

20 cors is about 1,100 gallons or about 4220 liters.

1 Kings 6

1 In the four hundred and eightieth year after the children of Israel had come out of the land of Egypt, in the fourth year of Solomon’s reign over Israel, in the month Ziv, which is the second month, he began to build Yahweh’s house. 2 The house which king Solomon built for Yahweh had a length of sixty cubits,[*] and its width twenty, and its height thirty cubits. 3 The porch in front of the temple of the house had a length of twenty cubits, which was along the width of the house. Ten cubits was its width in front of the house. 4 He made windows of fixed lattice work for the house. 5 Against the wall of the house, he built floors all around, against the walls of the house all around, both of the temple and of the inner sanctuary; and he made side rooms all around. 6 The lowest floor was five cubits wide, and the middle was six cubits wide, and the third was seven cubits wide; for on the outside he made offsets in the wall of the house all around, that the beams should not be inserted into the walls of the house. 7 The house, when it was under construction, was built of stone prepared at the quarry; and no hammer or ax or any tool of iron was heard in the house while it was under construction. 8 The door for the middle side rooms was in the right side of the house. They went up by winding stairs into the middle floor, and out of the middle into the third. 9 So he built the house, and finished it; and he covered the house with beams and planks of cedar. 10 He built the floors all along the house, each five cubits high; and they rested on the house with timber of cedar.

11 Yahweh’s word came to Solomon, saying, 12 “Concerning this house which you are building, if you will walk in my statutes, and execute my ordinances, and keep all my commandments to walk in them; then I will establish my word with you, which I spoke to David your father. 13 I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will not forsake my people Israel.”

14 So Solomon built the house, and finished it. 15 He built the walls of the house within with boards of cedar: from the floor of the house to the walls of the ceiling, he covered them on the inside with wood; and he covered the floor of the house with cypress boards. 16 He built twenty cubits on the back part of the house with boards of cedar from the floor to the ceiling. He built them for it within, for an inner sanctuary, even for the most holy place. 17 In front of the temple sanctuary was forty cubits. 18 There was cedar on the house within, carved with buds and open flowers. All was cedar. No stone was visible. 19 He prepared an inner sanctuary in the middle of the house within, to set the ark of Yahweh’s covenant there. 20 Within the inner sanctuary was twenty cubits in length, and twenty cubits in width, and twenty cubits in its height; and he overlaid it with pure gold; and he covered the altar with cedar. 21 So Solomon overlaid the house within with pure gold. He drew chains of gold across before the inner sanctuary, and he overlaid it with gold. 22 He overlaid the whole house with gold, until all the house was finished. He also overlaid the whole altar that belonged to the inner sanctuary with gold. 23 In the inner sanctuary he made two cherubim[*] of olive wood, each ten cubits high. 24 Five cubits was the one wing of the cherub, and five cubits the other wing of the cherub. From the tip of one wing to the tip of the other was ten cubits. 25 The other cherub was ten cubits. Both the cherubim were of one measure and one form. 26 One cherub was ten cubits high, and so was the other cherub. 27 He set the cherubim within the inner house. The wings of the cherubim were stretched out, so that the wing of the one touched the one wall, and the wing of the other cherub touched the other wall; and their wings touched one another in the middle of the house. 28 He overlaid the cherubim with gold. 29 He carved all the walls of the house around with carved figures of cherubim, palm trees, and open flowers, inside and outside. 30 He overlaid the floor of the house with gold, inside and outside. 31 For the entrance of the inner sanctuary, he made doors of olive wood. The lintel and door posts were a fifth part of the wall. 32 So he made two doors of olive wood; and he carved on them carvings of cherubim, palm trees, and open flowers, and overlaid them with gold. He spread the gold on the cherubim and on the palm trees. 33 He also did so for the entrance of the temple door posts of olive wood, out of a fourth part of the wall; 34 and two doors of cypress wood. The two leaves of the one door were folding, and the two leaves of the other door were folding. 35 He carved cherubim, palm trees, and open flowers; and he overlaid them with gold fitted on the engraved work. 36 He built the inner court with three courses of cut stone and a course of cedar beams. 37 The foundation of Yahweh’s house was laid in the fourth year, in the month Ziv. 38 In the eleventh year, in the month Bul, which is the eighth month, the house was finished throughout all its parts, and according to all its specifications. So he spent seven years building it.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

“Cherubim” is plural of “cherub”, an angelic being.

1 Kings 7

1 Solomon was building his own house thirteen years, and he finished all his house. 2 For he built the House of the Forest of Lebanon. Its length was one hundred cubits,[*] its width fifty cubits, and its height thirty cubits, on four rows of cedar pillars, with cedar beams on the pillars. 3 It was covered with cedar above over the forty-five beams, that were on the pillars, fifteen in a row. 4 There were beams in three rows, and window was facing window in three ranks. 5 All the doors and posts were made square with beams: and window was facing window in three ranks. 6 He made the porch of pillars. Its length was fifty cubits and its width thirty cubits; with a porch before them, and pillars and a threshold before them. 7 He made the porch of the throne where he was to judge, even the porch of judgment; and it was covered with cedar from floor to floor. 8 His house where he was to dwell, the other court within the porch, was of the like work. He made also a house for Pharaoh’s daughter (whom Solomon had taken as wife), like this porch. 9 All these were of costly stones, even of cut stone, according to measure, sawed with saws, inside and outside, even from the foundation to the coping, and so on the outside to the great court. 10 The foundation was of costly stones, even great stones, stones of ten cubits, and stones of eight cubits. 11 Above were costly stones, even cut stone, according to measure, and cedar wood. 12 The great court around had three courses of cut stone, and a course of cedar beams; like the inner court of Yahweh’s house and the porch of the house. 13 King Solomon sent and brought Hiram out of Tyre. 14 He was the son of a widow of the tribe of Naphtali, and his father was a man of Tyre, a worker in brass; and he was filled with wisdom and understanding and skill, to work all works in brass. He came to king Solomon, and performed all his work. 15 For he fashioned the two pillars of brass, eighteen cubits high apiece; and a line of twelve cubits encircled either of them. 16 He made two capitals of molten brass, to set on the tops of the pillars. The height of the one capital was five cubits, and the height of the other capital was five cubits. 17 There were nets of checker work, and wreaths of chain work, for the capitals which were on the top of the pillars; seven for the one capital, and seven for the other capital. 18 So he made the pillars; and there were two rows around on the one network, to cover the capitals that were on the top of the pillars: and he did so for the other capital. 19 The capitals that were on the top of the pillars in the porch were of lily work, four cubits. 20 There were capitals above also on the two pillars, close by the belly which was beside the network. There were two hundred pomegranates in rows around the other capital. 21 He set up the pillars at the porch of the temple. He set up the right pillar, and called its name Jachin; and he set up the left pillar, and called its name Boaz. 22 On the top of the pillars was lily work: so the work of the pillars was finished. 23 He made the molten sea of ten cubits from brim to brim, round in shape. Its height was five cubits; and a line of thirty cubits encircled it. 24 Under its brim around there were buds which encircled it for ten cubits, encircling the sea. The buds were in two rows, cast when it was cast. 25 It stood on twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east; and the sea was set on them above, and all their hindquarters were inward. 26 It was a hand width thick. Its brim was worked like the brim of a cup, like the flower of a lily. It held two thousand baths. 27 He made the ten bases of brass. The length of one base was four cubits, four cubits its width, and three cubits its height. 28 The work of the bases was like this: they had panels; and there were panels between the ledges; 29 and on the panels that were between the ledges were lions, oxen, and cherubim; and on the ledges there was a pedestal above; and beneath the lions and oxen were wreaths of hanging work. 30 Every base had four bronze wheels, and axles of brass; and the four feet of it had supports. The supports were cast beneath the basin, with wreaths at the side of each. 31 Its mouth within the capital and above was a cubit. Its mouth was round after the work of a pedestal, a cubit and a half; and also on its mouth were engravings, and their panels were square, not round. 32 The four wheels were underneath the panels; and the axles of the wheels were in the base. The height of a wheel was a cubit and half a cubit. 33 The work of the wheels was like the work of a chariot wheel. Their axles, and their rims, and their spokes, and their naves, were all of cast metal. 34 There were four supports at the four corners of each base. Its supports were of the base itself. 35 In the top of the base there was a round band half a cubit high; and on the top of the base its supports and its panels were of the same. 36 On the plates of its supports, and on its panels, he engraved cherubim, lions, and palm trees, each in its space, with wreaths all around. 37 He made the ten bases in this way: all of them had one casting, one measure, and one form. 38 He made ten basins of brass. One basin contained forty baths;[*] and every basin was four cubits; and on every one of the ten bases one basin. 39 He set the bases, five on the right side of the house, and five on the left side of the house. He set the sea on the right side of the house eastward and toward the south. 40 Hiram made the basins, the shovels, and the basins. So Hiram finished doing all the work that he worked for king Solomon in Yahweh’s house: 41 the two pillars; the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; the two networks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; 42 the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks; two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the pillars; 43 the ten bases; the ten basins on the bases; 44 the one sea; the twelve oxen under the sea; 45 the pots; the shovels; and the basins: even all these vessels, which Hiram made for king Solomon, in Yahweh’s house, were of burnished brass. 46 The king cast them in the plain of the Jordan, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zarethan. 47 Solomon left all the vessels unweighed, because there were so many of them. The weight of the brass could not be determined. 48 Solomon made all the vessels that were in Yahweh’s house: the golden altar and the table that the show bread was on, of gold; 49 and the lamp stands, five on the right side, and five on the left, before the inner sanctuary, of pure gold; and the flowers, the lamps, and the tongs, of gold; 50 the cups, the snuffers, the basins, the spoons, and the fire pans, of pure gold; and the hinges, both for the doors of the inner house, the most holy place, and for the doors of the house, of the temple, of gold. 51 Thus all the work that king Solomon did in Yahweh’s house was finished. Solomon brought in the things which David his father had dedicated, the silver, the gold, and the vessels, and put them in the treasuries of Yahweh’s house.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

1 bath is one tenth of a cor, or about 5.6 U. S. gallons or 21 liters, so 4 baths was about 224 gallons or 840 liters.

1 Kings 8

1 Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, with all the heads of the tribes, the princes of the fathers’ households of the children of Israel, to king Solomon in Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of Yahweh’s covenant out of David’s city, which is Zion. 2 All the men of Israel assembled themselves to king Solomon at the feast, in the month Ethanim, which is the seventh month. 3 All the elders of Israel came, and the priests picked up the ark. 4 They brought up Yahweh’s ark, the Tent of Meeting, and all the holy vessels that were in the Tent. The priests and the Levites brought these up. 5 King Solomon and all the congregation of Israel, who were assembled to him, were with him before the ark, sacrificing sheep and cattle, that could not be counted or numbered for multitude. 6 The priests brought in the ark of Yahweh’s covenant to its place, into the inner sanctuary of the house, to the most holy place, even under the cherubim’s wings. 7 For the cherubim spread their wings out over the place of the ark, and the cherubim covered the ark and its poles above. 8 The poles were so long that the ends of the poles were seen from the holy place before the inner sanctuary; but they were not seen outside. They are there to this day. 9 There was nothing in the ark except the two stone tablets which Moses put there at Horeb, when Yahweh made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of the land of Egypt. 10 It came to pass, when the priests had come out of the holy place, that the cloud filled Yahweh’s house, 11 so that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud; for Yahweh’s glory filled Yahweh’s house. 12 Then Solomon said, “Yahweh has said that he would dwell in the thick darkness. 13 I have surely built you a house of habitation, a place for you to dwell in forever.”

14 The king turned his face around, and blessed all the assembly of Israel; and all the assembly of Israel stood. 15 He said, “Blessed is Yahweh, the God of Israel, who spoke with his mouth to David your father, and has with his hand fulfilled it, saying, 16 ‘Since the day that I brought my people Israel out of Egypt, I chose no city out of all the tribes of Israel to build a house, that my name might be there; but I chose David to be over my people Israel.’

17 “Now it was in the heart of David my father to build a house for the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel. 18 But Yahweh said to David my father, ‘Whereas it was in your heart to build a house for my name, you did well that it was in your heart. 19 Nevertheless, you shall not build the house; but your son who shall come out of your body, he shall build the house for my name.’ 20 Yahweh has established his word that he spoke; for I have risen up in the place of David my father, and I sit on the throne of Israel, as Yahweh promised, and have built the house for the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel. 21 There I have set a place for the ark, in which is Yahweh’s covenant, which he made with our fathers, when he brought them out of the land of Egypt.”

22 Solomon stood before Yahweh’s altar in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and spread out his hands toward heaven; 23 and he said, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, there is no God like you, in heaven above, or on earth beneath; who keeps covenant and loving kindness with your servants, who walk before you with all their heart; 24 who has kept with your servant David my father that which you promised him. Yes, you spoke with your mouth, and have fulfilled it with your hand, as it is today. 25 Now therefore, may Yahweh, the God of Israel, keep with your servant David my father that which you have promised him, saying, ‘There shall not fail from you a man in my sight to sit on the throne of Israel, if only your children take heed to their way, to walk before me as you have walked before me.’

26 “Now therefore, God of Israel, please let your word be verified, which you spoke to your servant David my father. 27 But will God in very deed dwell on the earth? Behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens can’t contain you; how much less this house that I have built! 28 Yet have respect for the prayer of your servant, and for his supplication, Yahweh my God, to listen to the cry and to the prayer which your servant prays before you today; 29 that your eyes may be open toward this house night and day, even toward the place of which you have said, ‘My name shall be there;’ to listen to the prayer which your servant prays toward this place. 30 Listen to the supplication of your servant, and of your people Israel, when they pray toward this place. Yes, hear in heaven, your dwelling place; and when you hear, forgive.

31 “If a man sins against his neighbor, and an oath is laid on him to cause him to swear, and he comes and swears before your altar in this house; 32 then hear in heaven, and act, and judge your servants, condemning the wicked, to bring his way on his own head, and justifying the righteous, to give him according to his righteousness.

33 “When your people Israel are struck down before the enemy, because they have sinned against you; if they turn again to you, and confess your name, and pray and make supplication to you in this house; 34 then hear in heaven, and forgive the sin of your people Israel, and bring them again to the land which you gave to their fathers.

35 “When the sky is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against you; if they pray toward this place, and confess your name, and turn from their sin, when you afflict them, 36 then hear in heaven, and forgive the sin of your servants, and of your people Israel, when you teach them the good way in which they should walk; and send rain on your land, which you have given to your people for an inheritance.

37 “If there is famine in the land, if there is pestilence, if there is blight, mildew, locust or caterpillar; if their enemy besieges them in the land of their cities; whatever plague, whatever sickness there is; 38 whatever prayer and supplication is made by any man, or by all your people Israel, who shall each know the plague of his own heart, and spread out his hands toward this house, 39 then hear in heaven, your dwelling place, and forgive, and act, and give to every man according to all his ways, whose heart you know; (for you, even you only, know the hearts of all the children of men;) 40 that they may fear you all the days that they live in the land which you gave to our fathers.

41 “Moreover concerning the foreigner, who is not of your people Israel, when he comes out of a far country for your name’s sake 42 (for they shall hear of your great name, and of your mighty hand, and of your outstretched arm); when he comes and prays toward this house; 43 hear in heaven, your dwelling place, and do according to all that the foreigner calls to you for; that all the peoples of the earth may know your name, to fear you, as do your people Israel, and that they may know that this house which I have built is called by your name.

44 “If your people go out to battle against their enemy, by whatever way you shall send them, and they pray to Yahweh toward the city which you have chosen, and toward the house which I have built for your name; 45 then hear in heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause. 46 If they sin against you (for there is no man who doesn’t sin), and you are angry with them, and deliver them to the enemy, so that they carry them away captive to the land of the enemy, far off or near; 47 yet if they repent in the land where they are carried captive, and turn again, and make supplication to you in the land of those who carried them captive, saying, ‘We have sinned, and have done perversely; we have dealt wickedly;’ 48 if they return to you with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their enemies, who carried them captive, and pray to you toward their land, which you gave to their fathers, the city which you have chosen, and the house which I have built for your name; 49 then hear their prayer and their supplication in heaven, your dwelling place, and maintain their cause; 50 and forgive your people who have sinned against you, and all their transgressions in which they have transgressed against you; and give them compassion before those who carried them captive, that they may have compassion on them 51 (for they are your people, and your inheritance, which you brought out of Egypt, from the middle of the iron furnace); 52 that your eyes may be open to the supplication of your servant, and to the supplication of your people Israel, to listen to them whenever they cry to you. 53 For you separated them from among all the peoples of the earth, to be your inheritance, as you spoke by Moses your servant, when you brought our fathers out of Egypt, Lord Yahweh.”

54 It was so, that when Solomon had finished praying all this prayer and supplication to Yahweh, he arose from before Yahweh’s altar, from kneeling on his knees with his hands spread out toward heaven. 55 He stood, and blessed all the assembly of Israel with a loud voice, saying, 56 “Blessed be Yahweh, who has given rest to his people Israel, according to all that he promised. There has not failed one word of all his good promise, which he promised by Moses his servant. 57 May Yahweh our God be with us, as he was with our fathers. Let him not leave us or forsake us; 58 that he may incline our hearts to him, to walk in all his ways, and to keep his commandments, and his statutes, and his ordinances, which he commanded our fathers. 59 Let these my words, with which I have made supplication before Yahweh, be near to Yahweh our God day and night, that he may maintain the cause of his servant, and the cause of his people Israel, as every day requires; 60 that all the peoples of the earth may know that Yahweh himself is God. There is no one else.

61 “Let your heart therefore be perfect with Yahweh our God, to walk in his statutes, and to keep his commandments, as it is today.”

62 The king, and all Israel with him, offered sacrifice before Yahweh. 63 Solomon offered for the sacrifice of peace offerings, which he offered to Yahweh, twenty two thousand head of cattle, and one hundred twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the children of Israel dedicated Yahweh’s house. 64 The same day the king made the middle of the court holy that was before Yahweh’s house; for there he offered the burnt offering, and the meal offering, and the fat of the peace offerings, because the bronze altar that was before Yahweh was too little to receive the burnt offering, the meal offering, and the fat of the peace offerings. 65 So Solomon held the feast at that time, and all Israel with him, a great assembly, from the entrance of Hamath to the brook of Egypt, before Yahweh our God, seven days and seven more days, even fourteen days. 66 On the eighth day he sent the people away; and they blessed the king, and went to their tents joyful and glad in their hearts for all the goodness that Yahweh had shown to David his servant, and to Israel his people.

1 Kings 9

1 When Solomon had finished the building of Yahweh’s house, the king’s house, and all Solomon’s desire which he was pleased to do, 2 Yahweh appeared to Solomon the second time, as he had appeared to him at Gibeon. 3 Yahweh said to him, “I have heard your prayer and your supplication, that you have made before me. I have made this house holy, which you have built, to put my name there forever; and my eyes and my heart shall be there perpetually. 4 As for you, if you will walk before me, as David your father walked, in integrity of heart, and in uprightness, to do according to all that I have commanded you, and will keep my statutes and my ordinances; 5 then I will establish the throne of your kingdom over Israel forever, as I promised to David your father, saying, ‘There shall not fail from you a man on the throne of Israel.’ 6 But if you turn away from following me, you or your children, and not keep my commandments and my statutes which I have set before you, but go and serve other gods, and worship them; 7 then I will cut off Israel out of the land which I have given them; and I will cast this house, which I have made holy for my name, out of my sight; and Israel will be a proverb and a byword among all peoples. 8 Though this house is so high, yet everyone who passes by it will be astonished and hiss; and they will say, ‘Why has Yahweh done this to this land, and to this house?’ 9 and they will answer, ‘Because they abandoned Yahweh their God, who brought their fathers out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold of other gods, and worshiped them, and served them. Therefore Yahweh has brought all this evil on them.’”

10 At the end of twenty years, in which Solomon had built the two houses, Yahweh’s house and the king’s house 11 (now Hiram the king of Tyre had furnished Solomon with cedar trees and cypress trees, and with gold, according to all his desire), King Solomon gave Hiram twenty cities in the land of Galilee. 12 Hiram came out of Tyre to see the cities which Solomon had given him; and they didn’t please him. 13 He said, “What cities are these which you have given me, my brother?” He called them the land of Cabul[*] to this day. 14 Hiram sent to the king one hundred twenty talents[*] of gold.

15 This is the reason of the levy which king Solomon raised, to build Yahweh’s house, his own house, Millo, Jerusalem’s wall, Hazor, Megiddo, and Gezer. 16 Pharaoh king of Egypt had gone up, taken Gezer, burned it with fire, killed the Canaanites who lived in the city, and given it for a wedding gift to his daughter, Solomon’s wife. 17 Solomon built in the land Gezer, Beth Horon the lower, 18 Baalath, Tamar in the wilderness, 19 all the storage cities that Solomon had, the cities for his chariots, the cities for his horsemen, and that which Solomon desired to build for his pleasure in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion. 20 As for all the people who were left of the Amorites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, who were not of the children of Israel; 21 their children who were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel were not able utterly to destroy, of them Solomon raised a levy of bondservants to this day. 22 But of the children of Israel Solomon made no bondservants; but they were the men of war, his servants, his princes, his captains, and rulers of his chariots and of his horsemen. 23 These were the five hundred fifty chief officers who were over Solomon’s work, who ruled over the people who labored in the work. 24 But Pharaoh’s daughter came up out of David’s city to her house which Solomon had built for her. Then he built Millo. 25 Solomon offered burnt offerings and peace offerings on the altar which he built to Yahweh three times per year, burning incense with them, on the altar that was before Yahweh. So he finished the house. 26 King Solomon made a fleet of ships in Ezion Geber, which is beside Eloth, on the shore of the Red Sea, in the land of Edom. 27 Hiram sent in the fleet his servants, sailors who had knowledge of the sea, with the servants of Solomon. 28 They came to Ophir, and fetched from there gold, four hundred and twenty talents,[*] and brought it to king Solomon.

“Cabul” sounds like Hebrew for “good-for-nothing”.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 120 talents is about 3.6 metric tons

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 420 talents is about 12.6 metric tons

1 Kings 10

1 When the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon concerning Yahweh’s name, she came to test him with hard questions. 2 She came to Jerusalem with a very great caravan, with camels that bore spices, very much gold, and precious stones; and when she had come to Solomon, she talked with him about all that was in her heart. 3 Solomon answered all her questions. There was not anything hidden from the king which he didn’t tell her. 4 When the queen of Sheba had seen all the wisdom of Solomon, the house that he had built, 5 the food of his table, the sitting of his servants, the attendance of his officials, their clothing, his cup bearers, and his ascent by which he went up to Yahweh’s house; there was no more spirit in her. 6 She said to the king, “It was a true report that I heard in my own land of your acts, and of your wisdom. 7 However I didn’t believe the words until I came and my eyes had seen it. Behold, not even half was told me! Your wisdom and prosperity exceed the fame which I heard. 8 Happy are your men, happy are these your servants, who stand continually before you, who hear your wisdom. 9 Blessed is Yahweh your God, who delighted in you, to set you on the throne of Israel. Because Yahweh loved Israel forever, therefore he made you king, to do justice and righteousness.” 10 She gave the king one hundred twenty talents of gold, and a very great quantity of spices, and precious stones. Never again was there such an abundance of spices as these which the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon.

11 The fleet of Hiram that brought gold from Ophir, also brought in from Ophir great quantities of almug trees[*] and precious stones. 12 The king made of the almug trees pillars for Yahweh’s house, and for the king’s house, harps also and stringed instruments for the singers; no such almug trees came or were seen, to this day. 13 King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatever she asked, besides that which Solomon gave her of his royal bounty. So she turned and went to her own land, she and her servants. 14 Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred sixty-six talents[*] of gold, 15 besides that which the traders brought, and the traffic of the merchants, and of all the kings of the mixed people, and of the governors of the country. 16 King Solomon made two hundred bucklers of beaten gold; six hundred shekels[*] of gold went to one buckler. 17 he made three hundred shields of beaten gold; three minas[*] of gold went to one shield; and the king put them in the House of the Forest of Lebanon. 18 Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with the finest gold. 19 There were six steps to the throne, and the top of the throne was round behind; and there were armrests on either side by the place of the seat, and two lions standing beside the armrests. 20 Twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other on the six steps. Nothing like it was made in any kingdom. 21 All king Solomon’s drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Lebanon were of pure gold. None were of silver, because it was considered of little value in the days of Solomon. 22 For the king had a fleet of Tarshish at sea with Hiram’s fleet. Once every three years the fleet of Tarshish came, bringing gold, silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks. 23 So king Solomon exceeded all the kings of the earth in riches and in wisdom. 24 All the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. 25 Year after year, every man brought his tribute, vessels of silver, vessels of gold, clothing, armor, spices, horses, and mules. 26 Solomon gathered together chariots and horsemen. He had one thousand four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, that he kept in the chariot cities and with the king at Jerusalem. 27 The king made silver as common as stones in Jerusalem, and cedars as common as the sycamore trees that are in the lowland. 28 The horses which Solomon had were brought out of Egypt. The king’s merchants received them in droves, each drove at a price. 29 A chariot came up and went out of Egypt for six hundred shekels[*] of silver, and a horse for one hundred fifty shekels; and so they exported them to all the kings of the Hittites, and to the kings of Syria.

possibly an Indian sandalwood, with nice grain and a pleasant scent, and good for woodworking

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 666 talents is about 20 metric tons

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.32 Troy ounces, so 600 shekels is about 6 kilograms or 13.2 pounds or 192 Troy ounces.

A mina is about 600 grams or 1.3 U. S. pounds.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

1 Kings 11

1 Now king Solomon loved many foreign women, together with the daughter of Pharaoh, women of the Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites, Sidonians, and Hittites; 2 of the nations concerning which Yahweh said to the children of Israel, “You shall not go among them, neither shall they come among you; for surely they will turn away your heart after their gods.” Solomon joined to these in love. 3 He had seven hundred wives, princesses, and three hundred concubines; and his wives turned away his heart. 4 When Solomon was old, his wives turned away his heart after other gods; and his heart was not perfect with Yahweh his God, as the heart of David his father was. 5 For Solomon went after Ashtoreth the goddess of the Sidonians, and after Milcom the abomination of the Ammonites. 6 Solomon did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and didn’t go fully after Yahweh, as David his father did. 7 Then Solomon built a high place for Chemosh the abomination of Moab, on the mountain that is before Jerusalem, and for Molech the abomination of the children of Ammon. 8 So he did for all his foreign wives, who burned incense and sacrificed to their gods. 9 Yahweh was angry with Solomon, because his heart was turned away from Yahweh, the God of Israel, who had appeared to him twice, 10 and had commanded him concerning this thing, that he should not go after other gods; but he didn’t keep that which Yahweh commanded. 11 Therefore Yahweh said to Solomon, “Because this is done by you, and you have not kept my covenant and my statutes, which I have commanded you, I will surely tear the kingdom from you, and will give it to your servant. 12 Nevertheless, I will not do it in your days, for David your father’s sake; but I will tear it out of your son’s hand. 13 However I will not tear away all the kingdom; but I will give one tribe to your son, for David my servant’s sake, and for Jerusalem’s sake which I have chosen.”

14 Yahweh raised up an adversary to Solomon: Hadad the Edomite. He was one of the king’s offspring[*] in Edom. 15 For when David was in Edom, and Joab the captain of the army had gone up to bury the slain, and had struck every male in Edom 16 (for Joab and all Israel remained there six months, until he had cut off every male in Edom); 17 Hadad fled, he and certain Edomites of his father’s servants with him, to go into Egypt, when Hadad was still a little child. 18 They arose out of Midian, and came to Paran; and they took men with them out of Paran, and they came to Egypt, to Pharaoh king of Egypt, who gave him a house, and appointed him food, and gave him land. 19 Hadad found great favor in the sight of Pharaoh, so that he gave him as wife the sister of his own wife, the sister of Tahpenes the queen. 20 The sister of Tahpenes bore him Genubath his son, whom Tahpenes weaned in Pharaoh’s house; and Genubath was in Pharaoh’s house among the sons of Pharaoh. 21 When Hadad heard in Egypt that David slept with his fathers, and that Joab the captain of the army was dead, Hadad said to Pharaoh, “Let me depart, that I may go to my own country.”

22 Then Pharaoh said to him, “But what have you lacked with me, that behold, you seek to go to your own country?”

He answered, “Nothing, however only let me depart.”

23 God raised up an adversary to him, Rezon the son of Eliada, who had fled from his lord Hadadezer king of Zobah. 24 He gathered men to himself, and became captain over a troop, when David killed them of Zobah. They went to Damascus, and lived there, and reigned in Damascus. 25 He was an adversary to Israel all the days of Solomon, besides the mischief of Hadad. He abhorred Israel, and reigned over Syria. 26 Jeroboam the son of Nebat, an Ephraimite of Zeredah, a servant of Solomon, whose mother’s name was Zeruah, a widow, also lifted up his hand against the king. 27 This was the reason why he lifted up his hand against the king: Solomon built Millo, and repaired the breach of his father David’s city. 28 The man Jeroboam was a mighty man of valor; and Solomon saw the young man that he was industrious, and he put him in charge of all the labor of the house of Joseph. 29 At that time, when Jeroboam went out of Jerusalem, the prophet Ahijah the Shilonite found him on the way; now Ahijah had clad himself with a new garment; and they two were alone in the field. 30 Ahijah laid hold of the new garment that was on him, and tore it in twelve pieces. 31 He said to Jeroboam, “Take ten pieces; for Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, ‘Behold, I will tear the kingdom out of the hand of Solomon, and will give ten tribes to you 32 (but he shall have one tribe, for my servant David’s sake and for Jerusalem’s sake, the city which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel); 33 because that they have forsaken me, and have worshiped Ashtoreth the goddess of the Sidonians, Chemosh the god of Moab, and Milcom the god of the children of Ammon. They have not walked in my ways, to do that which is right in my eyes, and to keep my statutes and my ordinances, as David his father did.

34 “‘However I will not take the whole kingdom out of his hand; but I will make him prince all the days of his life, for David my servant’s sake whom I chose, who kept my commandments and my statutes; 35 but I will take the kingdom out of his son’s hand, and will give it to you, even ten tribes. 36 To his son will I give one tribe, that David my servant may have a lamp always before me in Jerusalem, the city which I have chosen me to put my name there. 37 I will take you, and you shall reign according to all that your soul desires, and shall be king over Israel. 38 It shall be, if you will listen to all that I command you, and will walk in my ways, and do that which is right in my eyes, to keep my statutes and my commandments, as David my servant did; that I will be with you, and will build you a sure house, as I built for David, and will give Israel to you. 39 I will afflict the offspring[*] of David for this, but not forever.’”

40 Therefore Solomon sought to kill Jeroboam; but Jeroboam arose, and fled into Egypt, to Shishak king of Egypt, and was in Egypt until the death of Solomon. 41 Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, and all that he did, and his wisdom, aren’t they written in the book of the acts of Solomon? 42 The time that Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel was forty years. 43 Solomon slept with his fathers, and was buried in his father David’s city; and Rehoboam his son reigned in his place.

or, seed

or, seed

1 Kings 12

1 Rehoboam went to Shechem, for all Israel had come to Shechem to make him king. 2 When Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard of it (for he was yet in Egypt, where he had fled from the presence of king Solomon, and Jeroboam lived in Egypt, 3 and they sent and called him), Jeroboam and all the assembly of Israel came, and spoke to Rehoboam, saying, 4 “Your father made our yoke difficult. Now therefore make the hard service of your father, and his heavy yoke which he put on us, lighter, and we will serve you.”

5 He said to them, “Depart for three days, then come back to me.”

The people departed.

6 King Rehoboam took counsel with the old men, who had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, “What counsel do you give me to answer these people?”

7 They replied, “If you will be a servant to this people today, and will serve them, and answer them with good words, then they will be your servants forever.”

8 But he abandoned the counsel of the old men which they had given him, and took counsel with the young men who had grown up with him, who stood before him. 9 He said to them, “What counsel do you give, that we may answer these people, who have spoken to me, saying, ‘Make the yoke that your father put on us lighter?’”

10 The young men who had grown up with him said to him, “Tell these people who spoke to you, saying, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but make it lighter to us;’ tell them, ‘My little finger is thicker than my father’s waist. 11 Now my father burdened you with a heavy yoke, but I will add to your yoke. My father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.’”

12 So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king asked, saying, “Come to me again the third day.” 13 The king answered the people roughly, and abandoned the counsel of the old men which they had given him, 14 and spoke to them according to the counsel of the young men, saying, “My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to your yoke. My father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.”

15 So the king didn’t listen to the people; for it was a thing brought about from Yahweh, that he might establish his word, which Yahweh spoke by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat. 16 When all Israel saw that the king didn’t listen to them, the people answered the king, saying, “What portion have we in David? We don’t have an inheritance in the son of Jesse. To your tents, Israel! Now see to your own house, David.” So Israel departed to their tents.

17 But as for the children of Israel who lived in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. 18 Then king Rehoboam sent Adoram, who was over the men subject to forced labor; and all Israel stoned him to death with stones. King Rehoboam hurried to get himself up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem. 19 So Israel rebelled against David’s house to this day. 20 When all Israel heard that Jeroboam had returned, they sent and called him to the congregation, and made him king over all Israel. There was no one who followed David’s house, except for the tribe of Judah only. 21 When Rehoboam had come to Jerusalem, he assembled all the house of Judah and the tribe of Benjamin, a hundred and eighty thousand chosen men, who were warriors, to fight against the house of Israel, to bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam the son of Solomon. 22 But the word of God came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, 23 “Speak to Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all the house of Judah and Benjamin, and to the rest of the people, saying, 24 ‘Yahweh says, “You shall not go up or fight against your brothers, the children of Israel. Everyone return to his house; for this thing is from me.”’” So they listened to Yahweh’s word, and returned and went their way, according to Yahweh’s word.

25 Then Jeroboam built Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim, and lived in it; and he went out from there, and built Penuel. 26 Jeroboam said in his heart, “Now the kingdom will return to David’s house. 27 If this people goes up to offer sacrifices in Yahweh’s house at Jerusalem, then the heart of this people will turn again to their lord, even to Rehoboam king of Judah; and they will kill me, and return to Rehoboam king of Judah.” 28 So the king took counsel, and made two calves of gold; and he said to them, “It is too much for you to go up to Jerusalem. Look and behold your gods, Israel, which brought you up out of the land of Egypt!” 29 He set the one in Bethel, and the other put he in Dan. 30 This thing became a sin; for the people went even as far as Dan to worship before the one there. 31 He made houses of high places, and made priests from among all the people, who were not of the sons of Levi. 32 Jeroboam ordained a feast in the eighth month, on the fifteenth day of the month, like the feast that is in Judah, and he went up to the altar. He did so in Bethel, sacrificing to the calves that he had made, and he placed in Bethel the priests of the high places that he had made. 33 He went up to the altar which he had made in Bethel on the fifteenth day in the eighth month, even in the month which he had devised of his own heart; and he ordained a feast for the children of Israel, and went up to the altar, to burn incense.

1 Kings 13

1 Behold, a man of God came out of Judah by Yahweh’s word to Beth El; and Jeroboam was standing by the altar to burn incense. 2 He cried against the altar by Yahweh’s word, and said, “Altar! Altar! Yahweh says: ‘Behold, a son will be born to David’s house, Josiah by name. On you he will sacrifice the priests of the high places who burn incense on you, and they will burn men’s bones on you.’” 3 He gave a sign the same day, saying, “This is the sign which Yahweh has spoken: Behold, the altar will be split apart, and the ashes that are on it will be poured out.”

4 When the king heard the saying of the man of God, which he cried against the altar in Bethel, Jeroboam put out his hand from the altar, saying, “Seize him!” His hand, which he put out against him, dried up, so that he could not draw it back again to himself. 5 The altar was also split apart, and the ashes poured out from the altar, according to the sign which the man of God had given by Yahweh’s word. 6 The king answered the man of God, “Now intercede for the favor of Yahweh your God, and pray for me, that my hand may be restored me again.”

The man of God interceded with Yahweh, and the king’s hand was restored to him again, and became as it was before.

7 The king said to the man of God, “Come home with me, and refresh yourself, and I will give you a reward.”

8 The man of God said to the king, “Even if you gave me half of your house, I would not go in with you, neither would I eat bread nor drink water in this place; 9 for so was it commanded me by Yahweh’s word, saying, ‘You shall eat no bread, drink no water, and don’t return by the way that you came.’” 10 So he went another way, and didn’t return by the way that he came to Bethel.

11 Now an old prophet lived in Bethel, and one of his sons came and told him all the works that the man of God had done that day in Bethel. They also told their father the words which he had spoken to the king.

12 Their father said to them, “Which way did he go?” Now his sons had seen which way the man of God went, who came from Judah. 13 He said to his sons, “Saddle the donkey for me.” So they saddled the donkey for him; and he rode on it. 14 He went after the man of God, and found him sitting under an oak. He said to him, “Are you the man of God who came from Judah?”

He said, “I am.” 15 Then he said to him, “Come home with me, and eat bread.”

16 He said, “I may not return with you, nor go in with you. I will not eat bread or drink water with you in this place. 17 For it was said to me by Yahweh’s word, ‘You shall eat no bread or drink water there, and don’t turn again to go by the way that you came.’”

18 He said to him, “I also am a prophet as you are; and an angel spoke to me by Yahweh’s word, saying, ‘Bring him back with you into your house, that he may eat bread and drink water.’” He lied to him.

19 So he went back with him, ate bread in his house, and drank water. 20 As they sat at the table, Yahweh’s word came to the prophet who brought him back; 21 and he cried out to the man of God who came from Judah, saying, “Yahweh says, ‘Because you have been disobedient to Yahweh’s mouth, and have not kept the commandment which Yahweh your God commanded you, 22 but came back, and have eaten bread and drank water in the place of which he said to you, “Eat no bread, and drink no water”; your body will not come to the tomb of your fathers.’”

23 After he had eaten bread, and after he drank, he saddled the donkey for the prophet whom he had brought back. 24 When he had gone, a lion met him by the way and killed him. His body was thrown on the path, and the donkey stood by it. The lion also stood by the body. 25 Behold, men passed by, and saw the body thrown on the path, and the lion standing by the body; and they came and told it in the city where the old prophet lived. 26 When the prophet who brought him back from the way heard of it, he said, “It is the man of God who was disobedient to Yahweh’s mouth. Therefore Yahweh has delivered him to the lion, which has mauled him and slain him, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke to him.” 27 He said to his sons, saying, “Saddle the donkey for me,” and they saddled it. 28 He went and found his body thrown on the path, and the donkey and the lion standing by the body. The lion had not eaten the body, nor mauled the donkey. 29 The prophet took up the body of the man of God, and laid it on the donkey, and brought it back. He came to the city of the old prophet to mourn, and to bury him. 30 He laid his body in his own grave; and they mourned over him, saying, “Alas, my brother!”

31 After he had buried him, he spoke to his sons, saying, “When I am dead, bury me in the tomb in which the man of God is buried. Lay my bones beside his bones. 32 For the saying which he cried by Yahweh’s word against the altar in Bethel, and against all the houses of the high places which are in the cities of Samaria, will surely happen.”

33 After this thing Jeroboam didn’t return from his evil way, but again made priests of the high places from among all the people. Whoever wanted to, he consecrated him, that there might be priests of the high places. 34 This thing became sin to the house of Jeroboam, even to cut it off, and to destroy it from off the surface of the earth.

1 Kings 14

1 At that time Abijah the son of Jeroboam became sick. 2 Jeroboam said to his wife, “Please get up and disguise yourself, so that you won’t be recognized as Jeroboam’s wife. Go to Shiloh. Behold, Ahijah the prophet is there, who said that that I would be king over this people. 3 Take with you ten loaves of bread, some cakes, and a jar of honey, and go to him. He will tell you what will become of the child.”

4 Jeroboam’s wife did so, and arose, and went to Shiloh, and came to Ahijah’s house. Now Ahijah could not see; for his eyes were set by reason of his age. 5 Yahweh said to Ahijah, “Behold, Jeroboam’s wife is coming to inquire of you concerning her son; for he is sick. Tell her such and such; for it will be, when she comes in, that she will pretend to be another woman.”

6 So when Ahijah heard the sound of her feet as she came in at the door, he said, “Come in, Jeroboam’s wife! Why do you pretend to be another? For I am sent to you with heavy news. 7 Go, tell Jeroboam, ‘Yahweh, the God of Israel, says: “Because I exalted you from among the people, and made you prince over my people Israel, 8 and tore the kingdom away from David’s house, and gave it you; and yet you have not been as my servant David, who kept my commandments, and who followed me with all his heart, to do that only which was right in my eyes, 9 but have done evil above all who were before you, and have gone and made for yourself other gods, molten images, to provoke me to anger, and have cast me behind your back; 10 therefore, behold, I will bring evil on the house of Jeroboam, and will cut off from Jeroboam everyone who urinates on a wall,[*] he who is shut up and he who is left at large in Israel, and will utterly sweep away the house of Jeroboam, as a man sweeps away dung, until it is all gone. 11 The dogs will eat he who belongs to Jeroboam who dies in the city; and the birds of the sky will eat he who dies in the field: for Yahweh has spoken it.”’ 12 Arise therefore, and go to your house. When your feet enter into the city, the child will die. 13 All Israel will mourn for him and bury him; for he only of Jeroboam will come to the grave, because in him there is found some good thing toward Yahweh, the God of Israel, in the house of Jeroboam. 14 Moreover Yahweh will raise up a king for himself over Israel, who will cut off the house of Jeroboam. This is the day! What? Even now. 15 For Yahweh will strike Israel, as a reed is shaken in the water; and he will root up Israel out of this good land which he gave to their fathers, and will scatter them beyond the River,[*] because they have made their Asherah poles, provoking Yahweh to anger. 16 He will give Israel up because of the sins of Jeroboam, which he has sinned, and with which he has made Israel to sin.”

17 Jeroboam’s wife arose and departed, and came to Tirzah. As she came to the threshold of the house, the child died. 18 All Israel buried him and mourned for him, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke by his servant Ahijah the prophet. 19 The rest of the acts of Jeroboam, how he fought, and how he reigned, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. 20 The days which Jeroboam reigned were twenty two years, then he slept with his fathers, and Nadab his son reigned in his place.

21 Rehoboam the son of Solomon reigned in Judah. Rehoboam was forty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which Yahweh had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there. His mother’s name was Naamah the Ammonitess. 22 Judah did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and they provoked him to jealousy with their sins which they committed, above all that their fathers had done. 23 For they also built for themselves high places, sacred pillars, and Asherah poles on every high hill and under every green tree. 24 There were also sodomites in the land. They did according to all the abominations of the nations which Yahweh drove out before the children of Israel. 25 In the fifth year of king Rehoboam, Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, 26 and he took away the treasures of Yahweh’s house, and the treasures of the king’s house. He even took away all of it, including all the gold shields which Solomon had made. 27 King Rehoboam made shields of brass in their place, and committed them to the hands of the captains of the guard, who kept the door of the king’s house. 28 It was so, that as often as the king went into Yahweh’s house, the guard bore them, and brought them back into the guard room.

29 Now the rest of the acts of Rehoboam, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 30 There was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually. 31 Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in David’s city. His mother’s name was Naamah the Ammonitess. Abijam his son reigned in his place.

or, male

That is, the Euphrates.

1 Kings 15

1 Now in the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam the son of Nebat, Abijam began to reign over Judah. 2 He reigned three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Maacah the daughter of Abishalom. 3 He walked in all the sins of his father, which he had done before him; and his heart was not perfect with Yahweh his God, as the heart of David his father. 4 Nevertheless for David’s sake, Yahweh his God gave him a lamp in Jerusalem, to set up his son after him, and to establish Jerusalem; 5 because David did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, and didn’t turn aside from anything that he commanded him all the days of his life, except only in the matter of Uriah the Hittite. 6 Now there was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all the days of his life. 7 The rest of the acts of Abijam, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? There was war between Abijam and Jeroboam. 8 Abijam slept with his fathers, and they buried him in David’s city; and Asa his son reigned in his place.

9 In the twentieth year of Jeroboam king of Israel, Asa began to reign over Judah. 10 He reigned forty-one years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Maacah the daughter of Abishalom. 11 Asa did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, as David his father did. 12 He put away the sodomites out of the land, and removed all the idols that his fathers had made. 13 He also removed Maacah his mother from being queen, because she had made an abominable image for an Asherah. Asa cut down her image and burned it at the brook Kidron. 14 But the high places were not taken away. Nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect with Yahweh all his days. 15 He brought into Yahweh’s house the things that his father had dedicated, and the things that he himself had dedicated: silver, gold, and utensils. 16 There was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days. 17 Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah, and built Ramah, that he might not allow anyone to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. 18 Then Asa took all the silver and the gold that was left in the treasures of Yahweh’s house, and the treasures of the king’s house, and delivered it into the hand of his servants. Then King Asa sent them to Ben Hadad, the son of Tabrimmon, the son of Hezion, king of Syria, who lived at Damascus, saying, 19 “There is a treaty between me and you, between my father and your father. Behold, I have sent to you a present of silver and gold. Go, break your treaty with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me.”

20 Ben Hadad listened to king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel, and struck Ijon, and Dan, and Abel Beth Maacah, and all Chinneroth, with all the land of Naphtali. 21 When Baasha heard of it, he stopped building Ramah, and lived in Tirzah. 22 Then king Asa made a proclamation to all Judah. No one was exempted. They carried away the stones of Ramah, and its timber, with which Baasha had built; and king Asa used it to build Geba of Benjamin, and Mizpah. 23 Now the rest of all the acts of Asa, and all his might, and all that he did, and the cities which he built, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? But in the time of his old age he was diseased in his feet. 24 Asa slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in his father David’s city; and Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his place.

25 Nadab the son of Jeroboam began to reign over Israel in the second year of Asa king of Judah; and he reigned over Israel two years. 26 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and walked in the way of his father, and in his sin with which he made Israel to sin. 27 Baasha the son of Ahijah, of the house of Issachar, conspired against him; and Baasha struck him at Gibbethon, which belonged to the Philistines; for Nadab and all Israel were besieging Gibbethon. 28 Even in the third year of Asa king of Judah, Baasha killed him, and reigned in his place. 29 As soon as he was king, he struck all the house of Jeroboam. He didn’t leave to Jeroboam any who breathed, until he had destroyed him; according to the saying of Yahweh, which he spoke by his servant Ahijah the Shilonite; 30 for the sins of Jeroboam which he sinned, and with which he made Israel to sin, because of his provocation with which he provoked Yahweh, the God of Israel, to anger. 31 Now the rest of the acts of Nadab, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 32 There was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days.

33 In the third year of Asa king of Judah, Baasha the son of Ahijah began to reign over all Israel in Tirzah for twenty-four years. 34 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and walked in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin with which he made Israel to sin.

1 Kings 16

1 Yahweh’s word came to Jehu the son of Hanani against Baasha, saying, 2 “Because I exalted you out of the dust, and made you prince over my people Israel, and you have walked in the way of Jeroboam, and have made my people Israel to sin, to provoke me to anger with their sins; 3 behold, I will utterly sweep away Baasha and his house; and I will make your house like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat. 4 The dogs will eat Baasha’s descendants who die in the city; and he who dies of his in the field, the birds of the sky will eat.”

5 Now the rest of the acts of Baasha, and what he did, and his might, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 6 Baasha slept with his fathers, and was buried in Tirzah; and Elah his son reigned in his place.

7 Moreover Yahweh’s word came by the prophet Jehu the son of Hanani against Baasha and against his house, both because of all the evil that he did in Yahweh’s sight, to provoke him to anger with the work of his hands, in being like the house of Jeroboam, and because he struck him.

8 In the twenty-sixth year of Asa king of Judah, Elah the son of Baasha began to reign over Israel in Tirzah for two years. 9 His servant Zimri, captain of half his chariots, conspired against him. Now he was in Tirzah, drinking himself drunk in the house of Arza, who was over the household in Tirzah; 10 and Zimri went in and struck him, and killed him, in the twenty-seventh year of Asa king of Judah, and reigned in his place.

11 When he began to reign, as soon as he sat on his throne, he attacked all the house of Baasha. He didn’t leave him a single one who urinates on a wall[*] among his relatives or his friends. 12 Thus Zimri destroyed all the house of Baasha, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke against Baasha by Jehu the prophet, 13 for all the sins of Baasha, and the sins of Elah his son, which they sinned, and with which they made Israel to sin, to provoke Yahweh, the God of Israel, to anger with their vanities. 14 Now the rest of the acts of Elah, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 15 In the twenty-seventh year of Asa king of Judah, Zimri reigned seven days in Tirzah. Now the people were encamped against Gibbethon, which belonged to the Philistines. 16 The people who were encamped heard that Zimri had conspired, and had also killed the king. Therefore all Israel made Omri, the captain of the army, king over Israel that day in the camp. 17 Omri went up from Gibbethon, and all Israel with him, and they besieged Tirzah. 18 When Zimri saw that the city was taken, he went into the fortified part of the king’s house, and burned the king’s house over him with fire, and died, 19 for his sins which he sinned in doing that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, in walking in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin which he did, to make Israel to sin. 20 Now the rest of the acts of Zimri, and his treason that he committed, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?

21 Then the people of Israel were divided into two parts: half of the people followed Tibni the son of Ginath, to make him king; and half followed Omri. 22 But the people who followed Omri prevailed against the people who followed Tibni the son of Ginath; so Tibni died, and Omri reigned. 23 In the thirty-first year of Asa king of Judah, Omri began to reign over Israel for twelve years. He reigned six years in Tirzah. 24 He bought the hill Samaria of Shemer for two talents[*] of silver; and he built on the hill, and called the name of the city which he built Samaria, after the name of Shemer, the owner of the hill. 25 Omri did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and dealt wickedly above all who were before him. 26 For he walked in all the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and in his sins with which he made Israel to sin, to provoke Yahweh, the God of Israel, to anger with their vanities. 27 Now the rest of the acts of Omri which he did, and his might that he showed, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 28 So Omri slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria; and Ahab his son reigned in his place.

29 In the thirty-eighth year of Asa king of Judah, Ahab the son of Omri began to reign over Israel. Ahab the son of Omri reigned over Israel in Samaria twenty-two years. 30 Ahab the son of Omri did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight above all that were before him. 31 As if it had been a light thing for him to walk in the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, he took as wife Jezebel the daughter of Ethbaal king of the Sidonians, and went and served Baal, and worshiped him. 32 He raised up an altar for Baal in the house of Baal, which he had built in Samaria. 33 Ahab made the Asherah; and Ahab did more yet to provoke Yahweh, the God of Israel, to anger than all the kings of Israel who were before him. 34 In his days Hiel the Bethelite built Jericho. He laid its foundation with the loss of Abiram his firstborn, and set up its gates with the loss of his youngest son Segub, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke by Joshua the son of Nun.

or, male

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds.

1 Kings 17

1 Elijah the Tishbite, who was one of the settlers of Gilead, said to Ahab, “As Yahweh, the God of Israel, lives, before whom I stand, there shall not be dew nor rain these years, but according to my word.”

2 Then Yahweh’s word came to him, saying, 3 “Go away from here, turn eastward, and hide yourself by the brook Cherith, that is before the Jordan. 4 You shall drink from the brook. I have commanded the ravens to feed you there.” 5 So he went and did according to Yahweh’s word; for he went and lived by the brook Cherith that is before the Jordan. 6 The ravens brought him bread and meat in the morning, and bread and meat in the evening; and he drank from the brook. 7 After a while, the brook dried up, because there was no rain in the land.

8 Yahweh’s word came to him, saying, 9 “Arise, go to Zarephath, which belongs to Sidon, and stay there. Behold, I have commanded a widow there to sustain you.”

10 So he arose and went to Zarephath; and when he came to the gate of the city, behold, a widow was there gathering sticks. He called to her, and said, “Please get me a little water in a jar, that I may drink.”

11 As she was going to get it, he called to her, and said, “Please bring me a morsel of bread in your hand.”

12 She said, “As Yahweh your God lives, I don’t have a cake, but a handful of meal in a jar, and a little oil in a jar. Behold, I am gathering two sticks, that I may go in and bake it for me and my son, that we may eat it, and die.”

13 Elijah said to her, “Don’t be afraid. Go and do as you have said; but make me a little cake from it first, and bring it out to me, and afterward make some for you and for your son. 14 For Yahweh, the God of Israel says, ‘The jar of meal will not run out, and the jar of oil will not fail, until the day that Yahweh sends rain on the earth.’”

15 She went and did according to the saying of Elijah; and she, and he, and her house, ate many days. 16 The jar of meal didn’t run out, and the jar of oil did not fail, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke by Elijah. 17 After these things, the son of the woman, the mistress of the house, became sick; and his sickness was so severe that there was no breath left in him. 18 She said to Elijah, “What have I to do with you, you man of God? You have come to me to bring my sin to memory, and to kill my son!”

19 He said to her, “Give me your son.” He took him out of her bosom, and carried him up into the room where he stayed, and laid him on his own bed. 20 He cried to Yahweh, and said, “Yahweh my God, have you also brought evil on the widow with whom I am staying, by killing her son?”

21 He stretched himself on the child three times, and cried to Yahweh, and said, “Yahweh my God, please let this child’s soul come into him again.”

22 Yahweh listened to the voice of Elijah; and the soul of the child came into him again, and he revived. 23 Elijah took the child, and brought him down out of the room into the house, and delivered him to his mother; and Elijah said, “Behold, your son lives.”

24 The woman said to Elijah, “Now I know that you are a man of God, and that Yahweh’s word in your mouth is truth.”

1 Kings 18

1 After many days, Yahweh’s word came to Elijah, in the third year, saying, “Go, show yourself to Ahab; and I will send rain on the earth.”

2 Elijah went to show himself to Ahab. The famine was severe in Samaria. 3 Ahab called Obadiah, who was over the household. (Now Obadiah feared Yahweh greatly; 4 for when Jezebel cut off Yahweh’s prophets, Obadiah took one hundred prophets, and hid them by fifty in a cave, and fed them with bread and water.) 5 Ahab said to Obadiah, “Go through the land, to all the springs of water, and to all the brooks. Perhaps we may find grass and save the horses and mules alive, that we not lose all the animals.”

6 So they divided the land between them to pass throughout it. Ahab went one way by himself, and Obadiah went another way by himself. 7 As Obadiah was on the way, behold, Elijah met him. He recognized him, and fell on his face, and said, “Is it you, my lord Elijah?”

8 He answered him, “It is I. Go, tell your lord, ‘Behold, Elijah is here!’”

9 He said, “How have I sinned, that you would deliver your servant into the hand of Ahab, to kill me? 10 As Yahweh your God lives, there is no nation or kingdom where my lord has not sent to seek you. When they said, ‘He is not here,’ he took an oath of the kingdom and nation, that they didn’t find you. 11 Now you say, ‘Go, tell your lord, “Behold, Elijah is here.”’ 12 It will happen, as soon as I leave you, that Yahweh’s Spirit will carry you I don’t know where; and so when I come and tell Ahab, and he can’t find you, he will kill me. But I, your servant, have feared Yahweh from my youth. 13 Wasn’t it told my lord what I did when Jezebel killed Yahweh’s prophets, how I hid one hundred men of Yahweh’s prophets with fifty to a cave, and fed them with bread and water? 14 Now you say, ‘Go, tell your lord, “Behold, Elijah is here”.’ He will kill me.”

15 Elijah said, “As Yahweh of Armies lives, before whom I stand, I will surely show myself to him today.” 16 So Obadiah went to meet Ahab, and told him; and Ahab went to meet Elijah. 17 When Ahab saw Elijah, Ahab said to him, “Is that you, you troubler of Israel?”

18 He answered, “I have not troubled Israel; but you, and your father’s house, in that you have forsaken Yahweh’s commandments, and you have followed the Baals. 19 Now therefore send, and gather to me all Israel to Mount Carmel, and four hundred fifty of the prophets of Baal, and four hundred of the prophets of the Asherah, who eat at Jezebel’s table.”

20 So Ahab sent to all the children of Israel, and gathered the prophets together to Mount Carmel. 21 Elijah came near to all the people, and said, “How long will you waver between the two sides? If Yahweh is God, follow him; but if Baal, then follow him.”

The people didn’t say a word.

22 Then Elijah said to the people, “I, even I only, am left as a prophet of Yahweh; but Baal’s prophets are four hundred fifty men. 23 Let them therefore give us two bulls; and let them choose one bull for themselves, and cut it in pieces, and lay it on the wood, and put no fire under; and I will dress the other bull, and lay it on the wood, and put no fire under it. 24 You call on the name of your god, and I will call on Yahweh’s name. The God who answers by fire, let him be God.”

All the people answered, “What you say is good.”

25 Elijah said to the prophets of Baal, “Choose one bull for yourselves, and dress it first; for you are many; and call on the name of your god, but put no fire under it.”

26 They took the bull which was given them, and they dressed it, and called on the name of Baal from morning even until noon, saying, “Baal, hear us!” But there was no voice, and nobody answered. They leaped about the altar which was made. 27 At noon, Elijah mocked them, and said, “Cry aloud; for he is a god. Either he is deep in thought, or he has gone somewhere, or he is on a journey, or perhaps he sleeps and must be awakened.”

28 They cried aloud, and cut themselves in their way with knives and lances, until the blood gushed out on them. 29 When midday was past, they prophesied until the time of the evening offering; but there was no voice, no answer, and nobody paid attention.

30 Elijah said to all the people, “Come near to me!”; and all the people came near to him. He repaired Yahweh’s altar that had been thrown down. 31 Elijah took twelve stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, to whom Yahweh’s word came, saying, “Israel shall be your name.” 32 With the stones he built an altar in Yahweh’s name. He made a trench around the altar, large enough to contain two seahs[*] of seed. 33 He put the wood in order, and cut the bull in pieces, and laid it on the wood. He said, “Fill four jars with water, and pour it on the burnt offering, and on the wood.” 34 He said, “Do it a second time”; and they did it the second time. He said, “Do it a third time”; and they did it the third time. 35 The water ran around the altar; and he also filled the trench with water.

36 At the time of the evening offering, Elijah the prophet came near, and said, “Yahweh, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel, let it be known today that you are God in Israel, and that I am your servant, and that I have done all these things at your word. 37 Hear me, Yahweh, hear me, that this people may know that you, Yahweh, are God, and that you have turned their heart back again.”

38 Then Yahweh’s fire fell, and consumed the burnt offering, the wood, the stones, and the dust, and licked up the water that was in the trench. 39 When all the people saw it, they fell on their faces. They said, “Yahweh, he is God! Yahweh, he is God!”

40 Elijah said to them, “Seize the prophets of Baal! Don’t let one of them escape!”

They seized them; and Elijah brought them down to the brook Kishon, and killed them there. 41 Elijah said to Ahab, “Get up, eat and drink; for there is the sound of abundance of rain.”

42 So Ahab went up to eat and to drink. Elijah went up to the top of Carmel; and he bowed himself down on the earth, and put his face between his knees. 43 He said to his servant, “Go up now, and look toward the sea.”

He went up, and looked, and said, “There is nothing.”

He said, “Go again” seven times.

44 On the seventh time, he said, “Behold, a small cloud, like a man’s hand, is rising out of the sea.”

He said, “Go up, tell Ahab, ‘Get ready and go down, so that the rain doesn’t stop you.’”

45 In a little while, the sky grew black with clouds and wind, and there was a great rain. Ahab rode, and went to Jezreel. 46 Yahweh’s hand was on Elijah; and he tucked his cloak into his belt and ran before Ahab to the entrance of Jezreel.

1 seah is about 7 liters or 1.9 gallons or 0.8 pecks

1 Kings 19

1 Ahab told Jezebel all that Elijah had done, and how he had killed all the prophets with the sword. 2 Then Jezebel sent a messenger to Elijah, saying, “So let the gods do to me, and more also, if I don’t make your life as the life of one of them by tomorrow about this time!”

3 When he saw that, he arose, and ran for his life, and came to Beersheba, which belongs to Judah, and left his servant there. 4 But he himself went a day’s journey into the wilderness, and came and sat down under a juniper tree. Then he requested for himself that he might die, and said, “It is enough. Now, O Yahweh, take away my life; for I am not better than my fathers.”

5 He lay down and slept under a juniper tree; and behold, an angel touched him, and said to him, “Arise and eat!”

6 He looked, and behold, there was at his head a cake baked on the coals, and a jar of water. He ate and drank, and lay down again. 7 Yahweh’s angel came again the second time, and touched him, and said, “Arise and eat, because the journey is too great for you.”

8 He arose, and ate and drank, and went in the strength of that food forty days and forty nights to Horeb, God’s Mountain. 9 He came to a cave there, and camped there; and behold, Yahweh’s word came to him, and he said to him, “What are you doing here, Elijah?”

10 He said, “I have been very jealous for Yahweh, the God of Armies; for the children of Israel have forsaken your covenant, thrown down your altars, and killed your prophets with the sword. I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away.”

11 He said, “Go out, and stand on the mountain before Yahweh.”

Behold, Yahweh passed by, and a great and strong wind tore the mountains, and broke in pieces the rocks before Yahweh; but Yahweh was not in the wind. After the wind there was an earthquake; but Yahweh was not in the earthquake. 12 After the earthquake a fire passed; but Yahweh was not in the fire. After the fire, there was a still small voice. 13 When Elijah heard it, he wrapped his face in his mantle, went out, and stood in the entrance of the cave. Behold, a voice came to him, and said, “What are you doing here, Elijah?”

14 He said, “I have been very jealous for Yahweh, the God of Armies; for the children of Israel have forsaken your covenant, thrown down your altars, and killed your prophets with the sword. I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away.”

15 Yahweh said to him, “Go, return on your way to the wilderness of Damascus. When you arrive, anoint Hazael to be king over Syria. 16 Anoint Jehu the son of Nimshi to be king over Israel; and anoint Elisha the son of Shaphat of Abel Meholah to be prophet in your place. 17 He who escapes from the sword of Hazael, Jehu will kill; and he who escapes from the sword of Jehu, Elisha will kill. 18 Yet I reserved seven thousand in Israel, all the knees of which have not bowed to Baal, and every mouth which has not kissed him.”

19 So he departed from there, and found Elisha the son of Shaphat, who was plowing with twelve yoke of oxen before him, and he with the twelfth. Elijah went over to him, and put his mantle on him. 20 Elisha left the oxen, and ran after Elijah, and said, “Let me please kiss my father and my mother, and then I will follow you.”

He said to him, “Go back again; for what have I done to you?”

21 He returned from following him, and took the yoke of oxen, and killed them, and boiled their meat with the instruments of the oxen, and gave to the people, and they ate. Then he arose, and went after Elijah, and served him.

1 Kings 20

1 Ben Hadad the king of Syria gathered all his army together; and there were thirty-two kings with him, with horses and chariots. He went up and besieged Samaria, and fought against it. 2 He sent messengers to Ahab king of Israel, into the city, and said to him, “Thus says Ben Hadad, 3 ‘Your silver and your gold is mine. Your wives also and your children, even the best, are mine.’”

4 The king of Israel answered, “It is according to your saying, my lord, O king. I am yours, and all that I have.”

5 The messengers came again, and said, “Ben Hadad says, ‘I sent indeed to you, saying, “You shall deliver me your silver, and your gold, and your wives, and your children; 6 but I will send my servants to you tomorrow about this time, and they will search your house, and the houses of your servants; whatever is pleasant in your eyes, they will put it in their hand, and take it away.”’”

7 Then the king of Israel called all the elders of the land, and said, “Please notice how this man seeks mischief; for he sent to me for my wives, and for my children, and for my silver, and for my gold; and I didn’t deny him.”

8 All the elders and all the people said to him, “Don’t listen, and don’t consent.”

9 Therefore he said to the messengers of Ben Hadad, “Tell my lord the king, ‘All that you sent for to your servant at the first I will do; but this thing I cannot do.’”

The messengers departed, and brought him back the message. 10 Ben Hadad sent to him, and said, “The gods do so to me, and more also, if the dust of Samaria will be enough for handfuls for all the people who follow me.”

11 The king of Israel answered, “Tell him, ‘Don’t let him who puts on his armor brag like he who takes it off.’”

12 When Ben Hadad heard this message, as he was drinking, he and the kings, in the pavilions, he said to his servants, “Prepare to attack!” They prepared to attack the city.

13 Behold, a prophet came near to Ahab king of Israel, and said, “Yahweh says, ‘Have you seen all this great multitude? Behold, I will deliver it into your hand today; and you will know that I am Yahweh.’”

14 Ahab said, “By whom?”

He said, “Yahweh says, ‘By the young men of the princes of the provinces.’”

Then he said, “Who shall begin the battle?”

He answered, “You.”

15 Then he mustered the young men of the princes of the provinces, and they were two hundred and thirty-two. After them, he mustered all the people, even all the children of Israel, being seven thousand. 16 They went out at noon. But Ben Hadad was drinking himself drunk in the pavilions, he and the kings, the thirty-two kings who helped him. 17 The young men of the princes of the provinces went out first; and Ben Hadad sent out, and they told him, saying, “Men are coming out from Samaria.”

18 He said, “If they have come out for peace, take them alive; or if they have come out for war, take them alive.”

19 So these went out of the city, the young men of the princes of the provinces, and the army which followed them. 20 They each killed his man. The Syrians fled, and Israel pursued them. Ben Hadad the king of Syria escaped on a horse with horsemen. 21 The king of Israel went out, and struck the horses and chariots, and killed the Syrians with a great slaughter. 22 The prophet came near to the king of Israel, and said to him, “Go, strengthen yourself, and mark, and see what you do; for at the return of the year the king of Syria will come up against you.”

23 The servants of the king of Syria said to him, “Their god is a god of the hills; therefore they were stronger than we. But let us fight against them in the plain, and surely we will be stronger than they. 24 Do this thing: take the kings away, every man out of his place, and put captains in their place. 25 Muster an army, like the army that you have lost, horse for horse, and chariot for chariot. We will fight against them in the plain, and surely we will be stronger than them.”

He listened to their voice, and did so. 26 At the return of the year, Ben Hadad mustered the Syrians, and went up to Aphek, to fight against Israel. 27 The children of Israel were mustered and given provisions, and went against them. The children of Israel encamped before them like two little flocks of young goats; but the Syrians filled the country. 28 A man of God came near and spoke to the king of Israel, and said, “Yahweh says, ‘Because the Syrians have said, “Yahweh is a god of the hills, but he is not a god of the valleys”; therefore I will deliver all this great multitude into your hand, and you shall know that I am Yahweh.’”

29 They encamped opposite each other for seven days. So it was, that in the seventh day the battle was joined; and the children of Israel killed one hundred thousand footmen of the Syrians in one day. 30 But the rest fled to Aphek, into the city; and the wall fell on twenty-seven thousand men who were left. Ben Hadad fled, and came into the city, into an inner room. 31 His servants said to him, “See now, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel are merciful kings. Please let us put sackcloth on our bodies, and ropes on our heads, and go out to the king of Israel. Maybe he will save your life.”

32 So they put sackcloth on their bodies and ropes on their heads, and came to the king of Israel, and said, “Your servant Ben Hadad says, ‘Please let me live.’”

He said, “Is he still alive? He is my brother.”

33 Now the men observed diligently, and hurried to take this phrase; and they said, “Your brother Ben Hadad.”

Then he said, “Go, bring him.”

Then Ben Hadad came out to him; and he caused him to come up into the chariot. 34 Ben Hadad said to him, “The cities which my father took from your father I will restore. You shall make streets for yourself in Damascus, as my father made in Samaria.”

“I”, said Ahab, “will let you go with this covenant.” So he made a covenant with him, and let him go.

35 A certain man of the sons of the prophets said to his fellow by Yahweh’s word, “Please strike me!”

The man refused to strike him. 36 Then he said to him, “Because you have not obeyed Yahweh’s voice, behold, as soon as you have departed from me, a lion will kill you.” As soon as he had departed from him, a lion found him and killed him.

37 Then he found another man, and said, “Please strike me.”

The man struck him and wounded him. 38 So the prophet departed, and waited for the king by the way, and disguised himself with his headband over his eyes. 39 As the king passed by, he cried to the king; and he said, “Your servant went out into the middle of the battle; and behold, a man turned aside, and brought a man to me, and said, ‘Guard this man! If by any means he is missing, then your life shall be for his life, or else you shall pay a talent[*] of silver.’ 40 As your servant was busy here and there, he was gone.”

The king of Israel said to him, “So shall your judgment be. You yourself have decided it.”

41 He hurried, and took the headband away from his eyes; and the king of Israel recognized that he was one of the prophets. 42 He said to him, “Yahweh says, ‘Because you have let go out of your hand the man whom I had devoted to destruction, therefore your life will take the place of his life, and your people take the place of his people.’”

43 The king of Israel went to his house sullen and angry, and came to Samaria.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds

1 Kings 21

1 After these things, Naboth the Jezreelite had a vineyard, which was in Jezreel, next to the palace of Ahab king of Samaria. 2 Ahab spoke to Naboth, saying, “Give me your vineyard, that I may have it for a garden of herbs, because it is near my house; and I will give you for it a better vineyard than it. Or, if it seems good to you, I will give you its worth in money.”

3 Naboth said to Ahab, “May Yahweh forbid me, that I should give the inheritance of my fathers to you!”

4 Ahab came into his house sullen and angry because of the word which Naboth the Jezreelite had spoken to him; for he had said, “I will not give you the inheritance of my fathers.” He laid himself down on his bed, and turned away his face, and would eat no bread. 5 But Jezebel his wife came to him, and said to him, “Why is your spirit so sad, that you eat no bread?”

6 He said to her, “Because I spoke to Naboth the Jezreelite, and said to him, ‘Give me your vineyard for money; or else, if it pleases you, I will give you another vineyard for it.’ He answered, ‘I will not give you my vineyard.’”

7 Jezebel his wife said to him, “Do you now govern the kingdom of Israel? Arise, and eat bread, and let your heart be merry. I will give you the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite.” 8 So she wrote letters in Ahab’s name, and sealed them with his seal, and sent the letters to the elders and to the nobles who were in his city, who lived with Naboth. 9 She wrote in the letters, saying, “Proclaim a fast, and set Naboth on high among the people. 10 Set two men, base fellows, before him, and let them testify against him, saying, ‘You cursed God and the king!’ Then carry him out, and stone him to death.”

11 The men of his city, even the elders and the nobles who lived in his city, did as Jezebel had instructed them in the letters which she had written and sent to them. 12 They proclaimed a fast, and set Naboth on high among the people. 13 The two men, the base fellows, came in and sat before him. The base fellows testified against him, even against Naboth, in the presence of the people, saying, “Naboth cursed God and the king!” Then they carried him out of the city and stoned him to death with stones. 14 Then they sent to Jezebel, saying, “Naboth has been stoned, and is dead.”

15 When Jezebel heard that Naboth had been stoned, and was dead, Jezebel said to Ahab, “Arise, take possession of the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, which he refused to give you for money; for Naboth is not alive, but dead.”

16 When Ahab heard that Naboth was dead, Ahab rose up to go down to the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, to take possession of it.

17 Yahweh’s word came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, 18 “Arise, go down to meet Ahab king of Israel, who dwells in Samaria. Behold, he is in the vineyard of Naboth, where he has gone down to take possession of it. 19 You shall speak to him, saying, ‘Yahweh says, “Have you killed and also taken possession?”’ You shall speak to him, saying, ‘Yahweh says, “In the place where dogs licked the blood of Naboth, dogs will lick your blood, even yours.”’”

20 Ahab said to Elijah, “Have you found me, my enemy?”

He answered, “I have found you, because you have sold yourself to do that which is evil in Yahweh’s sight. 21 Behold, I will bring evil on you, and will utterly sweep you away and will cut off from Ahab everyone who urinates against a wall,[*] and him who is shut up and him who is left at large in Israel. 22 I will make your house like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of Baasha the son of Ahijah for the provocation with which you have provoked me to anger, and have made Israel to sin.” 23 Yahweh also spoke of Jezebel, saying, “The dogs will eat Jezebel by the rampart of Jezreel. 24 The dogs will eat he who dies of Ahab in the city; and the birds of the sky will eat he who dies in the field.”

25 But there was no one like Ahab, who sold himself to do that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, whom Jezebel his wife stirred up. 26 He did very abominably in following idols, according to all that the Amorites did, whom Yahweh cast out before the children of Israel. 27 When Ahab heard those words, he tore his clothes, and put sackcloth on his flesh, and fasted, and lay in sackcloth, and went softly.

28 Yahweh’s word came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, 29 “See how Ahab humbles himself before me? Because he humbles himself before me, I will not bring the evil in his days; but I will bring the evil on his house in his son’s day.”

or, male

1 Kings 22

1 They continued three years without war between Syria and Israel. 2 In the third year, Jehoshaphat the king of Judah came down to the king of Israel. 3 The king of Israel said to his servants, “You know that Ramoth Gilead is ours, and we do nothing, and don’t take it out of the hand of the king of Syria?” 4 He said to Jehoshaphat, “Will you go with me to battle to Ramoth Gilead?”

Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, “I am as you are, my people as your people, my horses as your horses.” 5 Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, “Please inquire first for Yahweh’s word.”

6 Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, about four hundred men, and said to them, “Should I go against Ramoth Gilead to battle, or should I refrain?”

They said, “Go up; for the Lord will deliver it into the hand of the king.”

7 But Jehoshaphat said, “Isn’t there here a prophet of Yahweh, that we may inquire of him?”

8 The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “There is yet one man by whom we may inquire of Yahweh, Micaiah the son of Imlah; but I hate him, for he does not prophesy good concerning me, but evil.”

Jehoshaphat said, “Don’t let the king say so.”

9 Then the king of Israel called an officer, and said, “Quickly get Micaiah the son of Imlah.”

10 Now the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah were sitting each on his throne, arrayed in their robes, in an open place at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets were prophesying before them. 11 Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made himself horns of iron, and said, “Yahweh says, ‘With these you will push the Syrians, until they are consumed.’” 12 All the prophets prophesied so, saying, “Go up to Ramoth Gilead, and prosper; for Yahweh will deliver it into the hand of the king.”

13 The messenger who went to call Micaiah spoke to him, saying, “See now, the prophets declare good to the king with one mouth. Please let your word be like the word of one of them, and speak good.”

14 Micaiah said, “As Yahweh lives, what Yahweh says to me, that I will speak.”

15 When he had come to the king, the king said to him, “Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth Gilead to battle, or shall we forbear?”

He answered him, “Go up and prosper; and Yahweh will deliver it into the hand of the king.” 16 The king said to him, “How many times do I have to adjure you that you speak to me nothing but the truth in Yahweh’s name?”

17 He said, “I saw all Israel scattered on the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd. Yahweh said, ‘These have no master. Let them each return to his house in peace.’”

18 The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “Didn’t I tell you that he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil?”

19 Micaiah said, “Therefore hear Yahweh’s word. I saw Yahweh sitting on his throne, and all the army of heaven standing by him on his right hand and on his left. 20 Yahweh said, ‘Who will entice Ahab, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth Gilead?’ One said one thing; and another said another.

21 A spirit came out and stood before Yahweh, and said, ‘I will entice him.’

22 Yahweh said to him, ‘How?’

He said, ‘I will go out and will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’

He said, ‘You will entice him, and will also prevail. Go out and do so.’ 23 Now therefore, behold, Yahweh has put a lying spirit in the mouth of all these your prophets; and Yahweh has spoken evil concerning you.”

24 Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and struck Micaiah on the cheek, and said, “Which way did Yahweh’s Spirit go from me to speak to you?”

25 Micaiah said, “Behold, you will see on that day, when you go into an inner room to hide yourself.”

26 The king of Israel said, “Take Micaiah, and carry him back to Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king’s son. 27 Say, ‘Thus says the king, “Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I come in peace.”’”

28 Micaiah said, “If you return at all in peace, Yahweh has not spoken by me.” He said, “Listen, all you people!”

29 So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth Gilead. 30 The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “I will disguise myself, and go into the battle; but you put on your robes.” The king of Israel disguised himself, and went into the battle.

31 Now the king of Syria had commanded the thirty-two captains of his chariots, saying, “Don’t fight with small nor great, except only with the king of Israel.”

32 When the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, they said, “Surely that is the king of Israel!” and they turned aside to fight against him. Jehoshaphat cried out. 33 When the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, they turned back from pursuing him. 34 A certain man drew his bow at random, and struck the king of Israel between the joints of the armor. Therefore he said to the driver of his chariot, “Turn your hand, and carry me out of the battle; for I am severely wounded.” 35 The battle increased that day. The king was propped up in his chariot facing the Syrians, and died at evening. The blood ran out of the wound into the bottom of the chariot. 36 A cry went throughout the army about the going down of the sun, saying, “Every man to his city, and every man to his country!”

37 So the king died, and was brought to Samaria; and they buried the king in Samaria. 38 They washed the chariot by the pool of Samaria; and the dogs licked up his blood where the prostitutes washed themselves; according to Yahweh’s word which he spoke.

39 Now the rest of the acts of Ahab, and all that he did, and the ivory house which he built, and all the cities that he built, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 40 So Ahab slept with his fathers; and Ahaziah his son reigned in his place.

41 Jehoshaphat the son of Asa began to reign over Judah in the fourth year of Ahab king of Israel. 42 Jehoshaphat was thirty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. 43 He walked in all the way of Asa his father. He didn’t turn aside from it, doing that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes. However the high places were not taken away. The people still sacrificed and burned incense on the high places. 44 Jehoshaphat made peace with the king of Israel. 45 Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, and his might that he showed, and how he fought, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 46 The remnant of the sodomites, that remained in the days of his father Asa, he put away out of the land. 47 There was no king in Edom. A deputy ruled. 48 Jehoshaphat made ships of Tarshish to go to Ophir for gold, but they didn’t go; for the ships wrecked at Ezion Geber. 49 Then Ahaziah the son of Ahab said to Jehoshaphat, “Let my servants go with your servants in the ships.” But Jehoshaphat would not. 50 Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in his father David’s city. Jehoram his son reigned in his place.

51 Ahaziah the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria in the seventeenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and he reigned two years over Israel. 52 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and walked in the way of his father, and in the way of his mother, and in the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, in which he made Israel to sin. 53 He served Baal and worshiped him, and provoked Yahweh, the God of Israel, to anger, in all the ways that his father had done so.

2 Kings 1

1 Moab rebelled against Israel after the death of Ahab. 2 Ahaziah fell down through the lattice in his upper room that was in Samaria, and was sick. So he sent messengers, and said to them, “Go, inquire of Baal Zebub, the god of Ekron, whether I will recover of this sickness.”

3 But Yahweh’s[*] angel said to Elijah the Tishbite, “Arise, go up to meet the messengers of the king of Samaria, and tell them, ‘Is it because there is no God[*] in Israel, that you go to inquire of Baal Zebub, the god of Ekron? 4 Now therefore Yahweh says, “You will not come down from the bed where you have gone up, but you will surely die.”’” Then Elijah departed.

5 The messengers returned to him, and he said to them, “Why is it that you have returned?”

6 They said to him, “A man came up to meet us, and said to us, ‘Go, return to the king who sent you, and tell him, “Yahweh says, ‘Is it because there is no God in Israel, that you send to inquire of Baal Zebub, the god of Ekron? Therefore you will not come down from the bed where you have gone up, but you will surely die.’”’”

7 He said to them, “What kind of man was he who came up to meet you, and told you these words?”

8 They answered him, “He was a hairy man, and wearing a leather belt around his waist.”

He said, “It’s Elijah the Tishbite.”

9 Then the king sent a captain of fifty with his fifty to him. He went up to him; and behold,[*] he was sitting on the top of the hill. He said to him, “Man of God, the king has said, ‘Come down!’”

10 Elijah answered to the captain of fifty, “If I am a man of God, then let fire come down from the sky, and consume you and your fifty!” Then fire came down from the sky, and consumed him and his fifty.

11 Again he sent to him another captain of fifty with his fifty. He answered him, “Man of God, the king has said, ‘Come down quickly!’”

12 Elijah answered them, “If I am a man of God, then let fire come down from the sky, and consume you and your fifty!” Then God’s fire came down from the sky, and consumed him and his fifty.

13 Again he sent the captain of a third fifty with his fifty. The third captain of fifty went up, and came and fell on his knees before Elijah, and begged him, and said to him, “Man of God, please let my life, and the life of these fifty of your servants, be precious in your sight. 14 Behold, fire came down from the sky, and consumed the last two captains of fifty with their fifties. But now let my life be precious in your sight.”

15 Yahweh’s angel said to Elijah, “Go down with him. Don’t be afraid of him.”

Then he arose, and went down with him to the king. 16 He said to him, “Yahweh says, ‘Because you have sent messengers to inquire of Baal Zebub, the god of Ekron, is it because there is no God in Israel to inquire of his word? Therefore you will not come down from the bed where you have gone up, but you will surely die.’”

17 So he died according to Yahweh’s word which Elijah had spoken. Jehoram began to reign in his place in the second year of Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, because he had no son. 18 Now the rest of the acts of Ahaziah which he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

2 Kings 2

1 When Yahweh was about to take Elijah up by a whirlwind into heaven, Elijah went with Elisha from Gilgal. 2 Elijah said to Elisha, “Please wait here, for Yahweh has sent me as far as Bethel.”

Elisha said, “As Yahweh lives, and as your soul lives, I will not leave you.” So they went down to Bethel.

3 The sons of the prophets who were at Bethel came out to Elisha, and said to him, “Do you know that Yahweh will take away your master from your head today?”

He said, “Yes, I know it. Hold your peace.”

4 Elijah said to him, “Elisha, please wait here, for Yahweh has sent me to Jericho.”

He said, “As Yahweh lives, and as your soul lives, I will not leave you.” So they came to Jericho.

5 The sons of the prophets who were at Jericho came near to Elisha, and said to him, “Do you know that Yahweh will take away your master from your head today?”

He answered, “Yes, I know it. Hold your peace.”

6 Elijah said to him, “Please wait here, for Yahweh has sent me to the Jordan.”

He said, “As Yahweh lives, and as your soul lives, I will not leave you.” Then they both went on. 7 Fifty men of the sons of the prophets went, and stood opposite them at a distance; and they both stood by the Jordan. 8 Elijah took his mantle, and rolled it up, and struck the waters, and they were divided here and there, so that they both went over on dry ground. 9 When they had gone over, Elijah said to Elisha, “Ask what I shall do for you, before I am taken from you.”

Elisha said, “Please let a double portion of your spirit be on me.”

10 He said, “You have asked a hard thing. If you see me when I am taken from you, it will be so for you; but if not, it will not be so.”

11 As they continued on and talked, behold, a chariot of fire and horses of fire separated them, and Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven. 12 Elisha saw it, and he cried, “My father, my father, the chariots of Israel and its horsemen!”

He saw him no more. Then he took hold of his own clothes, and tore them in two pieces. 13 He also took up Elijah’s mantle that fell from him, and went back, and stood by the bank of the Jordan. 14 He took Elijah’s mantle that fell from him, and struck the waters, and said, “Where is Yahweh, the God of Elijah?” When he also had struck the waters, they were divided apart, and Elisha went over. 15 When the sons of the prophets who were at Jericho over against him saw him, they said, “The spirit of Elijah rests on Elisha.” They came to meet him, and bowed themselves to the ground before him. 16 They said to him, “See now, there are with your servants fifty strong men. Please let them go and seek your master. Perhaps Yahweh’s Spirit has taken him up, and put him on some mountain, or into some valley.

He said, “Don’t send them.”

17 When they urged him until he was ashamed, he said, “Send them.”

Therefore they sent fifty men; and they searched for three days, but didn’t find him. 18 They came back to him, while he stayed at Jericho; and he said to them, “Didn’t I tell you, ‘Don’t go?’”

19 The men of the city said to Elisha, “Behold, please, the situation of this city is pleasant, as my lord sees; but the water is bad, and the land is barren.”

20 He said, “Bring me a new jar, and put salt in it.” Then they brought it to him. 21 He went out to the spring of the waters, and threw salt into it, and said, “Yahweh says, ‘I have healed these waters. There shall not be from there any more death or barren wasteland.’” 22 So the waters were healed to this day, according to Elisha’s word which he spoke.

23 He went up from there to Bethel. As he was going up by the way, some youths came out of the city and mocked him, and said to him, “Go up, you baldy! Go up, you baldy!” 24 He looked behind him and saw them, and cursed them in Yahweh’s name. Then two female bears came out of the woods, and mauled forty-two of those youths. 25 He went from there to Mount Carmel, and from there he returned to Samaria.

2 Kings 3

1 Now Jehoram the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria in the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and reigned twelve years. 2 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, but not like his father, and like his mother, for he put away the pillar of Baal that his father had made. 3 Nevertheless he held to the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin. He didn’t depart from them. 4 Now Mesha king of Moab was a sheep breeder; and he supplied the king of Israel with the wool of one hundred thousand lambs, and of one hundred thousand rams. 5 But when Ahab was dead, the king of Moab rebelled against the king of Israel. 6 King Jehoram went out of Samaria at that time, and mustered all Israel. 7 He went and sent to Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, saying, “The king of Moab has rebelled against me. Will you go with me against Moab to battle?”

He said, “I will go up. I am as you are, my people as your people, my horses as your horses.” 8 He said, “Which way shall we go up?”

He answered, “The way of the wilderness of Edom.” 9 So the king of Israel went with the king of Judah and the king of Edom, and they marched for seven days along a circuitous route. There was no water for the army or for the animals that followed them. 10 The king of Israel said, “Alas! For Yahweh has called these three kings together to deliver them into the hand of Moab.”

11 But Jehoshaphat said, “Isn’t there a prophet of Yahweh here, that we may inquire of Yahweh by him?”

One of the king of Israel’s servants answered, “Elisha the son of Shaphat, who poured water on the hands of Elijah, is here.”

12 Jehoshaphat said, “Yahweh’s word is with him.” So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went down to him.

13 Elisha said to the king of Israel, “What have I to do with you? Go to the prophets of your father, and to the prophets of your mother.”

The king of Israel said to him, “No, for Yahweh has called these three kings together to deliver them into the hand of Moab.” 14 Elisha said, “As Yahweh of Armies lives, before whom I stand, surely, were it not that I respect the presence of Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, I would not look toward you, nor see you. 15 But now bring me a musician.” When the musician played, Yahweh’s hand came on him. 16 He said, “Yahweh says, ‘Make this valley full of trenches.’ 17 For Yahweh says, ‘You will not see wind, neither will you see rain, yet that valley will be filled with water, and you will drink, both you and your livestock and your other animals. 18 This is an easy thing in Yahweh’s sight. He will also deliver the Moabites into your hand. 19 You shall strike every fortified city, and every choice city, and shall fell every good tree, and stop all springs of water, and mar every good piece of land with stones.’”

20 In the morning, about the time of offering the sacrifice, behold, water came by the way of Edom, and the country was filled with water.

21 Now when all the Moabites heard that the kings had come up to fight against them, they gathered themselves together, all who were able to put on armor, young and old, and stood on the border. 22 They rose up early in the morning, and the sun shone on the water, and the Moabites saw the water opposite them as red as blood. 23 They said, “This is blood. The kings are surely destroyed, and they have struck each other. Now therefore, Moab, to the plunder!”

24 When they came to the camp of Israel, the Israelites rose up and struck the Moabites, so that they fled before them; and they went forward into the land attacking the Moabites. 25 They beat down the cities; and on every good piece of land each man cast his stone, and filled it. They also stopped all the springs of water, and felled all the good trees, until in Kir Hareseth all they left was its stones; however the men armed with slings went around it, and attacked it. 26 When the king of Moab saw that the battle was too severe for him, he took with him seven hundred men who drew a sword, to break through to the king of Edom; but they could not. 27 Then he took his oldest son who would have reigned in his place, and offered him for a burnt offering on the wall. There was great wrath against Israel; and they departed from him, and returned to their own land.

2 Kings 4

1 Now a certain woman of the wives of the sons of the prophets cried out to Elisha, saying, “Your servant my husband is dead. You know that your servant feared Yahweh. Now the creditor has come to take for himself my two children to be slaves.”

2 Elisha said to her, “What should I do for you? Tell me: what do you have in the house?”

She said, “Your servant has nothing in the house, except a pot of oil.”

3 Then he said, “Go, borrow empty containers from of all your neighbors. Don’t borrow just a few containers. 4 Go in and shut the door on you and on your sons, and pour oil into all those containers; and set aside those which are full.”

5 So she went from him, and shut the door on herself and on her sons. They brought the containers to her, and she poured oil. 6 When the containers were full, she said to her son, “Bring me another container.”

He said to her, “There isn’t another container.” Then the oil stopped flowing.

7 Then she came and told the man of God. He said, “Go, sell the oil, and pay your debt; and you and your sons live on the rest.”

8 One day Elisha went to Shunem, where there was a prominent woman; and she persuaded him to eat bread. So it was, that as often as he passed by, he turned in there to eat bread. 9 She said to her husband, “See now, I perceive that this is a holy man of God who passes by us continually. 10 Please let us make a little room on the roof. Let us set for him there a bed, a table, a chair, and a lamp stand. When he comes to us, he can stay there.”

11 One day he came there, and he went to the room and lay there. 12 He said to Gehazi his servant, “Call this Shunammite.” When he had called her, she stood before him. 13 He said to him, “Say now to her, ‘Behold, you have cared for us with all this care. What is to be done for you? Would you like to be spoken for to the king, or to the captain of the army?’”

She answered, “I dwell among my own people.”

14 He said, “What then is to be done for her?”

Gehazi answered, “Most certainly she has no son, and her husband is old.”

15 He said, “Call her.” When he had called her, she stood in the door. 16 He said, “At this season, when the time comes around, you will embrace a son.”

She said, “No, my lord, you man of God, do not lie to your servant.”

17 The woman conceived, and bore a son at that season, when the time came around, as Elisha had said to her. 18 When the child was grown, one day he went out to his father to the reapers. 19 He said to his father, “My head! My head!”

He said to his servant, “Carry him to his mother.”

20 When he had taken him, and brought him to his mother, he sat on her knees until noon, and then died. 21 She went up and laid him on the man of God’s bed, and shut the door on him, and went out. 22 She called to her husband, and said, “Please send me one of the servants, and one of the donkeys, that I may run to the man of God, and come again.”

23 He said, “Why would you want go to him today? It is not a new moon or a Sabbath.”

She said, “It’s alright.”

24 Then she saddled a donkey, and said to her servant, “Drive, and go forward! Don’t slow down for me, unless I ask you to.”

25 So she went, and came to the man of God to Mount Carmel. When the man of God saw her afar off, he said to Gehazi his servant, “Behold, there is the Shunammite. 26 Please run now to meet her, and ask her, ‘Is it well with you? Is it well with your husband? Is it well with your child?’”

She answered, “It is well.”

27 When she came to the man of God to the hill, she caught hold of his feet. Gehazi came near to thrust her away; but the man of God said, “Leave her alone; for her soul is troubled within her; and Yahweh has hidden it from me, and has not told me.”

28 Then she said, “Did I ask you for a son, my lord? Didn’t I say, ‘Do not deceive me’?”

29 Then he said to Gehazi, “Tuck your cloak into your belt, take my staff in your hand, and go your way. If you meet any man, don’t greet him; and if anyone greets you, don’t answer him again. Then lay my staff on the child’s face.”

30 The child’s mother said, “As Yahweh lives, and as your soul lives, I will not leave you.”

So he arose, and followed her.

31 Gehazi went ahead of them, and laid the staff on the child’s face; but there was no voice and no hearing. Therefore he returned to meet him, and told him, “The child has not awakened.”

32 When Elisha had come into the house, behold, the child was dead, and lying on his bed. 33 He went in therefore, and shut the door on them both, and prayed to Yahweh. 34 He went up, and lay on the child, and put his mouth on his mouth, and his eyes on his eyes, and his hands on his hands. He stretched himself on him; and the child’s flesh grew warm. 35 Then he returned, and walked in the house once back and forth; and went up, and stretched himself out on him. Then the child sneezed seven times, and the child opened his eyes. 36 He called Gehazi, and said, “Call this Shunammite!” So he called her.

When she had come in to him, he said, “Take up your son.”

37 Then she went in, fell at his feet, and bowed herself to the ground; then she picked up her son, and went out.

38 Elisha came again to Gilgal. There was a famine in the land; and the sons of the prophets were sitting before him; and he said to his servant, “Get the large pot, and boil stew for the sons of the prophets.”

39 One went out into the field to gather herbs, and found a wild vine, and gathered a lap full of wild gourds from it, and came and cut them up into the pot of stew; for they didn’t recognize them. 40 So they poured out for the men to eat. As they were eating some of the stew, they cried out, and said, “Man of God, there is death in the pot!” And they could not eat it.

41 But he said, “Then bring meal.” He threw it into the pot; and he said, “Serve it to the people, that they may eat.” And there was nothing harmful in the pot.

42 A man from Baal Shalishah came, and brought the man of God bread some of the first fruits: twenty loaves of barley, and fresh ears of grain in his sack. He said, “Give to the people, that they may eat.”

43 His servant said, “What, should I set this before a hundred men?”

But he said, “Give the people, that they may eat; for Yahweh says, ‘They will eat, and will have some left over.’”

44 So he set it before them, and they ate, and had some left over, according to Yahweh’s word.

2 Kings 5

1 Now Naaman, captain of the army of the king of Syria, was a great man with his master, and honorable, because by him Yahweh had given victory to Syria: he was also a mighty man of valor, but he was a leper. 2 The Syrians had gone out in bands, and had brought away captive out of the land of Israel a little maiden; and she waited on Naaman’s wife. 3 She said to her mistress, “I wish that my lord were with the prophet who is in Samaria! Then he would heal him of his leprosy.”

4 Someone went in, and told his lord, saying, “The maiden who is from the land of Israel said this.”

5 The king of Syria said, “Go now, and I will send a letter to the king of Israel.”

He departed, and took with him ten talents[*] of silver, and six thousand pieces of gold, and ten changes of clothing. 6 He brought the letter to the king of Israel, saying, “Now when this letter has come to you, behold, I have sent Naaman my servant to you, that you may heal him of his leprosy.”

7 When the king of Israel had read the letter, he tore his clothes, and said, “Am I God, to kill and to make alive, that this man sends to me to heal a man of his leprosy? But please consider and see how he seeks a quarrel against me.”

8 It was so, when Elisha the man of God heard that the king of Israel had torn his clothes, that he sent to the king, saying, “Why have you torn your clothes? Let him come now to me, and he shall know that there is a prophet in Israel.”

9 So Naaman came with his horses and with his chariots, and stood at the door of the house of Elisha. 10 Elisha sent a messenger to him, saying, “Go and wash in the Jordan seven times, and your flesh shall come again to you, and you shall be clean.”

11 But Naaman was angry, and went away, and said, “Behold, I thought, ‘He will surely come out to me, and stand, and call on the name of Yahweh his God, and wave his hand over the place, and heal the leper.’ 12 Aren’t Abanah and Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? Couldn’t I wash in them, and be clean?” So he turned and went away in a rage.

13 His servants came near, and spoke to him, and said, “My father, if the prophet had asked you do some great thing, wouldn’t you have done it? How much rather then, when he says to you, ‘Wash, and be clean?’”

14 Then went he down, and dipped himself seven times in the Jordan, according to the saying of the man of God; and his flesh was restored like the flesh of a little child, and he was clean. 15 He returned to the man of God, he and all his company, and came, and stood before him; and he said, “See now, I know that there is no God in all the earth, but in Israel. Now therefore, please take a gift from your servant.”

16 But he said, “As Yahweh lives, before whom I stand, I will receive none.”

He urged him to take it; but he refused. 17 Naaman said, “If not, then, please let two mules’ burden of earth be given to your servant; for your servant will from now on offer neither burnt offering nor sacrifice to other gods, but to Yahweh. 18 In this thing may Yahweh pardon your servant: when my master goes into the house of Rimmon to worship there, and he leans on my hand, and I bow myself in the house of Rimmon. When I bow myself in the house of Rimmon, may Yahweh pardon your servant in this thing.”

19 He said to him, “Go in peace.”

So he departed from him a little way. 20 But Gehazi the servant of Elisha the man of God, said, “Behold, my master has spared this Naaman the Syrian, in not receiving at his hands that which he brought. As Yahweh lives, I will run after him, and take something from him.”

21 So Gehazi followed after Naaman. When Naaman saw one running after him, he came down from the chariot to meet him, and said, “Is all well?”

22 He said, “All is well. My master has sent me, saying, ‘Behold, even now two young men of the sons of the prophets have come to me from the hill country of Ephraim. Please give them a talent[*] of silver and two changes of clothing.’”

23 Naaman said, “Be pleased to take two talents.” He urged him, and bound two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of clothing, and laid them on two of his servants; and they carried them before him. 24 When he came to the hill, he took them from their hand, and stored them in the house. Then he let the men go, and they departed. 25 But he went in, and stood before his master. Elisha said to him, “Where did you come from, Gehazi?”

He said, “Your servant went nowhere.”

26 He said to him, “Didn’t my heart go with you, when the man turned from his chariot to meet you? Is it a time to receive money, and to receive garments, and olive groves and vineyards, and sheep and cattle, and male servants and female servants? 27 Therefore the leprosy of Naaman will cling to you and to your offspring[*] forever.”

He went out from his presence a leper, as white as snow.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds

or, seed

2 Kings 6

1 The sons of the prophets said to Elisha, “See now, the place where we live and meet with you is too small for us. 2 Please let us go to the Jordan, and each man take a beam from there, and let us make us a place there, where we may live.”

He answered, “Go!”

3 One said, “Please be pleased to go with your servants.”

He answered, “I will go.” 4 So he went with them. When they came to the Jordan, they cut down wood. 5 But as one was cutting down a tree, the ax head fell into the water. Then he cried, and said, “Alas, my master! For it was borrowed.”

6 The man of God asked, “Where did it fall?” He showed him the place. He cut down a stick, threw it in there, and made the iron float. 7 He said, “Take it.” So he put out his hand and took it.

8 Now the king of Syria was at war against Israel; and he took counsel with his servants, saying, “My camp will be in such and such a place.”

9 The man of God sent to the king of Israel, saying, “Beware that you not pass this place; for the Syrians are coming down there.” 10 The king of Israel sent to the place which the man of God told him and warned him of; and he saved himself there, not once or twice. 11 The king of Syria’s heart was very troubled about this. He called his servants, and said to them, “Won’t you show me which of us is for the king of Israel?”

12 One of his servants said, “No, my lord, O king; but Elisha, the prophet who is in Israel, tells the king of Israel the words that you speak in your bedroom.”

13 He said, “Go and see where he is, that I may send and get him.”

He was told, “Behold, he is in Dothan.”

14 Therefore he sent horses, chariots, and a great army there. They came by night, and surrounded the city. 15 When the servant of the man of God had risen early, and gone out, behold, an army with horses and chariots was around the city. His servant said to him, “Alas, my master! What shall we do?”

16 He answered, “Don’t be afraid; for those who are with us are more than those who are with them.” 17 Elisha prayed, and said, “Yahweh, please open his eyes, that he may see.” Yahweh opened the young man’s eyes; and he saw: and behold, the mountain was full of horses and chariots of fire around Elisha. 18 When they came down to him, Elisha prayed to Yahweh, and said, “Please strike this people with blindness.”

He struck them with blindness according to Elishah’s word. 19 Elisha said to them, “This is not the way, neither is this the city. Follow me, and I will bring you to the man whom you seek.” He led them to Samaria. 20 When they had come into Samaria, Elisha said, “Yahweh, open these men’s eyes, that they may see.”

Yahweh opened their eyes, and they saw; and behold, they were in the middle of Samaria. 21 The king of Israel said to Elisha, when he saw them, “My father, shall I strike them? Shall I strike them?”

22 He answered, “You shall not strike them. Would you strike those whom you have taken captive with your sword and with your bow? Set bread and water before them, that they may eat and drink, and go to their master.”

23 He prepared great feast for them. When they had eaten and drunk, he sent them away, and they went to their master. So the bands of Syria stopped raiding the land of Israel.

24 After this, Benhadad king of Syria gathered all his army, and went up and besieged Samaria. 25 There was a great famine in Samaria. Behold, they besieged it, until a donkey’s head was sold for eighty pieces of silver, and the fourth part of a kab[*] of dove’s dung for five pieces of silver. 26 As the king of Israel was passing by on the wall, a woman cried to him, saying, “Help, my lord, O king!”

27 He said, “If Yahweh doesn’t help you, where could I get help for you? From of the threshing floor, or from the wine press?” 28 The king said to her, “What is your problem?”

She answered, “This woman said to me, ‘Give your son, that we may eat him today, and we will eat my son tomorrow.’ 29 So we boiled my son, and ate him: and I said to her on the next day, ‘Give your son, that we may eat him;’ and she has hidden her son.”

30 When the king heard the words of the woman, he tore his clothes. Now he was passing by on the wall, and the people looked, and behold, he had sackcloth underneath on his body. 31 Then he said, “God do so to me, and more also, if the head of Elisha the son of Shaphat stays on him today.”

32 But Elisha was sitting in his house, and the elders were sitting with him. Then the king sent a man from before him; but before the messenger came to him, he said to the elders, “Do you see how this son of a murderer has sent to take away my head? Behold, when the messenger comes, shut the door, and hold the door shut against him. Isn’t the sound of his master’s feet behind him?”

33 While he was still talking with them, behold, the messenger came down to him. Then he said, “Behold, this evil is from Yahweh. Why should I wait for Yahweh any longer?”

A kab was about 2 liters, so a fourth of a kab would be about 500 milliliters or about a pint

2 Kings 8

1 Now Elisha had spoken to the woman whose son he had restored to life, saying, “Arise, and go, you and your household, and stay for a while wherever you can; for Yahweh has called for a famine. It will also come on the land for seven years.”

2 The woman arose, and did according to the man of God’s word. She went with her household, and lived in the land of the Philistines for seven years. 3 At the end of seven years, the woman returned from the land of the Philistines. Then she went out to beg the king for her house and for her land. 4 Now the king was talking with Gehazi the servant of the man of God, saying, “Please tell me all the great things that Elisha has done.” 5 As he was telling the king how he had restored to life him who was dead, behold, the woman, whose son he had restored to life, begged the king for her house and for her land. Gehazi said, “My lord, O king, this is the woman, and this is her son, whom Elisha restored to life.”

6 When the king asked the woman, she told him. So the king appointed to her a certain officer, saying, “Restore all that was hers, and all the fruits of the field since the day that she left the land, even until now.”

7 Elisha came to Damascus; and Benhadad the king of Syria was sick. He was told, “The man of God has come here.”

8 The king said to Hazael, “Take a present in your hand, and go, meet the man of God, and inquire of Yahweh by him, saying, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’”

9 So Hazael went to meet him, and took a present with him, even of every good thing of Damascus, forty camels’ burden, and came and stood before him, and said, “Your son Benhadad king of Syria has sent me to you, saying, ‘Will I recover from this sickness?’”

10 Elisha said to him, “Go, tell him, ‘You will surely recover;’ however Yahweh has shown me that he will surely die.” 11 He settled his gaze steadfastly on him, until he was ashamed. Then the man of God wept.

12 Hazael said, “Why do you weep, my lord?”

He answered, “Because I know the evil that you will do to the children of Israel. You will set their strongholds on fire, and you will kill their young men with the sword, and will dash their little ones in pieces, and rip up their pregnant women.”

13 Hazael said, “But what is your servant, who is but a dog, that he could do this great thing?”

Elisha answered, “Yahweh has shown me that you will be king over Syria.”

14 Then he departed from Elisha, and came to his master, who said to him, “What did Elisha say to you?”

He answered, “He told me that you would surely recover.”

15 On the next day, he took a thick cloth, dipped it in water, and spread it on his face, so that he died. Then Hazael reigned in his place.

16 In the fifth year of Joram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Jehoshaphat being king of Judah then, Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah began to reign. 17 He was thirty-two years old when he began to reign. He reigned eight years in Jerusalem. 18 He walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as did Ahab’s house; for he married Ahab’s daughter. He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight. 19 However Yahweh would not destroy Judah, for David his servant’s sake, as he promised him to give to him a lamp for his children always.

20 In his days Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and made a king over themselves. 21 Then Joram passed over to Zair, and all his chariots with him: and he rose up by night, and struck the Edomites who surrounded him, and the captains of the chariots; and the people fled to their tents. 22 So Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah to this day. Then Libnah revolted at the same time. 23 The rest of the acts of Joram, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 24 Joram slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in David’s city; and Ahaziah his son reigned in his place. 25 In the twelfth year of Joram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah began to reign. 26 Ahaziah was twenty-two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri king of Israel. 27 He walked in the way of Ahab’s house, and did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, as did Ahab’s house; for he was the son-in-law of Ahab’s house. 28 He went with Joram the son of Ahab to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth Gilead, and the Syrians wounded Joram. 29 King Joram returned to be healed in Jezreel from the wounds which the Syrians had given him at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Joram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick.

2 Kings 9

1 Elisha the prophet called one of the sons of the prophets, and said to him, “Put your belt on your waist, take this vial of oil in your hand, and go to Ramoth Gilead. 2 When you come there, find Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the son of Nimshi, and go in, and make him rise up from among his brothers, and take him to an inner room. 3 Then take the vial of oil, and pour it on his head, and say, ‘Yahweh says, “I have anointed you king over Israel.”’ Then open the door, flee, and don’t wait.”

4 So the young man, even the young man, the prophet, went to Ramoth Gilead. 5 When he came, behold, the captains of the army were sitting. Then he said, “I have a message for you, captain.”

Jehu said, “To which of us all?”

He said, “To you, O captain.” 6 He arose, and went into the house. Then he poured the oil on his head, and said to him, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says, ‘I have anointed you king over the people of Yahweh, even over Israel. 7 You must strike your master Ahab’s house, that I may avenge the blood of my servants the prophets, and the blood of all the servants of Yahweh, at the hand of Jezebel. 8 For the whole house of Ahab will perish. I will cut off from Ahab everyone who urinates against a wall,[*] both him who is shut up and him who is left at large in Israel. 9 I will make Ahab’s house like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of Baasha the son of Ahijah. 10 The dogs will eat Jezebel on the plot of ground of Jezreel, and there shall be no one to bury her.’” Then he opened the door and fled.

11 When Jehu came out to the servants of his lord, and one said to him, “Is all well? Why did this mad fellow come to you?”

He said to them, “You know the man and how he talks.” 12 They said, “That is a lie. Tell us now.”

He said, “He said to me, ‘Yahweh says, I have anointed you king over Israel.’”

13 Then they hurried, and each man took his cloak, and put it under him on the top of the stairs, and blew the trumpet, saying, “Jehu is king.”

14 So Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the son of Nimshi conspired against Joram. (Now Joram was keeping Ramoth Gilead, he and all Israel, because of Hazael king of Syria; 15 but king Joram had returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which the Syrians had given him, when he fought with Hazael king of Syria.) Jehu said, “If this is your thinking, then let no one escape and go out of the city, to go to tell it in Jezreel.” 16 So Jehu rode in a chariot and went to Jezreel, for Joram lay there. Ahaziah king of Judah had come down to see Joram. 17 Now the watchman was standing on the tower in Jezreel, and he spied the company of Jehu as he came, and said, “I see a company.”

Joram said, “Take a horseman, and send to meet them, and let him say, ‘Is it peace?’”

18 So one went on horseback to meet him, and said, “Thus says the king, ‘Is it peace?’”

Jehu said, “What do you have to do with peace? Fall in behind me!”

The watchman said, “The messenger came to them, but he isn’t coming back.”

19 Then he sent out a second on horseback, who came to them, and said, “Thus says the king, ‘Is it peace?’”

Jehu answered, “What do you have to do with peace? Fall in behind me!”

20 The watchman said, “He came to them, and isn’t coming back. The driving is like the driving of Jehu the son of Nimshi, for he drives furiously.”

21 Joram said, “Get ready!”

They got his chariot ready. Then Joram king of Israel and Ahaziah king of Judah went out, each in his chariot, and they went out to meet Jehu, and found him on Naboth the Jezreelite’s land. 22 When Joram saw Jehu, he said, “Is it peace, Jehu?”

He answered, “What peace, so long as the prostitution of your mother Jezebel and her witchcraft abound?”

23 Joram turned his hands, and fled, and said to Ahaziah, “This is treason, Ahaziah!”

24 Jehu drew his bow with his full strength, and struck Joram between his arms; and the arrow went out at his heart, and he sunk down in his chariot. 25 Then Jehu said to Bidkar his captain, “Pick him up, and throw him in the plot of the field of Naboth the Jezreelite; for remember how, when you and I rode together after Ahab his father, Yahweh laid this burden on him: 26 ‘Surely I have seen yesterday the blood of Naboth, and the blood of his sons,’ says Yahweh; ‘and I will repay you in this plot of ground,’ says Yahweh. Now therefore take and cast him onto the plot of ground, according to Yahweh’s word.”

27 But when Ahaziah the king of Judah saw this, he fled by the way of the garden house. Jehu followed after him, and said, “Strike him also in the chariot!” They struck him at the ascent of Gur, which is by Ibleam. He fled to Megiddo, and died there. 28 His servants carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and buried him in his tomb with his fathers in David’s city. 29 In the eleventh year of Joram the son of Ahab, Ahaziah began to reign over Judah.

30 When Jehu had come to Jezreel, Jezebel heard of it; and she painted her eyes, and adorned her head, and looked out at the window. 31 As Jehu entered in at the gate, she said, “Do you come in peace, Zimri, you murderer of your master?”

32 He lifted up his face to the window, and said, “Who is on my side? Who?”

Two or three eunuchs looked out at him.

33 He said, “Throw her down!”

So they threw her down; and some of her blood was sprinkled on the wall, and on the horses. Then he trampled her under foot. 34 When he had come in, he ate and drank. Then he said, “See now to this cursed woman, and bury her; for she is a king’s daughter.”

35 They went to bury her, but they found no more of her than the skull, the feet, and the palms of her hands. 36 Therefore they came back, and told him.

He said, “This is Yahweh’s word, which he spoke by his servant Elijah the Tishbite, saying, ‘The dogs will eat the flesh of Jezebel on the plot of Jezreel, 37 and the body of Jezebel will be as dung on the face of the field on Jezreel’s land, so that they won’t say, “This is Jezebel.”’”

or, male

2 Kings 10

1 Now Ahab had seventy sons in Samaria. Jehu wrote letters, and sent to Samaria, to the rulers of Jezreel, even the elders, and to those who brought up Ahab’s sons, saying, 2 “Now as soon as this letter comes to you, since your master’s sons are with you, and you have chariots and horses, a fortified city also, and armor, 3 Select the best and fittest of your master’s sons, set him on his father’s throne, and fight for your master’s house.”

4 But they were exceedingly afraid, and said, “Behold, the two kings didn’t stand before him! How then shall we stand?” 5 He who was over the household, and he who was over the city, the elders also, and those who raised the children, sent to Jehu, saying, “We are your servants, and will do all that you ask us. We will not make any man king. You do that which is good in your eyes.”

6 Then he wrote a letter the second time to them, saying, “If you are on my side, and if you will listen to my voice, take the heads of the men who are your master’s sons, and come to me to Jezreel by tomorrow this time.”

Now the king’s sons, being seventy persons, were with the great men of the city, who brought them up. 7 When the letter came to them, they took the king’s sons and killed them, even seventy people, and put their heads in baskets, and sent them to him to Jezreel. 8 A messenger came and told him, “They have brought the heads of the king’s sons.”

He said, “Lay them in two heaps at the entrance of the gate until the morning.” 9 In the morning, he went out, and stood, and said to all the people, “You are righteous. Behold, I conspired against my master and killed him, but who killed all these? 10 Know now that nothing will fall to the earth of Yahweh’s word, which Yahweh spoke concerning Ahab’s house. For Yahweh has done that which he spoke by his servant Elijah.”

11 So Jehu struck all that remained of Ahab’s house in Jezreel, with all his great men, his familiar friends, and his priests, until he left him no one remaining.

12 He arose and departed, and went to Samaria. As he was at the shearing house of the shepherds on the way, 13 Jehu met with the brothers of Ahaziah king of Judah, and said, “Who are you?”

They answered, “We are the brothers of Ahaziah. We are going down to greet the children of the king and the children of the queen.”

14 He said, “Take them alive!”

They took them alive, and killed them at the pit of the shearing house, even forty-two men. He didn’t leave any of them.

15 When he had departed from there, he met Jehonadab the son of Rechab coming to meet him. He greeted him, and said to him, “Is your heart right, as my heart is with your heart?”

Jehonadab answered, “It is.”

“If it is, give me your hand.” He gave him his hand; and he took him up to him into the chariot. 16 He said, “Come with me, and see my zeal for Yahweh.” So they made him ride in his chariot. 17 When he came to Samaria, he struck all who remained to Ahab in Samaria, until he had destroyed him, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke to Elijah. 18 Jehu gathered all the people together, and said to them, “Ahab served Baal a little; but Jehu will serve him much. 19 Now therefore call to me all the prophets of Baal, all of his worshipers, and all of his priests. Let no one be absent; for I have a great sacrifice to Baal. Whoever is absent, he shall not live.” But Jehu did deceptively, intending to destroy the worshipers of Baal.

20 Jehu said, “Sanctify a solemn assembly for Baal!”

So they proclaimed it. 21 Jehu sent through all Israel; and all the worshipers of Baal came, so that there was not a man left that didn’t come. They came into the house of Baal; and the house of Baal was filled from one end to another. 22 He said to him who kept the wardrobe, “Bring out robes for all the worshipers of Baal!”

So he brought robes out to them. 23 Jehu went with Jehonadab the son of Rechab into the house of Baal. Then he said to the worshipers of Baal, “Search, and see that none of the servants of Yahweh are here with you, but only the worshipers of Baal.”

24 So they went in to offer sacrifices and burnt offerings. Now Jehu had appointed for himself eighty men outside, and said, “If any of the men whom I bring into your hands escape, he who lets him go, his life shall be for the life of him.”

25 As soon as he had finished offering the burnt offering, Jehu said to the guard and to the captains, “Go in and kill them! Let no one escape.” So they struck them with the edge of the sword. The guard and the captains threw the bodies out, and went to the inner shrine of the house of Baal. 26 They brought out the pillars that were in the house of Baal, and burned them. 27 They broke down the pillar of Baal, and broke down the house of Baal, and made it a latrine, to this day. 28 Thus Jehu destroyed Baal out of Israel.

29 However, Jehu didn’t depart from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin, the golden calves that were in Bethel and that were in Dan. 30 Yahweh said to Jehu, “Because you have done well in executing that which is right in my eyes, and have done to Ahab’s house according to all that was in my heart, your descendants shall sit on the throne of Israel to the fourth generation.”

31 But Jehu took no heed to walk in the law of Yahweh, the God of Israel, with all his heart. He didn’t depart from the sins of Jeroboam, with which he made Israel to sin. 32 In those days Yahweh began to cut away parts of Israel; and Hazael struck them in all the borders of Israel; 33 from the Jordan eastward, all the land of Gilead, the Gadites, and the Reubenites, and the Manassites, from Aroer, which is by the valley of the Arnon, even Gilead and Bashan. 34 Now the rest of the acts of Jehu, and all that he did, and all his might, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 35 Jehu slept with his fathers; and they buried him in Samaria. Jehoahaz his son reigned in his place. 36 The time that Jehu reigned over Israel in Samaria was twenty-eight years.

2 Kings 11

1 Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the royal offspring.[*] 2 But Jehosheba, the daughter of king Joram, sister of Ahaziah, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king’s sons who were slain, even him and his nurse, and put them in the bedroom; and they hid him from Athaliah, so that he was not slain. 3 He was with her hidden in Yahweh’s house six years while Athaliah reigned over the land. 4 In the seventh year Jehoiada sent and fetched the captains over hundreds of the Carites and of the guard, and brought them to him into Yahweh’s house; and he made a covenant with them, and made a covenant with them in Yahweh’s house, and showed them the king’s son. 5 He commanded them, saying, “This is what you must do: a third of you, who come in on the Sabbath, shall be keepers of the watch of the king’s house; 6 a third of you shall be at the gate Sur; and a third of you at the gate behind the guard. So you shall keep the watch of the house, and be a barrier. 7 The two companies of you, even all who go out on the Sabbath, shall keep the watch of Yahweh’s house around the king. 8 You shall surround the king, every man with his weapons in his hand; and he who comes within the ranks, let him be slain. Be with the king when he goes out, and when he comes in.”

9 The captains over hundreds did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded; and they each took his men, those who were to come in on the Sabbath, with those who were to go out on the Sabbath, and came to Jehoiada the priest. 10 The priest delivered to the captains over hundreds the spears and shields that had been king David’s, which were in Yahweh’s house. 11 The guard stood, every man with his weapons in his hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, along by the altar and the house, around the king. 12 Then he brought out the king’s son, and put the crown on him, and gave him the covenant; and they made him king, and anointed him; and they clapped their hands, and said, “Long live the king!”

13 When Athaliah heard the noise of the guard and of the people, she came to the people into Yahweh’s house: 14 and she looked, and behold, the king stood by the pillar, as the tradition was, with the captains and the trumpets by the king; and all the people of the land rejoiced, and blew trumpets. Then Athaliah tore her clothes, and cried, “Treason! Treason!”

15 Jehoiada the priest commanded the captains of hundreds who were set over the army, and said to them, “Bring her out between the ranks. Kill anyone who follows her with the sword.” For the priest said, “Don’t let her be slain in Yahweh’s house.” 16 So they made way for her; and she went by the way of the horses’ entry to the king’s house, and she was slain there. 17 Jehoiada made a covenant between Yahweh and the king and the people, that they should be Yahweh’s people; also between the king and the people. 18 All the people of the land went to the house of Baal, and broke it down; his altars and his images broke they in pieces thoroughly, and killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. The priest appointed officers over Yahweh’s house. 19 He took the captains over hundreds, and the Carites, and the guard, and all the people of the land; and they brought down the king from Yahweh’s house, and came by the way of the gate of the guard to the king’s house. He sat on the throne of the kings. 20 So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. They had slain Athaliah with the sword at the king’s house.

21 Jehoash was seven years old when he began to reign.

or, seed

2 Kings 12

1 Jehoash began to reign in the seventh year of Jehu, and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Zibiah of Beersheba. 2 Jehoash did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes all his days in which Jehoiada the priest instructed him. 3 However the high places were not taken away. The people still sacrificed and burned incense in the high places. 4 Jehoash said to the priests, “All the money of the holy things that is brought into Yahweh’s house, in current money, the money of the people for whom each man is evaluated,[*] and all the money that it comes into any man’s heart to bring into Yahweh’s house, 5 let the priests take it to them, each man from his donor; and they shall repair the damage to the house, wherever any damage is found.”

6 But it was so, that in the twenty-third year of king Jehoash the priests had not repaired the damage to the house. 7 Then king Jehoash called for Jehoiada the priest, and for the other priests, and said to them, “Why don’t you repair the damage to the house? Now therefore take no more money from your treasurers, but deliver it for repair of the damage to the house.”

8 The priests consented that they should take no more money from the people, and not repair the damage to the house. 9 But Jehoiada the priest took a chest, and bored a hole in its lid, and set it beside the altar, on the right side as one comes into Yahweh’s house; and the priests who kept the threshold put all the money that was brought into Yahweh’s house into it. 10 When they saw that there was much money in the chest, the king’s scribe and the high priest came up, and they put it in bags and counted the money that was found in Yahweh’s house. 11 They gave the money that was weighed out into the hands of those who did the work, who had the oversight of Yahweh’s house; and they paid it out to the carpenters and the builders, who worked on Yahweh’s house, 12 and to the masons and the stone cutters, and for buying timber and cut stone to repair the damage to Yahweh’s house, and for all that was laid out for the house to repair it. 13 But there were not made for Yahweh’s house cups of silver, snuffers, basins, trumpets, any vessels of gold, or vessels of silver, of the money that was brought into Yahweh’s house; 14 for they gave that to those who did the work, and repaired Yahweh’s house with it. 15 Moreover they didn’t demand an accounting from the men into whose hand they delivered the money to give to those who did the work; for they dealt faithfully. 16 The money for the trespass offerings, and the money for the sin offerings was not brought into Yahweh’s house. It was the priests’.

17 Then Hazael king of Syria went up, and fought against Gath, and took it; and Hazael set his face to go up to Jerusalem. 18 Jehoash king of Judah took all the holy things that Jehoshaphat and Jehoram and Ahaziah, his fathers, kings of Judah, had dedicated, and his own holy things, and all the gold that was found in the treasures of Yahweh’s house, and of the king’s house, and sent it to Hazael king of Syria; and he went away from Jerusalem. 19 Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 20 His servants arose, and made a conspiracy, and struck Joash at the house of Millo, on the way that goes down to Silla. 21 For Jozacar the son of Shimeath, and Jehozabad the son of Shomer, his servants, struck him, and he died; and they buried him with his fathers in David’s city; and Amaziah his son reigned in his place.

Exodus 30:12

2 Kings 13

1 In the twenty-third year of Joash the son of Ahaziah, king of Judah, Jehoahaz the son of Jehu began to reign over Israel in Samaria for seventeen years. 2 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, and followed the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin. He didn’t depart from it. 3 Yahweh’s anger burned against Israel, and he delivered them into the hand of Hazael king of Syria, and into the hand of Benhadad the son of Hazael, continually. 4 Jehoahaz begged Yahweh, and Yahweh listened to him; for he saw the oppression of Israel, how the king of Syria oppressed them. 5 (Yahweh gave Israel a savior, so that they went out from under the hand of the Syrians; and the children of Israel lived in their tents as before. 6 Nevertheless they didn’t depart from the sins of the house of Jeroboam, with which he made Israel to sin, but walked in them; and the Asherah also remained in Samaria.) 7 For he didn’t leave to Jehoahaz of the people any more than fifty horsemen, and ten chariots, and ten thousand footmen; for the king of Syria destroyed them, and made them like the dust in threshing. 8 Now the rest of the acts of Jehoahaz, and all that he did, and his might, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 9 Jehoahaz slept with his fathers; and they buried him in Samaria; and Joash his son reigned in his place.

10 In the thirty-seventh year of Joash king of Judah, Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz began to reign over Israel in Samaria for sixteen years. 11 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight. He didn’t depart from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin; but he walked in them. 12 Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, and his might with which he fought against Amaziah king of Judah, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 13 Joash slept with his fathers; and Jeroboam sat on his throne. Joash was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel.

14 Now Elisha became sick with the illness of which he died; and Joash the king of Israel came down to him, and wept over him, and said, “My father, my father, the chariots of Israel and its horsemen!”

15 Elisha said to him, “Take bow and arrows”; and he took bow and arrows for himself. 16 He said to the king of Israel, “Put your hand on the bow”; and he put his hand on it. Elisha laid his hands on the king’s hands. 17 He said, “Open the window eastward”; and he opened it. Then Elisha said, “Shoot!” and he shot. He said, “Yahweh’s arrow of victory, even the arrow of victory over Syria; for you will strike the Syrians in Aphek, until you have consumed them.”

18 He said, “Take the arrows”; and he took them. He said to the king of Israel, “Strike the ground”; and he struck three times, and stopped. 19 The man of God was angry with him, and said, “You should have struck five or six times. Then you would have struck Syria until you had consumed it; whereas now you will strike Syria just three times.”

20 Elisha died, and they buried him.

Now the bands of the Moabites invaded the land at the coming in of the year. 21 As they were burying a man, behold, they saw a band of raiders; and they threw the man into Elisha’s tomb. As soon as the man touched Elisha’s bones, he revived, and stood up on his feet.

22 Hazael king of Syria oppressed Israel all the days of Jehoahaz. 23 But Yahweh was gracious to them, and had compassion on them, and had respect for them, because of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and would not destroy them, and he didn’t cast them from his presence as yet.

24 Hazael king of Syria died; and Benhadad his son reigned in his place. 25 Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz took again out of the hand of Benhadad the son of Hazael the cities which he had taken out of the hand of Jehoahaz his father by war. Joash struck him three times, and recovered the cities of Israel.

2 Kings 14

1 In the second year of Joash son of Joahaz king of Israel Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah began to reign. 2 He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jehoaddin of Jerusalem. 3 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, yet not like David his father. He did according to all that Joash his father had done. 4 However the high places were not taken away. The people still sacrificed and burned incense in the high places. 5 As soon as the kingdom was established in his hand, he killed his servants who had slain the king his father, 6 but the children of the murderers he didn’t put to death; according to that which is written in the book of the law of Moses, as Yahweh commanded, saying, “The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, nor the children be put to death for the fathers; but every man shall die for his own sin.”

7 He killed ten thousand Edomites in the Valley of Salt, and took Sela by war, and called its name Joktheel, to this day. 8 Then Amaziah sent messengers to Jehoash, the son of Jehoahaz son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, “Come, let us look one another in the face.”

9 Jehoash the king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, “The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, ‘Give your daughter to my son as wife. Then a wild animal that was in Lebanon passed by, and trampled down the thistle. 10 You have indeed struck Edom, and your heart has lifted you up. Enjoy the glory of it, and stay at home; for why should you meddle to your harm, that you fall, even you, and Judah with you?’” 11 But Amaziah would not listen. So Jehoash king of Israel went up; and he and Amaziah king of Judah looked one another in the face at Beth Shemesh, which belongs to Judah. 12 Judah was defeated by Israel; and each man fled to his tent. 13 Jehoash king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Jehoash the son of Ahaziah, at Beth Shemesh, and came to Jerusalem, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim to the corner gate, four hundred cubits.[*] 14 He took all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in Yahweh’s house and in the treasures of the king’s house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.

15 Now the rest of the acts of Jehoash which he did, and his might, and how he fought with Amaziah king of Judah, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 16 Jehoash slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel; and Jeroboam his son reigned in his place.

17 Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived after the death of Jehoash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel fifteen years. 18 Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 19 They made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Lachish; but they sent after him to Lachish, and killed him there. 20 They brought him on horses, and he was buried at Jerusalem with his fathers in David’s city.

21 All the people of Judah took Azariah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the place of his father Amaziah. 22 He built Elath, and restored it to Judah. After that the king slept with his fathers.

23 In the fifteenth year of Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah, Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel began to reign in Samaria for forty-one years. 24 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight. He didn’t depart from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, with which he made Israel to sin. 25 He restored the border of Israel from the entrance of Hamath to the sea of the Arabah, according to Yahweh, the God of Israel’s word, which he spoke by his servant Jonah the son of Amittai, the prophet, who was from Gath Hepher. 26 For Yahweh saw the affliction of Israel, that it was very bitter; for all, slave and free, and there was no helper for Israel. 27 Yahweh didn’t say that he would blot out the name of Israel from under the sky; but he saved them by the hand of Jeroboam the son of Joash. 28 Now the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, and all that he did, and his might, how he fought, and how he recovered Damascus, and Hamath, which had belonged to Judah, for Israel, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 29 Jeroboam slept with his fathers, even with the kings of Israel; and Zechariah his son reigned in his place.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

2 Kings 16

1 In the seventeenth year of Pekah the son of Remaliah, Ahaz the son of Jotham king of Judah began to reign. 2 Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. He didn’t do that which was right in Yahweh his God’s eyes, like David his father. 3 But he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, yes, and made his son to pass through the fire, according to the abominations of the nations whom Yahweh cast out from before the children of Israel. 4 He sacrificed and burned incense in the high places, on the hills, and under every green tree. 5 Then Rezin king of Syria and Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel came up to Jerusalem to wage war. They besieged Ahaz, but could not overcome him. 6 At that time Rezin king of Syria recovered Elath to Syria, and drove the Jews from Elath; and the Syrians came to Elath, and lived there, to this day. 7 So Ahaz sent messengers to Tiglath Pileser king of Assyria, saying, “I am your servant and your son. Come up and save me out of the hand of the king of Syria, and out of the hand of the king of Israel, who rise up against me.” 8 Ahaz took the silver and gold that was found in Yahweh’s house, and in the treasures of the king’s house, and sent it for a present to the king of Assyria. 9 The king of Assyria listened to him; and the king of Assyria went up against Damascus, and took it, and carried its people captive to Kir, and killed Rezin. 10 King Ahaz went to Damascus to meet Tiglath Pileser king of Assyria, and saw the altar that was at Damascus; and king Ahaz sent to Urijah the priest a drawing of the altar and plans to build it. 11 Urijah the priest built an altar. According to all that king Ahaz had sent from Damascus, so Urijah the priest made it for the coming of king Ahaz from Damascus. 12 When the king had come from Damascus, the king saw the altar; and the king came near to the altar, and offered on it. 13 He burned his burnt offering and his meal offering, poured his drink offering, and sprinkled the blood of his peace offerings on the altar. 14 The bronze altar, which was before Yahweh, he brought from the front of the house, from between his altar and Yahweh’s house, and put it on the north side of his altar. 15 King Ahaz commanded Urijah the priest, saying, “On the great altar burn the morning burnt offering, the evening meal offering, the king’s burnt offering, his meal offering, with the burnt offering of all the people of the land, their meal offering, and their drink offerings; and sprinkle on it all the blood of the burnt offering, and all the blood of the sacrifice; but the bronze altar will be for me to inquire by.” 16 Urijah the priest did so, according to all that king Ahaz commanded. 17 King Ahaz cut off the panels of the bases, and removed the basin from off them, and took down the sea from off the bronze oxen that were under it, and put it on a pavement of stone. 18 He removed the covered way for the Sabbath that they had built in the house, and the king’s entry outside to Yahweh’s house, because of the king of Assyria. 19 Now the rest of the acts of Ahaz which he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 20 Ahaz slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in David’s city, and Hezekiah his son reigned in his place.

2 Kings 17

1 In the twelfth year of Ahaz king of Judah, Hoshea the son of Elah began to reign in Samaria over Israel for nine years. 2 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, yet not as the kings of Israel who were before him. 3 Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against him, and Hoshea became his servant, and brought him tribute. 4 The king of Assyria found conspiracy in Hoshea; for he had sent messengers to So king of Egypt, and offered no tribute to the king of Assyria, as he had done year by year. Therefore the king of Assyria seized him, and bound him in prison. 5 Then the king of Assyria came up throughout all the land, went up to Samaria, and besieged it three years. 6 In the ninth year of Hoshea the king of Assyria took Samaria, and carried Israel away to Assyria, and placed them in Halah, and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes. 7 It was so because the children of Israel had sinned against Yahweh their God, who brought them up out of the land of Egypt from under the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and had feared other gods, 8 and walked in the statutes of the nations whom Yahweh cast out from before the children of Israel, and of the kings of Israel, which they made. 9 The children of Israel secretly did things that were not right against Yahweh their God; and they built high places for themselves in all their cities, from the tower of the watchmen to the fortified city; 10 and they set up for themselves pillars and Asherah poles on every high hill, and under every green tree; 11 and there they burned incense in all the high places, as the nations whom Yahweh carried away before them did; and they did wicked things to provoke Yahweh to anger; 12 and they served idols, of which Yahweh had said to them, “You shall not do this thing.” 13 Yet Yahweh testified to Israel, and to Judah, by every prophet, and every seer, saying, “Turn from your evil ways, and keep my commandments and my statutes, according to all the law which I commanded your fathers, and which I sent to you by my servants the prophets.” 14 Notwithstanding, they would not listen, but hardened their neck, like the neck of their fathers, who didn’t believe in Yahweh their God. 15 They rejected his statutes, and his covenant that he made with their fathers, and his testimonies which he testified to them; and they followed vanity, and became vain, and followed the nations that were around them, concerning whom Yahweh had commanded them that they should not do like them. 16 They abandoned all the commandments of Yahweh their God, and made molten images for themselves, even two calves, and made an Asherah, and worshiped all the army of the sky, and served Baal. 17 They caused their sons and their daughters to pass through the fire, used divination and enchantments, and sold themselves to do that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, to provoke him to anger. 18 Therefore Yahweh was very angry with Israel, and removed them out of his sight. There was none left but the tribe of Judah only. 19 Also Judah didn’t keep the commandments of Yahweh their God, but walked in the statutes of Israel which they made. 20 Yahweh rejected all the offspring[*] of Israel, afflicted them, and delivered them into the hands of raiders, until he had cast them out of his sight. 21 For he tore Israel from David’s house; and they made Jeroboam the son of Nebat king; and Jeroboam drove Israel from following Yahweh, and made them sin a great sin. 22 The children of Israel walked in all the sins of Jeroboam which he did; they didn’t depart from them 23 until Yahweh removed Israel out of his sight, as he said by all his servants the prophets. So Israel was carried away out of their own land to Assyria to this day.

24 The king of Assyria brought men from Babylon, from Cuthah, from Avva, and from Hamath and Sepharvaim, and placed them in the cities of Samaria instead of the children of Israel; and they possessed Samaria, and lived in its cities. 25 So it was, at the beginning of their dwelling there, that they didn’t fear Yahweh. Therefore Yahweh sent lions among them, which killed some of them. 26 Therefore they spoke to the king of Assyria, saying, “The nations which you have carried away and placed in the cities of Samaria don’t know the law of the god of the land. Therefore he has sent lions among them, and behold, they kill them, because they don’t know the law of the god of the land.”

27 Then the king of Assyria commanded, saying, “Carry there one of the priests whom you brought from there; and let them go and dwell there, and let him teach them the law of the god of the land.”

28 So one of the priests whom they had carried away from Samaria came and lived in Bethel, and taught them how they should fear Yahweh. 29 However every nation made gods of their own, and put them in the houses of the high places which the Samaritans had made, every nation in their cities in which they lived. 30 The men of Babylon made Succoth Benoth, and the men of Cuth made Nergal, and the men of Hamath made Ashima, 31 and the Avvites made Nibhaz and Tartak; and the Sepharvites burned their children in the fire to Adrammelech and Anammelech, the gods of Sepharvaim. 32 So they feared Yahweh, and also made from among themselves priests of the high places for themselves, who sacrificed for them in the houses of the high places. 33 They feared Yahweh, and also served their own gods, after the ways of the nations from among whom they had been carried away. 34 To this day they do what they did before. They don’t fear Yahweh, and they do not follow the statutes, or the ordinances, or the law, or the commandment which Yahweh commanded the children of Jacob, whom he named Israel; 35 with whom Yahweh had made a covenant, and commanded them, saying, “You shall not fear other gods, nor bow yourselves to them, nor serve them, nor sacrifice to them; 36 but you shall fear Yahweh, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt with great power and with an outstretched arm, and you shall bow yourselves to him, and you shall sacrifice to him. 37 The statutes and the ordinances, and the law and the commandment, which he wrote for you, you shall observe to do forever more. You shall not fear other gods. 38 You shall not forget the covenant that I have made with you. You shall not fear other gods. 39 But you shall fear Yahweh your God, and he will deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies.” 40 However they did not listen, but they did what they did before. 41 So these nations feared Yahweh, and also served their engraved images. Their children likewise, and their children’s children, as their fathers did, so they do to this day.

or, seed

2 Kings 18

1 Now in the third year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, Hezekiah the son of Ahaz king of Judah began to reign. 2 He was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Abi the daughter of Zechariah. 3 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, according to all that David his father had done. 4 He removed the high places, and broke the pillars, and cut down the Asherah. He also broke in pieces the bronze serpent that Moses had made, because in those days the children of Israel burned incense to it; and he called it Nehushtan. 5 He trusted in Yahweh, the God of Israel; so that after him was no one like him among all the kings of Judah, nor among them that were before him. 6 For he joined with Yahweh. He didn’t depart from following him, but kept his commandments, which Yahweh commanded Moses. 7 Yahweh was with him. Wherever he went, he prospered. He rebelled against the king of Assyria, and didn’t serve him. 8 He struck the Philistines to Gaza and its borders, from the tower of the watchmen to the fortified city.

9 In the fourth year of king Hezekiah, which was the seventh year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against Samaria, and besieged it. 10 At the end of three years they took it. In the sixth year of Hezekiah, which was the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel, Samaria was taken. 11 The king of Assyria carried Israel away to Assyria, and put them in Halah, and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes, 12 because they didn’t obey Yahweh their God’s voice, but transgressed his covenant, even all that Moses the servant of Yahweh commanded, and would not hear it or do it.

13 Now in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and took them. 14 Hezekiah king of Judah sent to the king of Assyria to Lachish, saying, “I have offended you. Return from me. That which you put on me, I will bear.” The king of Assyria appointed to Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents of silver and thirty talents[*] of gold. 15 Hezekiah gave him all the silver that was found in Yahweh’s house, and in the treasures of the king’s house. 16 At that time, Hezekiah cut off the gold from the doors of Yahweh’s temple, and from the pillars which Hezekiah king of Judah had overlaid, and gave it to the king of Assyria.

17 The king of Assyria sent Tartan and Rabsaris and Rabshakeh from Lachish to king Hezekiah with a great army to Jerusalem. They went up and came to Jerusalem. When they had come up, they came and stood by the conduit of the upper pool, which is in the highway of the fuller’s field. 18 When they had called to the king, Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebnah the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder came out to them. 19 Rabshakeh said to them, “Say now to Hezekiah, ‘Thus says the great king, the king of Assyria, “What confidence is this in which you trust? 20 You say (but they are but vain words), ‘There is counsel and strength for war.’ Now on whom do you trust, that you have rebelled against me? 21 Now, behold, you trust in the staff of this bruised reed, even in Egypt. If a man leans on it, it will go into his hand, and pierce it. So is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all who trust on him. 22 But if you tell me, ‘We trust in Yahweh our God;’ isn’t that he whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah has taken away, and has said to Judah and to Jerusalem, ‘You shall worship before this altar in Jerusalem?’ 23 Now therefore, please give pledges to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give you two thousand horses, if you are able on your part to set riders on them. 24 How then can you turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master’s servants, and put your trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? 25 Have I now come up without Yahweh against this place to destroy it? Yahweh said to me, ‘Go up against this land, and destroy it.’”’”

26 Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, Shebnah, and Joah, said to Rabshakeh, “Please speak to your servants in the Syrian language, for we understand it. Don’t speak with us in the Jews’ language, in the hearing of the people who are on the wall.”

27 But Rabshakeh said to them, “Has my master sent me to your master and to you, to speak these words? Hasn’t he sent me to the men who sit on the wall, to eat their own dung, and to drink their own urine with you?” 28 Then Rabshakeh stood, and cried with a loud voice in the Jews’ language, and spoke, saying, “Hear the word of the great king, the king of Assyria. 29 Thus says the king, ‘Don’t let Hezekiah deceive you; for he will not be able to deliver you out of his hand. 30 Don’t let Hezekiah make you trust in Yahweh, saying, “Yahweh will surely deliver us, and this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria.” 31 Don’t listen to Hezekiah.’ For thus says the king of Assyria, ‘Make your peace with me, and come out to me; and everyone of you eat from his own vine, and everyone from his own fig tree, and everyone drink water from his own cistern; 32 until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive trees and of honey, that you may live, and not die. Don’t listen to Hezekiah, when he persuades you, saying, “Yahweh will deliver us.” 33 Has any of the gods of the nations ever delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria? 34 Where are the gods of Hamath, and of Arpad? Where are the gods of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah? Have they delivered Samaria out of my hand? 35 Who are they among all the gods of the countries, that have delivered their country out of my hand, that Yahweh should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?’”

36 But the people stayed quiet, and answered him not a word; for the king’s commandment was, “Don’t answer him.” 37 Then Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, came with Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder, to Hezekiah with their clothes torn, and told him Rabshakeh’s words.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

2 Kings 19

1 When king Hezekiah heard it, he tore his clothes, covered himself with sackcloth, and went into Yahweh’s house. 2 He sent Eliakim, who was over the household, Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz. 3 They said to him, “Thus says Hezekiah, ‘Today is a day of trouble, of rebuke, and of rejection; for the children have come to the point of birth, and there is no strength to deliver them. 4 It may be Yahweh your God will hear all the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of Assyria his master has sent to defy the living God, and will rebuke the words which Yahweh your God has heard. Therefore lift up your prayer for the remnant that is left.’”

5 So the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah. 6 Isaiah said to them, “Tell your master this: ‘Yahweh says, “Don’t be afraid of the words that you have heard, with which the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me. 7 Behold, I will put a spirit in him, and he will hear news, and will return to his own land. I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land.”’”

8 So Rabshakeh returned and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah; for he had heard that he had departed from Lachish. 9 When he heard it said of Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, “Behold, he has come out to fight against you, he sent messengers again to Hezekiah, saying, 10 ‘Tell Hezekiah king of Judah this: “Don’t let your God in whom you trust deceive you, saying, Jerusalem will not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria. 11 Behold, you have heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands, by destroying them utterly. Will you be delivered? 12 Have the gods of the nations delivered them, which my fathers have destroyed, Gozan, Haran, Rezeph, and the children of Eden who were in Telassar? 13 Where is the king of Hamath, the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah?”’”

14 Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers and read it. Then Hezekiah went up to Yahweh’s house, and spread it before Yahweh. 15 Hezekiah prayed before Yahweh, and said, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, who sit above the cherubim, you are the God, even you alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth. You have made heaven and earth. 16 Incline your ear, Yahweh, and hear. Open your eyes, Yahweh, and see. Hear the words of Sennacherib, which he has sent to defy the living God. 17 Truly, Yahweh, the kings of Assyria have laid waste the nations and their lands, 18 and have cast their gods into the fire; for they were no gods, but the work of men’s hands, wood and stone. Therefore they have destroyed them. 19 Now therefore, Yahweh our God, save us, I beg you, out of his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that you, Yahweh, are God alone.”

20 Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent to Hezekiah, saying, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, says ‘You have prayed to me against Sennacherib king of Assyria, and I have heard you. 21 This is the word that Yahweh has spoken concerning him: ‘The virgin daughter of Zion has despised you and ridiculed you. The daughter of Jerusalem has shaken her head at you. 22 Whom have you defied and blasphemed? Against whom have you exalted your voice and lifted up your eyes on high? Against the Holy One of Israel! 23 By your messengers, you have defied the Lord, and have said, “With the multitude of my chariots, I have come up to the height of the mountains, to the innermost parts of Lebanon, and I will cut down its tall cedars and its choice cypress trees; and I will enter into his farthest lodging place, the forest of his fruitful field. 24 I have dug and drunk strange waters, and with the sole of my feet will I dry up all the rivers of Egypt.” 25 Haven’t you heard how I have done it long ago, and formed it of ancient times? Now I have brought it to pass, that it should be yours to lay waste fortified cities into ruinous heaps. 26 Therefore their inhabitants had little power. They were dismayed and confounded. They were like the grass of the field, and like the green herb, like the grass on the housetops, and like grain blasted before it has grown up. 27 But I know your sitting down, your going out, your coming in, and your raging against me. 28 Because of your raging against me, and because your arrogance has come up into my ears, therefore I will put my hook in your nose, and my bridle in your lips, and I will turn you back by the way by which you came.’

29 “This will be the sign to you: This year, you will eat that which grows of itself, and in the second year that which springs of the same; and in the third year sow, and reap, and plant vineyards, and eat its fruit. 30 The remnant that has escaped of the house of Judah will again take root downward, and bear fruit upward. 31 For out of Jerusalem a remnant will go out, and out of Mount Zion those who shall escape. Yahweh’s zeal will perform this.

32 “Therefore Yahweh says concerning the king of Assyria, ‘He will not come to this city, nor shoot an arrow there. He will not come before it with shield, nor cast up a mound against it. 33 By the way that he came, by the same he will return, and he will not come to this city,’ says Yahweh. 34 ‘For I will defend this city to save it, for my own sake, and for my servant David’s sake.’”

35 That night, Yahweh’s angel went out, and struck one hundred eighty-five thousand in the camp of the Assyrians. When men arose early in the morning, behold, these were all dead bodies. 36 So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and lived at Nineveh. 37 As he was worshiping in the house of Nisroch his god, Adrammelech and Sharezer struck him with the sword; and they escaped into the land of Ararat. Esar Haddon his son reigned in his place.

2 Kings 20

1 In those days Hezekiah was sick and dying. Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz came to him, and said to him, “Yahweh says, ‘Set your house in order; for you will die, and not live.’”

2 Then he turned his face to the wall, and prayed to Yahweh, saying, 3 “Remember now, Yahweh, I beg you, how I have walked before you in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in your sight.” And Hezekiah wept bitterly.

4 Before Isaiah had gone out into the middle part of the city, Yahweh’s word came to him, saying, 5 “Turn back, and tell Hezekiah the prince of my people, ‘Yahweh, the God of David your father, says, “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears. Behold, I will heal you. On the third day, you will go up to Yahweh’s house. 6 I will add to your days fifteen years. I will deliver you and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria. I will defend this city for my own sake, and for my servant David’s sake.”’”

7 Isaiah said, “Take a cake of figs.”

They took and laid it on the boil, and he recovered. 8 Hezekiah said to Isaiah, “What will be the sign that Yahweh will heal me, and that I will go up to Yahweh’s house the third day?”

9 Isaiah said, “This will be the sign to you from Yahweh, that Yahweh will do the thing that he has spoken: should the shadow go forward ten steps, or go back ten steps?”

10 Hezekiah answered, “It is a light thing for the shadow to go forward ten steps. No, but let the shadow return backward ten steps.”

11 Isaiah the prophet cried to Yahweh; and he brought the shadow ten steps backward, by which it had gone down on the sundial of Ahaz.

12 At that time Berodach Baladan the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah; for he had heard that Hezekiah had been sick. 13 Hezekiah listened to them, and showed them all the storehouse of his precious things, the silver, the gold, the spices, and the precious oil, and the house of his armor, and all that was found in his treasures. There was nothing in his house, or in all his dominion, that Hezekiah didn’t show them.

14 Then Isaiah the prophet came to king Hezekiah, and said to him, “What did these men say? From where did they come to you?”

Hezekiah said, “They have come from a far country, even from Babylon.”

15 He said, “What have they seen in your house?”

Hezekiah answered, “They have seen all that is in my house. There is nothing among my treasures that I have not shown them.”

16 Isaiah said to Hezekiah, “Hear Yahweh’s word. 17 ‘Behold, the days come that all that is in your house, and that which your fathers have laid up in store to this day, will be carried to Babylon. Nothing will be left,’ says Yahweh. 18 ‘They will take away some of your sons who will issue from you, whom you will father; and they will be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon.’”

19 Then Hezekiah said to Isaiah, “Yahweh’s word which you have spoken is good.” He said moreover, “Isn’t it so, if peace and truth will be in my days?”

20 Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and all his might, and how he made the pool, and the conduit, and brought water into the city, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 21 Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and Manasseh his son reigned in his place.

2 Kings 21

1 Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Hephzibah. 2 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, after the abominations of the nations whom Yahweh cast out before the children of Israel. 3 For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had destroyed; and he raised up altars for Baal, and made an Asherah, as Ahab king of Israel did, and worshiped all the army of the sky, and served them. 4 He built altars in Yahweh’s house, of which Yahweh said, “I will put my name in Jerusalem.” 5 He built altars for all the army of the sky in the two courts of Yahweh’s house. 6 He made his son to pass through the fire, practiced sorcery, used enchantments, and dealt with those who had familiar spirits, and with wizards. He did much evil in Yahweh’s sight, to provoke him to anger. 7 He set the engraved image of Asherah that he had made in the house of which Yahweh said to David and to Solomon his son, “In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name forever; 8 I will not cause the feet of Israel to wander any more out of the land which I gave their fathers, if only they will observe to do according to all that I have commanded them, and according to all the law that my servant Moses commanded them.” 9 But they didn’t listen, and Manasseh seduced them to do that which is evil more than the nations did whom Yahweh destroyed before the children of Israel. 10 Yahweh spoke by his servants the prophets, saying, 11 “Because Manasseh king of Judah has done these abominations, and has done wickedly above all that the Amorites did, who were before him, and has also made Judah to sin with his idols; 12 therefore Yahweh the God of Israel says, ‘Behold, I bring such evil on Jerusalem and Judah that whoever hears of it, both his ears will tingle. 13 I will stretch over Jerusalem the line of Samaria, and the plummet of Ahab’s house; and I will wipe Jerusalem as a man wipes a dish, wiping it and turning it upside down. 14 I will cast off the remnant of my inheritance, and deliver them into the hands of their enemies. They will become a prey and a plunder to all their enemies, 15 because they have done that which is evil in my sight, and have provoked me to anger, since the day their fathers came out of Egypt, even to this day.’”

16 Moreover Manasseh shed innocent blood very much, until he had filled Jerusalem from one end to another; besides his sin with which he made Judah to sin, in doing that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight. 17 Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and all that he did, and his sin that he sinned, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 18 Manasseh slept with his fathers, and was buried in the garden of his own house, in the garden of Uzza; and Amon his son reigned in his place.

19 Amon was twenty-two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Meshullemeth the daughter of Haruz of Jotbah. 20 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, as Manasseh his father did. 21 He walked in all the ways that his father walked in, and served the idols that his father served, and worshiped them; 22 and he abandoned Yahweh, the God of his fathers, and didn’t walk in the way of Yahweh. 23 The servants of Amon conspired against him, and put the king to death in his own house. 24 But the people of the land killed all those who had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his place. 25 Now the rest of the acts of Amon which he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 26 He was buried in his tomb in the garden of Uzza, and Josiah his son reigned in his place.

2 Kings 23

1 The king sent, and they gathered to him all the elders of Judah and of Jerusalem. 2 The king went up to Yahweh’s house, and all the men of Judah and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem with him, with the priests, the prophets, and all the people, both small and great; and he read in their hearing all the words of the book of the covenant which was found in Yahweh’s house. 3 The king stood by the pillar, and made a covenant before Yahweh, to walk after Yahweh, and to keep his commandments, his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and all his soul, to confirm the words of this covenant that were written in this book; and all the people agreed to the covenant. 4 The king commanded Hilkiah the high priest, and the priests of the second order, and the keepers of the threshold, to bring out of Yahweh’s temple all the vessels that were made for Baal, for the Asherah, and for all the army of the sky, and he burned them outside of Jerusalem in the fields of the Kidron, and carried their ashes to Bethel. 5 He got rid of the idolatrous priests, whom the kings of Judah had ordained to burn incense in the high places in the cities of Judah, and in the places around Jerusalem; those also who burned incense to Baal, to the sun, and to the moon, and to the planets, and to all the army of the sky. 6 He brought out the Asherah from Yahweh’s house, outside of Jerusalem, to the brook Kidron, and burned it at the brook Kidron, and beat it to dust, and cast its dust on the graves of the common people. 7 He broke down the houses of the male shrine prostitutes that were in Yahweh’s house, where the women wove hangings for the Asherah. 8 He brought all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and defiled the high places where the priests had burned incense, from Geba to Beersheba; and he broke down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the gate of Joshua the governor of the city, which were on a man’s left hand at the gate of the city. 9 Nevertheless the priests of the high places didn’t come up to Yahweh’s altar in Jerusalem, but they ate unleavened bread among their brothers. 10 He defiled Topheth, which is in the valley of the children of Hinnom, that no man might make his son or his daughter to pass through the fire to Molech. 11 He took away the horses that the kings of Judah had given to the sun, at the entrance of Yahweh’s house, by the room of Nathan Melech the officer, who was in the court; and he burned the chariots of the sun with fire. 12 The king broke down the altars that were on the roof of the upper room of Ahaz, which the kings of Judah had made, and the altars which Manasseh had made in the two courts of Yahweh’s house, and beat them down from there, and cast their dust into the brook Kidron. 13 The king defiled the high places that were before Jerusalem, which were on the right hand of the mountain of corruption, which Solomon the king of Israel had built for Ashtoreth the abomination of the Sidonians, and for Chemosh the abomination of Moab, and for Milcom the abomination of the children of Ammon. 14 He broke in pieces the pillars, cut down the Asherah poles, and filled their places with men’s bones. 15 Moreover the altar that was at Bethel, and the high place which Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who made Israel to sin, had made, even that altar and the high place he broke down; and he burned the high place and beat it to dust, and burned the Asherah. 16 As Josiah turned himself, he spied the tombs that were there in the mountain; and he sent, and took the bones out of the tombs, and burned them on the altar, and defiled it, according to Yahweh’s word which the man of God proclaimed, who proclaimed these things. 17 Then he said, “What monument is that which I see?”

The men of the city told him, “It is the tomb of the man of God, who came from Judah, and proclaimed these things that you have done against the altar of Bethel.”

18 He said, “Let him be! Let no one move his bones.” So they let his bones alone, with the bones of the prophet who came out of Samaria. 19 All the houses also of the high places that were in the cities of Samaria, which the kings of Israel had made to provoke Yahweh to anger, Josiah took away, and did to them according to all the acts that he had done in Bethel. 20 He killed all the priests of the high places that were there, on the altars, and burned men’s bones on them; and he returned to Jerusalem.

21 The king commanded all the people, saying, “Keep the Passover to Yahweh your God, as it is written in this book of the covenant.” 22 Surely there was not kept such a Passover from the days of the judges who judged Israel, nor in all the days of the kings of Israel, nor of the kings of Judah; 23 but in the eighteenth year of king Josiah, this Passover was kept to Yahweh in Jerusalem. 24 Moreover Josiah removed those who had familiar spirits, the wizards, and the teraphim,[*] and the idols, and all the abominations that were seen in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, that he might confirm the words of the law which were written in the book that Hilkiah the priest found in Yahweh’s house. 25 There was no king like him before him, who turned to Yahweh with all his heart, and with all his soul, and with all his might, according to all the law of Moses; and there was none like him who arose after him. 26 Notwithstanding, Yahweh didn’t turn from the fierceness of his great wrath, with which his anger burned against Judah, because of all the provocation with which Manasseh had provoked him. 27 Yahweh said, “I will also remove Judah out of my sight, as I have removed Israel, and I will cast off this city which I have chosen, even Jerusalem, and the house of which I said, ‘My name shall be there.’”

28 Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 29 In his days Pharaoh Necoh king of Egypt went up against the king of Assyria to the river Euphrates; and king Josiah went against him; and Pharaoh Necoh killed him at Megiddo, when he had seen him. 30 His servants carried him in a chariot dead from Megiddo, and brought him to Jerusalem, and buried him in his own tomb. The people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and anointed him, and made him king in his father’s place.

31 Jehoahaz was twenty-three years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. 32 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, according to all that his fathers had done. 33 Pharaoh Necoh put him in bonds at Riblah in the land of Hamath, that he might not reign in Jerusalem; and put the land to a tribute of one hundred talents of silver, and a talent[*] of gold. 34 Pharaoh Necoh made Eliakim the son of Josiah king in the place of Josiah his father, and changed his name to Jehoiakim; but he took Jehoahaz away, and he came to Egypt and died there. 35 Jehoiakim gave the silver and the gold to Pharaoh; but he taxed the land to give the money according to the commandment of Pharaoh. He exacted the silver and the gold of the people of the land, from everyone according to his assessment, to give it to Pharaoh Necoh. 36 Jehoiakim was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Zebidah the daughter of Pedaiah of Rumah. 37 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, according to all that his fathers had done.

teraphim were household idols.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

2 Kings 24

1 In his days Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up, and Jehoiakim became his servant three years. Then he turned and rebelled against him. 2 Yahweh sent against him bands of the Chaldeans, and bands of the Syrians, and bands of the Moabites, and bands of the children of Ammon, and sent them against Judah to destroy it, according to Yahweh’s word, which he spoke by his servants the prophets. 3 Surely at the commandment of Yahweh this came on Judah, to remove them out of his sight, for the sins of Manasseh, according to all that he did, 4 and also for the innocent blood that he shed; for he filled Jerusalem with innocent blood, and Yahweh would not pardon. 5 Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and all that he did, aren’t they written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 6 So Jehoiakim slept with his fathers, and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his place.

7 The king of Egypt didn’t come out of his land any more; for the king of Babylon had taken, from the brook of Egypt to the river Euphrates, all that belonged to the king of Egypt.

8 Jehoiachin was eighteen years old when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem three months. His mother’s name was Nehushta the daughter of Elnathan of Jerusalem. 9 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, according to all that his father had done. 10 At that time the servants of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up to Jerusalem, and the city was besieged. 11 Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came to the city while his servants were besieging it, 12 and Jehoiachin the king of Judah went out to the king of Babylon, he, and his mother, and his servants, and his princes, and his officers; and the king of Babylon captured him in the eighth year of his reign. 13 He carried out from there all the treasures of Yahweh’s house, and the treasures of the king’s house, and cut in pieces all the vessels of gold, which Solomon king of Israel had made in Yahweh’s temple, as Yahweh had said. 14 He carried away all Jerusalem, and all the princes, and all the mighty men of valor, even ten thousand captives, and all the craftsmen and the smiths. No one remained, except the poorest people of the land. 15 He carried away Jehoiachin to Babylon, with the king’s mother, the king’s wives, his officers, and the chief men of the land. He carried them into captivity from Jerusalem to Babylon. 16 All the men of might, even seven thousand, and the craftsmen and the smiths one thousand, all of them strong and fit for war, even them the king of Babylon brought captive to Babylon. 17 The king of Babylon made Mattaniah, Jehoiachin’s father’s brother, king in his place, and changed his name to Zedekiah. 18 Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. 19 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, according to all that Jehoiakim had done. 20 For through the anger of Yahweh, this happened in Jerusalem and Judah, until he had cast them out from his presence.

Then Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon.

2 Kings 25

1 In the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, in the tenth day of the month, Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came, he and all his army, against Jerusalem, and encamped against it; and they built forts against it around it. 2 So the city was besieged until the eleventh year of king Zedekiah. 3 On the ninth day of the fourth month, the famine was severe in the city, so that there was no bread for the people of the land. 4 Then a breach was made in the city, and all the men of war fled by night by the way of the gate between the two walls, which was by the king’s garden (now the Chaldeans were against the city around it); and the king went by the way of the Arabah. 5 But the Chaldean army pursued the king, and overtook him in the plains of Jericho; and all his army was scattered from him. 6 Then they captured the king, and carried him up to the king of Babylon to Riblah; and they passed judgment on him. 7 They killed Zedekiah’s sons before his eyes, then put out Zedekiah’s eyes, bound him in fetters, and carried him to Babylon.

8 Now in the fifth month, on the seventh day of the month, which was the nineteenth year of king Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard, a servant of the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem. 9 He burned Yahweh’s house, the king’s house, and all the houses of Jerusalem, even every great house, he burned with fire. 10 All the army of the Chaldeans, who were with the captain of the guard, broke down the walls around Jerusalem. 11 Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carried away captive the residue of the people who were left in the city, and those who fell away, who fell to the king of Babylon, and the residue of the multitude. 12 But the captain of the guard left some of the poorest of the land to work the vineyards and fields. 13 The Chaldeans broke up the pillars of brass that were in Yahweh’s house and the bases and the bronze sea that were in Yahweh’s house, and carried the brass pieces to Babylon. 14 They took away the pots, the shovels, the snuffers, the spoons, and all the vessels of brass with which they ministered. 15 The captain of the guard took away the fire pans, the basins, that which was of gold, in gold, and that which was of silver, in silver. 16 The two pillars, the one sea, and the bases, which Solomon had made for Yahweh’s house, the brass of all these vessels was not weighed. 17 The height of the one pillar was eighteen cubits,[*] and a capital of brass was on it. The height of the capital was three cubits, with network and pomegranates on the capital around it, all of brass; and the second pillar with its network was like these.

18 The captain of the guard took Seraiah the chief priest, Zephaniah the second priest, and the three keepers of the threshold; 19 and out of the city he took an officer who was set over the men of war; and five men of those who saw the king’s face, who were found in the city; and the scribe, the captain of the army, who mustered the people of the land; and sixty men of the people of the land, who were found in the city. 20 Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard took them, and brought them to the king of Babylon to Riblah. 21 The king of Babylon attacked them, and put them to death at Riblah in the land of Hamath. So Judah was carried away captive out of his land. 22 As for the people who were left in the land of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had left, even over them he made Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, governor. 23 Now when all the captains of the forces, they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah governor, they came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, even Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan the son of Kareah, and Seraiah the son of Tanhumeth the Netophathite, and Jaazaniah the son of the Maacathite, they and their men. 24 Gedaliah swore to them and to their men, and said to them, “Don’t be afraid because of the servants of the Chaldeans. Dwell in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it will be well with you.”

25 But in the seventh month, Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, of the royal offspring[*] came, and ten men with him, and struck Gedaliah, so that he died, with the Jews and the Chaldeans that were with him at Mizpah. 26 All the people, both small and great, and the captains of the forces, arose, and came to Egypt; for they were afraid of the Chaldeans. 27 In the thirty-seventh year of the captivity of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-seventh day of the month, Evilmerodach king of Babylon, in the year that he began to reign, lifted up the head of Jehoiachin king of Judah out of prison; 28 and he spoke kindly to him, and set his throne above the throne of the kings who were with him in Babylon, 29 and changed his prison garments. Jehoiachin ate bread before him continually all the days of his life; 30 and for his allowance, there was a continual allowance given him from the king, every day a portion, all the days of his life.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

or, seed

1 Chronicles 2

1 These are the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Zebulun, 2 Dan, Joseph, Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher. 3 The sons of Judah: Er, Onan, and Shelah; which three were born to him of Shua’s daughter the Canaanitess. Er, Judah’s firstborn, was wicked in Yahweh’s[*] sight; and he killed him. 4 Tamar his daughter-in-law bore him Perez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah were five. 5 The sons of Perez: Hezron and Hamul. 6 The sons of Zerah: Zimri, Ethan, Heman, Calcol, and Dara; five of them in all. 7 The son of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who committed a trespass in the devoted thing. 8 The son of Ethan: Azariah. 9 The sons also of Hezron, who were born to him: Jerahmeel, Ram, and Chelubai. 10 Ram became the father of Amminadab, and Amminadab became the father of Nahshon, prince of the children of Judah; 11 and Nahshon became the father of Salma, and Salma became the father of Boaz, 12 and Boaz became the father of Obed, and Obed became the father of Jesse; 13 and Jesse became the father of his firstborn Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimea the third, 14 Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth, 15 Ozem the sixth, David the seventh; 16 and their sisters were Zeruiah and Abigail. The sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, Joab, and Asahel, three. 17 Abigail bore Amasa; and the father of Amasa was Jether the Ishmaelite.

18 Caleb the son of Hezron became the father of children of Azubah his wife, and of Jerioth; and these were her sons: Jesher, Shobab, and Ardon. 19 Azubah died, and Caleb married Ephrath, who bore him Hur. 20 Hur became the father of Uri, and Uri became the father of Bezalel.

21 Afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Gilead, whom he took as wife when he was sixty years old; and she bore him Segub. 22 Segub became the father of Jair, who had twenty-three cities in the land of Gilead. 23 Geshur and Aram took the towns of Jair from them, with Kenath, and its villages, even sixty cities. All these were the sons of Machir the father of Gilead. 24 After Hezron died in Caleb Ephrathah, Abijah Hezron’s wife bore him Ashhur the father of Tekoa. 25 The sons of Jerahmeel the firstborn of Hezron were Ram the firstborn, Bunah, Oren, Ozem, and Ahijah. 26 Jerahmeel had another wife, whose name was Atarah. She was the mother of Onam. 27 The sons of Ram the firstborn of Jerahmeel were Maaz, Jamin, and Eker. 28 The sons of Onam were Shammai and Jada. The sons of Shammai: Nadab and Abishur. 29 The name of the wife of Abishur was Abihail; and she bore him Ahban and Molid. 30 The sons of Nadab: Seled and Appaim; but Seled died without children. 31 The son of Appaim: Ishi. The son of Ishi: Sheshan. The son of Sheshan: Ahlai. 32 The sons of Jada the brother of Shammai: Jether and Jonathan; and Jether died without children. 33 The sons of Jonathan: Peleth and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel. 34 Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name was Jarha. 35 Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant as wife; and she bore him Attai. 36 Attai became the father of Nathan, and Nathan became the father of Zabad, 37 and Zabad became the father of Ephlal, and Ephlal became the father of Obed, 38 and Obed became the father of Jehu, and Jehu became the father of Azariah, 39 and Azariah became the father of Helez, and Helez became the father of Eleasah, 40 and Eleasah became the father of Sismai, and Sismai became the father of Shallum, 41 and Shallum became the father of Jekamiah, and Jekamiah became the father of Elishama. 42 The sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were Mesha his firstborn, who was the father of Ziph; and the sons of Mareshah the father of Hebron. 43 The sons of Hebron: Korah, Tappuah, Rekem, and Shema. 44 Shema became the father of Raham, the father of Jorkeam; and Rekem became the father of Shammai. 45 The son of Shammai was Maon; and Maon was the father of Beth Zur. 46 Ephah, Caleb’s concubine, bore Haran, Moza, and Gazez; and Haran became the father of Gazez. 47 The sons of Jahdai: Regem, Jothan, Geshan, Pelet, Ephah, and Shaaph. 48 Maacah, Caleb’s concubine, bore Sheber and Tirhanah. 49 She bore also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbena, and the father of Gibea; and the daughter of Caleb was Achsah. 50 These were the sons of Caleb, the son of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah: Shobal the father of Kiriath Jearim, 51 Salma the father of Bethlehem, and Hareph the father of Beth Gader. 52 Shobal the father of Kiriath Jearim had sons: Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth. 53 The families of Kiriath Jearim: the Ithrites, the Puthites, the Shumathites, and the Mishraites; from them came the Zorathites and the Eshtaolites. 54 The sons of Salma: Bethlehem, the Netophathites, Atroth Beth Joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites. 55 The families of scribes who lived at Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, and the Sucathites. These are the Kenites who came from Hammath, the father of the house of Rechab.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

1 Chronicles 4

1 The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, Carmi, Hur, and Shobal. 2 Reaiah the son of Shobal became the father of Jahath; and Jahath became the father of Ahumai and Lahad. These are the families of the Zorathites. 3 These were the sons of the father of Etam: Jezreel, Ishma, and Idbash. The name of their sister was Hazzelelponi. 4 Penuel was the father of Gedor and Ezer the father of Hushah. These are the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah, the father of Bethlehem. 5 Ashhur the father of Tekoa had two wives, Helah and Naarah. 6 Naarah bore him Ahuzzam, Hepher, Temeni, and Haahashtari. These were the sons of Naarah. 7 The sons of Helah were Zereth, Izhar, and Ethnan. 8 Hakkoz became the father of Anub, Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel the son of Harum.

9 Jabez was more honorable than his brothers. His mother named him Jabez,[*] saying, “Because I bore him with sorrow.”

10 Jabez called on the God[*] of Israel, saying, “Oh that you would bless me indeed, and enlarge my border! May your hand be with me, and may you keep me from evil, that I may not cause pain!”

God granted him that which he requested. 11 Chelub the brother of Shuhah became the father of Mehir, who was the father of Eshton. 12 Eshton became the father of Beth Rapha, Paseah, and Tehinnah the father of Ir Nahash. These are the men of Recah. 13 The sons of Kenaz: Othniel and Seraiah. The sons of Othniel: Hathath. 14 Meonothai became the father of Ophrah: and Seraiah became the father of Joab the father of Ge Harashim; for they were craftsmen. 15 The sons of Caleb the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam. The son of Elah: Kenaz. 16 The sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel. 17 The sons of Ezrah: Jether, Mered, Epher, and Jalon; and she bore Miriam, Shammai, and Ishbah the father of Eshtemoa. 18 His wife the Jewess bore Jered the father of Gedor, Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. These are the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered took. 19 The sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, were the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maacathite. 20 The sons of Shimon: Amnon, Rinnah, Ben Hanan, and Tilon. The sons of Ishi: Zoheth, and Ben Zoheth. 21 The sons of Shelah the son of Judah: Er the father of Lecah, Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of those who worked fine linen, of the house of Ashbea; 22 and Jokim, and the men of Cozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who had dominion in Moab, and Jashubilehem. These records are ancient. 23 These were the potters, and the inhabitants of Netaim and Gederah: they lived there with the king for his work. 24 The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul; 25 Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, and Mishma his son. 26 The sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zaccur his son, Shimei his son. 27 Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters; but his brothers didn’t have many children, and all their family did not multiply like the children of Judah. 28 They lived at Beersheba, Moladah, Hazarshual, 29 at Bilhah, at Ezem, at Tolad, 30 at Bethuel, at Hormah, at Ziklag, 31 at Beth Marcaboth, Hazar Susim, at Beth Biri, and at Shaaraim. These were their cities until David’s reign. 32 Their villages were Etam, Ain, Rimmon, Tochen, and Ashan, five cities; 33 and all their villages that were around the same cities, to Baal. These were their settlements, and they have their genealogy. 34 Meshobab, Jamlech, Joshah the son of Amaziah, 35 Joel, Jehu the son of Joshibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel, 36 Elioenai, Jaakobah, Jeshohaiah, Asaiah, Adiel, Jesimiel, Benaiah, 37 and Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah— 38 these mentioned by name were princes in their families. Their fathers’ houses increased greatly.

39 They went to the entrance of Gedor, even to the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks. 40 They found fat pasture and good, and the land was wide, and quiet, and peaceful; for those who lived there before were descended from Ham. 41 These written by name came in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and struck their tents. The Meunim who were found there, and they destroyed them utterly to this day, and lived in their place; because there was pasture there for their flocks. 42 Some of them, even of the sons of Simeon, five hundred men, went to Mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah, Neariah, Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi. 43 They struck the remnant of the Amalekites who escaped, and have lived there to this day.

“Jabez” sounds similar to the Hebrew word for “pain”.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

1 Chronicles 5

1 The sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel (for he was the firstborn; but, because he defiled his father’s couch, his birthright was given to the sons of Joseph the son of Israel; and the genealogy is not to be listed according to the birthright. 2 For Judah prevailed above his brothers, and from him came the prince; but the birthright was Joseph’s)— 3 the sons of Reuben the firstborn of Israel: Hanoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi. 4 The sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son, 5 Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son, 6 and Beerah his son, whom Tilgath Pilneser king of Assyria carried away captive. He was prince of the Reubenites. 7 His brothers by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was listed: the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah, 8 and Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, who lived in Aroer, even to Nebo and Baal Meon; 9 and he lived eastward even to the entrance of the wilderness from the river Euphrates, because their livestock were multiplied in the land of Gilead.

10 In the days of Saul, they made war with the Hagrites, who fell by their hand; and they lived in their tents throughout all the land east of Gilead. 11 The sons of Gad lived over against them, in the land of Bashan to Salecah: 12 Joel the chief, Shapham the second, Janai, and Shaphat in Bashan. 13 Their brothers of their fathers’ houses: Michael, Meshullam, Sheba, Jorai, Jacan, Zia, and Eber, seven. 14 These were the sons of Abihail, the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz; 15 Ahi the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, chief of their fathers’ houses. 16 They lived in Gilead in Bashan, and in its towns, and in all the suburbs of Sharon, as far as their borders. 17 All these were listed by genealogies in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.

18 The sons of Reuben, the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, of valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword, and to shoot with bow, and skillful in war, were forty-four thousand seven hundred sixty, that were able to go out to war. 19 They made war with the Hagrites, with Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab. 20 They were helped against them, and the Hagrites were delivered into their hand, and all who were with them; for they cried to God in the battle, and he was answered them, because they put their trust in him. 21 They took away their livestock; of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred fifty thousand, and of donkeys two thousand, and of men one hundred thousand. 22 For many fell slain, because the war was of God. They lived in their place until the captivity. 23 The children of the half-tribe of Manasseh lived in the land: they increased from Bashan to Baal Hermon, Senir, and Mount Hermon. 24 These were the heads of their fathers’ houses: even Epher, Ishi, Eliel, Azriel, Jeremiah, Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valor, famous men, heads of their fathers’ houses. 25 They trespassed against the God of their fathers, and played the prostitute after the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God destroyed before them. 26 So the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgath Pilneser king of Assyria, and he carried them away, even the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, and brought them to Halah, Habor, Hara, and to the river of Gozan, to this day.

1 Chronicles 6

1 The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. 2 The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel. 3 The children of Amram: Aaron, Moses, and Miriam. The sons of Aaron: Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. 4 Eleazar became the father of Phinehas, Phinehas became the father of Abishua, 5 Abishua became the father of Bukki. Bukki became the father of Uzzi. 6 Uzzi became the father of Zerahiah. Zerahiah became the father of Meraioth. 7 Meraioth became the father of Amariah. Amariah became the father of Ahitub. 8 Ahitub became the father of Zadok. Zadok became the father of Ahimaaz. 9 Ahimaaz became the father of Azariah. Azariah became the father of Johanan. 10 Johanan became the father of Azariah, who executed the priest’s office in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem. 11 Azariah became the father of Amariah. Amariah became the father of Ahitub. 12 Ahitub became the father of Zadok. Zadok became the father of Shallum. 13 Shallum became the father of Hilkiah. Hilkiah became the father of Azariah. 14 Azariah became the father of Seraiah. Seraiah became the father of Jehozadak. 15 Jehozadak went into captivity, when Yahweh carried Judah and Jerusalem away by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.

16 The sons of Levi: Gershom, Kohath, and Merari. 17 These are the names of the sons of Gershom: Libni and Shimei. 18 The sons of Kohath were Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel. 19 The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. These are the families of the Levites according to their fathers’ households. 20 Of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son, 21 Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, and Jeatherai his son. 22 The sons of Kohath: Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son, 23 Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, Assir his son, 24 Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son. 25 The sons of Elkanah: Amasai and Ahimoth. 26 As for Elkanah, the sons of Elkanah: Zophai his son, Nahath his son, 27 Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, and Elkanah his son. 28 The sons of Samuel: the firstborn, Joel, and the second, Abijah. 29 The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son, 30 Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son. 31 These are they whom David set over the service of song in Yahweh’s house, after the ark came to rest there. 32 They ministered with song before the tabernacle of the Tent of Meeting, until Solomon had built Yahweh’s house in Jerusalem. They performed the duties of their office according to their order. 33 These are those who served, and their sons. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman the singer, the son of Joel, the son of Samuel, 34 the son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah, 35 the son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai, 36 the son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah, 37 the son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, 38 the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel. 39 His brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, even Asaph the son of Berechiah, the son of Shimea, 40 the son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchijah, 41 the son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah, 42 the son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei, 43 the son of Jahath, the son of Gershom, the son of Levi. 44 On the left hand their brothers the sons of Merari: Ethan the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch, 45 the son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah, 46 the son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shemer, 47 the son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi. 48 Their brothers the Levites were appointed for all the service of the tabernacle of God’s house. 49 But Aaron and his sons offered on the altar of burnt offering, and on the altar of incense, for all the work of the most holy place, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded.

50 These are the sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son, 51 Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son, 52 Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son, 53 Zadok his son, and Ahimaaz his son. 54 Now these are their dwelling places according to their encampments in their borders: to the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites (for theirs was the first lot), 55 to them they gave Hebron in the land of Judah, and its suburbs around it; 56 but the fields of the city, and its villages, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh. 57 To the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge, Hebron; Libnah also with its suburbs, Jattir, Eshtemoa with its suburbs, 58 Hilen with its suburbs, Debir with its suburbs, 59 Ashan with its suburbs, and Beth Shemesh with its suburbs; 60 and out of the tribe of Benjamin, Geba with its suburbs, Allemeth with its suburbs, and Anathoth with its suburbs. All their cities throughout their families were thirteen cities.

61 To the rest of the sons of Kohath were given by lot, out of the family of the tribe, out of the half-tribe, the half of Manasseh, ten cities. 62 To the sons of Gershom, according to their families, out of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities. 63 To the sons of Merari were given by lot, according to their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities. 64 The children of Israel gave to the Levites the cities with their suburbs. 65 They gave by lot out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, these cities which are mentioned by name. 66 Some of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities of their borders out of the tribe of Ephraim. 67 They gave to them the cities of refuge, Shechem in the hill country of Ephraim with its suburbs; Gezer also with its suburbs, 68 Jokmeam with its suburbs, Beth Horon with its suburbs, 69 Aijalon with its suburbs, Gath Rimmon with its suburbs; 70 and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Aner with its suburbs, and Bileam with its suburbs, for the rest of the family of the sons of Kohath.

71 To the sons of Gershom were given, out of the family of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with its suburbs, and Ashtaroth with its suburbs; 72 and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kedesh with its suburbs, Daberath with its suburbs, 73 Ramoth with its suburbs, and Anem with its suburbs; 74 and out of the tribe of Asher, Mashal with its suburbs, Abdon with its suburbs, 75 Hukok with its suburbs, and Rehob with its suburbs; 76 and out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its suburbs, Hammon with its suburbs, and Kiriathaim with its suburbs.

77 To the rest of the Levites, the sons of Merari, were given, out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmono with its suburbs, Tabor with its suburbs; 78 and beyond the Jordan at Jericho, on the east side of the Jordan, were given them, out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with its suburbs, and Jahzah with its suburbs, 79 Kedemoth with its suburbs, and Mephaath with its suburbs; 80 and out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with its suburbs, Mahanaim with its suburbs, 81 Heshbon with its suburbs, and Jazer with its suburbs.

1 Chronicles 7

1 Of the sons of Issachar: Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four. 2 The sons of Tola: Uzzi, Rephaiah, Jeriel, Jahmai, Ibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their fathers’ houses, of Tola; mighty men of valor in their generations. Their number in the days of David was twenty-two thousand six hundred. 3 The son of Uzzi: Izrahiah. The sons of Izrahiah: Michael, Obadiah, Joel, and Isshiah, five; all of them chief men. 4 With them, by their generations, after their fathers’ houses, were bands of the army for war, thirty-six thousand; for they had many wives and sons. 5 Their brothers among all the families of Issachar, mighty men of valor, listed in all by genealogy, were eighty-seven thousand. 6 The sons of Benjamin: Bela, Becher, and Jediael, three. 7 The sons of Bela: Ezbon, Uzzi, Uzziel, Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of fathers’ houses, mighty men of valor; and they were listed by genealogy twenty-two thousand thirty-four. 8 The sons of Becher: Zemirah, Joash, Eliezer, Elioenai, Omri, Jeremoth, Abijah, Anathoth, and Alemeth. All these were the sons of Becher. 9 They were listed by genealogy, after their generations, heads of their fathers’ houses, mighty men of valor, twenty thousand two hundred. 10 The son of Jediael: Bilhan. The sons of Bilhan: Jeush, Benjamin, Ehud, Chenaanah, Zethan, Tarshish, and Ahishahar. 11 All these were sons of Jediael, according to the heads of their fathers’ households, mighty men of valor, seventeen thousand two hundred, who were able to go out in the army for war. 12 So were Shuppim, Huppim, the sons of Ir, Hushim, and the sons of Aher.

13 The sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, Guni, Jezer, Shallum, and the sons of Bilhah. 14 The sons of Manasseh: Asriel, whom his concubine the Aramitess bore. She bore Machir the father of Gilead. 15 Machir took a wife of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sister’s name was Maacah. The name of the second was Zelophehad; and Zelophehad had daughters. 16 Maacah the wife of Machir bore a son, and she named him Peresh. The name of his brother was Sheresh; and his sons were Ulam and Rakem. 17 The sons of Ulam: Bedan. These were the sons of Gilead the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh. 18 His sister Hammolecheth bore Ishhod, Abiezer, and Mahlah. 19 The sons of Shemida were Ahian, Shechem, Likhi, and Aniam. 20 The sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, Bered his son, Tahath his son, Eleadah his son, Tahath his son, 21 Zabad his son, Shuthelah his son, Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath who were born in the land killed, because they came down to take away their livestock. 22 Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brothers came to comfort him. 23 He went in to his wife, and she conceived, and bore a son, and he named him Beriah,[*] because there was trouble with his house. 24 His daughter was Sheerah, who built Beth Horon the lower and the upper, and Uzzen Sheerah. 25 Rephah was his son, and Resheph, and Telah his son, Tahan his son, 26 Ladan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son, 27 Nun his son, and Joshua his son. 28 Their possessions and settlements were Bethel and its towns, and eastward Naaran, and westward Gezer, with its towns; Shechem also and its towns, to Azzah and its towns; 29 and by the borders of the children of Manasseh, Beth Shean and its towns, Taanach and its towns, Megiddo and its towns, and Dor and its towns. The children of Joseph the son of Israel lived in these. 30 The sons of Asher: Imnah, Ishvah, Ishvi, and Beriah. Serah was their sister. 31 The sons of Beriah: Heber and Malchiel, who was the father of Birzaith. 32 Heber became the father of Japhlet, Shomer, Hotham, and Shua their sister. 33 The sons of Japhlet: Pasach, Bimhal, and Ashvath. These are the children of Japhlet. 34 The sons of Shemer: Ahi, Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram. 35 The sons of Helem his brother: Zophah, Imna, Shelesh, and Amal. 36 The sons of Zophah: Suah, Harnepher, Shual, Beri, Imrah, 37 Bezer, Hod, Shamma, Shilshah, Ithran, and Beera. 38 The sons of Jether: Jephunneh, Pispa, and Ara. 39 The sons of Ulla: Arah, Hanniel, and Rizia. 40 All these were the children of Asher, heads of the fathers’ houses, choice and mighty men of valor, chief of the princes. The number of them listed by genealogy for service in war was twenty-six thousand men.

“Beriah” is similar to the Hebrew word for “misfortune”.

1 Chronicles 9

1 So all Israel were listed by genealogies; and behold,[*] they are written in the book of the kings of Israel. Judah was carried away captive to Babylon for their disobedience. 2 Now the first inhabitants who lived in their possessions in their cities were Israel, the priests, the Levites, and the temple servants. 3 In Jerusalem lived of the children of Judah, of the children of Benjamin, and of the children of Ephraim and Manasseh: 4 Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the children of Perez the son of Judah. 5 Of the Shilonites: Asaiah the firstborn, and his sons. 6 Of the sons of Zerah: Jeuel and their brothers, six hundred ninety. 7 Of the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah, 8 and Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri, and Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah; 9 and their brothers, according to their generations, nine hundred fifty-six. All these men were heads of fathers’ households by their fathers’ houses.

10 Of the priests: Jedaiah, Jehoiarib, Jachin, 11 and Azariah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of God’s house; 12 and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah, and Maasai the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer; 13 and their brothers, heads of their fathers’ houses, one thousand seven hundred sixty; very able men for the work of the service of God’s house.

14 Of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari; 15 and Bakbakkar, Heresh, Galal, and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zichri, the son of Asaph, 16 and Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, who lived in the villages of the Netophathites.

17 The porters: Shallum, Akkub, Talmon, Ahiman, and their brothers (Shallum was the chief), 18 who previously served in the king’s gate eastward. They were the porters for the camp of the children of Levi. 19 Shallum the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brothers, of his father’s house, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, keepers of the thresholds of the tent. Their fathers had been over Yahweh’s camp, keepers of the entry. 20 Phinehas the son of Eleazar was ruler over them in time past, and Yahweh was with him. 21 Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah was porter of the door of the Tent of Meeting. 22 All these who were chosen to be porters in the thresholds were two hundred twelve. These were listed by genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel the seer ordained in their office of trust. 23 So they and their children had the oversight of the gates of Yahweh’s house, even the house of the tent, by wards. 24 On the four sides were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and south. 25 Their brothers, in their villages, were to come in every seven days from time to time to be with them: 26 for the four chief porters, who were Levites, were in an office of trust, and were over the rooms and over the treasuries in God’s house. 27 They stayed around God’s house, because that duty was on them; and to their duty was its opening morning by morning. 28 Certain of them were in charge of the vessels of service; for these were brought in by count, and these were taken out by count. 29 Some of them also were appointed over the furniture, and over all the vessels of the sanctuary, over the fine flour, the wine, the oil, the frankincense, and the spices.

30 Some of the sons of the priests prepared the mixing of the spices. 31 Mattithiah, one of the Levites, who was the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite, had the office of trust over the things that were baked in pans. 32 Some of their brothers, of the sons of the Kohathites, were over the show bread, to prepare it every Sabbath. 33 These are the singers, heads of fathers’ households of the Levites, who lived in the rooms and were free from other service; for they were employed in their work day and night. 34 These were heads of fathers’ households of the Levites, throughout their generations, chief men. These lived at Jerusalem. 35 Jeiel the father of Gibeon, whose wife’s name was Maacah, lived in Gibeon with 36 his firstborn son Abdon, Zur, Kish, Baal, Ner, Nadab, 37 Gedor, Ahio, Zechariah, and Mikloth. 38 Mikloth became the father of Shimeam. They also lived with their brothers in Jerusalem, near their brothers. 39 Ner became the father of Kish. Kish became the father of Saul. Saul became the father of Jonathan, Malchishua, Abinadab, and Eshbaal. 40 The son of Jonathan was Merib Baal. Merib Baal became the father of Micah. 41 The sons of Micah: Pithon, Melech, Tahrea, and Ahaz. 42 Ahaz became the father of Jarah. Jarah became the father of Alemeth, Azmaveth, and Zimri. Zimri became the father of Moza. 43 Moza became the father of Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, and Azel his son. 44 Azel had six sons, whose names are these: Azrikam, Bocheru, Ishmael, Sheariah, Obadiah, and Hanan. These were the sons of Azel.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

1 Chronicles 10

1 Now the Philistines fought against Israel, and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain on Mount Gilboa. 2 The Philistines followed hard after Saul and after his sons; and the Philistines killed Jonathan, Abinadab, and Malchishua, the sons of Saul. 3 The battle went hard against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was distressed by reason of the archers. 4 Then Saul said to his armor bearer, “Draw your sword, and thrust me through with it, lest these uncircumcised come and abuse me.”

But his armor bearer would not; for he was terrified. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell on it. 5 When his armor bearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell on his sword, and died. 6 So Saul died with his three sons; and all his house died together. 7 When all the men of Israel who were in the valley saw that they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they abandoned their cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and lived in them.

8 On the next day, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, they found Saul and his sons fallen on Mount Gilboa. 9 They stripped him, and took his head and his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines all around, to carry the news to their idols, and to the people. 10 They put his armor in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in the house of Dagon. 11 When all Jabesh Gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul, 12 all the valiant men arose, and took away the body of Saul, and the bodies of his sons, and brought them to Jabesh, and buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh, and fasted seven days. 13 So Saul died for his trespass which he committed against Yahweh, because of Yahweh’s word, which he didn’t keep; and also because he asked counsel of one who had a familiar spirit, to inquire, 14 and didn’t inquire of Yahweh. Therefore he killed him, and turned the kingdom over to David the son of Jesse.

1 Chronicles 11

1 Then all Israel gathered themselves to David to Hebron, saying, “Behold, we are your bone and your flesh. 2 In times past, even when Saul was king, it was you who led out and brought in Israel. Yahweh your God said to you, ‘You shall be shepherd of my people Israel, and you shall be prince over my people Israel.’”

3 So all the elders of Israel came to the king to Hebron; and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before Yahweh; and they anointed David king over Israel, according to Yahweh’s word by Samuel. 4 David and all Israel went to Jerusalem (also called Jebus); and the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, were there. 5 The inhabitants of Jebus said to David, “You will not come in here.” Nevertheless David took the stronghold of Zion. The same is David’s city. 6 David said, “Whoever strikes the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain.” Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first, and was made chief. 7 David lived in the stronghold; therefore they called it David’s city. 8 He built the city all around, from Millo even around; and Joab repaired the rest of the city. 9 David grew greater and greater; for Yahweh of Armies was with him. 10 Now these are the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who showed themselves strong with him in his kingdom, together with all Israel, to make him king, according to Yahweh’s word concerning Israel.

11 This is the number of the mighty men whom David had: Jashobeam, the son of a Hachmonite, the chief of the thirty; he lifted up his spear against three hundred and killed them at one time. 12 After him was Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who was one of the three mighty men. 13 He was with David at Pasdammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where there was a plot of ground full of barley; and the people fled from before the Philistines. 14 They stood in the middle of the plot, defended it, and killed the Philistines; and Yahweh saved them by a great victory. 15 Three of the thirty chief men went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the army of the Philistines were encamped in the valley of Rephaim. 16 David was then in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines was in Bethlehem at that time. 17 David longed, and said, “Oh that one would give me water to drink from the well of Bethlehem, which is by the gate!”

18 The three broke through the army of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Bethlehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David; but David would not drink any of it, but poured it out to Yahweh, 19 and said, “My God forbid me, that I should do this! Shall I drink the blood of these men who have put their lives in jeopardy?” For they risked their lives to bring it. Therefore he would not drink it. The three mighty men did these things.

20 Abishai, the brother of Joab, he was chief of the three; for he lifted up his spear against three hundred and killed them, and had a name among the three. 21 Of the three, he was more honorable than the two, and was made their captain; however he wasn’t included in the three. 22 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done mighty deeds, killed the two sons of Ariel of Moab. He also went down and killed a lion in the middle of a pit on a snowy day. 23 He killed an Egyptian, a man of great stature, five cubits[*] high. In the Egyptian’s hand was a spear like a weaver’s beam; and he went down to him with a staff, plucked the spear out of the Egyptian’s hand, and killed him with his own spear. 24 Benaiah the son of Jehoiada did these things, and had a name among the three mighty men. 25 Behold, he was more honorable than the thirty, but he didn’t attain to the three; and David set him over his guard.

26 The mighty men of the armies also include Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Bethlehem, 27 Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite, 28 Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite, 29 Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite, 30 Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite, 31 Ithai the son of Ribai of Gibeah of the children of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite, 32 Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite, 33 Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite, 34 the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite, 35 Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur, 36 Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite, 37 Hezro the Carmelite, Naarai the son of Ezbai, 38 Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri, 39 Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the armor bearer of Joab the son of Zeruiah, 40 Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, 41 Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai, 42 Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a chief of the Reubenites, and thirty with him, 43 Hanan the son of Maacah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite, 44 Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite, 45 Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite, 46 Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite, 47 Eliel, and Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters. Therefore this Egyptian was bout 7 feet and 6 inches or 2.28 meters tall.

1 Chronicles 13

1 David consulted with the captains of thousands and of hundreds, even with every leader. 2 David said to all the assembly of Israel, “If it seems good to you, and if it is of Yahweh our God, let us send word everywhere to our brothers who are left in all the land of Israel, with whom the priests and Levites are in their cities that have suburbs, that they may gather themselves to us. 3 Also, let us again bring the ark of our God back to us; for we didn’t seek it in the days of Saul.”

4 All the assembly said that they would do so; for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people. 5 So David assembled all Israel together, from the Shihor the brook of Egypt even to the entrance of Hamath, to bring God’s ark from Kiriath Jearim.

6 David went up with all Israel to Baalah, that is, to Kiriath Jearim, which belonged to Judah, to bring up from there God Yahweh’s ark that sits above the cherubim, that is called by the Name. 7 They carried God’s ark on a new cart, and brought it out of Abinadab’s house; and Uzza and Ahio drove the cart. 8 David and all Israel played before God with all their might, even with songs, with harps, with stringed instruments, with tambourines, with cymbals, and with trumpets. 9 When they came to Chidon’s threshing floor, Uzza put out his hand to hold the ark; for the oxen stumbled. 10 Yahweh’s anger burned against Uzza, and he struck him, because he put his hand on the ark; and he died there before God. 11 David was displeased, because Yahweh had broken out against Uzza. He called that place Perez Uzza, to this day. 12 David was afraid of God that day, saying, “How can I bring God’s ark home to me?” 13 So David didn’t move the ark with him into David’s city, but carried it aside into Obed-Edom the Gittite’s house. 14 God’s ark remained with the family of Obed-Edom in his house three months; and Yahweh blessed Obed-Edom’s house and all that he had.

1 Chronicles 14

1 Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David with cedar trees, masons, and carpenters, to build him a house. 2 David perceived that Yahweh had established him king over Israel; for his kingdom was exalted on high, for his people Israel’s sake. 3 David took more wives at Jerusalem, and David became the father of more sons and daughters. 4 These are the names of the children whom he had in Jerusalem: Shammua, Shobab, Nathan, Solomon, 5 Ibhar, Elishua, Elpelet, 6 Nogah, Nepheg, Japhia, 7 Elishama, Beeliada, and Eliphelet.

8 When the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David; and David heard of it, and went out against them. 9 Now the Philistines had come and made a raid in the valley of Rephaim. 10 David inquired of God, saying, “Shall I go up against the Philistines? Will you deliver them into my hand?”

Yahweh said to him, “Go up; for I will deliver them into your hand.”

11 So they came up to Baal Perazim, and David defeated them there. David said, God has broken my enemies by my hand, like waters breaking out. Therefore they called the name of that place Baal Perazim.[*] 12 They left their gods there; and David gave a command, and they were burned with fire.

13 The Philistines made a another raid in the valley. 14 David inquired again of God; and God said to him, “You shall not go up after them. Turn away from them, and come on them opposite the mulberry trees. 15 When you hear the sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry trees, then go out to battle; for God has gone out before you to strike the army of the Philistines.”

16 David did as God commanded him; and they attacked the army of the Philistines from Gibeon even to Gezer. 17 The fame of David went out into all lands; and Yahweh brought the fear of him on all nations.

“Baal Perazim” means “The Lord who breaks out”.

1 Chronicles 15

1 David made himself houses in David’s city; and he prepared a place for God’s ark, and pitched a tent for it. 2 Then David said, “No one ought to carry God’s ark but the Levites. For Yahweh has chosen them to carry God’s ark, and to minister to him forever.”

3 David assembled all Israel at Jerusalem, to bring up Yahweh’s ark to its place, which he had prepared for it. 4 David gathered together the sons of Aaron and the Levites: 5 of the sons of Kohath, Uriel the chief, and his brothers one hundred twenty; 6 of the sons of Merari, Asaiah the chief, and his brothers two hundred twenty; 7 of the sons of Gershom, Joel the chief, and his brothers one hundred thirty; 8 of the sons of Elizaphan, Shemaiah the chief, and his brothers two hundred; 9 of the sons of Hebron, Eliel the chief, and his brothers eighty; 10 of the sons of Uzziel, Amminadab the chief, and his brothers one hundred twelve. 11 David called for Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, Joel, Shemaiah, Eliel, and Amminadab, 12 and said to them, “You are the heads of the fathers’ households of the Levites. Sanctify yourselves, both you and your brothers, that you may bring the ark of Yahweh, the God of Israel, up to the place that I have prepared for it. 13 For because you didn’t carry it at first, Yahweh our God broke out in anger against us, because we didn’t seek him according to the ordinance.”

14 So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of Yahweh, the God of Israel. 15 The children of the Levites bore God’s ark on their shoulders with its poles, as Moses commanded according to Yahweh’s word. 16 David spoke to the chief of the Levites to appoint their brothers as singers with instruments of music, stringed instruments, harps, and cymbals, sounding aloud and lifting up their voices with joy. 17 So the Levites appointed Heman the son of Joel; and of his brothers, Asaph the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari their brothers, Ethan the son of Kushaiah; 18 and with them their brothers of the second rank, Zechariah, Ben, Jaaziel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Unni, Eliab, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattithiah, Eliphelehu, Mikneiah, Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, the doorkeepers. 19 So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, were given cymbals of brass to sound aloud; 20 and Zechariah, Aziel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Unni, Eliab, Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with stringed instruments set to Alamoth; 21 and Mattithiah, Eliphelehu, Mikneiah, Obed-Edom, Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps tuned to the eight-stringed lyre, to lead. 22 Chenaniah, chief of the Levites, was over the singing. He taught the singers, because he was skillful. 23 Berechiah and Elkanah were doorkeepers for the ark. 24 Shebaniah, Joshaphat, Nethanel, Amasai, Zechariah, Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, blew the trumpets before God’s ark; and Obed-Edom and Jehiah were doorkeepers for the ark.

25 So David, the elders of Israel, and the captains over thousands, went to bring the ark of Yahweh’s covenant up out of the house of Obed-Edom with joy. 26 When God helped the Levites who bore the ark of Yahweh’s covenant, they sacrificed seven bulls and seven rams. 27 David was clothed with a robe of fine linen, as were all the Levites who bore the ark, the singers, and Chenaniah the choir master with the singers; and David had an ephod of linen on him. 28 Thus all Israel brought the ark of Yahweh’s covenant up with shouting, with sound of the cornet, with trumpets, and with cymbals, sounding aloud with stringed instruments and harps. 29 As the ark of Yahweh’s covenant came to David’s city, Michal the daughter of Saul looked out at the window, and saw king David dancing and playing; and she despised him in her heart.

1 Chronicles 16

1 They brought in God’s ark, and set it in the middle of the tent that David had pitched for it; and they offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before God. 2 When David had finished offering the burnt offering and the peace offerings, he blessed the people in Yahweh’s name. 3 He gave to everyone of Israel, both man and woman, to everyone a loaf of bread, a portion of meat, and a cake of raisins. 4 He appointed some of the Levites to minister before Yahweh’s ark, and to commemorate, to thank, and to praise Yahweh, the God of Israel: 5 Asaph the chief, and second to him Zechariah, then Jeiel, Shemiramoth, Jehiel, Mattithiah, Eliab, Benaiah, Obed-Edom, and Jeiel, with stringed instruments and with harps; and Asaph with cymbals, sounding aloud; 6 with Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests with trumpets continually, before the ark of the covenant of God.

7 Then on that day David first ordained to give thanks to Yahweh, by the hand of Asaph and his brothers.

8 Oh give thanks to Yahweh.

Call on his name.

Make what he has done known among the peoples.

9 Sing to him.

Sing praises to him.

Tell of all his marvelous works.

10 Glory in his holy name.

Let the heart of those who seek Yahweh rejoice.

11 Seek Yahweh and his strength.

Seek his face forever more.

12 Remember his marvelous works that he has done,

his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth,

13 you offspring[*] of Israel his servant,

you children of Jacob, his chosen ones.

14 He is Yahweh our God.

His judgments are in all the earth.

15 Remember his covenant forever,

the word which he commanded to a thousand generations,

16 the covenant which he made with Abraham,

his oath to Isaac.

17 He confirmed the same to Jacob for a statute,

and to Israel for an everlasting covenant,

18 saying, “I will give you the land of Canaan,

The lot of your inheritance,”

19 when you were but a few men in number,

yes, very few, and foreigners were in it.

20 They went about from nation to nation,

from one kingdom to another people.

21 He allowed no man to do them wrong.

Yes, he reproved kings for their sakes,

22 “Don’t touch my anointed ones!

Do my prophets no harm!”

23 Sing to Yahweh, all the earth!

Display his salvation from day to day.

24 Declare his glory among the nations,

and his marvelous works among all the peoples.

25 For great is Yahweh, and greatly to be praised.

He also is to be feared above all gods.

26 For all the gods of the peoples are idols,

but Yahweh made the heavens.

27 Honor and majesty are before him.

Strength and gladness are in his place.

28 Ascribe to Yahweh, you relatives of the peoples,

ascribe to Yahweh glory and strength!

29 Ascribe to Yahweh the glory due to his name.

Bring an offering, and come before him.

Worship Yahweh in holy array.

30 Tremble before him, all the earth.

The world also is established that it can’t be moved.

31 Let the heavens be glad,

and let the earth rejoice!

Let them say among the nations, “Yahweh reigns!”

32 Let the sea roar, and its fullness!

Let the field exult, and all that is in it!

33 Then the trees of the forest will sing for joy before Yahweh,

for he comes to judge the earth.

34 Oh give thanks to Yahweh, for he is good,

for his loving kindness endures forever.

35 Say, “Save us, God of our salvation!

Gather us together and deliver us from the nations,

to give thanks to your holy name,

to triumph in your praise.”

36 Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel,

from everlasting even to everlasting.

All the people said, “Amen,” and praised Yahweh.

37 So he left Asaph and his brothers there before the ark of Yahweh’s covenant, to minister before the ark continually, as every day’s work required; 38 and Obed-Edom with their brothers, sixty-eight; Obed-Edom also the son of Jeduthun and Hosah to be doorkeepers; 39 and Zadok the priest, and his brothers the priests, before Yahweh’s tabernacle in the high place that was at Gibeon, 40 to offer burnt offerings to Yahweh on the altar of burnt offering continually morning and evening, even according to all that is written in Yahweh’s law, which he commanded to Israel; 41 and with them Heman and Jeduthun, and the rest who were chosen, who were mentioned by name, to give thanks to Yahweh, because his loving kindness endures forever; 42 and with them Heman and Jeduthun with trumpets and cymbals for those that should sound aloud, and with instruments for the songs of God; and the sons of Jeduthun to be at the gate. 43 All the people departed, each man to his house; and David returned to bless his house.

or, seed

1 Chronicles 17

1 When David lived in his house, David said to Nathan the prophet, “Behold, I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of Yahweh’s covenant is in a tent.”

2 Nathan said to David, “Do all that is in your heart; for God is with you.”

3 That same night, the word of God came to Nathan, saying, 4 “Go and tell David my servant, ‘Yahweh says, “You shall not build me a house to dwell in; 5 for I have not lived in a house since the day that I brought up Israel to this day, but have gone from tent to tent, and from one tent to another. 6 In all places in which I have walked with all Israel, did I speak a word with any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to be shepherd of my people, saying, ‘Why have you not built me a house of cedar?’”’

7 “Now therefore, you shall tell my servant David, ‘Yahweh of Armies says, “I took you from the sheep pen, from following the sheep, to be prince over my people Israel. 8 I have been with you wherever you have gone, and have cut off all your enemies from before you. I will make you a name, like the name of the great ones who are in the earth. 9 I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that they may dwell in their own place, and be moved no more. The children of wickedness will not waste them any more, as at the first, 10 and from the day that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel. I will subdue all your enemies. Moreover I tell you that Yahweh will build you a house. 11 It will happen, when your days are fulfilled that you must go to be with your fathers, that I will set up your offspring[*] after you, who will be of your sons; and I will establish his kingdom. 12 He will build me a house, and I will establish his throne forever. 13 I will be his father, and he will be my son. I will not take my loving kindness away from him, as I took it from him that was before you; 14 but I will settle him in my house and in my kingdom forever. His throne will be established forever.”’” 15 According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so Nathan spoke to David.

16 Then David the king went in, and sat before Yahweh; and he said, “Who am I, Yahweh God, and what is my house, that you have brought me this far? 17 This was a small thing in your eyes, God; but you have spoken of your servant’s house for a great while to come, and have respected me according to the standard of a man of high degree, Yahweh God. 18 What can David say yet more to you concerning the honor which is done to your servant? For you know your servant. 19 Yahweh, for your servant’s sake, and according to your own heart, you have done all this greatness, to make known all these great things. 20 Yahweh, there is no one like you, neither is there any God besides you, according to all that we have heard with our ears. 21 What one nation in the earth is like your people Israel, whom God went to redeem to himself for a people, to make you a name by great and awesome things, in driving out nations from before your people, whom you redeem out of Egypt? 22 For you made your people Israel your own people forever; and you, Yahweh, became their God. 23 Now, Yahweh, let the word that you have spoken concerning your servant, and concerning his house, be established forever, and do as you have spoken. 24 Let your name be established and magnified forever, saying, ‘Yahweh of Armies is the God of Israel, even a God to Israel. The house of David your servant is established before you.’ 25 For you, my God, have revealed to your servant that you will build him a house. Therefore your servant has found courage to pray before you. 26 Now, Yahweh, you are God, and have promised this good thing to your servant. 27 Now it has pleased you to bless the house of your servant, that it may continue forever before you; for you, Yahweh, have blessed, and it is blessed forever.”

or, seed

1 Chronicles 18

1 After this, David defeated the Philistines and subdued them, and took Gath and its towns out of the hand of the Philistines. 2 He defeated Moab; and the Moabites became servants to David, and brought tribute. 3 David defeated Hadadezer king of Zobah to Hamath, as he went to establish his dominion by the river Euphrates. 4 David took from him one thousand chariots, seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen; and David hamstrung all the chariot horses, but reserved of them enough for one hundred chariots. 5 When the Syrians of Damascus came to help Hadadezer king of Zobah, David struck twenty-two thousand men of the Syrians. 6 Then David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus; and the Syrians became servants to David, and brought tribute. Yahweh gave victory to David wherever he went. 7 David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadadezer, and brought them to Jerusalem. 8 From Tibhath and from Cun, cities of Hadadezer, David took very much brass, with which Solomon made the bronze sea, the pillars, and the vessels of brass.

9 When Tou king of Hamath heard that David had struck all the army of Hadadezer king of Zobah, 10 he sent Hadoram his son to king David, to Greet him, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadadezer and struck him (for Hadadezer had wars with Tou); and he had with him all kinds of vessels of gold and silver and brass. 11 King David also dedicated these to Yahweh, with the silver and the gold that he carried away from all the nations; from Edom, from Moab, from the children of Ammon, from the Philistines, and from Amalek. 12 Moreover Abishai the son of Zeruiah struck eighteen thousand of the Edomites in the Valley of Salt. 13 He put garrisons in Edom; and all the Edomites became servants to David. Yahweh gave victory to David wherever he went.

14 David reigned over all Israel; and he executed justice and righteousness for all his people. 15 Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the army; Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was recorder; 16 Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech the son of Abiathar, were priests; Shavsha was scribe; 17 and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David were chief officials serving the king.

1 Chronicles 19

1 After this, Nahash the king of the children of Ammon died, and his son reigned in his place. 2 David said, “I will show kindness to Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father showed kindness to me.”

So David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. David’s servants came into the land of the children of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him. 3 But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun, “Do you think that David honors your father, in that he has sent comforters to you? Haven’t his servants come to you to search, to overthrow, and to spy out the land?” 4 So Hanun took David’s servants, shaved them, and cut off their garments in the middle at their buttocks, and sent them away. 5 Then some people went and told David how the men were treated. He sent to meet them; for the men were greatly humiliated. The king said, “Stay at Jericho until your beards have grown, and then return.”

6 When the children of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the children of Ammon sent one thousand talents[*] of silver to hire chariots and horsemen out of Mesopotamia, out of Aram-maacah, and out of Zobah. 7 So they hired for themselves thirty-two thousand chariots, and the king of Maacah with his people, who came and encamped near Medeba. The children of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities, and came to battle. 8 When David heard of it, he sent Joab with all the army of the mighty men. 9 The children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array at the gate of the city; and the kings who had come were by themselves in the field. 10 Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose some of all the choice men of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians. 11 The rest of the people he committed into the hand of Abishai his brother; and they put themselves in array against the children of Ammon. 12 He said, “If the Syrians are too strong for me, then you are to help me; but if the children of Ammon are too strong for you, then I will help you. 13 Be courageous, and let us be strong for our people and for the cities of our God. May Yahweh do that which seems good to him.”

14 So Joab and the people who were with him came near to the front of the Syrians to the battle; and they fled before him. 15 When the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians had fled, they likewise fled before Abishai his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem.

16 When the Syrians saw that they were defeated by Israel, they sent messengers, and called out the Syrians who were beyond the River,[*] with Shophach the captain of the army of Hadadezer leading them. 17 David was told that; so he gathered all Israel together, passed over the Jordan, came to them, and set the battle in array against them. So when David had put the battle in array against the Syrians, they fought with him. 18 The Syrians fled before Israel; and David killed of the Syrian men seven thousand chariots, and forty thousand footmen, and also killed Shophach the captain of the army. 19 When the servants of Hadadezer saw that they were defeated by Israel, they made peace with David, and served him. The Syrians would not help the children of Ammon any more.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds, so 1000 talents is about 30 metric tons

or, the Euphrates River

1 Chronicles 20

1 At the time of the return of the year, at the time when kings go out, Joab led out the army, and wasted the country of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged Rabbah. But David stayed at Jerusalem. Joab struck Rabbah, and overthrew it. 2 David took the crown of their king from off his head, and found it to weigh a talent of gold,[*] and there were precious stones in it. It was set on David’s head, and he brought very much plunder out of the city. 3 He brought out the people who were in it, and had them cut with saws, with iron picks, and with axes. David did so to all the cities of the children of Ammon. Then David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.

4 After this, war arose at Gezer with the Philistines. Then Sibbecai the Hushathite killed Sippai, of the sons of the giant; and they were subdued.

5 Again there was war with the Philistines; and Elhanan the son of Jair killed Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver’s beam. 6 There was again war at Gath, where there was a man of great stature, who had twenty-four fingers and toes, six on each hand, and six on each foot; and he also was born to the giant. 7 When he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimea David’s brother killed him. 8 These were born to the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

1 Chronicles 21

1 Satan stood up against Israel, and moved David to take a census of Israel. 2 David said to Joab and to the princes of the people, “Go, count Israel from Beersheba even to Dan; and bring me word, that I may know how many there are.”

3 Joab said, “May Yahweh make his people a hundred times as many as they are. But, my lord the king, aren’t they all my lord’s servants? Why does my lord require this thing? Why will he be a cause of guilt to Israel?”

4 Nevertheless the king’s word prevailed against Joab. Therefore Joab departed, and went throughout all Israel, then came to Jerusalem. 5 Joab gave up the sum of the census of the people to David. All those of Israel were one million one hundred thousand men who drew a sword; and in Judah were four hundred seventy thousand men who drew a sword. 6 But he didn’t count Levi and Benjamin among them; for the king’s word was abominable to Joab.

7 God was displeased with this thing; therefore he struck Israel. 8 David said to God, “I have sinned greatly, in that I have done this thing. But now put away, I beg you, the iniquity of your servant; for I have done very foolishly.”

9 Yahweh spoke to Gad, David’s seer, saying, 10 “Go and speak to David, saying, ‘Yahweh says, “I offer you three things. Choose one of them, that I may do it to you.”’”

11 So Gad came to David, and said to him, “Yahweh says, ‘Take your choice: 12 either three years of famine; or three months to be consumed before your foes, while the sword of your enemies overtakes you; or else three days the sword of Yahweh, even pestilence in the land, and Yahweh’s angel destroying throughout all the borders of Israel. Now therefore consider what answer I shall return to him who sent me.’”

13 David said to Gad, “I am in distress. Let me fall, I pray, into Yahweh’s hand; for his mercies are very great. Don’t let me fall into man’s hand.”

14 So Yahweh sent a pestilence on Israel, and seventy thousand men of Israel fell. 15 God sent an angel to Jerusalem to destroy it. As he was about to destroy, Yahweh saw, and he relented of the disaster, and said to the destroying angel, “It is enough. Now withdraw your hand.” Yahweh’s angel was standing by the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. 16 David lifted up his eyes, and saw Yahweh’s angel standing between earth and the sky, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem.

Then David and the elders, clothed in sackcloth, fell on their faces. 17 David said to God, “Isn’t it I who commanded the people to be counted? It is even I who have sinned and done very wickedly; but these sheep, what have they done? Please let your hand, O Yahweh my God, be against me, and against my father’s house; but not against your people, that they should be plagued.”

18 Then Yahweh’s angel commanded Gad to tell David that David should go up and raise an altar to Yahweh on the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. 19 David went up at the saying of Gad, which he spoke in Yahweh’s name.

20 Ornan turned back, and saw the angel; and his four sons who were with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat. 21 As David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David, and went out of the threshing floor, and bowed himself to David with his face to the ground.

22 Then David said to Ornan, “Give me the place of this threshing floor, that I may build an altar to Yahweh on it. You shall sell it to me for the full price, that the plague may be stopped from afflicting the people.”

23 Ornan said to David, “Take it for yourself, and let my lord the king do that which is good in his eyes. Behold, I give the oxen for burnt offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat for the meal offering. I give it all.”

24 King David said to Ornan, “No; but I will most certainly buy it for the full price. For I will not take that which is yours for Yahweh, nor offer a burnt offering that costs me nothing.”

25 So David gave to Ornan six hundred shekels[*] of gold by weight for the place. 26 David built an altar to Yahweh there, and offered burnt offerings and peace offerings, and called on Yahweh; and he answered him from the sky by fire on the altar of burnt offering.

27 Then Yahweh commanded the angel, and he put his sword back into its sheath. 28 At that time, when David saw that Yahweh had answered him in the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there. 29 For Yahweh’s tabernacle, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of burnt offering, were at that time in the high place at Gibeon. 30 But David couldn’t go before it to inquire of God; for he was afraid because of the sword of Yahweh’s angel.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.32 Troy ounces, so 600 shekels was about 6 kilograms or about 192 Troy ounces.

1 Chronicles 22

1 Then David said, “This is the house of Yahweh God, and this is the altar of burnt offering for Israel.”

2 David gave orders to gather together the foreigners who were in the land of Israel; and he set masons to cut dressed stones to build God’s house. 3 David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the couplings; and brass in abundance without weight; 4 and cedar trees without number, for the Sidonians and the people of Tyre brought cedar trees in abundance to David. 5 David said, “Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house that is to be built for Yahweh must be exceedingly magnificent, of fame and of glory throughout all countries. I will therefore make preparation for it.” So David prepared abundantly before his death. 6 Then he called for Solomon his son, and commanded him to build a house for Yahweh, the God of Israel. 7 David said to Solomon his son, “As for me, it was in my heart to build a house to the name of Yahweh my God. 8 But Yahweh’s word came to me, saying, ‘You have shed blood abundantly, and have made great wars. You shall not build a house to my name, because you have shed much blood on the earth in my sight. 9 Behold, a son shall be born to you, who shall be a man of peace. I will give him rest from all his enemies all around; for his name shall be Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness to Israel in his days. 10 He shall build a house for my name; and he will be my son, and I will be his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever.’ 11 Now, my son, may Yahweh be with you and prosper you, and build the house of Yahweh your God, as he has spoken concerning you. 12 May Yahweh give you discretion and understanding, and put you in charge of Israel; that so you may keep the law of Yahweh your God. 13 Then you will prosper, if you observe to do the statutes and the ordinances which Yahweh gave Moses concerning Israel. Be strong and courageous. Don’t be afraid, and don’t be dismayed. 14 Now, behold, in my affliction I have prepared for Yahweh’s house one hundred thousand talents[*] of gold, one million talents[*] of silver, and brass and iron without weight; for it is in abundance. I have also prepared timber and stone; and you may add to them. 15 There are also workmen with you in abundance, cutters and workers of stone and timber, and all kinds of men who are skillful in every kind of work; 16 of the gold, the silver, the brass, and the iron, there is no number. Arise and be doing, and may Yahweh be with you.”

17 David also commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon his son, saying, 18 “Isn’t Yahweh your God with you? Hasn’t he given you rest on every side? For he has delivered the inhabitants of the land into my hand; and the land is subdued before Yahweh, and before his people. 19 Now set your heart and your soul to follow Yahweh your God. Arise therefore, and build the sanctuary of Yahweh God, to bring the ark of Yahweh’s covenant and the holy vessels of God into the house that is to be built for Yahweh’s name.”

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 100,000 talents is about 3 metric tons

about 30,000 metric tons

1 Chronicles 23

1 Now David was old and full of days; and he made Solomon his son king over Israel. 2 He gathered together all the princes of Israel, with the priests and the Levites. 3 The Levites were counted from thirty years old and upward; and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty-eight thousand. 4 David said, “Of these, twenty-four thousand were to oversee the work of Yahweh’s house, six thousand were officers and judges, 5 four thousand were doorkeepers, and four thousand praised Yahweh with the instruments which I made for giving praise.”

6 David divided them into divisions according to the sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

7 Of the Gershonites: Ladan and Shimei. 8 The sons of Ladan: Jehiel the chief, Zetham, and Joel, three. 9 The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the heads of the fathers’ households of Ladan. 10 The sons of Shimei: Jahath, Zina, Jeush, and Beriah. These four were the sons of Shimei. 11 Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second; but Jeush and Beriah didn’t have many sons; therefore they became a fathers’ house in one reckoning.

12 The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four. 13 The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses; and Aaron was separated, that he should sanctify the most holy things, he and his sons, forever, to burn incense before Yahweh, to minister to him, and to bless in his name, forever. 14 But as for Moses the man of God, his sons were named among the tribe of Levi. 15 The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer. 16 The sons of Gershom: Shebuel the chief. 17 The sons of Eliezer were: Rehabiah the chief; and Eliezer had no other sons; but the sons of Rehabiah were very many. 18 The sons of Izhar: Shelomith the chief. 19 The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth. 20 The sons of Uzziel: Micah the chief, and Isshiah the second. 21 The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish. 22 Eleazar died, and had no sons, but daughters only: and their brothers the sons of Kish took them as wives. 23 The sons of Mushi: Mahli, Eder, and Jeremoth, three.

24 These were the sons of Levi after their fathers’ houses, even the heads of the fathers’ houses of those who were counted individually, in the number of names by their polls, who did the work for the service of Yahweh’s house, from twenty years old and upward. 25 For David said, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, has given rest to his people; and he dwells in Jerusalem forever. 26 Also the Levites will no longer need to carry the tabernacle and all its vessels for its service.” 27 For by the last words of David the sons of Levi were counted, from twenty years old and upward. 28 For their office was to wait on the sons of Aaron for the service of Yahweh’s house, in the courts, and in the rooms, and in the purifying of all holy things, even the work of the service of God’s house; 29 for the show bread also, and for the fine flour for a meal offering, whether of unleavened wafers, or of that which is baked in the pan, or of that which is soaked, and for all measurements of quantity and size; 30 and to stand every morning to thank and praise Yahweh, and likewise in the evening; 31 and to offer all burnt offerings to Yahweh, on the Sabbaths, on the new moons, and on the set feasts, in number according to the ordinance concerning them, continually before Yahweh; 32 and that they should keep the duty of the Tent of Meeting, the duty of the holy place, and the duty of the sons of Aaron their brothers, for the service of Yahweh’s house.

1 Chronicles 27

1 Now the children of Israel after their number, the heads of fathers’ households and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and their officers who served the king, in any matter of the divisions which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year—of every division were twenty-four thousand. 2 Over the first division for the first month was Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 3 He was of the children of Perez, the chief of all the captains of the army for the first month. 4 Over the division of the second month was Dodai the Ahohite, and his division; and Mikloth the ruler: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 5 The third captain of the army for the third month was Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada the priest, chief: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 6 This is that Benaiah who was the mighty man of the thirty, and over the thirty: and of his division was Ammizabad his son. 7 The fourth captain for the fourth month was Asahel the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 8 The fifth captain for the fifth month was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 9 The sixth captain for the sixth month was Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 10 The seventh captain for the seventh month was Helez the Pelonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 11 The eighth captain for the eighth month was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zerahites: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 12 The ninth captain for the ninth month was Abiezer the Anathothite, of the Benjamites: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 13 The tenth captain for the tenth month was Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zerahites: and in his division were Twenty-four thousand. 14 The eleventh captain for the eleventh month was Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 15 The twelfth captain for the twelfth month was Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel: and in his division were twenty-four thousand. 16 Furthermore over the tribes of Israel: of the Reubenites was Eliezer the son of Zichri the ruler; of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maacah; 17 of Levi, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel; of Aaron, Zadok; 18 of Judah, Elihu, one of the brothers of David; of Issachar, Omri the son of Michael; 19 of Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah; of Naphtali, Jeremoth the son of Azriel; 20 of the children of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah; of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah; 21 of the half-tribe of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah; of Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner; 22 of Dan, Azarel the son of Jeroham. These were the captains of the tribes of Israel. 23 But David didn’t take the number of them from twenty years old and under, because Yahweh had said he would increase Israel like the stars of the sky. 24 Joab the son of Zeruiah began to take a census, but didn’t finish; and wrath came on Israel for this. The number wasn’t put into the account in the chronicles of king David.

25 Over the king’s treasures was Azmaveth the son of Adiel: and over the treasures in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the towers, was Jonathan the son of Uzziah; 26 Over those who did the work of the field for tillage of the ground was Ezri the son of Chelub; 27 and over the vineyards was Shimei the Ramathite; and over the increase of the vineyards for the wine cellars was Zabdi the Shiphmite; 28 and over the olive trees and the sycamore trees that were in the lowland was Baal Hanan the Gederite; and over the cellars of oil was Joash; 29 and over the herds that fed in Sharon was Shitrai the Sharonite; and over the herds that were in the valleys was Shaphat the son of Adlai; 30 and over the camels was Obil the Ishmaelite; and over the donkeys was Jehdeiah the Meronothite; and over the flocks was Jaziz the Hagrite. 31 All these were the rulers of the property which was king David’s.

32 Also Jonathan, David’s uncle, was a counselor, a man of understanding, and a scribe; and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni was with the king’s sons. 33 Ahithophel was the king’s counselor: and Hushai the Archite was the king’s friend. 34 After Ahithophel was Jehoiada the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar. Joab was the captain of the king’s army.

1 Chronicles 28

1 David assembled all the princes of Israel, the princes of the tribes, the captains of the companies who served the king by division, the captains of thousands, the captains of hundreds, and the rulers over all the substance and possessions of the king and of his sons, with the officers and the mighty men, even all the mighty men of valor, to Jerusalem. 2 Then David the king stood up on his feet, and said, “Hear me, my brothers, and my people! As for me, it was in my heart to build a house of rest for the ark of Yahweh’s covenant, and for the footstool of our God; and I had prepared for the building. 3 But God said to me, ‘You shall not build a house for my name, because you are a man of war, and have shed blood.’ 4 However Yahweh, the God of Israel, chose me out of all the house of my father to be king over Israel forever. For he has chosen Judah to be prince; and in the house of Judah, the house of my father; and among the sons of my father he took pleasure in me to make me king over all Israel. 5 Of all my sons (for Yahweh has given me many sons), he has chosen Solomon my son to sit on the throne of Yahweh’s kingdom over Israel. 6 He said to me, ‘Solomon, your son, shall build my house and my courts; for I have chosen him to be my son, and I will be his father. 7 I will establish his kingdom forever if he continues to do my commandments and my ordinances, as it is today.’

8 Now therefore, in the sight of all Israel, Yahweh’s assembly, and in the audience of our God, observe and seek out all the commandments of Yahweh your God; that you may possess this good land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children after you forever. 9 You, Solomon my son, know the God of your father, and serve him with a perfect heart and with a willing mind; for Yahweh searches all hearts, and understands all the imaginations of the thoughts. If you seek him, he will be found by you; but if you forsake him, he will cast you off forever. 10 Take heed now; for Yahweh has chosen you to build a house for the sanctuary. Be strong, and do it.”

11 Then David gave to Solomon his son the plans for the porch of the temple, for its houses, for its treasuries, for its upper rooms, for its inner rooms, for the place of the mercy seat; 12 and the plans of all that he had by the Spirit, for the courts of Yahweh’s house, for all the surrounding rooms, for the treasuries of God’s house, and for the treasuries of the dedicated things; 13 also for the divisions of the priests and the Levites, for all the work of the service of Yahweh’s house, and for all the vessels of service in Yahweh’s house; 14 of gold by weight for the gold, for all vessels of every kind of service; for all the vessels of silver by weight, for all vessels of every kind of service; 15 by weight also for the lamp stands of gold, and for its lamps, of gold, by weight for every lamp stand and for its lamps; and for the lamp stands of silver, by weight for every lamp stand and for its lamps, according to the use of every lamp stand; 16 and the gold by weight for the tables of show bread, for every table; and silver for the tables of silver; 17 and the forks, the basins, and the cups, of pure gold; and for the golden bowls by weight for every bowl; and for the silver bowls by weight for every bowl; 18 and for the altar of incense refined gold by weight; and gold for the plans for the chariot, and the cherubim that spread out and cover the ark of Yahweh’s covenant. 19 “All this”, said David, “I have been made to understand in writing from Yahweh’s hand, even all the works of this pattern.”

20 David said to Solomon his son, “Be strong and courageous, and do it. Don’t be afraid, nor be dismayed; for Yahweh God, even my God, is with you. He will not fail you, nor forsake you, until all the work for the service of Yahweh’s house is finished. 21 Behold, there are the divisions of the priests and the Levites, for all the service of God’s house. Every willing man who has skill, for any kind of service, shall be with you in all kinds of work. Also the captains and all the people will be entirely at your command.”

1 Chronicles 29

1 David the king said to all the assembly, “Solomon my son, whom alone God has chosen, is yet young and tender, and the work is great; for the palace is not for man, but for Yahweh God. 2 Now I have prepared with all my might for the house of my God the gold for the things of gold, the silver for the things of silver, the brass for the things of brass, iron for the things of iron, and wood for the things of wood; also onyx stones, stones to be set, stones for inlaid work, of various colors, all kinds of precious stones, and marble stones in abundance. 3 In addition, because I have set my affection on the house of my God, since I have a treasure of my own of gold and silver, I give it to the house of my God, over and above all that I have prepared for the holy house, 4 even three thousand talents of gold,[*] of the gold of Ophir, and seven thousand talents[*] of refined silver, with which to overlay the walls of the houses; 5 of gold for the things of gold, and of silver for the things of silver, and for all kinds of work to be made by the hands of artisans. Who then offers willingly to consecrate himself today to Yahweh?”

6 Then the princes of the fathers’ households, and the princes of the tribes of Israel, and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, with the rulers over the king’s work, offered willingly; 7 and they gave for the service of God’s house of gold five thousand talents[*] and ten thousand darics,[*] of silver ten thousand talents, of brass eighteen thousand talents, and of iron one hundred thousand talents. 8 People with whom precious stones were found gave them to the treasure of Yahweh’s house, under the hand of Jehiel the Gershonite. 9 Then the people rejoiced, because they offered willingly, because with a perfect heart they offered willingly to Yahweh; and David the king also rejoiced with great joy. 10 Therefore David blessed Yahweh before all the assembly; and David said, “You are blessed, Yahweh, the God of Israel our father, forever and ever. 11 Yours, Yahweh, is the greatness, the power, the glory, the victory, and the majesty! For all that is in the heavens and in the earth is yours. Yours is the kingdom, Yahweh, and you are exalted as head above all. 12 Both riches and honor come from you, and you rule over all! In your hand is power and might! It is in your hand to make great, and to give strength to all! 13 Now therefore, our God, we thank you, and praise your glorious name. 14 But who am I, and what is my people, that we should be able to offer so willingly as this? For all things come from you, and of your own have we given you. 15 For we are strangers before you, and foreigners, as all our fathers were. Our days on the earth are as a shadow, and there is no remaining. 16 Yahweh our God, all this store that we have prepared to build you a house for your holy name comes from your hand, and is all your own. 17 I know also, my God, that you try the heart, and have pleasure in uprightness. As for me, in the uprightness of my heart I have willingly offered all these things. Now I have seen with joy your people, who are present here, offer willingly to you. 18 Yahweh, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel, our fathers, keep this desire forever in the thoughts of the heart of your people, and prepare their heart for you; 19 and give to Solomon my son a perfect heart, to keep your commandments, your testimonies, and your statutes, and to do all these things, and to build the palace, for which I have made provision.”

20 Then David said to all the assembly, “Now bless Yahweh your God!”

All the assembly blessed Yahweh, the God of their fathers, and bowed down their heads and prostrated themselves before Yahweh and the king. 21 They sacrificed sacrifices to Yahweh, and offered burnt offerings to Yahweh, on the next day after that day, even one thousand bulls, one thousand rams, and one thousand lambs, with their drink offerings and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel, 22 and ate and drank before Yahweh on that day with great gladness. They made Solomon the son of David king the second time, and anointed him before Yahweh to be prince, and Zadok to be priest.

23 Then Solomon sat on the throne of Yahweh as king instead of David his father, and prospered; and all Israel obeyed him. 24 All the princes, the mighty men, and also all of the sons of king David submitted themselves to Solomon the king. 25 Yahweh magnified Solomon exceedingly in the sight of all Israel, and gave to him such royal majesty as had not been on any king before him in Israel. 26 Now David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel. 27 The time that he reigned over Israel was forty years; he reigned seven years in Hebron, and he reigned thirty-three years in Jerusalem. 28 He died at a good old age, full of days, riches, and honor; and Solomon his son reigned in his place. 29 Now the acts of David the king, first and last, behold, they are written in the history of Samuel the seer, and in the history of Nathan the prophet, and in the history of Gad the seer, 30 with all his reign and his might, and the times that went over him, and over Israel, and over all the kingdoms of the countries.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 3000 talents is about 90 metric tons

about 21 metric tons

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 5000 talents is about 150 metric tons

a daric was a gold coin issued by a Persian king, weighing about 8.4 grams or about 0.27 troy ounces each.

2 Chronicles 1

1 Solomon the son of David was firmly established in his kingdom, and Yahweh[*] his God[*] was with him, and made him exceedingly great. 2 Solomon spoke to all Israel, to the captains of thousands and of hundreds, to the judges, and to every prince in all Israel, the heads of the fathers’ households. 3 So Solomon, and all the assembly with him, went to the high place that was at Gibeon; for God’s Tent of Meeting was there, which Yahweh’s servant Moses had made in the wilderness. 4 But David had brought God’s ark up from Kiriath Jearim to the place that David had prepared for it; for he had pitched a tent for it at Jerusalem. 5 Moreover the bronze altar that Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, had made was there before Yahweh’s tabernacle; and Solomon and the assembly were seeking counsel there. 6 Solomon went up there to the bronze altar before Yahweh, which was at the Tent of Meeting, and offered one thousand burnt offerings on it.

7 That night, God appeared to Solomon and said to him, “Ask for what you want me to give you.”

8 Solomon said to God, “You have shown great loving kindness to David my father, and have made me king in his place. 9 Now, Yahweh God, let your promise to David my father be established; for you have made me king over a people like the dust of the earth in multitude. 10 Now give me wisdom and knowledge, that I may go out and come in before this people; for who can judge this great people of yours?”

11 God said to Solomon, “Because this was in your heart, and you have not asked riches, wealth, honor, or the life of those who hate you, nor yet have you asked for long life; but have asked for wisdom and knowledge for yourself, that you may judge my people, over whom I have made you king, 12 therefore wisdom and knowledge is granted to you. I will give you riches, wealth, and honor, such as none of the kings have had who have been before you had, and none after you will have.”

13 So Solomon came from the high place that was at Gibeon, from before the Tent of Meeting, to Jerusalem; and he reigned over Israel.

14 Solomon gathered chariots and horsemen. He had one thousand four hundred chariots and twelve thousand horsemen that he placed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. 15 The king made silver and gold to be as common as stones in Jerusalem, and he made cedars to be as common as the sycamore trees that are in the lowland. 16 The horses which Solomon had were brought out of Egypt and from Kue. The king’s merchants purchased them from Kue. 17 They brought up and brought out of Egypt a chariot for six hundred pieces of silver, and a horse for one hundred fifty.[*] They also exported them to the Hittite kings and the Syrian[*] kings.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

The pieces of silver were probably shekels, so 600 pieces would be about 13.2 lbs. or 6 kg. of silver, and 150 would be about 3.3 lbs. or 1.5 kg. of silver.

or, Aramean

2 Chronicles 2

1 Now Solomon decided to build a house for Yahweh’s name, and a house for his kingdom. 2 Solomon counted out seventy thousand men to bear burdens, eighty thousand men who were stone cutters in the mountains, and three thousand six hundred to oversee them. 3 Solomon sent to Huram the king of Tyre, saying, “As you dealt with David my father, and sent him cedars to build him a house in which to dwell, so deal with me. 4 Behold,[*] I am about to build a house for the name of Yahweh my God, to dedicate it to him, to burn before him incense of sweet spices, for the continual show bread, and for the burnt offerings morning and evening, on the Sabbaths, on the new moons, and on the set feasts of Yahweh our God. This is an ordinance forever to Israel.

5 “The house which I am building will be great; for our God is greater than all gods. 6 But who is able to build him a house, since heaven and the heaven of heavens can’t contain him? Who am I then, that I should build him a house, except just to burn incense before him?

7 “Now therefore send me a man skillful to work in gold, in silver, in brass, in iron, and in purple, crimson, and blue, and who knows how to engrave engravings, to be with the skillful men who are with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father provided.

8 “Send me also cedar trees, cypress trees, and algum trees out of Lebanon; for I know that your servants know how to cut timber in Lebanon. Behold, my servants will be with your servants, 9 even to prepare me timber in abundance; for the house which I am about to build will be great and wonderful. 10 Behold, I will give to your servants, the cutters who cut timber, twenty thousand cors[*] of beaten wheat, twenty thousand baths[*] of barley, twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil.”

11 Then Huram the king of Tyre answered in writing, which he sent to Solomon, “Because Yahweh loves his people, he has made you king over them.” 12 Huram continued, “Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, who made heaven and earth, who has given to David the king a wise son, endowed with discretion and understanding, who would build a house for Yahweh, and a house for his kingdom. 13 Now I have sent a skillful man, endowed with understanding, of Huram my father’s, 14 the son of a woman of the daughters of Dan; and his father was a man of Tyre, skillful to work in gold, in silver, in brass, in iron, in stone, in timber, and in purple, in blue, in fine linen, and in crimson, also to engrave any kind of engraving and to devise any device; that there may be a place appointed to him with your skillful men, and with the skillful men of my lord David your father.

15 “Now therefore the wheat the barley, the oil and the wine, which my lord has spoken of, let him send to his servants; 16 and we will cut wood out of Lebanon, as much as you need. We will bring it to you in floats by sea to Joppa; and you shall carry it up to Jerusalem.”

17 Solomon counted all the foreigners who were in the land of Israel, after the census with which David his father had counted them; and they found one hundred fifty-three thousand six hundred. 18 He set seventy thousand of them to bear burdens, eighty thousand who were stone cutters in the mountains, and three thousand six hundred overseers to assign the people their work.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

1 cor is the same as a homer, or about 55.9 U. S. gallons (liquid) or 211 liters or 6 bushels, so 20,000 cors of wheat would weigh about 545 metric tons

1 bath is one tenth of a cor, or about 5.6 U. S. gallons or 21 liters or 2.4 pecks 20,000 baths of barley would weigh about 262 metric tons.

2 Chronicles 3

1 Then Solomon began to build Yahweh’s house at Jerusalem on Mount Moriah, where Yahweh appeared to David his father, which he prepared in the place that David had appointed, on the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. 2 He began to build in the second day of the second month, in the fourth year of his reign. 3 Now these are the foundations which Solomon laid for the building of God’s house. The length by cubits[*] after the first measure was sixty cubits, and the width twenty cubits. 4 The porch that was in front, its length, according to the width of the house, was twenty cubits, and the height one hundred twenty; and he overlaid it within with pure gold. 5 He made the larger room with a ceiling of cypress wood, which he overlaid with fine gold, and ornamented it with palm trees and chains. 6 He decorated the house with precious stones for beauty. The gold was gold from Parvaim. 7 He also overlaid the house, the beams, the thresholds, its walls, and its doors with gold; and engraved cherubim on the walls.

8 He made the most holy place. Its length, according to the width of the house, was twenty cubits, and its width twenty cubits; and he overlaid it with fine gold, amounting to six hundred talents.[*] 9 The weight of the nails was fifty shekels[*] of gold. He overlaid the upper rooms with gold.

10 In the most holy place he made two cherubim by carving; and they overlaid them with gold. 11 The wings of the cherubim were twenty cubits long: the wing of the one was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house; and the other wing was five cubits, reaching to the wing of the other cherub. 12 The wing of the other cherub was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house; and the other wing was five cubits, joining to the wing of the other cherub. 13 The wings of these cherubim spread themselves out twenty cubits. They stood on their feet, and their faces were toward the house. 14 He made the veil of blue, purple, crimson, and fine linen, and ornamented it with cherubim.

15 Also he made before the house two pillars of thirty-five cubits height, and the capital that was on the top of each of them was five cubits. 16 He made chains in the inner sanctuary, and put them on the tops of the pillars; and he made one hundred pomegranates, and put them on the chains. 17 He set up the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand, and the other on the left; and called the name of that on the right hand Jachin, and the name of that on the left Boaz.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 600 talents is about 18 metric tons

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.32 Troy ounces, so 50 shekels was about 0.5 kilograms or about 16 Troy ounces.

2 Chronicles 4

1 Then he made an altar of brass, twenty cubits[*] long, twenty cubits wide, and ten cubits high. 2 Also he made the molten sea[*] of ten cubits from brim to brim. It was round, five cubits high, and thirty cubits in circumference. 3 Under it was the likeness of oxen, which encircled it, for ten cubits, encircling the sea. The oxen were in two rows, cast when it was cast. 4 It stood on twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east; and the sea was set on them above, and all their hindquarters were inward. 5 It was a handbreadth thick; and its brim was made like the brim of a cup, like the flower of a lily. It received and held three thousand baths.[*] 6 He also made ten basins, and put five on the right hand, and five on the left, to wash in them. The things that belonged to the burnt offering were washed in them; but the sea was for the priests to wash in.

7 He made the ten lamp stands of gold according to the ordinance concerning them; and he set them in the temple, five on the right hand, and five on the left. 8 He made also ten tables, and placed them in the temple, five on the right side, and five on the left. He made one hundred basins of gold. 9 Furthermore he made the court of the priests, the great court, and doors for the court, and overlaid their doors with brass. 10 He set the sea on the right side of the house eastward, toward the south.

11 Huram made the pots, the shovels, and the basins.

So Huram finished doing the work that he did for king Solomon in God’s house: 12 the two pillars, the bowls, the two capitals which were on the top of the pillars, the two networks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars, 13 and the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks; two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the pillars. 14 He also made the bases, and he made the basins on the bases; 15 one sea, and the twelve oxen under it. 16 Huram his father also made the pots, the shovels, the forks, and all its vessels for king Solomon, for Yahweh’s house, of bright brass. 17 The king cast them in the plain of the Jordan, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zeredah. 18 Thus Solomon made all these vessels in great abundance; for the weight of the brass could not be determined.

19 Solomon made all the vessels that were in God’s house, the golden altar also, and the tables with the show bread on them; 20 and the lamp stands with their lamps, to burn according to the ordinance before the inner sanctuary, of pure gold; 21 and the flowers, the lamps, and the tongs of gold that was perfect gold; 22 and the snuffers, the basins, the spoons, and the fire pans of pure gold. As for the entry of the house, its inner doors for the most holy place and the doors of the main hall of the temple were of gold.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

or, pool, or, reservoir

A bath is about 5.6 U. S. gallons or 21.1 liters, so 3,000 baths is about 16,800 gallons or 63.3 kiloliters.

2 Chronicles 5

1 Thus all the work that Solomon did for Yahweh’s house was finished. Solomon brought in the things that David his father had dedicated, even the silver, the gold, and all the vessels, and put them in the treasuries of God’s house.

2 Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the princes of the fathers’ households of the children of Israel, to Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of Yahweh’s covenant out of David’s city, which is Zion. 3 So all the men of Israel assembled themselves to the king at the feast, which was in the seventh month. 4 All the elders of Israel came. The Levites took up the ark; 5 and they brought up the ark, the Tent of Meeting, and all the holy vessels that were in the Tent; these the priests the Levites brought up. 6 King Solomon and all the congregation of Israel, who were assembled to him, were before the ark, sacrificing sheep and cattle that could not be counted or counted for multitude. 7 The priests brought in the ark of Yahweh’s covenant to its place, into the inner sanctuary of the house, to the most holy place, even under the wings of the cherubim. 8 For the cherubim spread out their wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubim covered the ark and its poles above. 9 The poles were so long that the ends of the poles were seen from the ark in front of the inner sanctuary; but they were not seen outside; and it is there to this day. 10 There was nothing in the ark except the two tablets which Moses put at Horeb, when Yahweh made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of Egypt.

11 When the priests had come out of the holy place (for all the priests who were present had sanctified themselves, and didn’t keep their divisions; 12 also the Levites who were the singers, all of them, even Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, and their sons and their brothers, arrayed in fine linen, with cymbals and stringed instruments and harps, stood at the east end of the altar, and with them one hundred twenty priests sounding with trumpets); 13 when the trumpeters and singers were as one, to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking Yahweh; and when they lifted up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of music, and praised Yahweh, saying,

“For he is good;

for his loving kindness endures forever!”

then the house was filled with a cloud, even Yahweh’s house, 14 so that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud; for Yahweh’s glory filled God’s house.

2 Chronicles 6

1 Then Solomon said, “Yahweh has said that he would dwell in the thick darkness. 2 But I have built you a house and home, a place for you to dwell in forever.”

3 The king turned his face, and blessed all the assembly of Israel: and all the assembly of Israel stood.

4 He said, “Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, who spoke with his mouth to David my father, and has with his hands fulfilled it, saying, 5 ‘Since the day that I brought my people out of the land of Egypt, I chose no city out of all the tribes of Israel to build a house in, that my name might be there and I chose no man to be prince over my people Israel; 6 but now I have chosen Jerusalem, that my name might be there; and I have chosen David to be over my people Israel.’ 7 Now it was in the heart of David my father to build a house for the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel. 8 But Yahweh said to David my father, ‘Whereas it was in your heart to build a house for my name, you did well that it was in your heart; 9 nevertheless you shall not build the house; but your son who will come out of your body, he shall build the house for my name.’

10 “Yahweh has performed his word that he spoke; for I have risen up in the place of David my father, and sit on the throne of Israel, as Yahweh promised, and have built the house for the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel. 11 There I have set the ark, in which is Yahweh’s covenant, which he made with the children of Israel.”

12 He stood before Yahweh’s altar in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and spread out his hands 13 (for Solomon had made a bronze scaffold, five cubits[*] long, and five cubits wide, and three cubits high, and had set it in the middle of the court; and he stood on it, and knelt down on his knees before all the assembly of Israel, and spread out his hands toward heaven) 14 and he said, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, there is no God like you in heaven or on earth; you who keep covenant and loving kindness with your servants who walk before you with all their heart; 15 who have kept with your servant David my father that which you promised him. Yes, you spoke with your mouth, and have fulfilled it with your hand, as it is today.

16 “Now therefore, Yahweh, the God of Israel, keep with your servant David my father that which you have promised him, saying, ‘There shall not fail you a man in my sight to sit on the throne of Israel, if only your children take heed to their way, to walk in my law as you have walked before me.’ 17 Now therefore, Yahweh, the God of Israel, let your word be verified, which you spoke to your servant David.

18 “But will God indeed dwell with men on the earth? Behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens can’t contain you; how much less this house which I have built! 19 Yet have respect for the prayer of your servant, and to his supplication, Yahweh my God, to listen to the cry and to the prayer which your servant prays before you; 20 that your eyes may be open toward this house day and night, even toward the place where you have said that you would put your name; to listen to the prayer which your servant will pray toward this place. 21 Listen to the petitions of your servant, and of your people Israel, when they pray toward this place. Yes, hear from your dwelling place, even from heaven; and when you hear, forgive.

22 “If a man sins against his neighbor, and an oath is laid on him to cause him to swear, and he comes and swears before your altar in this house; 23 then hear from heaven, act, and judge your servants, bringing retribution to the wicked, to bring his way on his own head; and justifying the righteous, to give him according to his righteousness.

24 “If your people Israel are struck down before the enemy because they have sinned against you, and they turn again and confess your name, and pray and make supplication before you in this house; 25 then hear from heaven, and forgive the sin of your people Israel, and bring them again to the land which you gave to them and to their fathers.

26 “When the sky is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against you; if they pray toward this place, and confess your name, and turn from their sin, when you afflict them; 27 then hear in heaven, and forgive the sin of your servants of your people Israel, when you teach them the good way in which they should walk; and send rain on your land, which you have given to your people for an inheritance.

28 “If there is famine in the land, if there is pestilence, if there is blight or mildew, locust or caterpillar; if their enemies besiege them in the land of their cities; whatever plague or whatever sickness there is; 29 whatever prayer and supplication is made by any man, or by all your people Israel, who will each know his own plague and his own sorrow, and shall spread out his hands toward this house; 30 then hear from heaven your dwelling place and forgive, and render to every man according to all his ways, whose heart you know (for you, even you only, know the hearts of the children of men) 31 that they may fear you, to walk in your ways, so long as they live in the land which you gave to our fathers.

32 “Moreover concerning the foreigner, who is not of your people Israel, when he comes from a far country for your great name’s sake, and your mighty hand, and your outstretched arm; when they come and pray toward this house; 33 then hear from heaven, even from your dwelling place, and do according to all that the foreigner calls to you for; that all the peoples of the earth may know your name and fear you, as do your people Israel, and that they may know that this house which I have built is called by your name.

34 “If your people go out to battle against their enemies, by whatever way you send them, and they pray to you toward this city which you have chosen, and the house which I have built for your name; 35 then hear from heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause.

36 “If they sin against you (for there is no man who doesn’t sin), and you are angry with them, and deliver them to the enemy, so that they carry them away captive to a land far off or near; 37 yet if they come to their senses in the land where they are carried captive, and turn again, and make supplication to you in the land of their captivity, saying, ‘We have sinned, we have done perversely, and have dealt wickedly;’ 38 if they return to you with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their captivity, where they have carried them captive, and pray toward their land, which you gave to their fathers, and the city which you have chosen, and toward the house which I have built for your name; 39 then hear from heaven, even from your dwelling place, their prayer and their petitions, and maintain their cause, and forgive your people who have sinned against you.

40 “Now, my God, let, I beg you, your eyes be open, and let your ears be attentive, to the prayer that is made in this place.

41 “Now therefore arise, Yahweh God, into your resting place, you, and the ark of your strength. Let your priests, Yahweh God, be clothed with salvation, and let your saints rejoice in goodness.

42 “Yahweh God, don’t turn away the face of your anointed. Remember your loving kindnesses to David your servant.”

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

2 Chronicles 7

1 Now when Solomon had finished praying, fire came down from heaven and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices; and Yahweh’s glory filled the house. 2 The priests could not enter into Yahweh’s house, because Yahweh’s glory filled Yahweh’s house. 3 All the children of Israel looked on, when the fire came down, and Yahweh’s glory was on the house. They bowed themselves with their faces to the ground on the pavement, worshiped, and gave thanks to Yahweh, saying,

“For he is good;

for his loving kindness endures for ever.”

4 Then the king and all the people offered sacrifices before Yahweh. 5 King Solomon offered a sacrifice of twenty-two thousand head of cattle and a hundred twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the people dedicated God’s house. 6 The priests stood, according to their positions; the Levites also with instruments of music of Yahweh, which David the king had made to give thanks to Yahweh, when David praised by their ministry, saying “For his loving kindness endures for ever.” The priests sounded trumpets before them; and all Israel stood.

7 Moreover Solomon made the middle of the court that was before Yahweh’s house holy; for there he offered the burnt offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings, because the bronze altar which Solomon had made was not able to receive the burnt offering, the meal offering, and the fat.

8 So Solomon held the feast at that time for seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great assembly, from the entrance of Hamath to the brook of Egypt.

9 On the eighth day, they held a solemn assembly; for they kept the dedication of the altar seven days, and the feast seven days. 10 On the twenty-third day of the seventh month, he sent the people away to their tents, joyful and glad of heart for the goodness that Yahweh had shown to David, and to Solomon, and to Israel his people.

11 Thus Solomon finished Yahweh’s house and the king’s house; and he successfully completed all that came into Solomon’s heart to make in Yahweh’s house and in his own house.

12 Yahweh appeared to Solomon by night, and said to him, “I have heard your prayer, and have chosen this place for myself for a house of sacrifice.

13 “If I shut up the sky so that there is no rain, or if I command the locust to devour the land, or if I send pestilence among my people; 14 if my people, who are called by my name, will humble themselves, pray, seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways; then I will hear from heaven, will forgive their sin, and will heal their land. 15 Now my eyes will be open my ears attentive to prayer that is made in this place. 16 For now I have chosen and made this house holy, that my name may be there forever; and my eyes and my heart will be there perpetually.

17 “As for you, if you will walk before me as David your father walked, and do according to all that I have commanded you, and will keep my statutes and my ordinances; 18 then I will establish the throne of your kingdom, according as I covenanted with David your father, saying, ‘There shall not fail you a man to be ruler in Israel.’

19 But if you turn away, and forsake my statutes and my commandments which I have set before you, and shall go and serve other gods, and worship them; 20 then I will pluck them up by the roots out of my land which I have given them; and this house, which I have made holy for my name, I will cast out of my sight, and I will make it a proverb and a byword among all peoples. 21 This house, which is so high, everyone who passes by it shall be astonished, and shall say, ‘Why has Yahweh done this to this land and to this house?’ 22 They shall answer, ‘Because they abandoned Yahweh, the God of their fathers, who brought them out of the land of Egypt, and took other gods, worshiped them, and served them. Therefore he has brought all this evil on them.’”

2 Chronicles 8

1 At the end of twenty years, in which Solomon had built Yahweh’s house and his own house, 2 Solomon built the cities which Huram had given to Solomon, and caused the children of Israel to dwell there.

3 Solomon went to Hamath Zobah, and prevailed against it. 4 He built Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the storage cities, which he built in Hamath. 5 Also he built Beth Horon the upper and Beth Horon the lower, fortified cities, with walls, gates, and bars; 6 and Baalath, and all the storage cities that Solomon had, and all the cities for his chariots, the cities for his horsemen, and all that Solomon desired to build for his pleasure in Jerusalem, in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion.

7 As for all the people who were left of the Hittites, the Amorites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, who were not of Israel; 8 of their children who were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel didn’t consume, of them Solomon conscripted forced labor to this day. 9 But of the children of Israel, Solomon made no servants for his work; but they were men of war, and chief of his captains, and rulers of his chariots and of his horsemen. 10 These were the chief officers of king Solomon, even two-hundred fifty, who ruled over the people.

11 Solomon brought up Pharaoh’s daughter out of David’s city to the house that he had built for her; for he said, “My wife shall not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, because the places where Yahweh’s ark has come are holy.”

12 Then Solomon offered burnt offerings to Yahweh on Yahweh’s altar, which he had built before the porch, 13 even as the duty of every day required, offering according to the commandment of Moses, on the Sabbaths, on the new moons, and on the set feasts, three times per year, during the feast of unleavened bread, during the feast of weeks, and during the feast of tents.[*]

14 He appointed, according to the ordinance of David his father, the divisions of the priests to their service, and the Levites to their offices, to praise and to minister before the priests, as the duty of every day required; the doorkeepers also by their divisions at every gate, for David the man of God had so commanded. 15 They didn’t depart from the commandment of the king to the priests and Levites concerning any matter, or concerning the treasures.

16 Now all the work of Solomon was prepared from the day of the foundation of Yahweh’s house until it was finished. So Yahweh’s house was completed.

17 Then Solomon went to Ezion Geber and to Eloth, on the seashore in the land of Edom. 18 Huram sent him ships and servants who had knowledge of the sea by the hands of his servants; and they came with the servants of Solomon to Ophir, and brought from there four hundred fifty talents[*] of gold, and brought them to king Solomon.

or, booths (sukkot)

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 450 talents is about 13.5 metric tons

2 Chronicles 9

1 When the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to test Solomon with hard questions at Jerusalem, with a very great caravan, including camels that bore spices, gold in abundance, and precious stones. When she had come to Solomon, she talked with him about all that was in her heart. 2 Solomon answered all her questions. There wasn’t anything hidden from Solomon which he didn’t tell her. 3 When the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, the house that he had built, 4 the food of his table, the seating of his servants, the attendance of his ministers, their clothing, his cup bearers also, their clothing, and his ascent by which he went up to Yahweh’s house; there was no more spirit in her.[*]

5 She said to the king, “It was a true report that I heard in my own land of your acts and of your wisdom. 6 However I didn’t believe their words until I came, and my eyes had seen it; and behold, the half of the greatness of your wisdom was not told me. You exceed the fame that I heard! 7 Happy are your men, and happy are these your servants, who stand continually before you, and hear your wisdom. 8 Blessed be Yahweh your God, who delighted in you, to set you on his throne, to be king for Yahweh your God; because your God loved Israel, to establish them forever. Therefore made he you king over them, to do justice and righteousness.”

9 She gave the king one hundred and twenty talents[*] of gold, spices in great abundance, and precious stones. There was never before such spice as the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon. 10 The servants of Huram and the servants of Solomon, who brought gold from Ophir, also brought algum trees[*] and precious stones. 11 The king used algum tree wood to make terraces for Yahweh’s house and for the king’s house, and harps and stringed instruments for the singers. There were none like these seen before in the land of Judah. 12 King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatever she asked, besides that which she had brought to the king. So she turned, and went to her own land, she and her servants.

13 Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred sixty-six talents[*] of gold, 14 besides that which the traders and merchants brought. All the kings of Arabia and the governors of the country brought gold and silver to Solomon. 15 King Solomon made two hundred bucklers of beaten gold. Six hundred shekels[*] of beaten gold went to one buckler. 16 He made three hundred shields of beaten gold. Three hundred shekels[*] of gold went to one shield. The king put them in the House of the Forest of Lebanon. 17 Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold. 18 There were six steps to the throne, with a footstool of gold, which were fastened to the throne, and armrests on either side by the place of the seat, and two lions standing beside the armrests. 19 Twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other on the six steps. There was nothing like it made in any other kingdom. 20 All king Solomon’s drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the House of the Forest of Lebanon were of pure gold. Silver was not considered valuable in the days of Solomon. 21 For the king had ships that went to Tarshish with Huram’s servants. Once every three years, the ships of Tarshish came bringing gold, silver, ivory, apes, and peacocks.

22 So king Solomon exceeded all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. 23 All the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. 24 They each brought tribute, vessels of silver, vessels of gold, clothing, armor, spices, horses, and mules every year. 25 Solomon had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, that he stationed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. 26 He ruled over all the kings from the River even to the land of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt. 27 The king made silver as common in Jerusalem as stones, and he made cedars to be as abundant as the sycamore trees that are in the lowland. 28 They brought horses for Solomon out of Egypt and out of all lands.

29 Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, aren’t they written in the history of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat? 30 Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years. 31 Solomon slept with his fathers, and he was buried in his father David’s city: and Rehoboam his son reigned in his place.

or, she was breathless.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 120 talents is about 3.6 metric tons

possibly Indian sandalwood, which has nice grain and a pleasant scent and is good for woodworking

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces, so 666 talents is about 20 metric tons

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.32 Troy ounces, so 600 shekels was about 6 kilograms or about 192 Troy ounces.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.32 Troy ounces, so 300 shekels was about 3 kilograms or about 96 Troy ounces.

2 Chronicles 10

1 Rehoboam went to Shechem; for all Israel had come to Shechem to make him king. 2 When Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard of it (for he was in Egypt, where he had fled from the presence of king Solomon), Jeroboam returned out of Egypt. 3 They sent and called him; and Jeroboam and all Israel came, and they spoke to Rehoboam, saying, 4 “Your father made our yoke grievous: now therefore make the grievous service of your father, and his heavy yoke which he put on us, lighter, and we will serve you.”

5 He said to them, “Come again to me after three days.”

So the people departed. 6 King Rehoboam took counsel with the old men, who had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, “What counsel do you give me about how to answer these people?”

7 They spoke to him, saying, “If you are kind to these people, please them, and speak good words to them, then they will be your servants forever.”

8 But he abandoned the counsel of the old men which they had given him, and took counsel with the young men who had grown up with him, who stood before him. 9 He said to them, “What counsel do you give, that we may give an answer to these people, who have spoken to me, saying, ‘Make the yoke that your father put on us lighter?’”

10 The young men who had grown up with him spoke to him, saying, “Thus you shall tell the people who spoke to you, saying, ‘Your father made our yoke heavy, but make it lighter on us;’ thus you shall say to them, ‘My little finger is thicker than my father’s waist. 11 Now whereas my father burdened you with a heavy yoke, I will add to your yoke. My father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.’”

12 So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king asked, saying, “Come to me again the third day.” 13 The king answered them roughly; and king Rehoboam abandoned the counsel of the old men, 14 and spoke to them after the counsel of the young men, saying, “My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to it. My father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.”

15 So the king didn’t listen to the people; for it was brought about by God, that Yahweh might establish his word, which he spoke by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat. 16 When all Israel saw that the king didn’t listen to them, the people answered the king, saying, “What portion have we in David? We don’t have an inheritance in the son of Jesse! Every man to your tents, Israel! Now see to your own house, David.” So all Israel departed to their tents.

17 But as for the children of Israel who lived in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. 18 Then king Rehoboam sent Hadoram, who was over the men subject to forced labor; and the children of Israel stoned him to death with stones. King Rehoboam hurried to get himself up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem. 19 So Israel rebelled against David’s house to this day.

2 Chronicles 11

1 When Rehoboam had come to Jerusalem, he assembled the house of Judah and Benjamin, one hundred eighty thousand chosen men who were warriors, to fight against Israel, to bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam. 2 But Yahweh’s word came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, 3 “Speak to Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying, 4 ‘Yahweh says, “You shall not go up, nor fight against your brothers! Every man return to his house; for this thing is of me.”’” So they listened to Yahweh’s words, and returned from going against Jeroboam.

5 Rehoboam lived in Jerusalem, and built cities for defense in Judah. 6 He built Bethlehem, Etam, Tekoa, 7 Beth Zur, Soco, Adullam, 8 Gath, Mareshah, Ziph, 9 Adoraim, Lachish, Azekah, 10 Zorah, Aijalon, and Hebron, which are fortified cities in Judah and in Benjamin. 11 He fortified the strongholds, and put captains in them, and stores of food, oil and wine. 12 He put shields and spears in every city, and made them exceedingly strong. Judah and Benjamin belonged to him.

13 The priests and the Levites who were in all Israel stood with him out of all their territory. 14 For the Levites left their suburbs and their possession, and came to Judah and Jerusalem; for Jeroboam and his sons cast them off, that they should not execute the priest’s office to Yahweh. 15 He himself appointed priests for the high places, for the male goats, and for the calves which he had made. 16 After them, out of all the tribes of Israel, those who set their hearts to seek Yahweh, the God of Israel, came to Jerusalem to sacrifice to Yahweh, the God of their fathers. 17 So they strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and made Rehoboam the son of Solomon strong for three years; for they walked three years in the way of David and Solomon.

18 Rehoboam took a wife for himself, Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David and of Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of Jesse. 19 She bore him sons: Jeush, Shemariah, and Zaham. 20 After her, he took Maacah the daughter of Absalom; and she bore him Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith. 21 Rehoboam loved Maacah the daughter of Absalom above all his wives and his concubines; for he took eighteen wives and sixty concubines, and became the father of twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters. 22 Rehoboam appointed Abijah the son of Maacah to be chief, the prince among his brothers; for he intended to make him king. 23 He dealt wisely, and dispersed of all his sons throughout all the lands of Judah and Benjamin, to every fortified city. He gave them food in abundance and he sought many wives for them.

2 Chronicles 12

1 When the kingdom of Rehoboam was established and he was strong, he abandoned Yahweh’s law, and all Israel with him. 2 In the fifth year of king Rehoboam, Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, because they had trespassed against Yahweh, 3 with twelve hundred chariots, and sixty thousand horsemen. The people were without number who came with him out of Egypt: the Lubim, the Sukkiim, and the Ethiopians. 4 He took the fortified cities which belonged to Judah, and came to Jerusalem. 5 Now Shemaiah the prophet came to Rehoboam, and to the princes of Judah, who were gathered together to Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said to them, “Yahweh says, ‘You have forsaken me, therefore I have also left you in the hand of Shishak.’”

6 Then the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves; and they said, “Yahweh is righteous.”

7 When Yahweh saw that they humbled themselves, Yahweh’s word came to Shemaiah, saying, “They have humbled themselves. I will not destroy them; but I will grant them some deliverance, and my wrath won’t be poured out on Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak. 8 Nevertheless they will be his servants, that they may know my service, and the service of the kingdoms of the countries.”

9 So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem and took away the treasures of Yahweh’s house and the treasures of the king’s house. He took it all away. He also took away the shields of gold which Solomon had made. 10 King Rehoboam made shields of brass in their place, and committed them to the hands of the captains of the guard, who kept the door of the king’s house. 11 As often as the king entered into Yahweh’s house, the guard came and bore them, then brought them back into the guard room. 12 When he humbled himself, Yahweh’s wrath turned from him, so as not to destroy him altogether. Moreover, there were good things found in Judah.

13 So king Rehoboam strengthened himself in Jerusalem and reigned; for Rehoboam was forty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which Yahweh had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to put his name there. His mother’s name was Naamah the Ammonitess. 14 He did that which was evil, because he didn’t set his heart to seek Yahweh.

15 Now the acts of Rehoboam, first and last, aren’t they written in the histories of Shemaiah the prophet and of Iddo the seer, in the genealogies? There were wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually. 16 Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried in David’s city; and Abijah his son reigned in his place.

2 Chronicles 14

1 So Abijah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in David’s city; and Asa his son reigned in his place. In his days, the land was quiet ten years. 2 Asa did that which was good and right in Yahweh his God’s eyes; 3 for he took away the foreign altars and the high places, broke down the pillars, cut down the Asherah poles, 4 and commanded Judah to seek Yahweh, the God of their fathers, and to obey his law and command. 5 Also he took away out of all the cities of Judah the high places and the sun images; and the kingdom was quiet before him. 6 He built fortified cities in Judah; for the land was quiet, and he had no war in those years, because Yahweh had given him rest. 7 For he said to Judah, “Let us build these cities, and make walls around them, with towers, gates, and bars. The land is yet before us, because we have sought Yahweh our God. We have sought him, and he has given us rest on every side.” So they built and prospered.

8 Asa had an army of three hundred thousand out of Judah who bore bucklers and spears, and two hundred eighty thousand out of Benjamin who bore shields and drew bows. All these were mighty men of valor.

9 Zerah the Ethiopian came out against them with an army of a million troops and three hundred chariots, and he came to Mareshah. 10 Then Asa went out to meet him, and they set the battle in array in the valley of Zephathah at Mareshah. 11 Asa cried to Yahweh his God, and said, “Yahweh, there is no one besides you to help, between the mighty and him who has no strength. Help us, Yahweh our God; for we rely on you, and in your name are we come against this multitude. Yahweh, you are our God. Don’t let man prevail against you.”

12 So Yahweh struck the Ethiopians before Asa and before Judah; and the Ethiopians fled. 13 Asa and the people who were with him pursued them to Gerar: and so many of the Ethiopians fell that they could not recover themselves; for they were destroyed before Yahweh and before his army; and they carried away very much booty. 14 They struck all the cities around Gerar; for the fear of Yahweh came on them, and they plundered all the cities; for there was much plunder in them. 15 They also struck the tents of livestock, and carried away sheep in abundance, and camels, and returned to Jerusalem.

2 Chronicles 15

1 The Spirit of God came on Azariah the son of Oded: 2 and he went out to meet Asa, and said to him, “Hear me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin! Yahweh is with you, while you are with him; and if you seek him, he will be found by you; but if you forsake him, he will forsake you. 3 Now for a long time Israel was without the true God, without a teaching priest, and without law. 4 But when in their distress they turned to Yahweh, the God of Israel, and sought him, he was found by them. 5 In those times there was no peace to him who went out, nor to him who came in; but great troubles were on all the inhabitants of the lands. 6 They were broken in pieces, nation against nation, and city against city; for God troubled them with all adversity. 7 But you be strong, and don’t let your hands be slack; for your work will be rewarded.”

8 When Asa heard these words, and the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage, and put away the abominations out of all the land of Judah and Benjamin, and out of the cities which he had taken from the hill country of Ephraim; and he renewed Yahweh’s altar that was before Yahweh’s porch. 9 He gathered all Judah and Benjamin, and those who lived with them out of Ephraim, Manasseh, and Simeon; for they came to him out of Israel in abundance when they saw that Yahweh his God was with him. 10 So they gathered themselves together at Jerusalem in the third month, in the fifteenth year of Asa’s reign. 11 They sacrificed to Yahweh in that day, of the plunder which they had brought, seven hundred head of cattle and seven thousand sheep. 12 They entered into the covenant to seek Yahweh, the God of their fathers, with all their heart and with all their soul; 13 and that whoever would not seek Yahweh, the God of Israel, should be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. 14 They swore to Yahweh with a loud voice, with shouting, with trumpets, and with cornets. 15 All Judah rejoiced at the oath, for they had sworn with all their heart, and sought him with their whole desire; and he was found by them. Then Yahweh gave them rest all around.

16 Also Maacah, the mother of Asa the king, he removed from being queen, because she had made an abominable image for an Asherah; so Asa cut down her image, ground it into dust, and burned it at the brook Kidron. 17 But the high places were not taken away out of Israel; nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect all his days. 18 He brought the things that his father had dedicated, and that he himself had dedicated, silver, gold, and vessels into God’s house. 19 There was no more war to the thirty-fifth year of Asa’s reign.

2 Chronicles 16

1 In the thirty-sixth year of Asa’s reign, Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah, and built Ramah, that he might not allow anyone to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. 2 Then Asa brought out silver and gold out of the treasures of Yahweh’s house and of the king’s house, and sent to Ben Hadad king of Syria, who lived at Damascus, saying, 3 “Let there be a treaty between me and you, as there was between my father and your father. Behold, I have sent you silver and gold. Go, break your treaty with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me.”

4 Ben Hadad listened to king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel; and they struck Ijon, Dan, Abel Maim, and all the storage cities of Naphtali. 5 When Baasha heard of it, he stopped building Ramah, and let his work cease. 6 Then Asa the king took all Judah, and they carried away the stones of Rama, and its timber, with which Baasha had built; and he built Geba and Mizpah with them.

7 At that time Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah, and said to him, “Because you have relied on the king of Syria, and have not relied on Yahweh your God, therefore the army of the king of Syria has escaped out of your hand. 8 Weren’t the Ethiopians and the Lubim a huge army, with chariots and horsemen exceeding many? Yet, because you relied on Yahweh, he delivered them into your hand. 9 For Yahweh’s eyes run back and forth throughout the whole earth, to show himself strong in the behalf of them whose heart is perfect toward him. You have done foolishly in this; for from now on you will have wars.”

10 Then Asa was angry with the seer, and put him in the prison; for he was in a rage with him because of this thing. Asa oppressed some of the people at the same time.

11 Behold, the acts of Asa, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. 12 In the thirty-ninth year of his reign, Asa was diseased in his feet. His disease was exceedingly great: yet in his disease he didn’t seek Yahweh, but just the physicians. 13 Asa slept with his fathers, and died in the forty-first year of his reign. 14 They buried him in his own tomb, which he had dug out for himself in David’s city, and laid him in the bed which was filled with sweet odors and various kinds of spices prepared by the perfumers’ art; and they made a very great fire for him.

2 Chronicles 18

1 Now Jehoshaphat had riches and honor in abundance; and he allied himself with Ahab. 2 After some years, he went down to Ahab to Samaria. Ahab killed sheep and cattle for him in abundance, and for the people who were with him, and moved him to go up with him to Ramoth Gilead. 3 Ahab king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat king of Judah, “Will you go with me to Ramoth Gilead?”

He answered him, “I am as you are, and my people as your people. We will be with you in the war.” 4 Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, “Please inquire first for Yahweh’s word.”

5 Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, four hundred men, and said to them, “Shall we go to Ramoth Gilead to battle, or shall I forbear?”

They said, “Go up; for God will deliver it into the hand of the king.”

6 But Jehoshaphat said, “Isn’t there here a prophet of Yahweh besides, that we may inquire of him?”

7 The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “There is yet one man by whom we may inquire of Yahweh; but I hate him, for he never prophesies good concerning me, but always evil. He is Micaiah the son of Imla.”

Jehoshaphat said, “Don’t let the king say so.”

8 Then the king of Israel called an officer, and said, “Get Micaiah the son of Imla quickly.”

9 Now the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah each sat on his throne, arrayed in their robes, and they were sitting in an open place at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets were prophesying before them. 10 Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made himself horns of iron and said, “Yahweh says, ‘With these you shall push the Syrians, until they are consumed.’”

11 All the prophets prophesied so, saying, “Go up to Ramoth Gilead, and prosper; for Yahweh will deliver it into the hand of the king.”

12 The messenger who went to call Micaiah spoke to him, saying, “Behold, the words of the prophets declare good to the king with one mouth. Let your word therefore, please be like one of theirs, and speak good.”

13 Micaiah said, “As Yahweh lives, what my God says, that will I speak.”

14 When he had come to the king, the king said to him, “Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth Gilead to battle, or shall I forbear?”

He said, “Go up, and prosper. They shall be delivered into your hand.”

15 The king said to him, “How many times shall I adjure you that you speak to me nothing but the truth in Yahweh’s name?”

16 He said, “I saw all Israel scattered on the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd. Yahweh said, ‘These have no master. Let them each return to his house in peace.’”

17 The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “Didn’t I tell you that he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil?”

18 Micaiah said, “Therefore hear Yahweh’s word: I saw Yahweh sitting on his throne, and all the army of heaven standing on his right hand and on his left. 19 Yahweh said, ‘Who will entice Ahab king of Israel, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth Gilead?’ One spoke saying in this way, and another saying in that way. 20 A spirit came out, stood before Yahweh, and said, ‘I will entice him.’

“Yahweh said to him, ‘How?’

21 “He said, ‘I will go, and will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.’

“He said, ‘You will entice him, and will prevail also. Go and do so.’

22 “Now therefore, behold, Yahweh has put a lying spirit in the mouth of these your prophets; and Yahweh has spoken evil concerning you.”

23 Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and struck Micaiah on the cheek, and said, “Which way did Yahweh’s Spirit go from me to speak to you?”

24 Micaiah said, “Behold, you shall see on that day, when you go into an inner room to hide yourself.”

25 The king of Israel said, “Take Micaiah, and carry him back to Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king’s son; 26 and say, ‘Thus says the king, “Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I return in peace.”’”

27 Micaiah said, “If you return at all in peace, Yahweh has not spoken by me.” He said, “Listen, you people, all of you!”

28 So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth Gilead. 29 The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, “I will disguise myself, and go into the battle; but you put on your robes.” So the king of Israel disguised himself; and they went into the battle. 30 Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of his chariots, saying, “Don’t fight with small nor great, except only with the king of Israel.”

31 When the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, they said, “It is the king of Israel!” Therefore they turned around to fight against him. But Jehoshaphat cried out, and Yahweh helped him; and God moved them to depart from him. 32 When the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, they turned back from pursuing him. 33 A certain man drew his bow at random, and struck the king of Israel between the joints of the armor. Therefore he said to the driver of the chariot, “Turn your hand, and carry me out of the army; for I am severely wounded.” 34 The battle increased that day. However the king of Israel propped himself up in his chariot against the Syrians until the evening; and at about sunset, he died.

2 Chronicles 19

1 Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned to his house in peace to Jerusalem. 2 Jehu the son of Hanani the seer went out to meet him, and said to king Jehoshaphat, “Should you help the wicked, and love those who hate Yahweh? Because of this, wrath is on you from before Yahweh. 3 Nevertheless there are good things found in you, in that you have put away the Asheroth out of the land, and have set your heart to seek God.”

4 Jehoshaphat lived at Jerusalem; and he went out again among the people from Beersheba to the hill country of Ephraim, and brought them back to Yahweh, the God of their fathers. 5 He set judges in the land throughout all the fortified cities of Judah, city by city, 6 and said to the judges, “Consider what you do, for you don’t judge for man, but for Yahweh; and he is with you in the judgment. 7 Now therefore let the fear of Yahweh be on you. Take heed and do it; for there is no iniquity with Yahweh our God, nor respect of persons, nor taking of bribes.”

8 Moreover in Jerusalem Jehoshaphat appointed Levites and priests, and of the heads of the fathers’ households of Israel, for the judgment of Yahweh, and for controversies. They returned to Jerusalem. 9 He commanded them, saying, “You shall do this in the fear of Yahweh, faithfully, and with a perfect heart. 10 Whenever any controversy comes to you from your brothers who dwell in their cities, between blood and blood, between law and commandment, statutes and ordinances, you must warn them, that they not be guilty towards Yahweh, and so wrath come on you and on your brothers. Do this, and you will not be guilty. 11 Behold, Amariah the chief priest is over you in all matters of Yahweh; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the ruler of the house of Judah, in all the king’s matters. Also the Levites shall be officers before you. Deal courageously, and may Yahweh be with the good.”

2 Chronicles 20

1 After this, the children of Moab, the children of Ammon, and with them some of the Ammonites, came against Jehoshaphat to battle. 2 Then some came who told Jehoshaphat, saying, “A great multitude is coming against you from beyond the sea from Syria. Behold, they are in Hazazon Tamar” (that is, En Gedi). 3 Jehoshaphat was alarmed, and set himself to seek to Yahweh. He proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah. 4 Judah gathered themselves together to seek help from Yahweh. They came out of all the cities of Judah to seek Yahweh.

5 Jehoshaphat stood in the assembly of Judah and Jerusalem, in Yahweh’s house, before the new court; 6 and he said, “Yahweh, the God of our fathers, aren’t you God in heaven? Aren’t you ruler over all the kingdoms of the nations? Power and might are in your hand, so that no one is able to withstand you. 7 Didn’t you, our God, drive out the inhabitants of this land before your people Israel, and give it to the offspring[*] of Abraham your friend forever? 8 They lived in it, and have built you a sanctuary in it for your name, saying, 9 ‘If evil comes on us—the sword, judgment, pestilence, or famine—we will stand before this house, and before you (for your name is in this house), and cry to you in our affliction, and you will hear and save.’ 10 Now, behold, the children of Ammon and Moab and Mount Seir, whom you would not let Israel invade when they came out of the land of Egypt, but they turned aside from them, and didn’t destroy them; 11 behold, how they reward us, to come to cast us out of your possession, which you have given us to inherit. 12 Our God, will you not judge them? For we have no might against this great company that comes against us. We don’t know what to do, but our eyes are on you.”

13 All Judah stood before Yahweh, with their little ones, their wives, and their children.

14 Then Yahweh’s Spirit came on Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jeiel, the son of Mattaniah, the Levite, of the sons of Asaph, in the middle of the assembly; 15 and he said, “Listen, all Judah, and you inhabitants of Jerusalem, and you, king Jehoshaphat. Yahweh says to you, ‘Don’t be afraid, and don’t be dismayed because of this great multitude; for the battle is not yours, but God’s. 16 Tomorrow, go down against them. Behold, they are coming up by the ascent of Ziz. You will find them at the end of the valley, before the wilderness of Jeruel. 17 You will not need to fight this battle. Set yourselves, stand still, and see the salvation of Yahweh with you, O Judah and Jerusalem. Don’t be afraid, nor be dismayed. Go out against them tomorrow, for Yahweh is with you.’”

18 Jehoshaphat bowed his head with his face to the ground; and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell down before Yahweh, worshiping Yahweh. 19 The Levites, of the children of the Kohathites and of the children of the Korahites, stood up to praise Yahweh, the God of Israel, with an exceeding loud voice.

20 They rose early in the morning, and went out into the wilderness of Tekoa. As they went out, Jehoshaphat stood and said, “Listen to me, Judah, and you inhabitants of Jerusalem! Believe in Yahweh your God, so you will be established! Believe his prophets, so you will prosper.”

21 When he had taken counsel with the people, he appointed those who were to sing to Yahweh, and give praise in holy array, as they go out before the army, and say, “Give thanks to Yahweh; for his loving kindness endures forever.” 22 When they began to sing and to praise, Yahweh set ambushers against the children of Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir, who had come against Judah; and they were struck. 23 For the children of Ammon and Moab stood up against the inhabitants of Mount Seir to utterly kill and destroy them: and when they had finished the inhabitants of Seir, everyone helped to destroy another.

24 When Judah came to the place overlooking the wilderness, they looked at the multitude; and behold, they were dead bodies fallen to the earth, and there were none who escaped. 25 When Jehoshaphat and his people came to take their plunder, they found among them in abundance both riches and dead bodies, and precious jewels, which they stripped off for themselves, more than they could carry away. They took plunder for three days, it was so much. 26 On the fourth day, they assembled themselves in Beracah Valley, for there they blessed Yahweh. Therefore the name of that place was called “Beracah Valley” to this day. 27 Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, with Jehoshaphat in front of them, to go again to Jerusalem with joy; for Yahweh had made them to rejoice over their enemies. 28 They came to Jerusalem with stringed instruments, harps, and trumpets to Yahweh’s house. 29 The fear of God was on all the kingdoms of the countries, when they heard that Yahweh fought against the enemies of Israel. 30 So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet, for his God gave him rest all around.

31 Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah. He was thirty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty-five years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. 32 He walked in the way of Asa his father, and didn’t turn aside from it, doing that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes. 33 However the high places were not taken away, and the people had still not set their hearts on the God of their fathers. 34 Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, first and last, behold, they are written in the history of Jehu the son of Hanani, which is included in the book of the kings of Israel. 35 After this, Jehoshaphat king of Judah joined himself with Ahaziah king of Israel. The same did very wickedly. 36 He joined himself with him to make ships to go to Tarshish. They made the ships in Ezion Geber. 37 Then Eliezer the son of Dodavahu of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, “Because you have joined yourself with Ahaziah, Yahweh has destroyed your works.” The ships were wrecked, so that they were not able to go to Tarshish.

or, seed

2 Chronicles 21

1 Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in David’s city, and Jehoram his son reigned in his place. 2 He had brothers, the sons of Jehoshaphat: Azariah, Jehiel, Zechariah, Azariah, Michael, and Shephatiah. All these were the sons of Jehoshaphat king of Israel. 3 Their father gave them great gifts of silver, of gold, and of precious things, with fortified cities in Judah; but he gave the kingdom to Jehoram, because he was the firstborn. 4 Now when Jehoram had risen up over the kingdom of his father, and had strengthened himself, he killed all his brothers with the sword, and also some of the princes of Israel. 5 Jehoram was thirty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. 6 He walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as did Ahab’s house; for he had Ahab’s daughter as his wife. He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight. 7 However Yahweh would not destroy David’s house, because of the covenant that he had made with David, and as he promised to give a lamp to him and to his children always.

8 In his days Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and made a king over themselves. 9 Then Jehoram went there with his captains and all his chariots with him. He rose up by night and struck the Edomites who surrounded him, along with the captains of the chariots. 10 So Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah to this day. Then Libnah revolted at the same time from under his hand, because he had forsaken Yahweh, the God of his fathers.

11 Moreover he made high places in the mountains of Judah, and made the inhabitants of Jerusalem play the prostitute, and led Judah astray. 12 A letter came to him from Elijah the prophet, saying, “Yahweh, the God of David your father, says, ‘Because you have not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat your father, nor in the ways of Asa king of Judah, 13 but have walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and have made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to play the prostitute like Ahab’s house did, and also have slain your brothers of your father’s house, who were better than yourself, 14 behold, Yahweh will strike your people with a great plague, including your children, your wives, and all your posessions; 15 and you will have great sickness with a disease of your bowels, until your bowels fall out by reason of the sickness, day by day.’”

16 Yahweh stirred up against Jehoram the spirit of the Philistines, and of the Arabians who are beside the Ethiopians; 17 and they came up against Judah, broke into it, and carried away all the posessions that were found in the king’s house, including his sons and his wives; so that there was no son left him, except Jehoahaz, the youngest of his sons.

18 After all this Yahweh struck him in his bowels with an incurable disease. 19 In process of time, at the end of two years, his bowels fell out by reason of his sickness, and he died of severe diseases. His people made no burning for him, like the burning of his fathers. 20 He was thirty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years. He departed without being missed; and they buried him in David’s city, but not in the tombs of the kings.

2 Chronicles 22

1 The inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah his youngest son king in his place, because the band of men who came with the Arabians to the camp had slain all the oldest. So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah reigned. 2 Ahaziah was forty-two years old when he began to reign, and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri. 3 He also walked in the ways of Ahab’s house, because his mother was his counselor in acting wickedly. 4 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, as did Ahab’s house, for they were his counselors after the death of his father, to his destruction. 5 He also followed their counsel, and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth Gilead, and the Syrians wounded Joram. 6 He returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which they had given him at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. Azariah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Jehoram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick.

7 Now the destruction of Ahaziah was of God, in that he went to Joram; for when he had come, he went out with Jehoram against Jehu the son of Nimshi, whom Yahweh had anointed to cut off Ahab’s house. 8 When Jehu was executing judgment on Ahab’s house, he found the princes of Judah and the sons of the brothers of Ahaziah, serving Ahaziah, and killed them. 9 He sought Ahaziah, and they caught him (now he was hiding in Samaria), and they brought him to Jehu, and killed him; and they buried him, for they said, “He is the son of Jehoshaphat, who sought Yahweh with all his heart.” The house of Ahaziah had no power to hold the kingdom.

10 Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the royal offspring[*] of the house of Judah. 11 But Jehoshabeath, the king’s daughter, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stealthily rescued him from among the king’s sons who were slain, and put him and his nurse in the bedroom. So Jehoshabeath, the daughter of king Jehoram, the wife of Jehoiada the priest (for she was the sister of Ahaziah), hid him from Athaliah, so that she didn’t kill him. 12 He was with them hidden in God’s house six years while Athaliah reigned over the land.

or, seed

2 Chronicles 23

1 In the seventh year, Jehoiada strengthened himself, and took the captains of hundreds, Azariah the son of Jeroham, Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, Azariah the son of Obed, Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri, into a covenant with him. 2 They went around in Judah, and gathered the Levites out of all the cities of Judah, and the heads of fathers’ households of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem. 3 All the assembly made a covenant with the king in God’s house. He said to them, “Behold, the king’s son must reign, as Yahweh has spoken concerning the sons of David. 4 This is the thing that you must do. A third part of you, who come in on the Sabbath, of the priests and of the Levites, shall be porters of the thresholds. 5 A third part shall be at the king’s house; and a third part at the gate of the foundation. All the people will be in the courts of Yahweh’s house. 6 But let no one come into Yahweh’s house, except the priests and those who minister of the Levites. They shall come in, for they are holy, but all the people shall follow Yahweh’s instructions. 7 The Levites shall surround the king, every man with his weapons in his hand. Whoever comes into the house, let him be slain. Be with the king when he comes in, and when he goes out.”

8 So the Levites and all Judah did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded: and they each took his men, those who were to come in on the Sabbath; with those who were to go out on the Sabbath; for Jehoiada the priest didn’t dismiss the shift. 9 Jehoiada the priest delivered to the captains of hundreds the spears, and bucklers, and shields, that had been king David’s, which were in God’s house. 10 He set all the people, every man with his weapon in his hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, near the altar and the house, around the king. 11 Then they brought out the king’s son, and put the crown on him, and gave him the testimony, and made him king. Jehoiada and his sons anointed him, and they said, “Long live the king!”

12 When Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she came to the people into Yahweh’s house. 13 Then she looked, and, behold, the king stood by his pillar at the entrance, and the captains and the trumpets by the king. All the people of the land rejoiced, and blew trumpets. The singers also played musical instruments, and led the singing of praise. Then Athaliah tore her clothes, and said, “Treason! treason!”

14 Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains of hundreds who were set over the army, and said to them, “Bring her out between the ranks; and whoever follows her, let him be slain with the sword.” For the priest said, “Don’t kill her in Yahweh’s house.” 15 So they made way for her. She went to the entrance of the horse gate to the king’s house; and they killed her there.

16 Jehoiada made a covenant between himself, all the people, and the king, that they should be Yahweh’s people. 17 All the people went to the house of Baal, broke it down, broke his altars and his images in pieces, and killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. 18 Jehoiada appointed the officers of Yahweh’s house under the hand of the priests the Levites, whom David had distributed in Yahweh’s house, to offer the burnt offerings of Yahweh, as it is written in the law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, as David had ordered. 19 He set the porters at the gates of Yahweh’s house, that no one who was unclean in anything should enter in. 20 He took the captains of hundreds, the nobles, the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and brought the king down from Yahweh’s house. They came through the upper gate to the king’s house, and set the king on the throne of the kingdom. 21 So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. They had slain Athaliah with the sword.

2 Chronicles 25

1 Amaziah was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jehoaddan, of Jerusalem. 2 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, but not with a perfect heart. 3 Now when the kingdom was established to him, he killed his servants who had killed his father the king. 4 But he didn’t put their children to death, but did according to that which is written in the law in the book of Moses, as Yahweh commanded, saying, “The fathers shall not die for the children, neither shall the children die for the fathers; but every man shall die for his own sin.”

5 Moreover Amaziah gathered Judah together, and ordered them according to their fathers’ houses, under captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, even all Judah and Benjamin. He counted them from twenty years old and upward, and found that there were three hundred thousand chosen men, able to go out to war, who could handle spear and shield. 6 He also hired one hundred thousand mighty men of valor out of Israel for one hundred talents[*] of silver. 7 A man of God came to him, saying, “O king, don’t let the army of Israel go with you, for Yahweh is not with Israel, with all the children of Ephraim. 8 But if you will go, take action, and be strong for the battle. God will overthrow you before the enemy; for God has power to help, and to overthrow.”

9 Amaziah said to the man of God, “But what shall we do for the hundred talents[*] which I have given to the army of Israel?”

The man of God answered, “Yahweh is able to give you much more than this.”

10 Then Amaziah separated them, the army that had come to him out of Ephraim, to go home again. Therefore their anger was greatly kindled against Judah, and they returned home in fierce anger. 11 Amaziah took courage, and led his people out, and went to the Valley of Salt, and struck ten thousand of the children of Seir. 12 The children of Judah carried away ten thousand alive, and brought them to the top of the rock, and threw them down from the top of the rock, so that they all were broken in pieces. 13 But the men of the army whom Amaziah sent back, that they should not go with him to battle, fell on the cities of Judah, from Samaria even to Beth Horon, and struck of them three thousand, and took much plunder.

14 Now after Amaziah had come from the slaughter of the Edomites, he brought the gods of the children of Seir, and set them up to be his gods, and bowed down himself before them, and burned incense to them. 15 Therefore Yahweh’s anger burned against Amaziah, and he sent to him a prophet, who said to him, “Why have you sought after the gods of the people, which have not delivered their own people out of your hand?”

16 As he talked with him, the king said to him, “Have we made you one of the king’s counselors? Stop! Why should you be struck down?”

Then the prophet stopped, and said, “I know that God has determined to destroy you, because you have done this, and have not listened to my counsel.”

17 Then Amaziah king of Judah consulted his advisers, and sent to Joash, the son of Jehoahaz the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, “Come, let us look one another in the face.”

18 Joash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, “The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, ‘Give your daughter to my son as his wife. Then a wild animal that was in Lebanon passed by, and trampled down the thistle. 19 You say to yourself that you have struck Edom; and your heart lifts you up to boast. Now stay at home. Why should you meddle with trouble, that you should fall, even you, and Judah with you?’”

20 But Amaziah would not listen; for it was of God, that he might deliver them into the hand of their enemies, because they had sought after the gods of Edom. 21 So Joash king of Israel went up, and he and Amaziah king of Judah looked one another in the face at Beth Shemesh, which belongs to Judah. 22 Judah was defeated by Israel; and they every man fled to his tent.

23 Joash king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, at Beth Shemesh, and brought him to Jerusalem, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim to the corner gate, four hundred cubits.[*] 24 He took all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in God’s house with Obed-Edom, and the treasures of the king’s house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.

25 Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived for fifteen years after the death of Joash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel. 26 Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, first and last, behold, aren’t they written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel? 27 Now from the time that Amaziah turned away from following Yahweh, they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem. He fled to Lachish, but they sent after him to Lachish, and killed him there. 28 They brought him on horses, and buried him with his fathers in the City of Judah.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters, so 400 cubits is about 200 yards or 184 meters.

2 Chronicles 26

1 All the people of Judah took Uzziah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the place of his father Amaziah. 2 He built Eloth, and restored it to Judah, after that the king slept with his fathers. 3 Uzziah was sixteen years old when he began to reign; and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jechiliah, of Jerusalem. 4 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, according to all that his father Amaziah had done. 5 He set himself to seek God in the days of Zechariah, who had understanding in the vision of God; and as long as he sought Yahweh, God made him prosper.

6 He went out and fought against the Philistines, and broke down the wall of Gath, the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod; and he built cities in the country of Ashdod, and among the Philistines. 7 God helped him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians who lived in Gur Baal, and the Meunim. 8 The Ammonites gave tribute to Uzziah. His name spread abroad even to the entrance of Egypt; for he grew exceedingly strong. 9 Moreover Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at the corner gate, at the valley gate, and at the turning of the wall, and fortified them. 10 He built towers in the wilderness, and dug out many cisterns, for he had much livestock; in the lowland also, and in the plain. He had farmers and vineyard keepers in the mountains and in the fruitful fields, for he loved farming. 11 Moreover Uzziah had an army of fighting men, who went out to war by bands, according to the number of their reckoning made by Jeiel the scribe and Maaseiah the officer, under the hand of Hananiah, one of the king’s captains. 12 The whole number of the heads of fathers’ households, even the mighty men of valor, was two thousand six hundred. 13 Under their hand was an army, three hundred seven thousand five hundred, who made war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy. 14 Uzziah prepared for them, even for all the army, shields, spears, helmets, coats of mail, bows, and stones for slinging. 15 In Jerusalem, he made devices, invented by skillful men, to be on the towers and on the battlements, with which to shoot arrows and great stones. His name spread far abroad, because he was marvelously helped until he was strong.

16 But when he was strong, his heart was lifted up, so that he did corruptly, and he trespassed against Yahweh his God; for he went into Yahweh’s temple to burn incense on the altar of incense. 17 Azariah the priest went in after him, and with him eighty priests of Yahweh, who were valiant men. 18 They resisted Uzziah the king, and said to him, “It isn’t for you, Uzziah, to burn incense to Yahweh, but for the priests the sons of Aaron, who are consecrated to burn incense. Go out of the sanctuary, for you have trespassed. It will not be for your honor from Yahweh God.”

19 Then Uzziah was angry. He had a censer in his hand to burn incense, and while he was angry with the priests, the leprosy broke out on his forehead before the priests in Yahweh’s house, beside the altar of incense. 20 Azariah the chief priest, and all the priests, looked at him, and behold, he was leprous in his forehead, and they thrust him out quickly from there. Yes, he himself also hurried to go out, because Yahweh had struck him. 21 Uzziah the king was a leper to the day of his death, and lived in a separate house, being a leper; for he was cut off from Yahweh’s house. Jotham his son was over the king’s house, judging the people of the land. 22 Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, first and last, Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, wrote. 23 So Uzziah slept with his fathers; and they buried him with his fathers in the field of burial which belonged to the kings, for they said, “He is a leper.” Jotham his son reigned in his place.

2 Chronicles 27

1 Jotham was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Jerushah the daughter of Zadok. 2 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, according to all that his father Uzziah had done. However he didn’t enter into Yahweh’s temple. The people still acted corruptly. 3 He built the upper gate of Yahweh’s house, and he built much on the wall of Ophel. 4 Moreover he built cities in the hill country of Judah, and in the forests he built fortresses and towers. 5 He also fought with the king of the children of Ammon, and prevailed against them. The children of Ammon gave him the same year one hundred talents[*] of silver, ten thousand cors[*] of wheat, and ten thousand cors of barley.[*] The children of Ammon also gave that much to him in the second year, and in the third. 6 So Jotham became mighty, because he ordered his ways before Yahweh his God. 7 Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars, and his ways, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. 8 He was five and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. 9 Jotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in David’s city; and Ahaz his son reigned in his place.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds

1 cor is the same as a homer, or about 55.9 U. S. gallons (liquid) or 211 liters or 6 bushels 10,000 cors of wheat would weigh about 1,640 metric tons.

10,000 cors of barley would weigh about 1,310 metric tons.

2 Chronicles 28

1 Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. He didn’t do that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, like David his father, 2 but he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and also made molten images for the Baals. 3 Moreover he burned incense in the valley of the son of Hinnom, and burned his children in the fire, according to the abominations of the nations whom Yahweh cast out before the children of Israel. 4 He sacrificed and burned incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree.

5 Therefore Yahweh his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria. They struck him, and carried away from him a great multitude of captives, and brought them to Damascus. He was also delivered into the hand of the king of Israel, who struck him with a great slaughter. 6 For Pekah the son of Remaliah killed in Judah one hundred twenty thousand in one day, all of them valiant men, because they had forsaken Yahweh, the God of their fathers. 7 Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, killed Maaseiah the king’s son, Azrikam the ruler of the house, and Elkanah who was next to the king. 8 The children of Israel carried away captive of their brothers two hundred thousand, women, sons, and daughters, and took also away much plunder from them, and brought the plunder to Samaria. 9 But a prophet of Yahweh was there, whose name was Oded; and he went out to meet the army that came to Samaria, and said to them, “Behold, because Yahweh, the God of your fathers, was angry with Judah, he has delivered them into your hand, and you have slain them in a rage which has reached up to heaven. 10 Now you intend to degrade the children of Judah and Jerusalem as male and female slaves for yourselves. Aren’t there even with you trespasses of your own against Yahweh your God? 11 Now hear me therefore, and send back the captives that you have taken captive from your brothers, for the fierce wrath of Yahweh is on you.” 12 Then some of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against those who came from the war, 13 and said to them, “You must not bring in the captives here, for you intend that which will bring on us a trespass against Yahweh, to add to our sins and to our guilt; for our gulit is great, and there is fierce wrath against Israel.”

14 So the armed men left the captives and the plunder before the princes and all the assembly. 15 The men who have been mentioned by name rose up and took the captives, and with the plunder clothed all who were naked among them, dressed them, gave them sandals, and gave them something to eat and to drink, anointed them, carried all the feeble of them on donkeys, and brought them to Jericho, the city of palm trees, to their brothers. Then they returned to Samaria.

16 At that time king Ahaz sent to the kings of Assyria to help him. 17 For again the Edomites had come and struck Judah, and carried away captives. 18 The Philistines also had invaded the cities of the lowland, and of the South of Judah, and had taken Beth Shemesh, Aijalon, Gederoth, Soco with its villages, Timnah with its villages, and also Gimzo and its villages; and they lived there. 19 For Yahweh brought Judah low because of Ahaz king of Israel, because he acted without restraint in Judah and trespassed severely against Yahweh. 20 Tilgath Pilneser king of Assyria came to him, and gave him trouble, but didn’t strengthen him. 21 For Ahaz took away a portion out of Yahweh’s house, and out of the house of the king and of the princes, and gave it to the king of Assyria; but it didn’t help him.

22 In the time of his distress, he trespassed yet more against Yahweh, this same king Ahaz. 23 For he sacrificed to the gods of Damascus, which struck him. He said, “Because the gods of the kings of Syria helped them, so I will sacrifice to them, that they may help me.” But they were the ruin of him, and of all Israel. 24 Ahaz gathered together the vessels of God’s house, and cut the vessels of God’s house in pieces, and shut up the doors of Yahweh’s house; and he made himself altars in every corner of Jerusalem. 25 In every city of Judah he made high places to burn incense to other gods, and provoked Yahweh, the God of his fathers, to anger.

26 Now the rest of his acts, and all his ways, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. 27 Ahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, even in Jerusalem, because they didn’t bring him into the tombs of the kings of Israel; and Hezekiah his son reigned in his place.

2 Chronicles 29

1 Hezekiah began to reign when he was twenty-five years old, and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Abijah, the daughter of Zechariah. 2 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, according to all that David his father had done. 3 In the first year of his reign, in the first month, he opened the doors of Yahweh’s house, and repaired them. 4 He brought in the priests and the Levites, and gathered them together into the wide place on the east, 5 and said to them, “Listen to me, you Levites! Now sanctify yourselves, and sanctify Yahweh, the God of your fathers’ house, and carry the filthiness out of the holy place. 6 For our fathers were unfaithful, and have done that which was evil in Yahweh our God’s sight, and have forsaken him, and have turned away their faces from the habitation of Yahweh, and turned their backs. 7 Also they have shut up the doors of the porch, and put out the lamps, and have not burned incense nor offered burnt offerings in the holy place to the God of Israel. 8 Therefore Yahweh’s wrath was on Judah and Jerusalem, and he has delivered them to be tossed back and forth, to be an astonishment, and a hissing, as you see with your eyes. 9 For, behold, our fathers have fallen by the sword, and our sons and our daughters and our wives are in captivity for this. 10 Now it is in my heart to make a covenant with Yahweh, the God of Israel, that his fierce anger may turn away from us. 11 My sons, don’t be negligent now; for Yahweh has chosen you to stand before him, to minister to him, and that you should be his ministers, and burn incense.”

12 Then the Levites arose, Mahath, the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of the Kohathites; and of the sons of Merari, Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehallelel; and of the Gershonites, Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah; 13 and of the sons of Elizaphan, Shimri and Jeuel; and of the sons of Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah; 14 and of the sons of Heman, Jehuel and Shimei; and of the sons of Jeduthun, Shemaiah and Uzziel. 15 They gathered their brothers, sanctified themselves, and went in, according to the commandment of the king by Yahweh’s words, to cleanse Yahweh’s house. 16 The priests went into the inner part of Yahweh’s house to cleanse it, and brought out all the uncleanness that they found in Yahweh’s temple into the court of Yahweh’s house. The Levites took it from there to carry it out to the brook Kidron. 17 Now they began on the first day of the first month to sanctify, and on the eighth day of the month they came to Yahweh’s porch. They sanctified Yahweh’s house in eight days, and on the sixteenth day of the first month they finished. 18 Then they went in to Hezekiah the king within the palace, and said, “We have cleansed all Yahweh’s house, including the altar of burnt offering with all its vessels, and the table of show bread with all its vessels. 19 Moreover all the vessels, which king Ahaz in his reign threw away when he was unfaithful, have we prepared and sanctified. Behold, they are before Yahweh’s altar.”

20 Then Hezekiah the king arose early, gathered the princes of the city, and went up to Yahweh’s house. 21 They brought seven bulls, seven rams, seven lambs, and seven male goats, for a sin offering for the kingdom, for the sanctuary, and for Judah. He commanded the priests the sons of Aaron to offer them on Yahweh’s altar. 22 So they killed the bulls, and the priests received the blood, and sprinkled it on the altar. They killed the rams, and sprinkled the blood on the altar. They also killed the lambs, and sprinkled the blood on the altar. 23 They brought near the male goats for the sin offering before the king and the assembly; and they laid their hands on them. 24 Then the priests killed them, and they made a sin offering with their blood on the altar, to make atonement for all Israel; for the king commanded that the burnt offering and the sin offering should be made for all Israel.

25 He set the Levites in Yahweh’s house with cymbals, with stringed instruments, and with harps, according to the commandment of David, of Gad the king’s seer, and Nathan the prophet; for the commandment was from Yahweh by his prophets. 26 The Levites stood with David’s instruments, and the priests with the trumpets. 27 Hezekiah commanded them to offer the burnt offering on the altar. When the burnt offering began, Yahweh’s song also began, along with the trumpets and David king of Israel’s instruments. 28 All the assembly worshiped, the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded. All this continued until the burnt offering was finished.

29 When they had finished offering, the king and all who were present with him bowed themselves and worshiped. 30 Moreover Hezekiah the king and the princes commanded the Levites to sing praises to Yahweh with the words of David, and of Asaph the seer. They sang praises with gladness, and they bowed their heads and worshiped.

31 Then Hezekiah answered, “Now you have consecrated yourselves to Yahweh. Come near and bring sacrifices and thank offerings into Yahweh’s house.” The assembly brought in sacrifices and thank offerings, and as many as were of a willing heart brought burnt offerings. 32 The number of the burnt offerings which the assembly brought was seventy bulls, one hundred rams, and two hundred lambs. All these were for a burnt offering to Yahweh. 33 The consecrated things were six hundred head of cattle and three thousand sheep. 34 But the priests were too few, so that they could not flay all the burnt offerings. Therefore their brothers the Levites helped them, until the work was ended, and until the priests had sanctified themselves; for the Levites were more upright in heart to sanctify themselves than the priests. 35 Also the burnt offerings were in abundance, with the fat of the peace offerings, and with the drink offerings for every burnt offering. So the service of Yahweh’s house was set in order. 36 Hezekiah and all the people rejoiced, because of that which God had prepared for the people; for the thing was done suddenly.

2 Chronicles 30

1 Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to Yahweh’s house at Jerusalem, to keep the Passover to Yahweh, the God of Israel. 2 For the king had taken counsel with his princes and all the assembly in Jerusalem to keep the Passover in the second month. 3 For they could not keep it at that time, because the priests had not sanctified themselves in sufficient number, and the people had not gathered themselves together to Jerusalem. 4 The thing was right in the eyes of the king and of all the assembly. 5 So they established a decree to make proclamation throughout all Israel, from Beersheba even to Dan, that they should come to keep the Passover to Yahweh, the God of Israel, at Jerusalem, for they had not kept it in great numbers in the way it is written.

6 So the couriers went with the letters from the king and his princes throughout all Israel and Judah, and according to the commandment of the king, saying, “You children of Israel, turn again to Yahweh, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, that he may return to the remnant of you that have escaped out of the hand of the kings of Assyria. 7 Don’t be like your fathers and like your brothers, who trespassed against Yahweh, the God of their fathers, so that he gave them up to desolation, as you see. 8 Now don’t be stiff-necked, as your fathers were, but yield yourselves to Yahweh, and enter into his sanctuary, which he has sanctified forever, and serve Yahweh your God, that his fierce anger may turn away from you. 9 For if you turn again to Yahweh, your brothers and your children will find compassion before those who led them captive, and will come again into this land, because Yahweh your God is gracious and merciful, and will not turn away his face from you, if you return to him.”

10 So the couriers passed from city to city through the country of Ephraim and Manasseh, even to Zebulun, but people ridiculed them and mocked them. 11 Nevertheless some men of Asher and Manasseh and of Zebulun humbled themselves, and came to Jerusalem. 12 Also the hand of God came on Judah to give them one heart, to do the commandment of the king and of the princes by Yahweh’s word.

13 Many people assembled at Jerusalem to keep the feast of unleavened bread in the second month, a very great assembly. 14 They arose and took away the altars that were in Jerusalem, and they took away all the altars for incense and threw them into the brook Kidron. 15 Then they killed the Passover on the fourteenth day of the second month. The priests and the Levites were ashamed, and sanctified themselves, and brought burnt offerings into Yahweh’s house. 16 They stood in their place after their order, according to the law of Moses the man of God. The priests sprinkled the blood which they received of the hand of the Levites. 17 For there were many in the assembly who had not sanctified themselves: therefore the Levites were in charge of killing the Passovers for everyone who was not clean, to sanctify them to Yahweh. 18 For a multitude of the people, even many of Ephraim, Manasseh, Issachar, and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, yet they ate the Passover other than the way it is written. For Hezekiah had prayed for them, saying, “May the good Yahweh pardon everyone 19 who sets his heart to seek God, Yahweh, the God of his fathers, even if they aren’t clean according to the purification of the sanctuary.”

20 Yahweh listened to Hezekiah, and healed the people. 21 The children of Israel who were present at Jerusalem kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with great gladness. The Levites and the priests praised Yahweh day by day, singing with loud instruments to Yahweh. 22 Hezekiah spoke encouragingly to all the Levites who had good understanding in the service of Yahweh. So they ate throughout the feast for the seven days, offering sacrifices of peace offerings, and making confession to Yahweh, the God of their fathers.

23 The whole assembly took counsel to keep another seven days, and they kept another seven days with gladness. 24 For Hezekiah king of Judah gave to the assembly for offerings one thousand bulls and seven thousand sheep; and the princes gave to the assembly a thousand bulls and ten thousand sheep: and a great number of priests sanctified themselves. 25 All the assembly of Judah, with the priests and the Levites, and all the assembly who came out of Israel, and the foreigners who came out of the land of Israel, and who lived in Judah, rejoiced. 26 So there was great joy in Jerusalem; for since the time of Solomon the son of David king of Israel there was nothing like this in Jerusalem. 27 Then the priests the Levites arose and blessed the people. Their voice was heard, and their prayer came up to his holy habitation, even to heaven.

2 Chronicles 31

1 Now when all this was finished, all Israel who were present went out to the cities of Judah, and broke the pillars in pieces, cut down the Asherah poles, and broke down the high places and the altars out of all Judah and Benjamin, also in Ephraim and Manasseh, until they had destroyed them all. Then all the children of Israel returned, every man to his possession, into their own cities.

2 Hezekiah appointed the divisions of the priests and the Levites after their divisions, every man according to his service, both the priests and the Levites, for burnt offerings and for peace offerings, to minister, to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of Yahweh’s camp. 3 He also appointed the king’s portion of his posessions for the burnt offerings, for the morning and evening burnt offerings, and the burnt offerings for the Sabbaths, for the new moons, and for the set feasts, as it is written in Yahweh’s law. 4 Moreover he commanded the people who lived in Jerusalem to give the portion of the priests and the Levites, that they might give themselves to Yahweh’s law. 5 As soon as the commandment went out, the children of Israel gave in abundance the first fruits of grain, new wine, oil, honey, and of all the increase of the field; and they brought in the tithe of all things abundantly. 6 The children of Israel and Judah, who lived in the cities of Judah, also brought in the tithe of cattle and sheep, and the tithe of dedicated things which were consecrated to Yahweh their God, and laid them in heaps.

7 In the third month they began to lay the foundation of the heaps, and finished them in the seventh month. 8 When Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed Yahweh and his people Israel. 9 Then Hezekiah questioned the priests and the Levites about the heaps. 10 Azariah the chief priest, of the house of Zadok, answered him and said, “Since people began to bring the offerings into Yahweh’s house, we have eaten and had enough, and have plenty left over, for Yahweh has blessed his people; and that which is left is this great store.”

11 Then Hezekiah commanded them to prepare rooms in Yahweh’s house, and they prepared them. 12 They brought in the offerings, the tithes, and the dedicated things faithfully. Conaniah the Levite was ruler over them, and Shimei his brother was second. 13 Jehiel, Azaziah, Nahath, Asahel, Jerimoth, Jozabad, Eliel, Ismachiah, Mahath, and Benaiah were overseers under the hand of Conaniah and Shimei his brother, by the appointment of Hezekiah the king and Azariah the ruler of God’s house. 14 Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, the porter at the east gate, was over the freewill offerings of God, to distribute Yahweh’s offerings and the most holy things. 15 Under him were Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, in the cities of the priests, in their office of trust, to give to their brothers by divisions, to the great as well as to the small; 16 besides those who were listed by genealogy of males, from three years old and upward, even everyone who entered into Yahweh’s house, as the duty of every day required, for their service in their offices according to their divisions; 17 and those who were listed by genealogy of the priests by their fathers’ houses, and the Levites from twenty years old and upward, in their offices by their divisions; 18 and those who were listed by genealogy of all their little ones, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, through all the congregation; for in their office of trust they sanctified themselves in holiness. 19 Also for the sons of Aaron the priests, who were in the fields of the suburbs of their cities, in every city, there were men who were mentioned by name, to give portions to all the males among the priests, and to all who were listed by genealogy among the Levites.

20 Hezekiah did so throughout all Judah; and he did that which was good, right, and faithful before Yahweh his God. 21 In every work that he began in the service of God’s house, in the law, and in the commandments, to seek his God, he did it with all his heart, and prospered.

2 Chronicles 32

1 After these things and this faithfulness, Sennacherib king of Assyria came, entered into Judah, and encamped against the fortified cities, and intended to win them for himself. 2 When Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib had come, and that he was planning to fight against Jerusalem, 3 he took counsel with his princes and his mighty men to stop the waters of the springs which were outside of the city, and they helped him. 4 So, many people gathered together and they stopped all the springs and the brook that flowed through the middle of the land, saying, “Why should the kings of Assyria come, and find abundant water?”

5 He took courage, built up all the wall that was broken down, and raised it up to the towers, with the other wall outside, and strengthened Millo in David’s city, and made weapons and shields in abundance. 6 He set captains of war over the people, and gathered them together to him in the wide place at the gate of the city, and spoke encouragingly to them, saying, 7 “Be strong and courageous. Don’t be afraid or dismayed because of the king of Assyria, nor for all the multitude who is with him; for there is a greater one with us than with him. 8 An arm of flesh is with him, but Yahweh our God is with us to help us and to fight our battles.” The people rested themselves on the words of Hezekiah king of Judah.

9 After this, Sennacherib king of Assyria sent his servants to Jerusalem, (now he was before Lachish, and all his power with him), to Hezekiah king of Judah, and to all Judah who were at Jerusalem, saying, 10 Thus says Sennacherib king of Assyria, “In whom do you trust, that you remain under siege in Jerusalem? 11 Doesn’t Hezekiah persuade you, to give you over to die by famine and by thirst, saying, ‘Yahweh our God will deliver us out of the hand of the king of Assyria?’ 12 Hasn’t the same Hezekiah taken away his high places and his altars, and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, saying, ‘You shall worship before one altar, and you shall burn incense on it?’ 13 Don’t you know what I and my fathers have done to all the peoples of the lands? Were the gods of the nations of the lands in any way able to deliver their land out of my hand? 14 Who was there among all the gods of those nations which my fathers utterly destroyed, that could deliver his people out of my hand, that your God should be able to deliver you out of my hand? 15 Now therefore don’t let Hezekiah deceive you, nor persuade you in this way. Don’t believe him, for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people out of my hand, and out of the hand of my fathers. How much less will your God deliver you out of my hand?”

16 His servants spoke yet more against Yahweh God, and against his servant Hezekiah. 17 He also wrote letters insulting Yahweh, the God of Israel, and speaking against him, saying, “As the gods of the nations of the lands, which have not delivered their people out of my hand, so shall the God of Hezekiah not deliver his people out of my hand.” 18 They called out with a loud voice in the Jews’ language to the people of Jerusalem who were on the wall, to frighten them, and to trouble them; that they might take the city. 19 They spoke of the God of Jerusalem as of the gods of the peoples of the earth, which are the work of men’s hands.

20 Hezekiah the king and Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz, prayed because of this, and cried to heaven.

21 Yahweh sent an angel, who cut off all the mighty men of valor, and the leaders and captains, in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned with shame of face to his own land. When he had come into the house of his god, those who came out of his own bowels[*] killed him there with the sword. 22 Thus Yahweh saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib the king of Assyria and from the hand of all others, and guided them on every side. 23 Many brought gifts to Yahweh to Jerusalem, and precious things to Hezekiah king of Judah; so that he was exalted in the sight of all nations from then on.

24 In those days Hezekiah was terminally ill, and he prayed to Yahweh; and he spoke to him, and gave him a sign. 25 But Hezekiah didn’t reciprocate appropriate to the benefit done for him, because his heart was lifted up. Therefore there was wrath on him, and on Judah and Jerusalem. 26 Notwithstanding Hezekiah humbled himself for the pride of his heart, both he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that Yahweh’s wrath didn’t come on them in the days of Hezekiah.

27 Hezekiah had exceedingly much riches and honor. He provided himself with treasuries for silver, for gold, for precious stones, for spices, for shields, and for all kinds of valuable vessels; 28 also storehouses for the increase of grain, new wine, and oil; and stalls for all kinds of animals, and flocks in folds. 29 Moreover he provided for himself cities, and possessions of flocks and herds in abundance; for God had given him abundant posessions. 30 This same Hezekiah also stopped the upper spring of the waters of Gihon, and brought them straight down on the west side of David’s city. Hezekiah prospered in all his works.

31 However concerning the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, who sent to him to inquire of the wonder that was done in the land, God left him, to try him, that he might know all that was in his heart.

32 Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and his good deeds, behold, they are written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz, in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. 33 Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the ascent of the tombs of the sons of David. All Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem honored him at his death. Manasseh his son reigned in his place.

i.e., his own sons

2 Chronicles 33

1 Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign, and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. 2 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, after the abominations of the nations whom Yahweh cast out before the children of Israel. 3 For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had broken down; and he raised up altars for the Baals, made Asheroth, and worshiped all the army of the sky, and served them. 4 He built altars in Yahweh’s house, of which Yahweh said, “My name shall be in Jerusalem forever.” 5 He built altars for all the army of the sky in the two courts of Yahweh’s house. 6 He also made his children to pass through the fire in the valley of the son of Hinnom. He practiced sorcery, divination, and witchcraft, and dealt with those who had familiar spirits, and with wizards. He did much evil in Yahweh’s sight, to provoke him to anger. 7 He set the engraved image of the idol, which he had made, in God’s house, of which God said to David and to Solomon his son, “In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name forever. 8 I will not any more remove the foot of Israel from off the land which I have appointed for your fathers, if only they will observe to do all that I have commanded them, even all the law, the statutes, and the ordinances given by Moses.” 9 Manasseh seduced Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that they did more evil than the nations whom Yahweh destroyed before the children of Israel did.

10 Yahweh spoke to Manasseh, and to his people; but they didn’t listen. 11 Therefore Yahweh brought on them the captains of the army of the king of Assyria, who took Manasseh in chains, bound him with fetters, and carried him to Babylon.

12 When he was in distress, he begged Yahweh his God, and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers. 13 He prayed to him; and he was entreated by him, and heard his supplication, and brought him again to Jerusalem into his kingdom. Then Manasseh knew that Yahweh was God.

14 Now after this, he built an outer wall to David’s city, on the west side of Gihon, in the valley, even to the entrance at the fish gate. He encircled Ophel with it, and raised it up to a very great height; and he put valiant captains in all the fortified cities of Judah. 15 He took away the foreign gods, and the idol out of Yahweh’s house, and all the altars that he had built in the mountain of Yahweh’s house, and in Jerusalem, and cast them out of the city. 16 He built up Yahweh’s altar, and offered sacrifices of peace offerings and of thanksgiving on it, and commanded Judah to serve Yahweh, the God of Israel. 17 Nevertheless the people sacrificed still in the high places, but only to Yahweh their God.

18 Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and his prayer to his God, and the words of the seers who spoke to him in the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel, behold, they are written among the acts of the kings of Israel. 19 His prayer also, and how God was entreated of him, and all his sin and his trespass, and the places in which he built high places, and set up the Asherah poles and the engraved images, before he humbled himself: behold, they are written in the history of Hozai.[*] 20 So Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his own house; and Amon his son reigned in his place.

21 Amon was twenty-two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. 22 He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight, as did Manasseh his father; and Amon sacrificed to all the engraved images which Manasseh his father had made, and served them. 23 He didn’t humble himself before Yahweh, as Manasseh his father had humbled himself; but this same Amon trespassed more and more. 24 His servants conspired against him, and put him to death in his own house. 25 But the people of the land killed all those who had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his place.

or, the seers

2 Chronicles 34

1 Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem. 2 He did that which was right in Yahweh’s eyes, and walked in the ways of David his father, and didn’t turn aside to the right hand or to the left. 3 For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was yet young, he began to seek after the God of David his father; and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem from the high places, the Asherah poles, the engraved images, and the molten images. 4 They broke down the altars of the Baals in his presence; and he cut down the incense altars that were on high above them. He broke the Asherah poles, the engraved images, and the molten images in pieces, made dust of them, and scattered it on the graves of those who had sacrificed to them. 5 He burned the bones of the priests on their altars, and purged Judah and Jerusalem. 6 He did this in the cities of Manasseh, Ephraim, and Simeon, even to Naphtali, around in their ruins. 7 He broke down the altars, and beat the Asherah poles and the engraved images into powder, and cut down all the incense altars throughout all the land of Israel, then returned to Jerusalem.

8 Now in the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had purged the land and the house, he sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah, and Maaseiah the governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz the recorder, to repair Yahweh his God’s house. 9 They came to Hilkiah the high priest, and delivered the money that was brought into God’s house, which the Levites, the keepers of the threshold, had gathered from the hands of Manasseh, Ephraim, of all the remnant of Israel, of all Judah and Benjamin, and of the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 10 They delivered it into the hands of the workmen who had the oversight of Yahweh’s house; and the workmen who labored in Yahweh’s house gave it to mend and repair the house. 11 They gave it to the carpenters and to the builders, to buy cut stone and timber for couplings, and to make beams for the houses which the kings of Judah had destroyed. 12 The men did the work faithfully. Their overseers were Jahath and Obadiah, the Levites, of the sons of Merari; and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to give direction; and others of the Levites, who were all skillful with musical instruments. 13 Also they were over the bearers of burdens, and directed all who did the work in every kind of service. Of the Levites, there were scribes, officials, and porters.

14 When they brought out the money that was brought into Yahweh’s house, Hilkiah the priest found the book of Yahweh’s law given by Moses. 15 Hilkiah answered Shaphan the scribe, “I have found the book of the law in Yahweh’s house.” So Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan.

16 Shaphan carried the book to the king, and moreover brought back word to the king, saying, “All that was committed to your servants, they are doing. 17 They have emptied out the money that was found in Yahweh’s house, and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers, and into the hand of the workmen.” 18 Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, “Hilkiah the priest has delivered me a book.” Shaphan read from it to the king.

19 When the king had heard the words of the law, he tore his clothes. 20 The king commanded Hilkiah, Ahikam the son of Shaphan, Abdon the son of Micah, Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah the king’s servant, saying, 21 “Go inquire of Yahweh for me, and for those who are left in Israel and in Judah, concerning the words of the book that is found; for great is Yahweh’s wrath that is poured out on us, because our fathers have not kept Yahweh’s word, to do according to all that is written in this book.”

22 So Hilkiah, and they whom the king had commanded, went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tokhath, the son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe (now she lived in Jerusalem in the second quarter), and they spoke to her to that effect.

23 She said to them, “Yahweh, the God of Israel says: ‘Tell the man who sent you to me, 24 “Yahweh says, ‘Behold, I will bring evil on this place, and on its inhabitants, even all the curses that are written in the book which they have read before the king of Judah. 25 Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense to other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the works of their hands; therefore my wrath is poured out on this place, and it will not be quenched.’”’ 26 But to the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of Yahweh, you shall tell him this, ‘Yahweh, the God of Israel says: “About the words which you have heard, 27 because your heart was tender, and you humbled yourself before God, when you heard his words against this place, and against its inhabitants, and have humbled yourself before me, and have torn your clothes, and wept before me, I also have heard you,” says Yahweh. 28 “Behold, I will gather you to your fathers, and you will be gathered to your grave in peace. Your eyes won’t see all the evil that I will bring on this place and on its inhabitants.”’”

They brought back word to the king.

29 Then the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. 30 The king went up to Yahweh’s house, with all the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the priests, the Levites, and all the people, both great and small; and he read in their hearing all the words of the book of the covenant that was found in Yahweh’s house. 31 The king stood in his place, and made a covenant before Yahweh, to walk after Yahweh, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and with all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant that were written in this book. 32 He caused all who were found in Jerusalem and Benjamin to stand. The inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers. 33 Josiah took away all the abominations out of all the countries that belonged to the children of Israel, and made all who were found in Israel to serve, even to serve Yahweh their God. All his days they didn’t depart from following Yahweh, the God of their fathers.

2 Chronicles 35

1 Josiah kept a Passover to Yahweh in Jerusalem. They killed the Passover on the fourteenth day of the first month. 2 He set the priests in their offices, and encouraged them in the service of Yahweh’s house. 3 He said to the Levites who taught all Israel, who were holy to Yahweh, “Put the holy ark in the house which Solomon the son of David king of Israel built. It will no longer be a burden on your shoulders. Now serve Yahweh your God, and his people Israel. 4 Prepare yourselves after your fathers’ houses by your divisions, according to the writing of David king of Israel, and according to the writing of Solomon his son. 5 Stand in the holy place according to the divisions of the fathers’ houses of your brothers the children of the people, and let there be for each a portion of a fathers’ house of the Levites. 6 Kill the Passover, sanctify yourselves, and prepare for your brothers, to do according to Yahweh’s word by Moses.”

7 Josiah gave to the children of the people, of the flock, lambs and young goats, all of them for the Passover offerings, to all who were present, to the number of thirty thousand, and three thousand bulls. These were of the king’s substance. 8 His princes gave for a freewill offering to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. Hilkiah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, the rulers of God’s house, gave to the priests for the Passover offerings two thousand six hundred small livestock, and three hundred head of cattle. 9 Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethanel, his brothers, and Hashabiah, Jeiel, and Jozabad, the chiefs of the Levites, gave to the Levites for the Passover offerings five thousand small livestock and five hundred head of cattle.

10 So the service was prepared, and the priests stood in their place, and the Levites by their divisions, according to the king’s commandment. 11 They killed the Passover, and the priests sprinkled the blood which they received of their hand, and the Levites flayed them. 12 They removed the burnt offerings, that they might give them according to the divisions of the fathers’ houses of the children of the people, to offer to Yahweh, as it is written in the book of Moses. They did the same with the cattle. 13 They roasted the Passover with fire according to the ordinance. The boiled the holy offerings in pots, in cauldrons, and in pans, and carried them quickly to all the children of the people. 14 Afterward they prepared for themselves and for the priests, because the priests the sons of Aaron were busy with offering the burnt offerings and the fat until night. Therefore the Levites prepared for themselves and for the priests the sons of Aaron. 15 The singers the sons of Asaph were in their place, according to the commandment of David, Asaph, Heman, and Jeduthun the king’s seer; and the porters were at every gate. They didn’t need to depart from their service, because their brothers the Levites prepared for them.

16 So all the service of Yahweh was prepared the same day, to keep the Passover, and to offer burnt offerings on Yahweh’s altar, according to the commandment of king Josiah. 17 The children of Israel who were present kept the Passover at that time, and the feast of unleavened bread seven days. 18 There was no Passover like that kept in Israel from the days of Samuel the prophet, nor did any of the kings of Israel keep such a Passover as Josiah kept, with the priests, the Levites, and all Judah and Israel who were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. 19 This passover was kept in the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah.

20 After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Neco king of Egypt went up to fight against Carchemish by the Euphrates, and Josiah went out against him. 21 But he sent ambassadors to him, saying, “What have I to do with you, you king of Judah? I come not against you today, but against the house with which I have war. God has commanded me to make haste. Beware that it is God who is with me, that he not destroy you.”

22 Nevertheless Josiah would not turn his face from him, but disguised himself, that he might fight with him, and didn’t listen to the words of Neco from the mouth of God, and came to fight in the valley of Megiddo. 23 The archers shot at king Josiah; and the king said to his servants, “Take me away, because I am seriously wounded!”

24 So his servants took him out of the chariot, and put him in the second chariot that he had, and brought him to Jerusalem; and he died, and was buried in the tombs of his fathers. All Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah. 25 Jeremiah lamented for Josiah, and all the singing men and singing women spoke of Josiah in their lamentations to this day; and they made them an ordinance in Israel. Behold, they are written in the lamentations. 26 Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and his good deeds, according to that which is written in Yahweh’s law, 27 and his acts, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.

2 Chronicles 36

1 Then the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and made him king in his father’s place in Jerusalem. 2 Joahaz was twenty-three years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. 3 The king of Egypt removed him from office at Jerusalem, and fined the land one hundred talents of silver and a talent[*] of gold. 4 The king of Egypt made Eliakim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. Neco took Joahaz his brother, and carried him to Egypt.

5 Jehoiakim was twenty-five years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. He did that which was evil in Yahweh his God’s sight. 6 Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up against him, and bound him in fetters to carry him to Babylon. 7 Nebuchadnezzar also carried some of the vessels of Yahweh’s house to Babylon, and put them in his temple at Babylon. 8 Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and his abominations which he did, and that which was found in him, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah; and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his place.

9 Jehoiachin was eight years old when he began to reign, and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem. He did that which was evil in Yahweh’s sight. 10 At the return of the year, king Nebuchadnezzar sent and brought him to Babylon, with the valuable vessels of Yahweh’s house, and made Zedekiah his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem.

11 Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem. 12 He did that which was evil in Yahweh his God’s sight. He didn’t humble himself before Jeremiah the prophet speaking from Yahweh’s mouth. 13 He also rebelled against king Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by God; but he stiffened his neck, and hardened his heart against turning to Yahweh, the God of Israel. 14 Moreover all the chiefs of the priests, and the people, trespassed very greatly after all the abominations of the nations; and they polluted Yahweh’s house which he had made holy in Jerusalem. 15 Yahweh, the God of their fathers, sent to them by his messengers, rising up early and sending, because he had compassion on his people, and on his dwelling place; 16 but they mocked the messengers of God, and despised his words, and scoffed at his prophets, until Yahweh’s wrath arose against his people, until there was no remedy.

17 Therefore he brought on them the king of the Chaldeans, who killed their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and had no compassion on young man or virgin, old man or gray-headed. He gave them all into his hand. 18 All the vessels of God’s house, great and small, and the treasures of Yahweh’s house, and the treasures of the king, and of his princes, all these he brought to Babylon. 19 They burned God’s house, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem, and burned all its palaces with fire, and destroyed all of its valuable vessels. 20 He carried those who had escaped from the sword away to Babylon, and they were servants to him and his sons until the reign of the kingdom of Persia, 21 to fulfill Yahweh’s word by Jeremiah’s mouth, until the land had enjoyed its Sabbaths. As long as it lay desolate, it kept Sabbath, to fulfill seventy years.

22 Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that Yahweh’s word by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, Yahweh stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying, 23 “Thus says Cyrus king of Persia, ‘Yahweh, the God of heaven, has given all the kingdoms of the earth to me; and he has commanded me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Whoever there is among you of all his people, Yahweh his God be with him, and let him go up.’”

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

Ezra 1

1 Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that Yahweh’s word[*] by Jeremiah’s mouth might be accomplished, Yahweh stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying, 2 “Thus says Cyrus king of Persia, ‘Yahweh, the God[*] of heaven, has given me all the kingdoms of the earth; and he has commanded me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. 3 Whoever there is among you of all his people, may his God be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem, which is in Judah, and build the house of Yahweh, the God of Israel (he is God), which is in Jerusalem. 4 Whoever is left, in any place where he lives, let the men of his place help him with silver, with gold, with goods, and with animals, besides the freewill offering for God’s house which is in Jerusalem.’”

5 Then the heads of fathers’ households of Judah and Benjamin, the priests, and the Levites, all whose spirit God had stirred to go up rose up to build Yahweh’s house which is in Jerusalem. 6 All those who were around them strengthened their hands with vessels of silver, with gold, with goods, with animals, and with precious things, besides all that was willingly offered. 7 Also Cyrus the king brought out the vessels of Yahweh’s house, which Nebuchadnezzar had brought out of Jerusalem, and had put in the house of his gods; 8 even those, Cyrus king of Persia brought out by the hand of Mithredath the treasurer, and counted them out to Sheshbazzar, the prince of Judah. 9 This is the number of them: thirty platters of gold, one thousand platters of silver, twenty-nine knives, 10 thirty bowls of gold, four hundred ten silver bowls of a second sort, and one thousand other vessels. 11 All the vessels of gold and of silver were five thousand four hundred. Sheshbazzar brought all these up when the captives were brought up from Babylon to Jerusalem.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Ezra 3

1 When the seventh month had come, and the children of Israel were in the cities, the people gathered themselves together as one man to Jerusalem. 2 Then Jeshua the son of Jozadak stood up with his brothers the priests, and Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel and his brothers, and built the altar of the God of Israel, to offer burnt offerings on it, as it is written in the law of Moses the man of God. 3 In spite of their fear because of the peoples of the surrounding lands, they set the altar on its base; and they offered burnt offerings on it to Yahweh, even burnt offerings morning and evening. 4 They kept the feast of tents, as it is written, and offered the daily burnt offerings by number, according to the ordinance, as the duty of every day required; 5 and afterward the continual burnt offering, the offerings of the new moons, of all the set feasts of Yahweh that were consecrated, and of everyone who willingly offered a freewill offering to Yahweh. 6 From the first day of the seventh month, they began to offer burnt offerings to Yahweh; but the foundation of Yahweh’s temple was not yet laid. 7 They also gave money to the masons, and to the carpenters. They also gave food, drink, and oil to the people of Sidon and Tyre, to bring cedar trees from Lebanon to the sea, to Joppa, according to the grant that they had from Cyrus King of Persia.

8 Now in the second year of their coming to God’s house at Jerusalem, in the second month, Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak, and the rest of their brothers the priests and the Levites, and all those who had come out of the captivity to Jerusalem, began the work and appointed the Levites, from twenty years old and upward, to have the oversight of the work of Yahweh’s house. 9 Then Jeshua stood with his sons and his brothers, Kadmiel and his sons, the sons of Judah, together, to have the oversight of the workmen in God’s house: the sons of Henadad, with their sons and their brothers the Levites. 10 When the builders laid the foundation of Yahweh’s temple, they set the priests in their clothing with trumpets, with the Levites the sons of Asaph with cymbals, to praise Yahweh, according to the directions of David king of Israel. 11 They sang to one another in praising and giving thanks to Yahweh, “For he is good, for his loving kindness endures forever toward Israel.” All the people shouted with a great shout, when they praised Yahweh, because the foundation of Yahweh’s house had been laid.

12 But many of the priests and Levites and heads of fathers’ households, the old men who had seen the first house, when the foundation of this house was laid before their eyes, wept with a loud voice. Many also shouted aloud for joy, 13 so that the people could not discern the noise of the shout of joy from the noise of the weeping of the people; for the people shouted with a loud shout, and the noise was heard far away.

Ezra 4

1 Now when the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin heard that the children of the captivity were building a temple to Yahweh, the God of Israel; 2 they came near to Zerubbabel, and to the heads of fathers’ households, and said to them, “Let us build with you; for we seek your God, as you do; and we have been sacrificing to him since the days of Esar Haddon king of Assyria, who brought us up here.”

3 But Zerubbabel, and Jeshua, and the rest of the heads of fathers’ households of Israel, said to them, “You have nothing to do with us in building a house to our God; but we ourselves together will build to Yahweh, the God of Israel, as king Cyrus the king of Persia has commanded us.”

4 Then the people of the land weakened the hands of the people of Judah, and troubled them in building. 5 They hired counselors against them, to frustrate their purpose, all the days of Cyrus king of Persia, even until the reign of Darius king of Persia. 6 In the reign of Ahasuerus, in the beginning of his reign, wrote they an accusation against the inhabitants of Judah and Jerusalem.

7 In the days of Artaxerxes, Bishlam, Mithredath, Tabeel, and the rest of his companions, wrote to Artaxerxes king of Persia; and the writing of the letter was written in Syrian, and delivered in the Syrian language. 8 Rehum the chancellor and Shimshai the scribe wrote a letter against Jerusalem to Artaxerxes the king as follows, 9 then Rehum the chancellor, Shimshai the scribe, and the rest of their companions, the Dinaites, and the Apharsathchites, the Tarpelites, the Apharsites, the Archevites, the Babylonians, the Shushanchites, the Dehaites, the Elamites, 10 and the rest of the nations whom the great and noble Osnappar brought over, and set in the city of Samaria, and in the rest of the country beyond the River, and so forth, wrote.

11 This is the copy of the letter that they sent:

To King Artaxerxes,

From your servants the men beyond the River.

12 Be it known to the king that the Jews who came up from you have come to us to Jerusalem. They are building the rebellious and bad city, and have finished the walls, and repaired the foundations. 13 Be it known now to the king that if this city is built and the walls finished, they will not pay tribute, custom, or toll, and in the end it will be hurtful to the kings. 14 Now because we eat the salt of the palace, and it is not appropriate for us to see the king’s dishonor, therefore we have sent and informed the king, 15 that search may be made in the book of the records of your fathers. You will see in the book of the records, and know that this city is a rebellious city, and hurtful to kings and provinces, and that they have started rebellions within it in the past. That is why this city was destroyed. 16 We inform the king that, if this city is built and the walls finished, then you will have no possession beyond the River.

17 Then the king sent an answer to Rehum the chancellor, and to Shimshai the scribe, and to the rest of their companions who live in Samaria, and in the rest of the country beyond the River:

Peace.

18 The letter which you sent to us has been plainly read before me. 19 I decreed, and search has been made, and it was found that this city has made insurrection against kings in the past, and that rebellion and revolts have been made in it. 20 There have also been mighty kings over Jerusalem, who have ruled over all the country beyond the River; and tribute, custom, and toll, was paid to them. 21 Make a decree now to cause these men to cease, and that this city not be built, until a decree is made by me. 22 Be careful that you not be slack doing so. Why should damage grow to the hurt of the kings?

23 Then when the copy of king Artaxerxes’ letter was read before Rehum, Shimshai the scribe, and their companions, they went in haste to Jerusalem to the Jews, and made them to cease by force of arms. 24 Then work stopped on God’s house which is at Jerusalem. It stopped until the second year of the reign of Darius king of Persia.

Ezra 5

1 Now the prophets, Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo, prophesied to the Jews who were in Judah and Jerusalem. They prophesied to them in the name of the God of Israel. 2 Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Jeshua the son of Jozadak rose up and began to build God’s house which is at Jerusalem; and with them were the prophets of God, helping them. 3 At the same time Tattenai, the governor beyond the River came to them, with Shetharbozenai, and their companions, and asked them, “Who gave you a decree to build this house, and to finish this wall?” 4 They also asked for the names of the men were who were making this building. 5 But the eye of their God was on the elders of the Jews, and they did not make them cease, until the matter should come to Darius, and an answer should be returned by letter concerning it.

6 The copy of the letter that Tattenai, the governor beyond the River, and Shetharbozenai, and his companions the Apharsachites, who were beyond the River, sent to Darius the king follows. 7 They sent a letter to him, in which was written:

To Darius the king, all peace.

8 Be it known to the king that we went into the province of Judah, to the house of the great God, which is built with great stones, and timber is laid in the walls. This work goes on with diligence and prospers in their hands. 9 Then we asked those elders, and said to them thus, “Who gave you a decree to build this house, and to finish this wall?” 10 We asked them their names also, to inform you that we might write the names of the men who were at their head. 11 Thus they returned us answer, saying, “We are the servants of the God of heaven and earth, and are building the house that was built these many years ago, which a great king of Israel built and finished. 12 But after that our fathers had provoked the God of heaven to wrath, he gave them into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, the Chaldean, who destroyed this house, and carried the people away into Babylon. 13 But in the first year of Cyrus king of Babylon, Cyrus the king made a decree to build this house of God. 14 The gold and silver vessels of God’s house, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple that was in Jerusalem, and brought into the temple of Babylon, those Cyrus the king also took out of the temple of Babylon, and they were delivered to one whose name was Sheshbazzar, whom he had made governor. 15 He said to him, ‘Take these vessels, go, put them in the temple that is in Jerusalem, and let God’s house be built in its place.’ 16 Then the same Sheshbazzar came and laid the foundations of God’s house which is in Jerusalem. Since that time even until now has it been in building, and yet it is not completed.

17 Now therefore, if it seems good to the king, let a search be made in the king’s treasure house, which is there at Babylon, whether it is so, that a decree was made of Cyrus the king to build this house of God at Jerusalem; and let the king send his pleasure to us concerning this matter.”

Ezra 6

1 Then Darius the king made a decree, and the house of the archives, where the treasures were laid up in Babylon, was searched. 2 A scroll was found at Achmetha, in the palace that is in the province of Media, and in it this was written for a record:

3 In the first year of Cyrus the king, Cyrus the king made a decree: Concerning God’s house at Jerusalem, let the house be built, the place where they offer sacrifices, and let its foundations be strongly laid; with its height sixty cubits,[*] and its width sixty cubits; 4 with three courses of great stones and a course of new timber. Let the expenses be given out of the king’s house. 5 Also let the gold and silver vessels of God’s house, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the temple which is at Jerusalem, and brought to Babylon, be restored and brought again to the temple which is at Jerusalem, everything to its place. You shall put them in God’s house.

6 Now therefore, Tattenai, governor beyond the River, Shetharbozenai, and your companions the Apharsachites, who are beyond the River, you must stay far from there. 7 Leave the work of this house of God alone; let the governor of the Jews and the elders of the Jews build this house of God in its place. 8 Moreover I make a decree what you shall do for these elders of the Jews for the building of this house of God: that of the king’s goods, even of the tribute beyond the River, expenses must be given with all diligence to these men, that they not be hindered. 9 That which they have need of, including young bulls, rams, and lambs, for burnt offerings to the God of heaven; also wheat, salt, wine, and oil, according to the word of the priests who are at Jerusalem, let it be given them day by day without fail; 10 that they may offer sacrifices of pleasant aroma to the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the king, and of his sons. 11 I have also made a decree that whoever alters this message, let a beam be pulled out from his house, and let him be lifted up and fastened on it; and let his house be made a dunghill for this. 12 May the God who has caused his name to dwell there overthrow all kings and peoples who stretch out their hand to alter the same, to destroy this house of God which is at Jerusalem. I Darius have made a decree. Let it be done with all diligence.

13 Then Tattenai, the governor beyond the River, Shetharbozenai, and their companions did accordingly with all diligence, because Darius the king had sent a decree.

14 The elders of the Jews built and prospered, through the prophesying of Haggai the prophet and Zechariah the son of Iddo. They built and finished it, according to the commandment of the God of Israel, and according to the decree of Cyrus, Darius, and Artaxerxes king of Persia. 15 This house was finished on the third day of the month Adar, which was in the sixth year of the reign of Darius the king.

16 The children of Israel, the priests, the Levites, and the rest of the children of the captivity, kept the dedication of this house of God with joy. 17 They offered at the dedication of this house of God one hundred bulls, two hundred rams, four hundred lambs; and for a sin offering for all Israel, twelve male goats, according to the number of the tribes of Israel. 18 They set the priests in their divisions, and the Levites in their courses, for the service of God, which is at Jerusalem, as it is written in the book of Moses.

19 The children of the captivity kept the Passover on the fourteenth day of the first month. 20 Because the priests and the Levites had purified themselves together, all of them were pure. They killed the Passover for all the children of the captivity, for their brothers the priests, and for themselves. 21 The children of Israel who had returned out of the captivity, and all who had separated themselves to them from the filthiness of the nations of the land, to seek Yahweh, the God of Israel, ate, 22 and kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with joy; because Yahweh had made them joyful, and had turned the heart of the king of Assyria to them, to strengthen their hands in the work of God, the God of Israel’s house.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Ezra 7

1 Now after these things, in the reign of Artaxerxes king of Persia, Ezra the son of Seraiah, the son of Azariah, the son of Hilkiah, 2 the son of Shallum, the son of Zadok, the son of Ahitub, 3 the son of Amariah, the son of Azariah, the son of Meraioth, 4 the son of Zerahiah, the son of Uzzi, the son of Bukki, 5 the son of Abishua, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron the chief priest— 6 this Ezra went up from Babylon. He was a skilled scribe in the law of Moses, which Yahweh, the God of Israel, had given; and the king granted him all his request, according to Yahweh his God’s hand on him. 7 Some of the children of Israel, including some of the priests, the Levites, the singers, the porters, and the temple servants went up to Jerusalem in the seventh year of Artaxerxes the king. 8 He came to Jerusalem in the fifth month, which was in the seventh year of the king. 9 For on the first day of the first month he began to go up from Babylon; and on the first day of the fifth month he came to Jerusalem, according to the good hand of his God on him. 10 For Ezra had set his heart to seek Yahweh’s law, and to do it, and to teach statutes and ordinances in Israel.

11 Now this is the copy of the letter that the king Artaxerxes gave to Ezra the priest, the scribe, even the scribe of the words of Yahweh’s commandments, and of his statutes to Israel:

12 Artaxerxes, king of kings,

To Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the perfect God of heaven.

Now 13 I make a decree, that all those of the people of Israel, and their priests and the Levites, in my realm, who intend of their own free will to go to Jerusalem, go with you. 14 Because you are sent by the king and his seven counselors, to inquire concerning Judah and Jerusalem, according to the law of your God which is in your hand, 15 and to carry the silver and gold, which the king and his counselors have freely offered to the God of Israel, whose habitation is in Jerusalem, 16 and all the silver and gold that you will find in all the province of Babylon, with the freewill offering of the people, and of the priests, offering willingly for the house of their God which is in Jerusalem; 17 therefore you shall with all diligence buy with this money bulls, rams, lambs, with their meal offerings and their drink offerings, and shall offer them on the altar of the house of your God which is in Jerusalem. 18 Whatever seems good to you and to your brothers to do with the rest of the silver and the gold, do that according to the will of your God. 19 The vessels that are given to you for the service of the house of your God, deliver before the God of Jerusalem. 20 Whatever more will be needed for the house of your God, which you may have occasion to give, give it out of the king’s treasure house.

21 I, even I Artaxerxes the king, make a decree to all the treasurers who are beyond the River, that whatever Ezra the priest, the scribe of the law of the God of heaven, requires of you, it shall be done with all diligence, 22 up to one hundred talents[*] of silver, and to one hundred cors[*] of wheat, and to one hundred baths[*] of wine, and to one hundred baths of oil, and salt without prescribing how much. 23 Whatever is commanded by the God of heaven, let it be done exactly for the house of the God of heaven; for why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons?

24 Also we inform you that it shall not be lawful to impose tribute, custom, or toll, on any of the priests, Levites, singers, porters, temple servants, or laborers of this house of God.

25 You, Ezra, according to the wisdom of your God that is in your hand, appoint magistrates and judges, who may judge all the people who are beyond the River, who all know the laws of your God; and teach him who doesn’t know them. 26 Whoever will not do the law of your God and the law of the king, let judgment be executed on him with all diligence, whether it is to death, or to banishment, or to confiscation of goods, or to imprisonment.

27 Blessed be Yahweh, the God of our fathers, who has put such a thing as this in the king’s heart, to beautify Yahweh’s house which is in Jerusalem; 28 and has extended loving kindness to me before the king and his counselors, and before all the king’s mighty princes. I was strengthened according to Yahweh my God’s hand on me, and I gathered together chief men out of Israel to go up with me.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

1 cor is the same as a homer, or about 55.9 U. S. gallons (liquid) or 211 liters or 6 bushels.

1 bath is one tenth of a cor, or about 5.6 U. S. gallons or 21 liters or 2.4 pecks 100 baths would be about 2,100 liters.

Ezra 8

1 Now these are the heads of their fathers’ households, and this is the genealogy of those who went up with me from Babylon, in the reign of Artaxerxes the king:

2 Of the sons of Phinehas, Gershom.

Of the sons of Ithamar, Daniel.

Of the sons of David, Hattush.

3 Of the sons of Shecaniah, of the sons of Parosh, Zechariah; and with him were listed by genealogy of the males one hundred fifty.

4 Of the sons of Pahathmoab, Eliehoenai the son of Zerahiah; and with him two hundred males.

5 Of the sons of Shecaniah, the son of Jahaziel; and with him three hundred males.

6 Of the sons of Adin, Ebed the son of Jonathan; and with him fifty males.

7 Of the sons of Elam, Jeshaiah the son of Athaliah; and with him seventy males.

8 Of the sons of Shephatiah, Zebadiah the son of Michael; and with him eighty males.

9 Of the sons of Joab, Obadiah the son of Jehiel; and with him two hundred eighteen males.

10 Of the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah; and with him one hundred sixty males.

11 Of the sons of Bebai, Zechariah the son of Bebai; and with him twenty-eight males.

12 Of the sons of Azgad, Johanan the son of Hakkatan; and with him one hundred ten males.

13 Of the sons of Adonikam, who were the last; and these are their names: Eliphelet, Jeuel, and Shemaiah; and with them sixty males.

14 Of the sons of Bigvai, Uthai and Zabbud; and with them seventy males.

15 I gathered them together to the river that runs to Ahava; and there we encamped three days: and I looked around at the people the priests, and found there were none of the sons of Levi. 16 Then sent I for Eliezer, for Ariel, for Shemaiah, for Elnathan, for Jarib, for Elnathan, for Nathan, for Zechariah, and for Meshullam, chief men; also for Joiarib and for Elnathan, who were teachers. 17 I sent them out to Iddo the chief at the place Casiphia; and I told them what they should tell Iddo, and his brothers the temple servants, at the place Casiphia, that they should bring to us ministers for the house of our God. 18 According to the good hand of our God on us they brought us a man of discretion, of the sons of Mahli, the son of Levi, the son of Israel; and Sherebiah, with his sons and his brothers, eighteen; 19 and Hashabiah, and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari, his brothers and their sons, twenty; 20 and of the temple servants, whom David and the princes had given for the service of the Levites, two hundred twenty temple servants. All of them were mentioned by name.

21 Then I proclaimed a fast there, at the river Ahava, that we might humble ourselves before our God, to seek from him a straight way for us, and for our little ones, and for all our possessions. 22 For I was ashamed to ask of the king a band of soldiers and horsemen to help us against the enemy on the way, because we had spoken to the king, saying, “The hand of our God is on all those who seek him, for good; but his power and his wrath is against all those who forsake him.” 23 So we fasted and begged our God for this: and he granted our request.

24 Then I set apart twelve of the chiefs of the priests, even Sherebiah, Hashabiah, and ten of their brothers with them, 25 and weighed to them the silver, the gold, and the vessels, even the offering for the house of our God, which the king, his counselors, his princes, and all Israel there present, had offered. 26 I weighed into their hand six hundred fifty talents of silver,[*] one hundred talents of silver vessels; one hundred talents of gold, 27 twenty bowls of gold weighing one thousand darics;[*] and two vessels of fine bright brass, precious as gold. 28 I said to them, “You are holy to Yahweh, and the vessels are holy. The silver and the gold are a freewill offering to Yahweh, the God of your fathers. 29 Watch and keep them, until you weigh them before the chiefs of the priests and the Levites, and the princes of the fathers’ households of Israel, at Jerusalem, in the rooms of Yahweh’s house.”

30 So the priests and the Levites received the weight of the silver and the gold, and the vessels, to bring them to Jerusalem to the house of our God. 31 Then we departed from the river Ahava on the twelfth day of the first month, to go to Jerusalem. The hand of our God was on us, and he delivered us from the hand of the enemy and the bandit by the way. 32 We came to Jerusalem, and stayed there three days. 33 On the fourth day the silver and the gold and the vessels were weighed in the house of our God into the hand of Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest; and with him was Eleazar the son of Phinehas; and with them was Jozabad the son of Jeshua, and Noadiah the son of Binnui, the Levite; 34 everything by number and by weight; and all the weight was written at that time.

35 The children of the captivity, who had come out of exile, offered burnt offerings to the God of Israel, twelve bulls for all Israel, ninety-six rams, seventy-seven lambs, and twelve male goats for a sin offering. All this was a burnt offering to Yahweh. 36 They delivered the king’s commissions to the king’s satraps, and to the governors beyond the River. So they supported the people and God’s house.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

a daric was a gold coin issued by a Persian king, weighing about 8.4 grams or about 0.27 troy ounces each.

Ezra 9

1 Now when these things were done, the princes came near to me, saying, “The people of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, have not separated themselves from the peoples of the lands, following their abominations, even those of the Canaanites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Jebusites, the Ammonites, the Moabites, the Egyptians, and the Amorites. 2 For they have taken of their daughters for themselves and for their sons, so that the holy offspring[*] have mixed themselves with the peoples of the lands. Yes, the hand of the princes and rulers has been chief in this trespass.”

3 When I heard this thing, I tore my garment and my robe, and pulled the hair out of my head and of my beard, and sat down confounded. 4 Then everyone who trembled at the words of the God of Israel were assembled to me, because of their trespass of the captivity; and I sat confounded until the evening offering.

5 At the evening offering I arose up from my humiliation, even with my garment and my robe torn; and I fell on my knees, and spread out my hands to Yahweh my God; 6 and I said, “My God, I am ashamed and blush to lift up my face to you, my God; for our iniquities have increased over our head, and our guiltiness has grown up to the heavens. 7 Since the days of our fathers we have been exceeding guilty to this day; and for our iniquities we, our kings, and our priests, have been delivered into the hand of the kings of the lands, to the sword, to captivity, to plunder, and to confusion of face, as it is this day. 8 Now for a little moment grace has been shown from Yahweh our God, to leave us a remnant to escape, and to give us a nail in his holy place, that our God may lighten our eyes, and revived us a little in our bondage. 9 For we are bondservants; yet our God has not forsaken us in our bondage, but has extended loving kindness to us in the sight of the kings of Persia, to revive us, to set up the house of our God, and to repair its ruins, and to give us a wall in Judah and in Jerusalem.

10 “Now, our God, what shall we say after this? For we have forsaken your commandments, 11 which you have commanded by your servants the prophets, saying, ‘The land, to which you go to possess it, is an unclean land through the uncleanness of the peoples of the lands, through their abominations, which have filled it from one end to another with their filthiness. 12 Now therefore don’t give your daughters to their sons. Don’t take their daughters to your sons, nor seek their peace or their prosperity forever; that you may be strong, and eat the good of the land, and leave it for an inheritance to your children forever.’

13 “After all that has come on us for our evil deeds, and for our great guilt, since you, our God, have punished us less than our iniquities deserve, and have given us such a remnant, 14 shall we again break your commandments, and join in affinity with the peoples that do these abominations? Wouldn’t you be angry with us until you had consumed us, so that there would be no remnant, nor any to escape? 15 Yahweh, the God of Israel, you are righteous; for we are left a remnant that has escaped, as it is today. Behold,[*] we are before you in our guiltiness; for no one can stand before you because of this.”

or, seed

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Ezra 10

1 Now while Ezra prayed and made confession, weeping and casting himself down before God’s house, there was gathered together to him out of Israel a very great assembly of men and women and children; for the people wept very bitterly. 2 Shecaniah the son of Jehiel, one of the sons of Elam, answered Ezra, “We have trespassed against our God, and have married foreign women of the peoples of the land. Yet now there is hope for Israel concerning this thing. 3 Now therefore let us make a covenant with our God to put away all the wives, and those who as are born of them, according to the counsel of my lord, and of those who tremble at the commandment of our God. Let it be done according to the law. 4 Arise; for the matter belongs to you, and we are with you. Be courageous, and do it.”

5 Then Ezra arose, and made the chiefs of the priests, the Levites, and all Israel, to swear that they would do according to this word. So they swore. 6 Then Ezra rose up from before God’s house, and went into the room of Jehohanan the son of Eliashib. When he came there, he ate no bread, nor drank water; for he mourned because of their trespass of the captivity. 7 They made a proclamation throughout Judah and Jerusalem to all the children of the captivity, that they should gather themselves together to Jerusalem; 8 and that whoever didn’t come within three days, according to the counsel of the princes and the elders, all his possessions should be forfeited, and himself separated from the assembly of the captivity.

9 Then all the men of Judah and Benjamin gathered themselves together to Jerusalem within the three days. It was the ninth month, on the twentieth day of the month; and all the people sat in the wide place in front of God’s house, trembling because of this matter, and because of the great rain.

10 Ezra the priest stood up and said to them, “You have trespassed, and have married foreign women, to increase the guilt of Israel. 11 Now therefore make confession to Yahweh, the God of your fathers, and do his pleasure; and separate yourselves from the peoples of the land, and from the foreign women.”

12 Then all the assembly answered with a loud voice, “As you have said concerning us, so must we do. 13 But the people are many, and it is a time of much rain, and we are not able to stand outside. This is not a work of one day or two, for we have greatly transgressed in this matter. 14 Now let our princes be appointed for all the assembly, and let all those who are in our cities who have married foreign women come at appointed times, and with them the elders of every city, and its judges, until the fierce wrath of our God is turned from us, until this matter is resolved.”

15 Only Jonathan the son of Asahel and Jahzeiah the son of Tikvah stood up against this; and Meshullam and Shabbethai the Levite helped them.

16 The children of the captivity did so. Ezra the priest, with certain heads of fathers’ households, after their fathers’ houses, and all of them by their names, were set apart; and they sat down in the first day of the tenth month to examine the matter. 17 They finished with all the men who had married foreign women by the first day of the first month.

18 Among the sons of the priests there were found who had married foreign women:

of the sons of Jeshua, the son of Jozadak, and his brothers, Maaseiah, and Eliezer, and Jarib, and Gedaliah. 19 They gave their hand that they would put away their wives; and being guilty, they offered a ram of the flock for their guilt.

20 Of the sons of Immer: Hanani and Zebadiah.

21 Of the sons of Harim: Maaseiah, and Elijah, and Shemaiah, and Jehiel, and Uzziah.

22 Of the sons of Pashhur: Elioenai, Maaseiah, Ishmael, Nethanel, Jozabad, and Elasah.

23 Of the Levites: Jozabad, and Shimei, and Kelaiah (also called Kelita), Pethahiah, Judah, and Eliezer.

24 Of the singers: Eliashib. Of the porters: Shallum, and Telem, and Uri.

25 Of Israel: Of the sons of Parosh: Ramiah, and Izziah, and Malchijah, and Mijamin, and Eleazar, and Malchijah, and Benaiah.

26 Of the sons of Elam: Mattaniah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, and Abdi, and Jeremoth, and Elijah.

27 Of the sons of Zattu: Elioenai, Eliashib, Mattaniah, and Jeremoth, and Zabad, and Aziza.

28 Of the sons of Bebai: Jehohanan, Hananiah, Zabbai, Athlai.

29 Of the sons of Bani: Meshullam, Malluch, and Adaiah, Jashub, and Sheal, Jeremoth.

30 Of the sons of Pahathmoab: Adna, and Chelal, Benaiah, Maaseiah, Mattaniah, Bezalel, and Binnui, and Manasseh.

31 Of the sons of Harim: Eliezer, Isshijah, Malchijah, Shemaiah, Shimeon, 32 Benjamin, Malluch, Shemariah.

33 Of the sons of Hashum: Mattenai, Mattattah, Zabad, Eliphelet, Jeremai, Manasseh, Shimei.

34 Of the sons of Bani: Maadai, Amram, and Uel, 35 Benaiah, Bedeiah, Cheluhi, 36 Vaniah, Meremoth, Eliashib, 37 Mattaniah, Mattenai, and Jaasu, 38 and Bani, and Binnui, Shimei, 39 and Shelemiah, and Nathan, and Adaiah, 40 Machnadebai, Shashai, Sharai, 41 Azarel, and Shelemiah, Shemariah, 42 Shallum, Amariah, Joseph.

43 Of the sons of Nebo: Jeiel, Mattithiah, Zabad, Zebina, Iddo, and Joel, Benaiah.

44 All these had taken foreign wives; and some of them had wives by whom they had children.

Nehemiah 1

1 The words of Nehemiah the son of Hacaliah.

Now in the month Chislev, in the twentieth year, as I was in Shushan the palace, 2 Hanani, one of my brothers, came, he and certain men out of Judah; and I asked them about the Jews who had escaped, who were left of the captivity, and concerning Jerusalem. 3 They said to me, “The remnant who are left of the captivity there in the province are in great affliction and reproach. The wall of Jerusalem is also broken down, and its gates are burned with fire.”

4 When I heard these words, I sat down and wept, and mourned several days; and I fasted and prayed before the God[*] of heaven, 5 and said, “I beg you, Yahweh,[*] the God of heaven, the great and awesome God, who keeps covenant and loving kindness with those who love him and keep his commandments: 6 Let your ear now be attentive, and your eyes open, that you may listen to the prayer of your servant, which I pray before you at this time, day and night, for the children of Israel your servants, while I confess the sins of the children of Israel, which we have sinned against you. Yes, I and my father’s house have sinned. 7 We have dealt very corruptly against you, and have not kept the commandments, nor the statutes, nor the ordinances, which you commanded your servant Moses.

8 “Remember, I beg you, the word that you commanded your servant Moses, saying, ‘If you trespass, I will scatter you among the peoples; 9 but if you return to me, and keep my commandments and do them, though your outcasts were in the uttermost part of the heavens, yet I will gather them from there, and will bring them to the place that I have chosen, to cause my name to dwell there.’

10 “Now these are your servants and your people, whom you have redeemed by your great power, and by your strong hand. 11 Lord,[*] I beg you, let your ear be attentive now to the prayer of your servant, and to the prayer of your servants, who delight to fear your name; and please prosper your servant today, and grant him mercy in the sight of this man.”

Now I was cup bearer to the king.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Nehemiah 2

1 In the month Nisan, in the twentieth year of Artaxerxes the king, when wine was before him, I picked up the wine, and gave it to the king. Now I had not been sad before in his presence. 2 The king said to me, “Why is your face sad, since you are not sick? This is nothing else but sorrow of heart.”

Then I was very much afraid. 3 I said to the king, “Let the king live forever! Why shouldn’t my face be sad, when the city, the place of my fathers’ tombs, lies waste, and its gates have been consumed with fire?”

4 Then the king said to me, “What is your request?”

So I prayed to the God of heaven. 5 I said to the king, “If it pleases the king, and if your servant has found favor in your sight, that you would send me to Judah, to the city of my fathers’ tombs, that I may build it.”

6 The king said to me (the queen was also sitting by him), “How long will your journey be? When will you return?”

So it pleased the king to send me, and I set a time for he. 7 Moreover I said to the king, “If it pleases the king, let letters be given me to the governors beyond the River, that they may let me pass through until I come to Judah; 8 and a letter to Asaph the keeper of the king’s forest, that he may give me timber to make beams for the gates of the citadel by the temple, for the wall of the city, and for the house that I will occupy.”

The king granted my requests, because of the good hand of my God on me. 9 Then I came to the governors beyond the River, and gave them the king’s letters. Now the king had sent captains of the army and horsemen with me. 10 When Sanballat the Horonite, and Tobiah the servant, the Ammonite, heard of it, it grieved them exceedingly, because a man had come to seek the welfare of the children of Israel. 11 So I came to Jerusalem, and was there three days. 12 I arose in the night, I and a few men with me. I didn’t tell anyone what my God put into my heart to do for Jerusalem. There wasn’t any animal with me, except the animal that I rode on. 13 I went out by night by the valley gate, even toward the jackal’s well, then to the dung gate, and inspected the walls of Jerusalem, which were broken down, and its gates were consumed with fire. 14 Then I went on to the spring gate and to the king’s pool, but there was no place for the animal that was under me to pass. 15 Then went I up in the night by the brook, and inspected the wall; and I turned back, and entered by the valley gate, and so returned. 16 The rulers didn’t know where I went, or what I did. I had not as yet told it to the Jews, nor to the priests, nor to the nobles, nor to the rulers, nor to the rest who did the work.

17 Then I said to them, “You see the bad situation that we are in, how Jerusalem lies waste, and its gates are burned with fire. Come, let us build up the wall of Jerusalem, that we won’t be disgraced.” 18 I told them of the hand of my God which was good on me, as also of the king’s words that he had spoken to me.

They said, “Let’s rise up and build.” So they strengthened their hands for the good work.

19 But when Sanballat the Horonite, Tobiah the Ammontite servant, and Geshem the Arabian, heard it, they ridiculed us, and despised us, and said, “What is this thing that you are doing? Will you rebel against the king?”

20 Then I answered them, and said to them, “The God of heaven will prosper us. Therefore we, his servants, will arise and build; but you have no portion, nor right, nor memorial, in Jerusalem.”

Nehemiah 3

1 Then Eliashib the high priest rose up with his brothers the priests, and they built the sheep gate. They sanctified it, and set up its doors. They sanctified it even to the tower of Hammeah, to the tower of Hananel. 2 Next to him the men of Jericho built. Next to them Zaccur the son of Imri built.

3 The sons of Hassenaah built the fish gate. They laid its beams, and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars. 4 Next to them, Meremoth the son of Uriah, the son of Hakkoz made repairs. Next to them, Meshullam the son of Berechiah, the son of Meshezabel made repairs. Next to them, Zadok the son of Baana made repairs. 5 Next to them, the Tekoites made repairs; but their nobles didn’t put their necks to the Lord’s work.

6 Joiada the son of Paseah and Meshullam the son of Besodeiah repaired the old gate. They laid its beams, and set up its doors, and its bolts, and its bars. 7 Next to them, Melatiah the Gibeonite, and Jadon the Meronothite, the men of Gibeon and of Mizpah, repaired the residence of the governor beyond the River. 8 Next to him, Uzziel the son of Harhaiah, goldsmiths, made repairs. Next to him, Hananiah, one of the perfumers, made repairs, and they fortified Jerusalem even to the wide wall. 9 Next to them, Rephaiah the son of Hur, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem, made repairs. 10 Next to them, Jedaiah the son of Harumaph made repairs across from his house. Next to him, Hattush the son of Hashabneiah made repairs. 11 Malchijah the son of Harim, and Hasshub the son of Pahathmoab, repaired another portion, and the tower of the furnaces. 12 Next to him, Shallum the son of Hallohesh, the ruler of half the district of Jerusalem, he and his daughters, made repairs.

13 Hanun and the inhabitants of Zanoah repaired the valley gate. They built it, and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars, and one thousand cubits[*] of the wall to the dung gate.

14 Malchijah the son of Rechab, the ruler of the district of Beth Haccherem repaired the dung gate. He built it, and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars.

15 Shallun the son of Colhozeh, the ruler of the district of Mizpah repaired the spring gate. He built it, and covered it, and set up its doors, its bolts, and its bars, and the wall of the pool of Shelah by the king’s garden, even to the stairs that go down from David’s city. 16 After him, Nehemiah the son of Azbuk, the ruler of half the district of Beth Zur, made repairs to the place opposite the tombs of David, and to the pool that was made, and to the house of the mighty men. 17 After him, the Levites, Rehum the son of Bani made repairs. Next to him, Hashabiah, the ruler of half the district of Keilah, made repairs for his district. 18 After him, their brothers, Bavvai the son of Henadad, the ruler of half the district of Keilah made repairs. 19 Next to him, Ezer the son of Jeshua, the ruler of Mizpah, repaired another portion, across from the ascent to the armory at the turning of the wall. 20 After him, Baruch the son of Zabbai earnestly repaired another portion, from the turning of the wall to the door of the house of Eliashib the high priest. 21 After him, Meremoth the son of Uriah the son of Hakkoz repaired another portion, from the door of the house of Eliashib even to the end of the house of Eliashib. 22 After him, the priests, the men of the Plain made repairs. 23 After them, Benjamin and Hasshub made repairs across from their house. After them, Azariah the son of Maaseiah the son of Ananiah made repairs beside his own house. 24 After him, Binnui the son of Henadad repaired another portion, from the house of Azariah to the turning of the wall, and to the corner. 25 Palal the son of Uzai made repairs opposite the turning of the wall, and the tower that stands out from the upper house of the king, which is by the court of the guard. After him Pedaiah the son of Parosh made repairs. 26 (Now the temple servants lived in Ophel, to the place over against the water gate toward the east, and the tower that stands out.) 27 After him the Tekoites repaired another portion, over against the great tower that stands out, and to the wall of Ophel.

28 Above the horse gate, the priests made repairs, everyone across from his own house. 29 After them, Zadok the son of Immer made repairs across from his own house. After him, Shemaiah the son of Shecaniah, the keeper of the east gate made repairs. 30 After him, Hananiah the son of Shelemiah, and Hanun the sixth son of Zalaph, repaired another portion. After him, Meshullam the son of Berechiah made repairs across from his room. 31 After him, Malchijah, one of the goldsmiths to the house of the temple servants, and of the merchants, made repairs opposite the gate of Hammiphkad, and to the ascent of the corner. 32 Between the ascent of the corner and the sheep gate, the goldsmiths and the merchants made repairs.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Nehemiah 4

1 But when Sanballat heard that we were building the wall, he was angry, and was very indignant, and mocked the Jews. 2 He spoke before his brothers and the army of Samaria, and said, “What are these feeble Jews doing? Will they fortify themselves? Will they sacrifice? Will they finish in a day? Will they revive the stones out of the heaps of rubbish, since they are burned?”

3 Now Tobiah the Ammonite was by him, and he said, “What they are building, if a fox climbed up it, he would break down their stone wall.”

4 “Hear, our God; for we are despised; and turn back their reproach on their own head, give them up for a plunder in a land of captivity; 5 don’t cover their iniquity, and don’t let their sin be blotted out from before you; for they have insulted the builders.”

6 So we built the wall; and all the wall was joined together to half its height: for the people had a mind to work.

7 But when Sanballat, Tobiah, the Arabians, the Ammonites, and the Ashdodites heard that the repairing of the walls of Jerusalem went forward, and that the breaches began to be filled, they were very angry; 8 and they all conspired together to come and fight against Jerusalem, and to cause confusion among us. 9 But we made our prayer to our God, and set a watch against them day and night, because of them. 10 Judah said, “The strength of the bearers of burdens is fading, and there is much rubble; so that we are not able to build the wall.” 11 Our adversaries said, “They will not know or see, until we come in among them and kill them, and cause the work to cease.”

12 When the Jews who lived by them came, they said to us ten times from all places, “Wherever you turn, they will attack us.”

13 Therefore I set guards in the lowest parts of the space behind the wall, in the open places. I set the people by family groups with their swords, their spears, and their bows. 14 I looked, and rose up, and said to the nobles, to the rulers, and to the rest of the people, “Don’t be afraid of them! Remember the Lord, who is great and awesome, and fight for your brothers, your sons, your daughters, your wives, and your houses.”

15 When our enemies heard that it was known to us, and God had brought their counsel to nothing, all of us returned to the wall, everyone to his work. 16 From that time forth, half of my servants did the work, and half of them held the spears, the shields, the bows, and the coats of mail; and the rulers were behind all the house of Judah. 17 Those who built the wall, and those who bore burdens loaded themselves; everyone with one of his hands did the work, and with the other held his weapon. 18 Among the builders, everyone wore his sword at his side, and so built. He who sounded the trumpet was by me. 19 I said to the nobles, and to the rulers and to the rest of the people, “The work is great and large, and we are separated on the wall, one far from one another. 20 Wherever you hear the sound of the trumpet, rally there to us. Our God will fight for us.”

21 So we did the work. Half of the people held the spears from the rising of the morning until the stars appeared. 22 Likewise at the same time said I to the people, “Let everyone with his servant lodge within Jerusalem, that in the night they may be a guard to us, and may labor in the day.” 23 So neither I, nor my brothers, nor my servants, nor the men of the guard who followed me, none of us took off our clothes. Everyone took his weapon to the water.

Nehemiah 5

1 Then there arose a great cry of the people and of their wives against their brothers the Jews. 2 For there were that said, “We, our sons and our daughters, are many. Let us get grain, that we may eat and live.” 3 There were also some that said, “We are mortgaging our fields, and our vineyards, and our houses. Let us get grain, because of the famine.” 4 There were also some who said, “We have borrowed money for the king’s tribute using our fields and our vineyards as collateral. 5 Yet now our flesh is as the flesh of our brothers, our children as their children. Behold,[*] we bring our sons and our daughters into bondage to be servants, and some of our daughters have been brought into bondage. It is also not in our power to help it, because other men have our fields and our vineyards.”

6 I was very angry when I heard their cry and these words. 7 Then I consulted with myself, and contended with the nobles and the rulers, and said to them, “You exact usury, everyone of his brother.” I held a great assembly against them. 8 I said to them, “We, after our ability, have redeemed our brothers the Jews that were sold to the nations; and would you even sell your brothers, and should they be sold to us?” Then they held their peace, and found not a word to say. 9 Also I said, “The thing that you do is not good. Shouldn’t you walk in the fear of our God, because of the reproach of the nations our enemies? 10 I likewise, my brothers and my servants, lend them money and grain. Please let us stop this usury. 11 Please restore to them, even today, their fields, their vineyards, their olive groves, and their houses, also the hundredth part of the money, and of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, that you are charging them.”

12 Then they said, “We will restore them, and will require nothing of them. We will do so, even as you say.”

Then I called the priests, and took an oath of them, that they would do according to this promise. 13 Also I shook out my lap, and said, “So may God shake out every man from his house, and from his labor, that doesn’t perform this promise; even be he shaken out, and emptied like this.”

All the assembly said, “Amen,” and praised Yahweh. The people did according to this promise.

14 Moreover from the time that I was appointed to be their governor in the land of Judah, from the twentieth year even to the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes the king, that is, twelve years, I and my brothers have not eaten the bread of the governor. 15 But the former governors who were before me were supported by the people, and took bread and wine from them, plus forty shekels[*] of silver; yes, even their servants ruled over the people; but I didn’t do so, because of the fear of God. 16 Yes, I also continued in the work of this wall. We didn’t buy any land. All my servants were gathered there to the work. 17 Moreover there were at my table, of the Jews and the rulers, one hundred fifty men, besides those who came to us from among the nations that were around us. 18 Now that which was prepared for one day was one ox and six choice sheep. Also fowls were prepared for me, and once in ten days a store of all sorts of wine. Yet for all this, I didn’t demand the governor’s pay, because the bondage was heavy on this people. 19 Remember to me, my God, for good, all that I have done for this people.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

Nehemiah 6

1 Now when it was reported to Sanballat, Tobiah, and to Geshem the Arabian, and to the rest of our enemies, that I had built the wall, and that there was no breach left in it (though even to that time I had not set up the doors in the gates) 2 Sanballat and Geshem sent to me, saying, “Come, let us meet together in the villages in the plain of Ono.” But they intended to harm me.

3 I sent messengers to them, saying, “I am doing a great work, so that I can’t come down. Why should the work cease, while I leave it, and come down to you?” 4 They sent to me four times like this; and I answered them the same way. 5 Then Sanballat sent his servant to me the same way the fifth time with an open letter in his hand, 6 in which was written, “It is reported among the nations, and Gashmu says it, that you and the Jews intend to rebel. Because of that, you are building the wall. You would be their king, according to these words. 7 You have also appointed prophets to proclaim of you at Jerusalem, saying, ‘There is a king in Judah!’ Now it will be reported to the king according to these words. Come now therefore, and let us take counsel together.”

8 Then I sent to him, saying, “There are no such things done as you say, but you imagine them out of your own heart.” 9 For they all would have made us afraid, saying, “Their hands will be weakened from the work, that it not be done.” But now, strengthen my hands.

10 I went to the house of Shemaiah the son of Delaiah the son of Mehetabel, who was shut in at his home; and he said, “Let us meet together in God’s house, within the temple, and let us shut the doors of the temple; for they will come to kill you. Yes, in the night will they come to kill you.”

11 I said, “Should a man like me flee? Who is there that, being such as I, would go into the temple to save his life? I will not go in.” 12 I discerned, and behold, God had not sent him; but he pronounced this prophecy against me. Tobiah and Sanballat had hired him. 13 He hired so that I would be afraid, do so, and sin, and that they might have material for an evil report, that they might reproach me. 14 “Remember, my God, Tobiah and Sanballat according to these their works, and also the prophetess Noadiah, and the rest of the prophets, that would have put me in fear.”

15 So the wall was finished in the twenty-fifth day of Elul, in fifty-two days. 16 When all our enemies heard of it, all the nations that were around us were afraid, and they lost their confidence; for they perceived that this work was done by our God. 17 Moreover in those days the nobles of Judah sent many letters to Tobiah, and Tobiah’s letters came to them. 18 For there were many in Judah sworn to him, because he was the son-in-law of Shecaniah the son of Arah; and his son Jehohanan had taken the daughter of Meshullam the son of Berechiah as wife. 19 Also they spoke of his good deeds before me, and reported my words to him. Tobiah sent letters to put me in fear.

Nehemiah 7

1 Now when the wall was built, and I had set up the doors, and the porters and the singers and the Levites were appointed, 2 I put my brother Hanani, and Hananiah the governor of the fortress, in charge of Jerusalem; for he was a faithful man, and feared God above many. 3 I said to them, “Don’t let the gates of Jerusalem be opened until the sun is hot; and while they stand guard, let them shut the doors, and you bar them: and appoint watches of the inhabitants of Jerusalem, everyone in his watch, with everyone near his house.”

4 Now the city was wide and large; but the people were few therein, and the houses were not built.

5 My God put into my heart to gather together the nobles, and the rulers, and the people, that they might be listed by genealogy. I found the book of the genealogy of those who came up at the first, and I found this written in it:

6 These are the children of the province, who went up out of the captivity of those who had been carried away, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away, and who returned to Jerusalem and to Judah, everyone to his city; 7 who came with Zerubbabel, Jeshua, Nehemiah, Azariah, Raamiah, Nahamani, Mordecai, Bilshan, Mispereth, Bigvai, Nehum, Baanah.

The number of the men of the people of Israel:

8 The children of Parosh, two thousand one hundred seventy-two.

9 The children of Shephatiah, three hundred seventy-two.

10 The children of Arah, six hundred fifty-two.

11 The children of Pahathmoab, of the children of Jeshua and Joab, two thousand eight hundred eighteen.

12 The children of Elam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.

13 The children of Zattu, eight hundred forty-five.

14 The children of Zaccai, seven hundred sixty.

15 The children of Binnui, six hundred forty-eight.

16 The children of Bebai, six hundred twenty-eight.

17 The children of Azgad, two thousand three hundred twenty-two.

18 The children of Adonikam, six hundred sixty-seven.

19 The children of Bigvai, two thousand sixty-seven.

20 The children of Adin, six hundred fifty-five.

21 The children of Ater, of Hezekiah, ninety-eight.

22 The children of Hashum, three hundred Twenty-eight.

23 The children of Bezai, three hundred twenty-four.

24 The children of Hariph, one hundred twelve.

25 The children of Gibeon, ninety-five.

26 The men of Bethlehem and Netophah, one hundred eighty-eight.

27 The men of Anathoth, one hundred twenty-eight.

28 The men of Beth Azmaveth, forty-two.

29 The men of Kiriath Jearim, Chephirah, and Beeroth, seven hundred forty-three.

30 The men of Ramah and Geba, six hundred twenty-one.

31 The men of Michmas, one hundred twenty-two.

32 The men of Bethel and Ai, one hundred twenty-three.

33 The men of the other Nebo, fifty-two.

34 The children of the other Elam, one thousand two hundred fifty-four.

35 The children of Harim, three hundred twenty.

36 The children of Jericho, three hundred forty-five.

37 The children of Lod, Hadid, and Ono, seven hundred twenty-one.

38 The children of Senaah, three thousand nine hundred thirty.

39 The priests: The children of Jedaiah, of the house of Jeshua, nine hundred seventy-three.

40 The children of Immer, one thousand fifty-two.

41 The children of Pashhur, one thousand two hundred forty-seven.

42 The children of Harim, one thousand seventeen.

43 The Levites: the children of Jeshua, of Kadmiel, of the children of Hodevah, seventy-four.

44 The singers: the children of Asaph, one hundred forty-eight.

45 The porters: the children of Shallum, the children of Ater, the children of Talmon, the children of Akkub, the children of Hatita, the children of Shobai, one hundred thirty-eight.

46 The temple servants: the children of Ziha, the children of Hasupha, the children of Tabbaoth, 47 the children of Keros, the children of Sia, the children of Padon, 48 the children of Lebana, the children of Hagaba, the children of Salmai, 49 the children of Hanan, the children of Giddel, the children of Gahar, 50 the children of Reaiah, the children of Rezin, the children of Nekoda, 51 the children of Gazzam, the children of Uzza, the children of Paseah. 52 The children of Besai, the children of Meunim, the children of Nephushesim, 53 the children of Bakbuk, the children of Hakupha, the children of Harhur, 54 the children of Bazlith, the children of Mehida, the children of Harsha, 55 the children of Barkos, the children of Sisera, the children of Temah, 56 the children of Neziah, the children of Hatipha.

57 The children of Solomon’s servants: the children of Sotai, the children of Sophereth, the children of Perida, 58 the children of Jaala, the children of Darkon, the children of Giddel, 59 the children of Shephatiah, the children of Hattil, the children of Pochereth Hazzebaim, the children of Amon. 60 All the temple servants, and the children of Solomon’s servants, were three hundred ninety-two.

61 These were those who went up from Tel Melah, Tel Harsha, Cherub, Addon, and Immer; but they could not show their fathers’ houses, nor their offspring,[*] whether they were of Israel:

62 The children of Delaiah, the children of Tobiah, the children of Nekoda, six hundred forty-two.

63 Of the priests: the children of Hobaiah, the children of Hakkoz, the children of Barzillai, who took a wife of the daughters of Barzillai the Gileadite, and was called after their name.

64 These searched for their genealogical records, but couldn’t find them. Therefore were they deemed disqualified and removed from the priesthood. 65 The governor told that they should not eat of the most holy things until a priest stood up to minister with Urim and Thummim.

66 The whole assembly together was forty-two thousand three hundred sixty, 67 besides their male servants and their female servants, of whom there were seven thousand three hundred thirty-seven; and they had two hundred forty-five singing men and singing women. 68 Their horses were seven hundred thirty-six; their mules, two hundred forty-five; 69 their camels, four hundred thirty-five; their donkeys, six thousand seven hundred twenty.

70 Some from among the heads of fathers’ households gave to the work. The governor gave to the treasury one thousand darics of gold,[*] fifty basins, and five hundred thirty priests’ garments. 71 Some of the heads of fathers’ households gave into the treasury of the work twenty thousand darics of gold, and two thousand two hundred minas[*] of silver. 72 That which the rest of the people gave was twenty thousand darics of gold, plus two thousand minas of silver, and sixty-seven priests’ garments.

73 So the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, some of the people, the temple servants, and all Israel, lived in their cities.

When the seventh month had come, the children of Israel were in their cities.

or, seed

a daric was a gold coin issued by a Persian king, weighing about 8.4 grams or about 0.27 troy ounces each.

A mina is about 600 grams or 1.3 U. S. pounds, so 2,200 minas is about 1.3 metric tons.

Nehemiah 8

1 All the people gathered themselves together as one man into the wide place that was in front of the water gate; and they spoke to Ezra the scribe to bring the book of the law of Moses, which Yahweh had commanded to Israel. 2 Ezra the priest brought the law before the assembly, both men and women, and all who could hear with understanding, on the first day of the seventh month. 3 He read from it before the wide place that was in front of the water gate from early morning until midday, in the presence of the men and the women, and of those who could understand. The ears of all the people were attentive to the book of the law. 4 Ezra the scribe stood on a pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpose; and beside him stood Mattithiah, Shema, Anaiah, Uriah, Hilkiah, and Maaseiah, on his right hand; and on his left hand, Pedaiah, Mishael, Malchijah, Hashum, Hashbaddanah, Zechariah, and Meshullam. 5 Ezra opened the book in the sight of all the people (for he was above all the people), and when he opened it, all the people stood up. 6 Then Ezra blessed Yahweh, the great God.

All the people answered, “Amen, Amen,” with the lifting up of their hands. They bowed their heads, and worshiped Yahweh with their faces to the ground. 7 Also Jeshua, Bani, Sherebiah, Jamin, Akkub, Shabbethai, Hodiah, Maaseiah, Kelita, Azariah, Jozabad, Hanan, Pelaiah, and the Levites, caused the people to understand the law; and the people stayed in their place. 8 They read in the book, in the law of God, distinctly; and they gave the sense, so that they understood the reading.

9 Nehemiah, who was the governor, and Ezra the priest and scribe, and the Levites who taught the people, said to all the people, “Today is holy to Yahweh your God. Don’t mourn, nor weep.” For all the people wept when they heard the words of the law. 10 Then he said to them, “Go your way. Eat the fat, drink the sweet, and send portions to him for whom nothing is prepared, for today is holy to our Lord. Don’t be grieved, for the joy of Yahweh is your strength.”

11 So the Levites calmed all the people, saying, “Hold your peace, for the day is holy. Don’t be grieved.”

12 All the people went their way to eat, to drink, to send portions, and to celebrate, because they had understood the words that were declared to them.

13 On the second day, the heads of fathers’ households of all the people, the priests, and the Levites were gathered together to Ezra the scribe, to study the words of the law. 14 They found written in the law how Yahweh had commanded by Moses that the children of Israel should dwell in booths in the feast of the seventh month; 15 and that they should publish and proclaim in all their cities, and in Jerusalem, saying, “Go out to the mountain, and get olive branches, branches of wild olive, myrtle branches, palm branches, and branches of thick trees, to make temporary shelters,[*] as it is written.”

16 So the people went out, and brought them, and made themselves temporary shelters,[*] everyone on the roof of his house, in their courts, in the courts of God’s house, in the wide place of the water gate, and in the wide place of Ephraim’s gate. 17 All the assembly of those who had come back out of the captivity made temporary shelters,[*] and lived in the booths; for since the days of Jeshua the son of Nun to that day the children of Israel had not done so. There was very great gladness. 18 Also day by day, from the first day to the last day, he read in the book of the law of God. They kept the feast seven days; and on the eighth day was a solemn assembly, according to the ordinance.

or, booths

or, booths

or, booths

Nehemiah 9

1 Now in the twenty-fourth day of this month the children of Israel were assembled with fasting, with sackcloth, and dirt on them. 2 The offspring[*] of Israel separated themselves from all foreigners, and stood and confessed their sins, and the iniquities of their fathers. 3 They stood up in their place, and read in the book of the law of Yahweh their God a fourth part of the day; and a fourth part they confessed, and worshiped Yahweh their God. 4 Then Jeshua, Bani, Kadmiel, Shebaniah, Bunni, Sherebiah, Bani, and Chenani of the Levites stood up on the stairs, and cried with a loud voice to Yahweh their God.

5 Then the Levites, Jeshua, and Kadmiel, Bani, Hashabneiah, Sherebiah, Hodiah, Shebaniah, and Pethahiah, said, “Stand up and bless Yahweh your God from everlasting to everlasting! Blessed be your glorious name, which is exalted above all blessing and praise! 6 You are Yahweh, even you alone. You have made heaven, the heaven of heavens, with all their army, the earth and all things that are on it, the seas and all that is in them, and you preserve them all. The army of heaven worships you. 7 You are Yahweh, the God who chose Abram, brought him out of Ur of the Chaldees, gave him the name of Abraham, 8 found his heart faithful before you, and made a covenant with him to give the land of the Canaanite, the Hittite, the Amorite, the Perizzite, the Jebusite, and the Girgashite, to give it to his offspring,[*] and have performed your words; for you are righteous.

9 “You saw the affliction of our fathers in Egypt, and heard their cry by the Red Sea, 10 and showed signs and wonders against Pharaoh, and against all his servants, and against all the people of his land; for you knew that they dealt proudly against them, and made a name for yourself, as it is today. 11 You divided the sea before them, so that they went through the middle of the sea on the dry land; and you cast their pursuers into the depths, as a stone into the mighty waters. 12 Moreover, in a pillar of cloud you led them by day; and in a pillar of fire by night, to give them light in the way in which they should go.

13 “You also came down on Mount Sinai, and spoke with them from heaven, and gave them right ordinances and true laws, good statutes and commandments, 14 and made known to them your holy Sabbath, and commanded them commandments, statutes, and a law, by Moses your servant, 15 and gave them bread from the sky for their hunger, and brought water out of the rock for them for their thirst, and commanded them that they should go in to possess the land which you had sworn to give them.

16 “But they and our fathers behaved proudly, hardened their neck, didn’t listen to your commandments, 17 and refused to obey. They weren’t mindful of your wonders that you did among them, but hardened their neck, and in their rebellion appointed a captain to return to their bondage. But you are a God ready to pardon, gracious and merciful, slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness, and didn’t forsake them. 18 Yes, when they had made themselves a molten calf, and said, ‘This is your God who brought you up out of Egypt,’ and had committed awful blasphemies; 19 yet you in your manifold mercies didn’t forsake them in the wilderness. The pillar of cloud didn’t depart from over them by day, to lead them in the way; neither did the pillar of fire by night, to show them light, and the way in which they should go. 20 You gave also your good Spirit to instruct them, and didn’t withhold your manna from their mouth, and gave them water for their thirst.

21 “Yes, forty years you sustained them in the wilderness. They lacked nothing. Their clothes didn’t grow old, and their feet didn’t swell. 22 Moreover you gave them kingdoms and peoples, which you allotted according to their portions. So they possessed the land of Sihon, even the land of the king of Heshbon, and the land of Og king of Bashan. 23 You also multiplied their children as the stars of the sky, and brought them into the land concerning which you said to their fathers, that they should go in to possess it.

24 “So the children went in and possessed the land, and you subdued before them the inhabitants of the land, the Canaanites, and gave them into their hands, with their kings and the peoples of the land, that they might do with them as they pleased. 25 They took fortified cities and a rich land, and possessed houses full of all good things, cisterns dug out, vineyards, and olive groves, and fruit trees in abundance. So they ate, were filled, became fat, and delighted themselves in your great goodness.

26 “Nevertheless they were disobedient, and rebelled against you, cast your law behind their back, killed your prophets that testified against them to turn them again to you, and they committed awful blasphemies. 27 Therefore you delivered them into the hand of their adversaries, who distressed them. In the time of their trouble, when they cried to you, you heard from heaven; and according to your manifold mercies you gave them saviors who saved them out of the hands of their adversaries. 28 But after they had rest, they did evil again before you; therefore left you them in the hands of their enemies, so that they had the dominion over them; yet when they returned, and cried to you, you heard from heaven; and many times you delivered them according to your mercies, 29 and testified against them, that you might bring them again to your law. Yet they were arrogant, and didn’t listen to your commandments, but sinned against your ordinances (which if a man does, he shall live in them), turned their backs, stiffened their neck, and would not hear. 30 Yet many years you put up with them, and testified against them by your Spirit through your prophets. Yet would they not give ear. Therefore you gave them into the hand of the peoples of the lands.

31 “Nevertheless in your manifold mercies you did not make a full end of them, nor forsake them; for you are a gracious and merciful God.

32 Now therefore, our God, the great, the mighty, and the awesome God, who keeps covenant and loving kindness, don’t let all the travail seem little before you, that has come on us, on our kings, on our princes, on our priests, on our prophets, on our fathers, and on all your people, since the time of the kings of Assyria to this day. 33 However you are just in all that has come on us; for you have dealt truly, but we have done wickedly. 34 Also our kings, our princes, our priests, and our fathers have not kept your law, nor listened to your commandments and your testimonies with which you testified against them. 35 For they have not served you in their kingdom, and in your great goodness that you gave them, and in the large and rich land which you gave before them. They did not turn from their wicked works.

36 “Behold, we are servants today, and as for the land that you gave to our fathers to eat its fruit and its good, behold, we are servants in it. 37 It yields much increase to the kings whom you have set over us because of our sins. Also they have power over our bodies and over our livestock, at their pleasure, and we are in great distress. 38 Yet for all this, we make a sure covenant, and write it; and our princes, our Levites, and our priests, seal it.”

or, seed

or, seed

Nehemiah 10

1 Now those who sealed were: Nehemiah the governor, the son of Hacaliah, and Zedekiah, 2 Seraiah, Azariah, Jeremiah, 3 Pashhur, Amariah, Malchijah, 4 Hattush, Shebaniah, Malluch, 5 Harim, Meremoth, Obadiah, 6 Daniel, Ginnethon, Baruch, 7 Meshullam, Abijah, Mijamin, 8 Maaziah, Bilgai, and Shemaiah. These were the priests. 9 The Levites: namely, Jeshua the son of Azaniah, Binnui of the sons of Henadad, Kadmiel; 10 and their brothers, Shebaniah, Hodiah, Kelita, Pelaiah, Hanan, 11 Mica, Rehob, Hashabiah, 12 Zaccur, Sherebiah, Shebaniah, 13 Hodiah, Bani, and Beninu. 14 The chiefs of the people: Parosh, Pahathmoab, Elam, Zattu, Bani, 15 Bunni, Azgad, Bebai, 16 Adonijah, Bigvai, Adin, 17 Ater, Hezekiah, Azzur, 18 Hodiah, Hashum, Bezai, 19 Hariph, Anathoth, Nobai, 20 Magpiash, Meshullam, Hezir, 21 Meshezabel, Zadok, Jaddua, 22 Pelatiah, Hanan, Anaiah, 23 Hoshea, Hananiah, Hasshub, 24 Hallohesh, Pilha, Shobek, 25 Rehum, Hashabnah, Maaseiah, 26 and Ahiah, Hanan, Anan, 27 Malluch, Harim, and Baanah.

28 The rest of the people, the priests, the Levites, the porters, the singers, the temple servants, and all those who had separated themselves from the peoples of the lands to the law of God, their wives, their sons, and their daughters, everyone who had knowledge, and understanding— 29 they joined with their brothers, their nobles, and entered into a curse, and into an oath, to walk in God’s law, which was given by Moses the servant of God, and to observe and do all the commandments of Yahweh our Lord, and his ordinances and his statutes; 30 and that we would not give our daughters to the peoples of the land, nor take their daughters for our sons; 31 and if the peoples of the land bring wares or any grain on the Sabbath day to sell, that we would not buy from them on the Sabbath, or on a holy day; and that we would forego the seventh year, and the exaction of every debt.

32 Also we made ordinances for ourselves, to charge ourselves yearly with the third part of a shekel[*] for the service of the house of our God; 33 for the show bread, for the continual meal offering, for the continual burnt offering, for the Sabbaths, for the new moons, for the set feasts, and for the holy things, and for the sin offerings to make atonement for Israel, and for all the work of the house of our God. 34 We cast lots, the priests, the Levites, and the people, for the wood offering, to bring it into the house of our God, according to our fathers’ houses, at times appointed, year by year, to burn on Yahweh our God’s altar, as it is written in the law; 35 and to bring the first fruits of our ground, and the first fruits of all fruit of all kinds of trees, year by year, to Yahweh’s house; 36 also the firstborn of our sons, and of our livestock, as it is written in the law, and the firstborn of our herds and of our flocks, to bring to the house of our God, to the priests who minister in the house of our God; 37 and that we should bring the first fruits of our dough, our wave offerings, the fruit of all kinds of trees, and the new wine and the oil, to the priests, to the rooms of the house of our God; and the tithes of our ground to the Levites; for they, the Levites, take the tithes in all the cities of our tillage. 38 The priest the son of Aaron shall be with the Levites, when the Levites take tithes. The Levites shall bring up the tithe of the tithes to the house of our God, to the rooms, into the treasure house. 39 For the children of Israel and the children of Levi shall bring the wave offering of the grain, of the new wine, and of the oil, to the rooms, where the vessels of the sanctuary are, and the priests who minister, with the porters and the singers. We will not forsake the house of our God.

A shekel is about 10 grams or about 0.35 ounces.

Nehemiah 11

1 The princes of the people lived in Jerusalem. The rest of the people also cast lots, to bring one of ten to dwell in Jerusalem the holy city, and nine parts in the other cities. 2 The people blessed all the men who willingly offered themselves to dwell in Jerusalem.

3 Now these are the chiefs of the province who lived in Jerusalem; but in the cities of Judah everyone lived in his possession in their cities: Israel, the priests, the Levites, the temple servants, and the children of Solomon’s servants. 4 Some of the children of Judah and of the children of Benjamin lived in Jerusalem. Of the children of Judah: Athaiah the son of Uzziah, the son of Zechariah, the son of Amariah, the son of Shephatiah, the son of Mahalalel, of the children of Perez; 5 and Maaseiah the son of Baruch, the son of Colhozeh, the son of Hazaiah, the son of Adaiah, the son of Joiarib, the son of Zechariah, the son of the Shilonite. 6 All the sons of Perez who lived in Jerusalem were four hundred sixty-eight valiant men.

7 These are the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Joed, the son of Pedaiah, the son of Kolaiah, the son of Maaseiah, the son of Ithiel, the son of Jeshaiah. 8 After him Gabbai, Sallai, nine hundred twenty-eight. 9 Joel the son of Zichri was their overseer; and Judah the son of Hassenuah was second over the city.

10 Of the priests: Jedaiah the son of Joiarib, Jachin, 11 Seraiah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of God’s house, 12 and their brothers who did the work of the house, eight hundred twenty-two; and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pelaliah, the son of Amzi, the son of Zechariah, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah, 13 and his brothers, chiefs of fathers’ households, two hundred forty-two; and Amashsai the son of Azarel, the son of Ahzai, the son of Meshillemoth, the son of Immer, 14 and their brothers, mighty men of valor, one hundred twenty-eight; and their overseer was Zabdiel, the son of Haggedolim.

15 Of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Bunni; 16 and Shabbethai and Jozabad, of the chiefs of the Levites, who had the oversight of the outward business of God’s house; 17 and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zabdi, the son of Asaph, who was the chief to begin the thanksgiving in prayer, and Bakbukiah, the second among his brothers; and Abda the son of Shammua, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun. 18 All the Levites in the holy city were two hundred eighty-four.

19 Moreover the porters, Akkub, Talmon, and their brothers, who kept watch at the gates, were one hundred seventy-two. 20 The residue of Israel, of the priests, the Levites, were in all the cities of Judah, everyone in his inheritance. 21 But the temple servants lived in Ophel: and Ziha and Gishpa were over the temple servants.

22 The overseer also of the Levites at Jerusalem was Uzzi the son of Bani, the son of Hashabiah, the son of Mattaniah, the son of Mica, of the sons of Asaph, the singers, over the business of God’s house. 23 For there was a commandment from the king concerning them, and a settled provision for the singers, as every day required. 24 Pethahiah the son of Meshezabel, of the children of Zerah the son of Judah, was at the king’s hand in all matters concerning the people.

25 As for the villages, with their fields, some of the children of Judah lived in Kiriath Arba and its towns, in Dibon and its towns, in Jekabzeel and its villages, 26 in Jeshua, in Moladah, Beth Pelet, 27 in Hazar Shual, in Beersheba and its towns, 28 in Ziklag, in Meconah and in its towns, 29 in En Rimmon, in Zorah, in Jarmuth, 30 Zanoah, Adullam, and their villages, Lachish and its fields, and Azekah and its towns. So they encamped from Beersheba to the valley of Hinnom. 31 The children of Benjamin also lived from Geba onward, at Michmash and Aija, and at Bethel and its towns, 32 at Anathoth, Nob, Ananiah, 33 Hazor, Ramah, Gittaim, 34 Hadid, Zeboim, Neballat, 35 Lod, and Ono, the valley of craftsmen. 36 Of the Levites, certain divisions in Judah settled in Benjamin’s territory.

Nehemiah 13

1 On that day they read in the book of Moses in the hearing of the people; and it was found written in it that an Ammonite and a Moabite should not enter into the assembly of God forever, 2 because they didn’t meet the children of Israel with bread and with water, but hired Balaam against them, to curse them; however our God turned the curse into a blessing. 3 It came to pass, when they had heard the law, that they separated all the mixed multitude from Israel.

4 Now before this, Eliashib the priest, who was appointed over the rooms of the house of our God, being allied to Tobiah, 5 had prepared for him a great room, where before they laid the meal offerings, the frankincense, the vessels, and the tithes of the grain, the new wine, and the oil, which were given by commandment to the Levites, the singers, and the porters; and the wave offerings for the priests. 6 But in all this, I was not at Jerusalem; for in the thirty-second year of Artaxerxes king of Babylon I went to the king; and after some days I asked leave of the king, 7 and I came to Jerusalem, and understood the evil that Eliashib had done for Tobiah, in preparing him a room in the courts of God’s house. 8 It grieved me severely. Therefore I threw all Tobiah’s household stuff out of the room. 9 Then I commanded, and they cleansed the rooms. I brought into them the vessels of God’s house, with the meal offerings and the frankincense again.

10 I perceived that the portions of the Levites had not been given them; so that the Levites and the singers, who did the work, had each fled to his field. 11 Then I contended with the rulers, and said, “Why is God’s house forsaken?” I gathered them together, and set them in their place. 12 Then all Judah brought the tithe of the grain, the new wine, and the oil to the treasuries. 13 I made treasurers over the treasuries, Shelemiah the priest, and Zadok the scribe, and of the Levites, Pedaiah: and next to them was Hanan the son of Zaccur, the son of Mattaniah; for they were counted faithful, and their business was to distribute to their brothers.

14 Remember me, my God, concerning this, and don’t wipe out my good deeds that I have done for the house of my God, and for its observances.

15 In those days saw I in Judah some men treading wine presses on the Sabbath, bringing in sheaves, and loading donkeys; also with wine, grapes, figs, and all kinds of burdens, which they brought into Jerusalem on the Sabbath day; and I testified against them in the day in which they sold food. 16 Some men of Tyre also lived there, who brought in fish and all kinds of wares, and sold on the Sabbath to the children of Judah, and in Jerusalem. 17 Then I contended with the nobles of Judah, and said to them, “What evil thing is this that you do, and profane the Sabbath day? 18 Didn’t your fathers do thus, and didn’t our God bring all this evil on us, and on this city? Yet you bring more wrath on Israel by profaning the Sabbath.”

19 It came to pass that when the gates of Jerusalem began to be dark before the Sabbath, I commanded that the doors should be shut, and commanded that they should not be opened until after the Sabbath. I set some of my servants over the gates, so that no burden should be brought in on the Sabbath day. 20 So the merchants and sellers of all kinds of wares camped outside of Jerusalem once or twice. 21 Then I testified against them, and said to them, “Why do you stay around the wall? If you do so again, I will lay hands on you.” From that time on, they didn’t come on the Sabbath. 22 I commanded the Levites that they should purify themselves, and that they should come and keep the gates, to sanctify the Sabbath day. Remember to me, my God, this also, and spare me according to the greatness of your loving kindness.

23 In those days I also saw the Jews who had married women of Ashdod, of Ammon, and of Moab; 24 and their children spoke half in the speech of Ashdod, and could not speak in the Jews’ language, but according to the language of each people. 25 I contended with them, and cursed them, and struck certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them swear by God, “You shall not give your daughters to their sons, nor take their daughters for your sons, or for yourselves. 26 Didn’t Solomon king of Israel sin by these things? Yet among many nations was there no king like him, and he was beloved of his God, and God made him king over all Israel. Nevertheless foreign women caused even him to sin. 27 Shall we then listen to you to do all this great evil, to trespass against our God in marrying foreign women?”

28 One of the sons of Joiada, the son of Eliashib the high priest, was son-in-law to Sanballat the Horonite; therefore I chased him from me. 29 Remember them, my God, because they have defiled the priesthood, and the covenant of the priesthood and of the Levites.

30 Thus I cleansed them from all foreigners, and appointed duties for the priests and for the Levites, everyone in his work; 31 and for the wood offering, at times appointed, and for the first fruits. Remember me, my God, for good.

Esther 1

1 Now in the days of Ahasuerus (this is Ahasuerus who reigned from India even to Ethiopia, over one hundred twenty-seven provinces), 2 in those days, when the King Ahasuerus sat on the throne of his kingdom, which was in Shushan the palace, 3 in the third year of his reign, he made a feast for all his princes and his servants; the power of Persia and Media, the nobles and princes of the provinces, being before him. 4 He displayed the riches of his glorious kingdom and the honor of his excellent majesty many days, even one hundred eighty days. 5 When these days were fulfilled, the king made a seven day feast for all the people who were present in Shushan the palace, both great and small, in the court of the garden of the king’s palace. 6 There were hangings of white, green, and blue material, fastened with cords of fine linen and purple to silver rings and marble pillars. The couches were of gold and silver, on a pavement of red, white, yellow, and black marble. 7 They gave them drinks in golden vessels of various kinds, including royal wine in abundance, according to the bounty of the king. 8 In accordance with the law, the drinking was not compulsory; for so the king had instructed all the officials of his house, that they should do according to every man’s pleasure.

9 Also Vashti the queen made a feast for the women in the royal house which belonged to King Ahasuerus.

10 On the seventh day, when the heart of the king was merry with wine, he commanded Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, and Abagtha, Zethar, and Carcass, the seven eunuchs who served in the presence of Ahasuerus the king, 11 to bring Vashti the queen before the king with the royal crown, to show the people and the princes her beauty; for she was beautiful. 12 But the queen Vashti refused to come at the king’s commandment by the eunuchs. Therefore the king was very angry, and his anger burned in him.

13 Then the king said to the wise men, who knew the times (for it was the king’s custom to consult those who knew law and judgment; 14 and the next to him were Carshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshish, Meres, Marsena, and Memucan, the seven princes of Persia and Media, who saw the king’s face, and sat first in the kingdom), 15 “What shall we do to the queen Vashti according to law, because she has not done the bidding of the King Ahasuerus by the eunuchs?”

16 Memucan answered before the king and the princes, “Vashti the queen has not done wrong to just the king, but also to all the princes, and to all the people who are in all the provinces of the King Ahasuerus. 17 For this deed of the queen will become known to all women, causing them to show contempt for their husbands, when it is reported, ‘King Ahasuerus commanded Vashti the queen to be brought in before him, but she didn’t come.’ 18 Today, the princesses of Persia and Media who have heard of the queen’s deed will tell all the king’s princes. This will cause much contempt and wrath.

19 “If it please the king, let a royal commandment go from him, and let it be written among the laws of the Persians and the Medes, so that it cannot be altered, that Vashti may never again come before King Ahasuerus; and let the king give her royal estate to another who is better than she. 20 When the king’s decree which he shall make is published throughout all his kingdom (for it is great), all the wives will give their husbands honor, both great and small.”

21 This advice pleased the king and the princes, and the king did according to the word of Memucan: 22 for he sent letters into all the king’s provinces, into every province according to its writing, and to every people in their language, that every man should rule his own house, speaking in the language of his own people.

Esther 2

1 After these things, when the wrath of King Ahasuerus was pacified, he remembered Vashti, and what she had done, and what was decreed against her. 2 Then the king’s servants who served him said, “Let beautiful young virgins be sought for the king. 3 Let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of his kingdom, that they may gather together all the beautiful young virgins to the citadel of Susa, to the women’s house, to the custody of Hegai the king’s eunuch, keeper of the women. Let cosmetics be given them; 4 and let the maiden who pleases the king be queen instead of Vashti.” The thing pleased the king, and he did so.

5 There was a certain Jew in the citadel of Susa, whose name was Mordecai, the son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of Kish, a Benjamite, 6 who had been carried away from Jerusalem with the captives who had been carried away with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away. 7 He brought up Hadassah, that is, Esther, his uncle’s daughter; for she had neither father nor mother. The maiden was fair and beautiful; and when her father and mother were dead, Mordecai took her for his own daughter.

8 So, when the king’s commandment and his decree was heard, and when many maidens were gathered together to the citadel of Susa, to the custody of Hegai, Esther was taken into the king’s house, to the custody of Hegai, keeper of the women. 9 The maiden pleased him, and she obtained kindness from him. He quickly gave her cosmetics and her portions of food, and the seven choice maidens who were to be given her out of the king’s house. He moved her and her maidens to the best place in the women’s house. 10 Esther had not made known her people nor her relatives, because Mordecai had instructed her that she should not make it known. 11 Mordecai walked every day in front of the court of the women’s house, to find out how Esther was doing, and what would become of her.

12 Each young woman’s turn came to go in to King Ahasuerus after her purification for twelve months (for so were the days of their purification accomplished, six months with oil of myrrh, and six months with sweet fragrances and with preparations for beautifying women). 13 The young woman then came to the king like this: whatever she desired was given her to go with her out of the women’s house to the king’s house. 14 In the evening she went, and on the next day she returned into the second women’s house, to the custody of Shaashgaz, the king’s eunuch, who kept the concubines. She came in to the king no more, unless the king delighted in her, and she was called by name. 15 Now when the turn of Esther, the daughter of Abihail the uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her for his daughter, came to go in to the king, she required nothing but what Hegai the king’s eunuch, the keeper of the women, advised. Esther obtained favor in the sight of all those who looked at her.

16 So Esther was taken to King Ahasuerus into his royal house in the tenth month, which is the month Tebeth, in the seventh year of his reign. 17 The king loved Esther more than all the women, and she obtained favor and kindness in his sight more than all the virgins; so that he set the royal crown on her head, and made her queen instead of Vashti.

18 Then the king made a great feast for all his princes and his servants, even Esther’s feast; and he proclaimed a holiday in the provinces, and gave gifts according to the king’s bounty.

19 When the virgins were gathered together the second time, Mordecai was sitting in the king’s gate. 20 Esther had not yet made known her relatives nor her people, as Mordecai had commanded her; for Esther obeyed Mordecai, like she did when she was brought up by him. 21 In those days, while Mordecai was sitting in the king’s gate, two of the king’s eunuchs, Bigthan and Teresh, who were doorkeepers, were angry, and sought to lay hands on the King Ahasuerus. 22 This thing became known to Mordecai, who informed Esther the queen; and Esther informed the king in Mordecai’s name. 23 When this matter was investigated, and it was found to be so, they were both hanged on a tree; and it was written in the book of the chronicles in the king’s presence.

Esther 3

1 After these things King Ahasuerus promoted Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, and advanced him, and set his seat above all the princes who were with him. 2 All the king’s servants who were in the king’s gate bowed down, and paid homage to Haman; for the king had so commanded concerning him. But Mordecai didn’t bow down or pay him homage. 3 Then the king’s servants, who were in the king’s gate, said to Mordecai, “Why do you disobey the king’s commandment?” 4 Now it came to pass, when they spoke daily to him, and he didn’t listen to them, that they told Haman, to see whether Mordecai’s reason would stand; for he had told them that he was a Jew. 5 When Haman saw that Mordecai didn’t bow down, nor pay him homage, Haman was full of wrath. 6 But he scorned the thought of laying hands on Mordecai alone, for they had made known to him Mordecai’s people. Therefore Haman sought to destroy all the Jews who were throughout the whole kingdom of Ahasuerus, even Mordecai’s people.

7 In the first month, which is the month Nisan, in the twelfth year of King Ahasuerus, they cast Pur, that is, the lot, before Haman from day to day, and from month to month, and chose the twelfth month, which is the month Adar. 8 Haman said to King Ahasuerus, “There is a certain people scattered abroad and dispersed among the peoples in all the provinces of your kingdom, and their laws are different than other people’s. They don’t keep the king’s laws. Therefore it is not for the king’s profit to allow them to remain. 9 If it pleases the king, let it be written that they be destroyed; and I will pay ten thousand talents[*] of silver into the hands of those who are in charge of the king’s business, to bring it into the king’s treasuries.”

10 The king took his ring from his hand, and gave it to Haman the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the Jews’ enemy. 11 The king said to Haman, “The silver is given to you, the people also, to do with them as it seems good to you.”

12 Then the king’s scribes were called in on the first month, on the thirteenth day of the month; and all that Haman commanded was written to the king’s satraps, and to the governors who were over every province, and to the princes of every people, to every province according to its writing, and to every people in their language. It was written in the name of King Ahasuerus, and it was sealed with the king’s ring. 13 Letters were sent by couriers into all the king’s provinces, to destroy, to kill, and to cause to perish, all Jews, both young and old, little children and women, in one day, even on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, and to plunder their possessions. 14 A copy of the letter, that the decree should be given out in every province, was published to all the peoples, that they should be ready against that day. 15 The couriers went out in haste by the king’s commandment, and the decree was given out in the citadel of Susa. The king and Haman sat down to drink; but the city of Shushan was perplexed.

A talent is about 30 kilograms or 66 pounds or 965 Troy ounces

Esther 5

1 Now on the third day, Esther put on her royal clothing, and stood in the inner court of the king’s house, next to the king’s house. The king sat on his royal throne in the royal house, next to the entrance of the house. 2 When the king saw Esther the queen standing in the court, she obtained favor in his sight; and the king held out to Esther the golden scepter that was in his hand. So Esther came near, and touched the top of the scepter. 3 Then the king asked her, “What would you like, queen Esther? What is your request? It shall be given you even to the half of the kingdom.”

4 Esther said, “If it seems good to the king, let the king and Haman come today to the banquet that I have prepared for him.”

5 Then the king said, “Bring Haman quickly, so that it may be done as Esther has said.” So the king and Haman came to the banquet that Esther had prepared.

6 The king said to Esther at the banquet of wine, “What is your petition? It shall be granted you. What is your request? Even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed.”

7 Then Esther answered and said, “My petition and my request is this. 8 If I have found favor in the sight of the king, and if it please the king to grant my petition and to perform my request, let the king and Haman come to the banquet that I will prepare for them, and I will do tomorrow as the king has said.”

9 Then Haman went out that day joyful and glad of heart, but when Haman saw Mordecai in the king’s gate, that he didn’t stand up nor move for him, he was filled with wrath against Mordecai. 10 Nevertheless Haman restrained himself, and went home. There, he sent and called for his friends and Zeresh his wife. 11 Haman recounted to them the glory of his riches, the multitude of his children, all the things in which the king had promoted him, and how he had advanced him above the princes and servants of the king. 12 Haman also said, “Yes, Esther the queen let no man come in with the king to the banquet that she had prepared but myself; and tomorrow I am also invited by her together with the king. 13 Yet all this avails me nothing, so long as I see Mordecai the Jew sitting at the king’s gate.”

14 Then Zeresh his wife and all his friends said to him, “Let a gallows be made fifty cubits[*] high, and in the morning speak to the king about hanging Mordecai on it. Then go in merrily with the king to the banquet.” This pleased Haman, so he had the gallows made.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Esther 6

1 On that night, the king couldn’t sleep. He commanded the book of records of the chronicles to be brought, and they were read to the king. 2 It was found written that Mordecai had told of Bigthana and Teresh, two of the king’s eunuchs, who were doorkeepers, who had tried to lay hands on the King Ahasuerus. 3 The king said, “What honor and dignity has been given to Mordecai for this?”

Then the king’s servants who attended him said, “Nothing has been done for him.”

4 The king said, “Who is in the court?” Now Haman had come into the outer court of the king’s house, to speak to the king about hanging Mordecai on the gallows that he had prepared for him.

5 The king’s servants said to him, “Behold,[*] Haman stands in the court.”

The king said, “Let him come in.” 6 So Haman came in. The king said to him, “What shall be done to the man whom the king delights to honor?”

Now Haman said in his heart, “Who would the king delight to honor more than myself?” 7 Haman said to the king, “For the man whom the king delights to honor, 8 let royal clothing be brought which the king uses to wear, and the horse that the king rides on, and on the head of which a crown royal is set. 9 Let the clothing and the horse be delivered to the hand of one of the king’s most noble princes, that they may array the man whom the king delights to honor with them, and have him ride on horseback through the city square, and proclaim before him, ‘Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to honor!’”

10 Then the king said to Haman, “Hurry and take the clothing and the horse, as you have said, and do this for Mordecai the Jew, who sits at the king’s gate. Let nothing fail of all that you have spoken.”

11 Then Haman took the clothing and the horse, and arrayed Mordecai, and had him ride through the city square, and proclaimed before him, “Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to honor!”

12 Mordecai came back to the king’s gate, but Haman hurried to his house, mourning and having his head covered. 13 Haman recounted to Zeresh his wife and all his friends everything that had happened to him. Then his wise men and Zeresh his wife said to him, “If Mordecai, before whom you have begun to fall, is of Jewish descent, you will not prevail against him, but you will surely fall before him.” 14 While they were yet talking with him, the king’s eunuchs came, and hurried to bring Haman to the banquet that Esther had prepared.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Esther 7

1 So the king and Haman came to banquet with Esther the queen. 2 The king said again to Esther on the second day at the banquet of wine, “What is your petition, queen Esther? It shall be granted you. What is your request? Even to the half of the kingdom it shall be performed.”

3 Then Esther the queen answered, “If I have found favor in your sight, O king, and if it please the king, let my life be given me at my petition, and my people at my request. 4 For we are sold, I and my people, to be destroyed, to be slain, and to perish. But if we had been sold for male and female slaves, I would have held my peace, although the adversary could not have compensated for the king’s loss.”

5 Then King Ahasuerus said to Esther the queen, “Who is he, and where is he who dared presume in his heart to do so?”

6 Esther said, “An adversary and an enemy, even this wicked Haman!”

Then Haman was afraid before the king and the queen. 7 The king arose in his wrath from the banquet of wine and went into the palace garden. Haman stood up to make request for his life to Esther the queen; for he saw that there was evil determined against him by the king. 8 Then the king returned out of the palace garden into the place of the banquet of wine; and Haman had fallen on the couch where Esther was. Then the king said, “Will he even assault the queen in front of me in the house?” As the word went out of the king’s mouth, they covered Haman’s face.

9 Then Harbonah, one of the eunuchs who were with the king said, “Behold, the gallows fifty cubits[*] high, which Haman has made for Mordecai, who spoke good for the king, is standing at Haman’s house.”

The king said, “Hang him on it!”

10 So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai. Then was the king’s wrath pacified.

A cubit is the length from the tip of the middle finger to the elbow on a man’s arm, or about 18 inches or 46 centimeters.

Esther 9

1 Now in the twelfth month, which is the month Adar, on the thirteenth day of the month, when the king’s commandment and his decree came near to be put in execution, on the day that the enemies of the Jews hoped to conquer them, (but it was turned out the opposite happened, that the Jews conquered those who hated them), 2 the Jews gathered themselves together in their cities throughout all the provinces of the King Ahasuerus, to lay hands on those who wanted to harm them. No one could withstand them, because the fear of them had fallen on all the people. 3 All the princes of the provinces, the satraps, the governors, and those who did the king’s business helped the Jews, because the fear of Mordecai had fallen on them. 4 For Mordecai was great in the king’s house, and his fame went out throughout all the provinces; for the man Mordecai grew greater and greater. 5 The Jews struck all their enemies with the stroke of the sword, and with slaughter and destruction, and did what they wanted to those who hated them. 6 In the citadel of Susa, the Jews killed and destroyed five hundred men. 7 They killed Parshandatha, Dalphon, Aspatha, 8 Poratha, Adalia, Aridatha, 9 Parmashta, Arisai, Aridai, and Vaizatha, 10 the ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Jews’ enemy, but they didn’t lay their hand on the plunder.

11 On that day, the number of those who were slain in the citadel of Susa was brought before the king. 12 The king said to Esther the queen, “The Jews have slain and destroyed five hundred men in the citadel of Susa, including the ten sons of Haman; what then have they done in the rest of the king’s provinces! Now what is your petition? It shall be granted you. What is your further request? It shall be done.”

13 Then Esther said, “If it pleases the king, let it be granted to the Jews who are in Shushan to do tomorrow also according to today’s decree, and let Haman’s ten sons be hanged on the gallows.”

14 The king commanded this to be done. A decree was given out in Shushan; and they hanged Haman’s ten sons. 15 The Jews who were in Shushan gathered themselves together on the fourteenth day also of the month Adar, and killed three hundred men in Shushan; but they didn’t lay their hand on the plunder. 16 The other Jews who were in the king’s provinces gathered themselves together, defended their lives, had rest from their enemies, and killed seventy-five thousand of those who hated them; but they didn’t lay their hand on the plunder.

17 This was done on the thirteenth day of the month Adar; and on the fourteenth day of that month they rested and made it a day of feasting and gladness. 18 But the Jews who were in Shushan assembled together on the thirteenth and on the fourteenth days of the month; and on the fifteenth day of that month, they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness. 19 Therefore the Jews of the villages, who live in the unwalled towns, make the fourteenth day of the month Adar a day of gladness and feasting, a good day, and a day of sending presents of food to one another.

20 Mordecai wrote these things, and sent letters to all the Jews who were in all the provinces of the king Ahasuerus, both near and far, 21 to enjoin them that they should keep the fourteenth and fifteenth days of the month Adar yearly, 22 as the days in which the Jews had rest from their enemies, and the month which was turned to them from sorrow to gladness, and from mourning into a good day; that they should make them days of feasting and gladness, and of sending presents of food to one another, and gifts to the needy. 23 The Jews accepted the custom that they had begun, as Mordecai had written to them; 24 because Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite, the enemy of all the Jews, had plotted against the Jews to destroy them, and had cast “Pur”, that is the lot, to consume them, and to destroy them; 25 but when this became known to the king, he commanded by letters that his wicked device, which he had devised against the Jews, should return on his own head, and that he and his sons should be hanged on the gallows.

26 Therefore they called these days “Purim”,[*] from the word “Pur.” Therefore because of all the words of this letter, and of that which they had seen concerning this matter, and that which had come to them, 27 the Jews established, and imposed on themselves, and on their descendants, and on all those who joined themselves to them, so that it should not fail, that they would keep these two days according to what was written, and according to its appointed time, every year; 28 and that these days should be remembered and kept throughout every generation, every family, every province, and every city; and that these days of Purim should not fail from among the Jews, nor their memory perish from their offspring,[*]

29 Then Esther the queen, the daughter of Abihail, and Mordecai the Jew, wrote with all authority to confirm this second letter of Purim. 30 He sent letters to all the Jews, to the hundred twenty-seven provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, with words of peace and truth, 31 to confirm these days of Purim in their appointed times, as Mordecai the Jew and Esther the queen had decreed, and as they had imposed upon themselves and their descendants, in the matter of the fastings and their cry. 32 The commandment of Esther confirmed these matters of Purim; and it was written in the book.

Purim is the Hebrew plural for pur, which means lot.

or, seed

Job 1

1 There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name was Job. That man was blameless and upright, and one who feared God,[*] and turned away from evil. 2 There were born to him seven sons and three daughters. 3 His possessions also were seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of oxen, five hundred female donkeys, and a very great household; so that this man was the greatest of all the children of the east. 4 His sons went and held a feast in the house of each one on his birthday; and they sent and called for their three sisters to eat and to drink with them. 5 It was so, when the days of their feasting had run their course, that Job sent and sanctified them, and rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings according to the number of them all. For Job said, “It may be that my sons have sinned, and renounced God in their hearts.” Job did so continually.

6 Now on the day when God’s sons came to present themselves before Yahweh,[*] Satan also came among them. 7 Yahweh said to Satan, “Where have you come from?”

Then Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “From going back and forth in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.”

8 Yahweh said to Satan, “Have you considered my servant, Job? For there is no one like him in the earth, a blameless and an upright man, one who fears God, and turns away from evil.”

9 Then Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “Does Job fear God for nothing? 10 Haven’t you made a hedge around him, and around his house, and around all that he has, on every side? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land. 11 But stretch out your hand now, and touch all that he has, and he will renounce you to your face.”

12 Yahweh said to Satan, “Behold,[*] all that he has is in your power. Only on himself don’t stretch out your hand.”

So Satan went out from the presence of Yahweh. 13 It fell on a day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in their oldest brother’s house, 14 that there came a messenger to Job, and said, “The oxen were plowing, and the donkeys feeding beside them, 15 and the Sabeans attacked, and took them away. Yes, they have killed the servants with the edge of the sword, and I alone have escaped to tell you.”

16 While he was still speaking, there also came another, and said, “The fire of God has fallen from the sky, and has burned up the sheep and the servants, and consumed them, and I alone have escaped to tell you.”

17 While he was still speaking, there came also another, and said, “The Chaldeans made three bands, and swept down on the camels, and have taken them away, yes, and killed the servants with the edge of the sword; and I alone have escaped to tell you.”

18 While he was still speaking, there came also another, and said, “Your sons and your daughters were eating and drinking wine in their oldest brother’s house, 19 and behold, there came a great wind from the wilderness, and struck the four corners of the house, and it fell on the young men, and they are dead. I alone have escaped to tell you.”

20 Then Job arose, and tore his robe, and shaved his head, and fell down on the ground, and worshiped. 21 He said, “Naked I came out of my mother’s womb, and naked shall I return there. Yahweh gave, and Yahweh has taken away. Blessed be Yahweh’s name.” 22 In all this, Job did not sin, nor charge God with wrongdoing.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Job 2

1 Again, on the day when the God’s sons came to present themselves before Yahweh, Satan came also among them to present himself before Yahweh. 2 Yahweh said to Satan, “Where have you come from?”

Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “From going back and forth in the earth, and from walking up and down in it.”

3 Yahweh said to Satan, “Have you considered my servant Job? For there is no one like him in the earth, a blameless and an upright man, one who fears God, and turns away from evil. He still maintains his integrity, although you incited me against him, to ruin him without cause.”

4 Satan answered Yahweh, and said, “Skin for skin. Yes, all that a man has he will give for his life. 5 But stretch out your hand now, and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will renounce you to your face.”

6 Yahweh said to Satan, “Behold, he is in your hand. Only spare his life.”

7 So Satan went out from the presence of Yahweh, and struck Job with painful sores from the sole of his foot to his head. 8 He took for himself a potsherd to scrape himself with, and he sat among the ashes. 9 Then his wife said to him, “Do you still maintain your integrity? Renounce God, and die.”

10 But he said to her, “You speak as one of the foolish women would speak. What? Shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall we not receive evil?”

In all this Job didn’t sin with his lips. 11 Now when Job’s three friends heard of all this evil that had come on him, they each came from his own place: Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite; and they made an appointment together to come to sympathize with him and to comfort him. 12 When they lifted up their eyes from a distance, and didn’t recognize him, they raised their voices, and wept; and they each tore his robe, and sprinkled dust on their heads toward the sky. 13 So they sat down with him on the ground seven days and seven nights, and no one spoke a word to him, for they saw that his grief was very great.

Job 3

1 After this Job opened his mouth, and cursed the day of his birth. 2 Job answered:

3 “Let the day perish in which I was born,

the night which said, ‘There is a boy conceived.’

4 Let that day be darkness.

Don’t let God from above seek for it,

neither let the light shine on it.

5 Let darkness and the shadow of death claim it for their own.

Let a cloud dwell on it.

Let all that makes black the day terrify it.

6 As for that night, let thick darkness seize on it.

Let it not rejoice among the days of the year.

Let it not come into the number of the months.

7 Behold, let that night be barren.

Let no joyful voice come therein.

8 Let them curse it who curse the day,

who are ready to rouse up leviathan.

9 Let the stars of its twilight be dark.

Let it look for light, but have none,

neither let it see the eyelids of the morning,

10 because it didn’t shut up the doors of my mother’s womb,

nor did it hide trouble from my eyes.

11 “Why didn’t I die from the womb?

Why didn’t I give up the spirit when my mother bore me?

12 Why did the knees receive me?

Or why the breast, that I should nurse?

13 For now should I have lain down and been quiet.

I should have slept, then I would have been at rest,

14 with kings and counselors of the earth,

who built up waste places for themselves;

15 or with princes who had gold,

who filled their houses with silver:

16 or as a hidden untimely birth I had not been,

as infants who never saw light.

17 There the wicked cease from troubling.

There the weary are at rest.

18 There the prisoners are at ease together.

They don’t hear the voice of the taskmaster.

19 The small and the great are there.

The servant is free from his master.

20 “Why is light given to him who is in misery,

life to the bitter in soul,

21 Who long for death, but it doesn’t come;

and dig for it more than for hidden treasures,

22 who rejoice exceedingly,

and are glad, when they can find the grave?

23 Why is light given to a man whose way is hidden,

whom God has hedged in?

24 For my sighing comes before I eat.

My groanings are poured out like water.

25 For the thing which I fear comes on me,

That which I am afraid of comes to me.

26 I am not at ease, neither am I quiet, neither have I rest;

but trouble comes.”

Job 4

1 Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,

2 “If someone ventures to talk with you, will you be grieved?

But who can withhold himself from speaking?

3 Behold, you have instructed many,

you have strengthened the weak hands.

4 Your words have supported him who was falling,

You have made firm the feeble knees.

5 But now it has come to you, and you faint.

It touches you, and you are troubled.

6 Isn’t your piety your confidence?

Isn’t the integrity of your ways your hope?

7 “Remember, now, whoever perished, being innocent?

Or where were the upright cut off?

8 According to what I have seen, those who plow iniquity,

and sow trouble,

reap the same.

9 By the breath of God they perish.

By the blast of his anger are they consumed.

10 The roaring of the lion,

and the voice of the fierce lion,

the teeth of the young lions, are broken.

11 The old lion perishes for lack of prey.

The cubs of the lioness are scattered abroad.

12 “Now a thing was secretly brought to me.

My ear received a whisper of it.

13 In thoughts from the visions of the night,

when deep sleep falls on men,

14 fear came on me, and trembling,

which made all my bones shake.

15 Then a spirit passed before my face.

The hair of my flesh stood up.

16 It stood still, but I couldn’t discern its appearance.

A form was before my eyes.

Silence, then I heard a voice, saying,

17 ‘Shall mortal man be more just than God?

Shall a man be more pure than his Maker?

18 Behold, he puts no trust in his servants.

He charges his angels with error.

19 How much more, those who dwell in houses of clay,

whose foundation is in the dust,

who are crushed before the moth!

20 Between morning and evening they are destroyed.

They perish forever without any regarding it.

21 Isn’t their tent cord plucked up within them?

They die, and that without wisdom.’

Job 5

1 “Call now; is there any who will answer you?

To which of the holy ones will you turn?

2 For resentment kills the foolish man,

and jealousy kills the simple.

3 I have seen the foolish taking root,

but suddenly I cursed his habitation.

4 His children are far from safety.

They are crushed in the gate.

Neither is there any to deliver them,

5 whose harvest the hungry eats up,

and take it even out of the thorns.

The snare gapes for their substance.

6 For affliction doesn’t come out of the dust,

neither does trouble spring out of the ground;

7 but man is born to trouble,

as the sparks fly upward.

8 “But as for me, I would seek God.

I would commit my cause to God,

9 who does great things that can’t be fathomed,

marvelous things without number;

10 who gives rain on the earth,

and sends waters on the fields;

11 so that he sets up on high those who are low,

those who mourn are exalted to safety.

12 He frustrates the devices of the crafty,

So that their hands can’t perform their enterprise.

13 He takes the wise in their own craftiness;

the counsel of the cunning is carried headlong.

14 They meet with darkness in the day time,

and grope at noonday as in the night.

15 But he saves from the sword of their mouth,

even the needy from the hand of the mighty.

16 So the poor has hope,

and injustice shuts her mouth.

17 “Behold, happy is the man whom God corrects.

Therefore do not despise the chastening of the Almighty.

18 For he wounds, and binds up.

He injures, and his hands make whole.

19 He will deliver you in six troubles;

yes, in seven no evil shall touch you.

20 In famine he will redeem you from death;

in war, from the power of the sword.

21 You shall be hidden from the scourge of the tongue,

neither shall you be afraid of destruction when it comes.

22 At destruction and famine you shall laugh,

neither shall you be afraid of the animals of the earth.

23 For you shall be allied with the stones of the field.

The animals of the field shall be at peace with you.

24 You shall know that your tent is in peace.

You shall visit your fold, and shall miss nothing.

25 You shall know also that your offspring[*] shall be great,

Your offspring as the grass of the earth.

26 You shall come to your grave in a full age,

like a shock of grain comes in its season.

27 Look this, we have searched it, so it is.

Hear it, and know it for your good.”

or, seed

Job 6

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Oh that my anguish were weighed,

and all my calamity laid in the balances!

3 For now it would be heavier than the sand of the seas,

therefore have my words been rash.

4 For the arrows of the Almighty are within me.

My spirit drinks up their poison.

The terrors of God set themselves in array against me.

5 Does the wild donkey bray when he has grass?

Or does the ox low over his fodder?

6 Can that which has no flavor be eaten without salt?

Or is there any taste in the white of an egg?

7 My soul refuses to touch them.

They are as loathsome food to me.

8 “Oh that I might have my request,

that God would grant the thing that I long for,

9 even that it would please God to crush me;

that he would let loose his hand, and cut me off!

10 Be it still my consolation,

yes, let me exult in pain that doesn’t spare,

that I have not denied the words of the Holy One.

11 What is my strength, that I should wait?

What is my end, that I should be patient?

12 Is my strength the strength of stones?

Or is my flesh of brass?

13 Isn’t it that I have no help in me,

That wisdom is driven quite from me?

14 “To him who is ready to faint, kindness should be shown from his friend;

even to him who forsakes the fear of the Almighty.

15 My brothers have dealt deceitfully as a brook,

as the channel of brooks that pass away;

16 Which are black by reason of the ice,

in which the snow hides itself.

17 In the dry season, they vanish.

When it is hot, they are consumed out of their place.

18 The caravans that travel beside them turn aside.

They go up into the waste, and perish.

19 The caravans of Tema looked.

The companies of Sheba waited for them.

20 They were distressed because they were confident.

They came there, and were confounded.

21 For now you are nothing.

You see a terror, and are afraid.

22 Did I say, ‘Give to me?’

or, ‘Offer a present for me from your substance?’

23 or, ‘Deliver me from the adversary’s hand?’

or, ‘Redeem me from the hand of the oppressors?’

24 “Teach me, and I will hold my peace.

Cause me to understand wherein I have erred.

25 How forcible are words of uprightness!

But your reproof, what does it reprove?

26 Do you intend to reprove words,

since the speeches of one who is desperate are as wind?

27 Yes, you would even cast lots for the fatherless,

and make merchandise of your friend.

28 Now therefore be pleased to look at me,

for surely I shall not lie to your face.

29 Please return.

Let there be no injustice.

Yes, return again.

My cause is righteous.

30 Is there injustice on my tongue?

Can’t my taste discern mischievous things?

Job 7

1 “Isn’t a man forced to labor on earth?

Aren’t his days like the days of a hired hand?

2 As a servant who earnestly desires the shadow,

as a hireling who looks for his wages,

3 so am I made to possess months of misery,

wearisome nights are appointed to me.

4 When I lie down, I say,

‘When shall I arise, and the night be gone?’

I toss and turn until the dawning of the day.

5 My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust.

My skin closes up, and breaks out afresh.

6 My days are swifter than a weaver’s shuttle,

and are spent without hope.

7 Oh remember that my life is a breath.

My eye shall no more see good.

8 The eye of him who sees me shall see me no more.

Your eyes shall be on me, but I shall not be.

9 As the cloud is consumed and vanishes away,

so he who goes down to Sheol[*] shall come up no more.

10 He shall return no more to his house,

neither shall his place know him any more.

11 “Therefore I will not keep silent.

I will speak in the anguish of my spirit.

I will complain in the bitterness of my soul.

12 Am I a sea, or a sea monster,

that you put a guard over me?

13 When I say, ‘My bed shall comfort me.

My couch shall ease my complaint;’

14 then you scare me with dreams,

and terrify me through visions:

15 so that my soul chooses strangling,

death rather than my bones.

16 I loathe my life.

I don’t want to live forever.

Leave me alone, for my days are but a breath.

17 What is man, that you should magnify him,

that you should set your mind on him,

18 that you should visit him every morning,

and test him every moment?

19 How long will you not look away from me,

nor leave me alone until I swallow down my spittle?

20 If I have sinned, what do I do to you, you watcher of men?

Why have you set me as a mark for you,

so that I am a burden to myself?

21 Why do you not pardon my disobedience, and take away my iniquity?

For now shall I lie down in the dust.

You will seek me diligently, but I shall not be.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Job 8

1 Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,

2 “How long will you speak these things?

Shall the words of your mouth be a mighty wind?

3 Does God pervert justice?

Or does the Almighty pervert righteousness?

4 If your children have sinned against him,

He has delivered them into the hand of their disobedience.

5 If you want to seek God diligently,

make your supplication to the Almighty.

6 If you were pure and upright,

surely now he would awaken for you,

and make the habitation of your righteousness prosperous.

7 Though your beginning was small,

yet your latter end would greatly increase.

8 “Please inquire of past generations.

Find out about the learning of their fathers.

9 (For we are but of yesterday, and know nothing,

because our days on earth are a shadow.)

10 Shall they not teach you, tell you,

and utter words out of their heart?

11 “Can the papyrus grow up without mire?

Can the rushes grow without water?

12 While it is yet in its greenness, not cut down,

it withers before any other reed.

13 So are the paths of all who forget God.

The hope of the godless man shall perish,

14 Whose confidence shall break apart,

Whose trust is a spider’s web.

15 He shall lean on his house, but it shall not stand.

He shall cling to it, but it shall not endure.

16 He is green before the sun.

His shoots go out along his garden.

17 His roots are wrapped around the rock pile.

He sees the place of stones.

18 If he is destroyed from his place,

then it shall deny him, saying, ‘I have not seen you.’

19 Behold, this is the joy of his way:

out of the earth, others shall spring.

20 “Behold, God will not cast away a blameless man,

neither will he uphold the evildoers.

21 He will still fill your mouth with laughter,

your lips with shouting.

22 Those who hate you shall be clothed with shame.

The tent of the wicked shall be no more.”

Job 9

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Truly I know that it is so,

but how can man be just with God?

3 If he is pleased to contend with him,

he can’t answer him one time in a thousand.

4 God who is wise in heart, and mighty in strength:

who has hardened himself against him, and prospered?

5 He removes the mountains, and they don’t know it,

when he overturns them in his anger.

6 He shakes the earth out of its place.

Its pillars tremble.

7 He commands the sun, and it doesn’t rise,

and seals up the stars.

8 He alone stretches out the heavens,

and treads on the waves of the sea.

9 He makes the Bear, Orion, and the Pleiades,

and the rooms of the south.

10 He does great things past finding out;

yes, marvelous things without number.

11 Behold, he goes by me, and I don’t see him.

He passes on also, but I don’t perceive him.

12 Behold, he snatches away.

Who can hinder him?

Who will ask him, ‘What are you doing?’

13 “God will not withdraw his anger.

The helpers of Rahab stoop under him.

14 How much less shall I answer him,

And choose my words to argue with him?

15 Though I were righteous, yet I wouldn’t answer him.

I would make supplication to my judge.

16 If I had called, and he had answered me,

yet I wouldn’t believe that he listened to my voice.

17 For he breaks me with a storm,

and multiplies my wounds without cause.

18 He will not allow me to catch my breath,

but fills me with bitterness.

19 If it is a matter of strength, behold, he is mighty!

If of justice, ‘Who,’ says he, ‘will summon me?’

20 Though I am righteous, my own mouth shall condemn me.

Though I am blameless, it shall prove me perverse.

21 I am blameless.

I don’t respect myself.

I despise my life.

22 “It is all the same.

Therefore I say he destroys the blameless and the wicked.

23 If the scourge kills suddenly,

he will mock at the trial of the innocent.

24 The earth is given into the hand of the wicked.

He covers the faces of its judges.

If not he, then who is it?

25 “Now my days are swifter than a runner.

They flee away, they see no good.

26 They have passed away as the swift ships,

as the eagle that swoops on the prey.

27 If I say, ‘I will forget my complaint,

I will put off my sad face, and cheer up;’

28 I am afraid of all my sorrows,

I know that you will not hold me innocent.

29 I shall be condemned.

Why then do I labor in vain?

30 If I wash myself with snow,

and cleanse my hands with lye,

31 yet you will plunge me in the ditch.

My own clothes shall abhor me.

32 For he is not a man, as I am, that I should answer him,

that we should come together in judgment.

33 There is no umpire between us,

that might lay his hand on us both.

34 Let him take his rod away from me.

Let his terror not make me afraid;

35 then I would speak, and not fear him,

for I am not so in myself.

Job 10

1 “My soul is weary of my life.

I will give free course to my complaint.

I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.

2 I will tell God, ‘Do not condemn me.

Show me why you contend with me.

3 Is it good to you that you should oppress,

that you should despise the work of your hands,

and smile on the counsel of the wicked?

4 Do you have eyes of flesh?

Or do you see as man sees?

5 Are your days as the days of mortals,

or your years as man’s years,

6 that you inquire after my iniquity,

and search after my sin?

7 Although you know that I am not wicked,

there is no one who can deliver out of your hand.

8 “‘Your hands have framed me and fashioned me altogether,

yet you destroy me.

9 Remember, I beg you, that you have fashioned me as clay.

Will you bring me into dust again?

10 Haven’t you poured me out like milk,

and curdled me like cheese?

11 You have clothed me with skin and flesh,

and knit me together with bones and sinews.

12 You have granted me life and loving kindness.

Your visitation has preserved my spirit.

13 Yet you hid these things in your heart.

I know that this is with you:

14 if I sin, then you mark me.

You will not acquit me from my iniquity.

15 If I am wicked, woe to me.

If I am righteous, I still shall not lift up my head,

being filled with disgrace,

and conscious of my affliction.

16 If my head is held high, you hunt me like a lion.

Again you show yourself powerful to me.

17 You renew your witnesses against me,

and increase your indignation on me.

Changes and warfare are with me.

18 “‘Why, then, have you brought me out of the womb?

I wish I had given up the spirit, and no eye had seen me.

19 I should have been as though I had not been.

I should have been carried from the womb to the grave.

20 Aren’t my days few?

Cease then.

Leave me alone, that I may find a little comfort,

21 before I go where I shall not return from,

to the land of darkness and of the shadow of death;

22 the land dark as midnight,

of the shadow of death,

without any order,

where the light is as midnight.’”

Job 11

1 Then Zophar, the Naamathite, answered,

2 “Shouldn’t the multitude of words be answered?

Should a man full of talk be justified?

3 Should your boastings make men hold their peace?

When you mock, shall no man make you ashamed?

4 For you say, ‘My doctrine is pure.

I am clean in your eyes.’

5 But oh that God would speak,

and open his lips against you,

6 that he would show you the secrets of wisdom!

For true wisdom has two sides.

Know therefore that God exacts of you less than your iniquity deserves.

7 “Can you fathom the mystery of God?

Or can you probe the limits of the Almighty?

8 They are high as heaven. What can you do?

They are deeper than Sheol.[*] What can you know?

9 Its measure is longer than the earth,

and broader than the sea.

10 If he passes by, or confines,

or convenes a court, then who can oppose him?

11 For he knows false men.

He sees iniquity also, even though he doesn’t consider it.

12 An empty-headed man becomes wise

when a man is born as a wild donkey’s colt.

13 “If you set your heart aright,

stretch out your hands toward him.

14 If iniquity is in your hand, put it far away.

Don’t let unrighteousness dwell in your tents.

15 Surely then you shall lift up your face without spot;

Yes, you shall be steadfast, and shall not fear:

16 for you shall forget your misery.

You shall remember it like waters that have passed away.

17 Life shall be clearer than the noonday.

Though there is darkness, it shall be as the morning.

18 You shall be secure, because there is hope.

Yes, you shall search, and shall take your rest in safety.

19 Also you shall lie down, and no one shall make you afraid.

Yes, many shall court your favor.

20 But the eyes of the wicked shall fail.

They shall have no way to flee.

Their hope shall be the giving up of the spirit.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Job 12

1 Then Job answered,

2 “No doubt, but you are the people,

and wisdom shall die with you.

3 But I have understanding as well as you;

I am not inferior to you.

Yes, who doesn’t know such things as these?

4 I am like one who is a joke to his neighbor,

I, who called on God, and he answered.

The just, the blameless man is a joke.

5 In the thought of him who is at ease there is contempt for misfortune.

It is ready for them whose foot slips.

6 The tents of robbers prosper.

Those who provoke God are secure,

who carry their God in their hands.

7 “But ask the animals, now, and they shall teach you;

the birds of the sky, and they shall tell you.

8 Or speak to the earth, and it shall teach you.

The fish of the sea shall declare to you.

9 Who doesn’t know that in all these,

Yahweh’s hand has done this,

10 in whose hand is the life of every living thing,

and the breath of all mankind?

11 Doesn’t the ear try words,

even as the palate tastes its food?

12 With aged men is wisdom,

in length of days understanding.

13 “With God is wisdom and might.

He has counsel and understanding.

14 Behold, he breaks down, and it can’t be built again.

He imprisons a man, and there can be no release.

15 Behold, he withholds the waters, and they dry up.

Again, he sends them out, and they overturn the earth.

16 With him is strength and wisdom.

The deceived and the deceiver are his.

17 He leads counselors away stripped.

He makes judges fools.

18 He loosens the bond of kings.

He binds their waist with a belt.

19 He leads priests away stripped,

and overthrows the mighty.

20 He removes the speech of those who are trusted,

and takes away the understanding of the elders.

21 He pours contempt on princes,

and loosens the belt of the strong.

22 He uncovers deep things out of darkness,

and brings out to light the shadow of death.

23 He increases the nations, and he destroys them.

He enlarges the nations, and he leads them captive.

24 He takes away understanding from the chiefs of the people of the earth,

and causes them to wander in a wilderness where there is no way.

25 They grope in the dark without light.

He makes them stagger like a drunken man.

Job 13

1 “Behold, my eye has seen all this.

My ear has heard and understood it.

2 What you know, I know also.

I am not inferior to you.

3 “Surely I would speak to the Almighty.

I desire to reason with God.

4 But you are forgers of lies.

You are all physicians of no value.

5 Oh that you would be completely silent!

Then you would be wise.

6 Hear now my reasoning.

Listen to the pleadings of my lips.

7 Will you speak unrighteously for God,

and talk deceitfully for him?

8 Will you show partiality to him?

Will you contend for God?

9 Is it good that he should search you out?

Or as one deceives a man, will you deceive him?

10 He will surely reprove you,

if you secretly show partiality.

11 Shall not his majesty make you afraid,

And his dread fall on you?

12 Your memorable sayings are proverbs of ashes,

Your defenses are defenses of clay.

13 “Be silent, leave me alone, that I may speak.

Let come on me what will.

14 Why should I take my flesh in my teeth,

and put my life in my hand?

15 Behold, he will kill me.

I have no hope.

Nevertheless, I will maintain my ways before him.

16 This also shall be my salvation,

that a godless man shall not come before him.

17 Hear diligently my speech.

Let my declaration be in your ears.

18 See now, I have set my cause in order.

I know that I am righteous.

19 Who is he who will contend with me?

For then would I hold my peace and give up the spirit.

20 “Only don’t do two things to me;

then I will not hide myself from your face:

21 withdraw your hand far from me;

and don’t let your terror make me afraid.

22 Then call, and I will answer;

or let me speak, and you answer me.

23 How many are my iniquities and sins?

Make me know my disobedience and my sin.

24 Why hide you your face,

and hold me for your enemy?

25 Will you harass a driven leaf?

Will you pursue the dry stubble?

26 For you write bitter things against me,

and make me inherit the iniquities of my youth:

27 You also put my feet in the stocks,

and mark all my paths.

You set a bound to the soles of my feet,

28 though I am decaying like a rotten thing,

like a garment that is moth-eaten.

Job 14

1 “Man, who is born of a woman,

is of few days, and full of trouble.

2 He grows up like a flower, and is cut down.

He also flees like a shadow, and doesn’t continue.

3 Do you open your eyes on such a one,

and bring me into judgment with you?

4 Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?

Not one.

5 Seeing his days are determined,

the number of his months is with you,

and you have appointed his bounds that he can’t pass;

6 Look away from him, that he may rest,

until he shall accomplish, as a hireling, his day.

7 “For there is hope for a tree,

If it is cut down, that it will sprout again,

that the tender branch of it will not cease.

8 Though its root grows old in the earth,

and its stock dies in the ground,

9 yet through the scent of water it will bud,

and sprout boughs like a plant.

10 But man dies, and is laid low.

Yes, man gives up the spirit, and where is he?

11 As the waters fail from the sea,

and the river wastes and dries up,

12 so man lies down and doesn’t rise.

Until the heavens are no more, they shall not awake,

nor be roused out of their sleep.

13 “Oh that you would hide me in Sheol,[*]

that you would keep me secret, until your wrath is past,

that you would appoint me a set time, and remember me!

14 If a man dies, shall he live again?

All the days of my warfare would I wait,

until my release should come.

15 You would call, and I would answer you.

You would have a desire to the work of your hands.

16 But now you count my steps.

Don’t you watch over my sin?

17 My disobedience is sealed up in a bag.

You fasten up my iniquity.

18 “But the mountain falling comes to nothing.

The rock is removed out of its place;

19 The waters wear the stones.

The torrents of it wash away the dust of the earth.

So you destroy the hope of man.

20 You forever prevail against him, and he departs.

You change his face, and send him away.

21 His sons come to honor, and he doesn’t know it.

They are brought low, but he doesn’t perceive it of them.

22 But his flesh on him has pain,

and his soul within him mourns.”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Job 15

1 Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,

2 “Should a wise man answer with vain knowledge,

and fill himself with the east wind?

3 Should he reason with unprofitable talk,

or with speeches with which he can do no good?

4 Yes, you do away with fear,

and hinder devotion before God.

5 For your iniquity teaches your mouth,

and you choose the language of the crafty.

6 Your own mouth condemns you, and not I.

Yes, your own lips testify against you.

7 “Are you the first man who was born?

Or were you brought out before the hills?

8 Have you heard the secret counsel of God?

Do you limit wisdom to yourself?

9 What do you know, that we don’t know?

What do you understand, which is not in us?

10 With us are both the gray-headed and the very aged men,

much elder than your father.

11 Are the consolations of God too small for you,

even the word that is gentle toward you?

12 Why does your heart carry you away?

Why do your eyes flash,

13 That you turn your spirit against God,

and let such words go out of your mouth?

14 What is man, that he should be clean?

What is he who is born of a woman, that he should be righteous?

15 Behold, he puts no trust in his holy ones.

Yes, the heavens are not clean in his sight;

16 how much less one who is abominable and corrupt,

a man who drinks iniquity like water!

17 “I will show you, listen to me;

that which I have seen I will declare

18 (which wise men have told by their fathers,

and have not hidden it;

19 to whom alone the land was given,

and no stranger passed among them):

20 the wicked man writhes in pain all his days,

even the number of years that are laid up for the oppressor.

21 A sound of terrors is in his ears.

In prosperity the destroyer shall come on him.

22 He doesn’t believe that he shall return out of darkness.

He is waited for by the sword.

23 He wanders abroad for bread, saying, ‘Where is it?’

He knows that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.

24 Distress and anguish make him afraid.

They prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle.

25 Because he has stretched out his hand against God,

and behaves himself proudly against the Almighty;

26 he runs at him with a stiff neck,

with the thick shields of his bucklers;

27 because he has covered his face with his fatness,

and gathered fat on his thighs.

28 He has lived in desolate cities,

in houses which no one inhabited,

which were ready to become heaps.

29 He shall not be rich, neither shall his substance continue,

neither shall their possessions be extended on the earth.

30 He shall not depart out of darkness.

The flame shall dry up his branches.

By the breath of God’s mouth shall he go away.

31 Let him not trust in emptiness, deceiving himself;

for emptiness shall be his reward.

32 It shall be accomplished before his time.

His branch shall not be green.

33 He shall shake off his unripe grape as the vine,

and shall cast off his flower as the olive tree.

34 For the company of the godless shall be barren,

and fire shall consume the tents of bribery.

35 They conceive mischief, and produce iniquity.

Their heart prepares deceit.”

Job 16

1 Then Job answered,

2 “I have heard many such things.

You are all miserable comforters!

3 Shall vain words have an end?

Or what provokes you that you answer?

4 I also could speak as you do.

If your soul were in my soul’s place,

I could join words together against you,

and shake my head at you,

5 but I would strengthen you with my mouth.

The solace of my lips would relieve you.

6 “Though I speak, my grief is not subsided.

Though I forbear, what am I eased?

7 But now, God, you have surely worn me out.

You have made desolate all my company.

8 You have shriveled me up. This is a witness against me.

My leanness rises up against me.

It testifies to my face.

9 He has torn me in his wrath, and persecuted me.

He has gnashed on me with his teeth.

My adversary sharpens his eyes on me.

10 They have gaped on me with their mouth.

They have struck me on the cheek reproachfully.

They gather themselves together against me.

11 God delivers me to the ungodly,

and casts me into the hands of the wicked.

12 I was at ease, and he broke me apart.

Yes, he has taken me by the neck, and dashed me to pieces.

He has also set me up for his target.

13 His archers surround me.

He splits my kidneys apart, and does not spare.

He pours out my gall on the ground.

14 He breaks me with breach on breach.

He runs on me like a giant.

15 I have sewed sackcloth on my skin,

and have thrust my horn in the dust.

16 My face is red with weeping.

Deep darkness is on my eyelids.

17 Although there is no violence in my hands,

and my prayer is pure.

18 “Earth, don’t cover my blood.

Let my cry have no place to rest.

19 Even now, behold, my witness is in heaven.

He who vouches for me is on high.

20 My friends scoff at me.

My eyes pour out tears to God,

21 that he would maintain the right of a man with God,

of a son of man with his neighbor!

22 For when a few years have come,

I shall go the way of no return.

Job 17

1 “My spirit is consumed.

My days are extinct,

And the grave is ready for me.

2 Surely there are mockers with me.

My eye dwells on their provocation.

3 “Now give a pledge, be collateral for me with yourself.

Who is there who will strike hands with me?

4 For you have hidden their heart from understanding,

Therefore you shall not exalt them.

5 He who denounces his friends for plunder,

Even the eyes of his children shall fail.

6 “But he has made me a byword of the people.

They spit in my face.

7 My eye also is dim by reason of sorrow.

All my members are as a shadow.

8 Upright men shall be astonished at this.

The innocent shall stir up himself against the godless.

9 Yet shall the righteous hold on his way.

He who has clean hands shall grow stronger and stronger.

10 But as for you all, come on now again;

I shall not find a wise man among you.

11 My days are past, my plans are broken off,

as are the thoughts of my heart.

12 They change the night into day,

saying ‘The light is near’ in the presence of darkness.

13 If I look for Sheol[*] as my house,

if I have spread my couch in the darkness,

14 If I have said to corruption, ‘You are my father;’

to the worm, ‘My mother,’ and ‘my sister;’

15 where then is my hope?

as for my hope, who shall see it?

16 Shall it go down with me to the gates of Sheol,[*]

or descend together into the dust?”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Job 18

1 Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,

2 “How long will you hunt for words?

Consider, and afterwards we will speak.

3 Why are we counted as animals,

which have become unclean in your sight?

4 You who tear yourself in your anger,

shall the earth be forsaken for you?

Or shall the rock be removed out of its place?

5 “Yes, the light of the wicked shall be put out,

The spark of his fire shall not shine.

6 The light shall be dark in his tent.

His lamp above him shall be put out.

7 The steps of his strength shall be shortened.

His own counsel shall cast him down.

8 For he is cast into a net by his own feet,

and he wanders into its mesh.

9 A snare will take him by the heel.

A trap will catch him.

10 A noose is hidden for him in the ground,

a trap for him on the path.

11 Terrors shall make him afraid on every side,

and shall chase him at his heels.

12 His strength shall be famished.

Calamity shall be ready at his side.

13 The members of his body shall be devoured.

The firstborn of death shall devour his members.

14 He shall be rooted out of the security of his tent.

He shall be brought to the king of terrors.

15 There shall dwell in his tent that which is none of his.

Sulfur shall be scattered on his habitation.

16 His roots shall be dried up beneath.

Above shall his branch be cut off.

17 His memory shall perish from the earth.

He shall have no name in the street.

18 He shall be driven from light into darkness,

and chased out of the world.

19 He shall have neither son nor grandson among his people,

nor any remaining where he lived.

20 Those who come after shall be astonished at his day,

as those who went before were frightened.

21 Surely such are the dwellings of the unrighteous.

This is the place of him who doesn’t know God.”

Job 19

1 Then Job answered,

2 “How long will you torment me,

and crush me with words?

3 You have reproached me ten times.

You aren’t ashamed that you attack me.

4 If it is true that I have erred,

my error remains with myself.

5 If indeed you will magnify yourselves against me,

and plead against me my reproach;

6 know now that God has subverted me,

and has surrounded me with his net.

7 “Behold, I cry out of wrong, but I am not heard.

I cry for help, but there is no justice.

8 He has walled up my way so that I can’t pass,

and has set darkness in my paths.

9 He has stripped me of my glory,

and taken the crown from my head.

10 He has broken me down on every side, and I am gone.

My hope he has plucked up like a tree.

11 He has also kindled his wrath against me.

He counts me among his adversaries.

12 His troops come on together,

build a siege ramp against me,

and encamp around my tent.

13 “He has put my brothers far from me.

My acquaintances are wholly estranged from me.

14 My relatives have gone away.

My familiar friends have forgotten me.

15 Those who dwell in my house and my maids consider me a stranger.

I am an alien in their sight.

16 I call to my servant, and he gives me no answer.

I beg him with my mouth.

17 My breath is offensive to my wife.

I am loathsome to the children of my own mother.

18 Even young children despise me.

If I arise, they speak against me.

19 All my familiar friends abhor me.

They whom I loved have turned against me.

20 My bones stick to my skin and to my flesh.

I have escaped by the skin of my teeth.

21 “Have pity on me, have pity on me, you my friends;

for the hand of God has touched me.

22 Why do you persecute me as God,

and are not satisfied with my flesh?

23 “Oh that my words were now written!

Oh that they were inscribed in a book!

24 That with an iron pen and lead

they were engraved in the rock forever!

25 But as for me, I know that my Redeemer lives.

In the end, he will stand upon the earth.

26 After my skin is destroyed,

then in my flesh shall I see God,

27 Whom I, even I, shall see on my side.

My eyes shall see, and not as a stranger.

“My heart is consumed within me.

28 If you say, ‘How we will persecute him!’

because the root of the matter is found in me,

29 be afraid of the sword,

for wrath brings the punishments of the sword,

that you may know there is a judgment.”

Job 20

1 Then Zophar the Naamathite answered,

2 “Therefore do my thoughts give answer to me,

even by reason of my haste that is in me.

3 I have heard the reproof which puts me to shame.

The spirit of my understanding answers me.

4 Don’t you know this from old time,

since man was placed on earth,

5 that the triumphing of the wicked is short,

the joy of the godless but for a moment?

6 Though his height mount up to the heavens,

and his head reach to the clouds,

7 yet he shall perish forever like his own dung.

Those who have seen him shall say, ‘Where is he?’

8 He shall fly away as a dream, and shall not be found.

Yes, he shall be chased away like a vision of the night.

9 The eye which saw him shall see him no more,

neither shall his place any more see him.

10 His children shall seek the favor of the poor.

His hands shall give back his wealth.

11 His bones are full of his youth,

but youth shall lie down with him in the dust.

12 “Though wickedness is sweet in his mouth,

though he hide it under his tongue,

13 though he spare it, and will not let it go,

but keep it still within his mouth;

14 yet his food in his bowels is turned.

It is cobra venom within him.

15 He has swallowed down riches, and he shall vomit them up again.

God will cast them out of his belly.

16 He shall suck cobra venom.

The viper’s tongue shall kill him.

17 He shall not look at the rivers,

the flowing streams of honey and butter.

18 That for which he labored he shall restore, and shall not swallow it down.

According to the substance that he has gotten, he shall not rejoice.

19 For he has oppressed and forsaken the poor.

He has violently taken away a house, and he shall not build it up.

20 “Because he knew no quietness within him,

he shall not save anything of that in which he delights.

21 There was nothing left that he didn’t devour,

therefore his prosperity shall not endure.

22 In the fullness of his sufficiency, distress shall overtake him.

The hand of everyone who is in misery shall come on him.

23 When he is about to fill his belly, God will cast the fierceness of his wrath on him.

It will rain on him while he is eating.

24 He shall flee from the iron weapon.

The bronze arrow shall strike him through.

25 He draws it out, and it comes out of his body.

Yes, the glittering point comes out of his liver.

Terrors are on him.

26 All darkness is laid up for his treasures.

An unfanned fire shall devour him.

It shall consume that which is left in his tent.

27 The heavens shall reveal his iniquity.

The earth shall rise up against him.

28 The increase of his house shall depart.

They shall rush away in the day of his wrath.

29 This is the portion of a wicked man from God,

the heritage appointed to him by God.”

Job 21

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Listen diligently to my speech.

Let this be your consolation.

3 Allow me, and I also will speak;

After I have spoken, mock on.

4 As for me, is my complaint to man?

Why shouldn’t I be impatient?

5 Look at me, and be astonished.

Lay your hand on your mouth.

6 When I remember, I am troubled.

Horror takes hold of my flesh.

7 “Why do the wicked live,

become old, yes, and grow mighty in power?

8 Their child is established with them in their sight,

their offspring before their eyes.

9 Their houses are safe from fear,

neither is the rod of God upon them.

10 Their bulls breed without fail.

Their cows calve, and don’t miscarry.

11 They send out their little ones like a flock.

Their children dance.

12 They sing to the tambourine and harp,

and rejoice at the sound of the pipe.

13 They spend their days in prosperity.

In an instant they go down to Sheol.[*]

14 They tell God, ‘Depart from us,

for we don’t want to know about your ways.

15 What is the Almighty, that we should serve him?

What profit should we have, if we pray to him?’

16 Behold, their prosperity is not in their hand.

The counsel of the wicked is far from me.

17 “How often is it that the lamp of the wicked is put out,

that their calamity comes on them,

that God distributes sorrows in his anger?

18 How often is it that they are as stubble before the wind,

as chaff that the storm carries away?

19 You say, ‘God lays up his iniquity for his children.’

Let him recompense it to himself, that he may know it.

20 Let his own eyes see his destruction.

Let him drink of the wrath of the Almighty.

21 For what does he care for his house after him,

when the number of his months is cut off?

22 “Shall any teach God knowledge,

since he judges those who are high?

23 One dies in his full strength,

being wholly at ease and quiet.

24 His pails are full of milk.

The marrow of his bones is moistened.

25 Another dies in bitterness of soul,

and never tastes of good.

26 They lie down alike in the dust.

The worm covers them.

27 “Behold, I know your thoughts,

the devices with which you would wrong me.

28 For you say, ‘Where is the house of the prince?

Where is the tent in which the wicked lived?’

29 Haven’t you asked wayfaring men?

Don’t you know their evidences,

30 that the evil man is reserved to the day of calamity,

That they are led out to the day of wrath?

31 Who shall declare his way to his face?

Who shall repay him what he has done?

32 Yet he will be borne to the grave.

Men shall keep watch over the tomb.

33 The clods of the valley shall be sweet to him.

All men shall draw after him,

as there were innumerable before him.

34 So how can you comfort me with nonsense,

because in your answers there remains only falsehood?”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Job 22

1 Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,

2 “Can a man be profitable to God?

Surely he who is wise is profitable to himself.

3 Is it any pleasure to the Almighty, that you are righteous?

Or does it benefit him, that you make your ways perfect?

4 Is it for your piety that he reproves you,

that he enters with you into judgment?

5 Isn’t your wickedness great?

Neither is there any end to your iniquities.

6 For you have taken pledges from your brother for nothing,

and stripped the naked of their clothing.

7 You haven’t given water to the weary to drink,

and you have withheld bread from the hungry.

8 But as for the mighty man, he had the earth.

The honorable man, he lived in it.

9 You have sent widows away empty,

and the arms of the fatherless have been broken.

10 Therefore snares are around you.

Sudden fear troubles you,

11 or darkness, so that you can not see,

and floods of waters cover you.

12 “Isn’t God in the heights of heaven?

See the height of the stars, how high they are!

13 You say, ‘What does God know?

Can he judge through the thick darkness?

14 Thick clouds are a covering to him, so that he doesn’t see.

He walks on the vault of the sky.’

15 Will you keep the old way,

which wicked men have trodden,

16 who were snatched away before their time,

whose foundation was poured out as a stream,

17 who said to God, ‘Depart from us;’

and, ‘What can the Almighty do for us?’

18 Yet he filled their houses with good things,

but the counsel of the wicked is far from me.

19 The righteous see it, and are glad.

The innocent ridicule them,

20 saying, ‘Surely those who rose up against us are cut off.

The fire has consumed their remnant.’

21 “Acquaint yourself with him, now, and be at peace.

Thereby good shall come to you.

22 Please receive instruction from his mouth,

and lay up his words in your heart.

23 If you return to the Almighty, you shall be built up,

if you put away unrighteousness far from your tents.

24 Lay your treasure in the dust,

the gold of Ophir among the stones of the brooks.

25 The Almighty will be your treasure,

and precious silver to you.

26 For then you will delight yourself in the Almighty,

and shall lift up your face to God.

27 You shall make your prayer to him, and he will hear you.

You shall pay your vows.

28 You shall also decree a thing, and it shall be established to you.

Light shall shine on your ways.

29 When they cast down, you shall say, ‘be lifted up.’

He will save the humble person.

30 He will even deliver him who is not innocent.

Yes, he shall be delivered through the cleanness of your hands.”

Job 23

1 Then Job answered,

2 “Even today my complaint is rebellious.

His hand is heavy in spite of my groaning.

3 Oh that I knew where I might find him!

That I might come even to his seat!

4 I would set my cause in order before him,

and fill my mouth with arguments.

5 I would know the words which he would answer me,

and understand what he would tell me.

6 Would he contend with me in the greatness of his power?

No, but he would listen to me.

7 There the upright might reason with him,

so I should be delivered forever from my judge.

8 “If I go east, he is not there;

if west, I can’t find him;

9 He works to the north, but I can’t see him.

He turns south, but I can’t catch a glimpse of him.

10 But he knows the way that I take.

When he has tried me, I shall come out like gold.

11 My foot has held fast to his steps.

I have kept his way, and not turned aside.

12 I haven’t gone back from the commandment of his lips.

I have treasured up the words of his mouth more than my necessary food.

13 But he stands alone, and who can oppose him?

What his soul desires, even that he does.

14 For he performs that which is appointed for me.

Many such things are with him.

15 Therefore I am terrified at his presence.

When I consider, I am afraid of him.

16 For God has made my heart faint.

The Almighty has terrified me.

17 Because I was not cut off before the darkness,

neither did he cover the thick darkness from my face.

Job 24

1 “Why aren’t times laid up by the Almighty?

Why don’t those who know him see his days?

2 There are people who remove the landmarks.

They violently take away flocks, and feed them.

3 They drive away the donkey of the fatherless,

and they take the widow’s ox for a pledge.

4 They turn the needy out of the way.

The poor of the earth all hide themselves.

5 Behold, as wild donkeys in the desert,

they go out to their work, seeking diligently for food.

The wilderness yields them bread for their children.

6 They cut their food in the field.

They glean the vineyard of the wicked.

7 They lie all night naked without clothing,

and have no covering in the cold.

8 They are wet with the showers of the mountains,

and embrace the rock for lack of a shelter.

9 There are those who pluck the fatherless from the breast,

and take a pledge of the poor,

10 So that they go around naked without clothing.

Being hungry, they carry the sheaves.

11 They make oil within the walls of these men.

They tread wine presses, and suffer thirst.

12 From out of the populous city, men groan.

The soul of the wounded cries out,

yet God doesn’t regard the folly.

13 “These are of those who rebel against the light.

They don’t know its ways,

nor stay in its paths.

14 The murderer rises with the light.

He kills the poor and needy.

In the night he is like a thief.

15 The eye also of the adulterer waits for the twilight,

saying, ‘No eye shall see me.’

He disguises his face.

16 In the dark they dig through houses.

They shut themselves up in the daytime.

They don’t know the light.

17 For the morning is to all of them like thick darkness,

for they know the terrors of the thick darkness.

18 “They are foam on the surface of the waters.

Their portion is cursed in the earth.

They don’t turn into the way of the vineyards.

19 Drought and heat consume the snow waters,

so does Sheol[*] those who have sinned.

20 The womb shall forget him.

The worm shall feed sweetly on him.

He shall be no more remembered.

Unrighteousness shall be broken as a tree.

21 He devours the barren who don’t bear.

He shows no kindness to the widow.

22 Yet God preserves the mighty by his power.

He rises up who has no assurance of life.

23 God gives them security, and they rest in it.

His eyes are on their ways.

24 They are exalted; yet a little while, and they are gone.

Yes, they are brought low, they are taken out of the way as all others,

and are cut off as the tops of the ears of grain.

25 If it isn’t so now, who will prove me a liar,

and make my speech worth nothing?”

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Job 26

1 Then Job answered,

2 “How have you helped him who is without power!

How have you saved the arm that has no strength!

3 How have you counseled him who has no wisdom,

and plentifully declared sound knowledge!

4 To whom have you uttered words?

Whose spirit came out of you?

5 “The departed spirits tremble,

those beneath the waters and all that live in them.

6 Sheol[*] is naked before God,

and Abaddon[*] has no covering.

7 He stretches out the north over empty space,

and hangs the earth on nothing.

8 He binds up the waters in his thick clouds,

and the cloud is not burst under them.

9 He encloses the face of his throne,

and spreads his cloud on it.

10 He has described a boundary on the surface of the waters,

and to the confines of light and darkness.

11 The pillars of heaven tremble

and are astonished at his rebuke.

12 He stirs up the sea with his power,

and by his understanding he strikes through Rahab.

13 By his Spirit the heavens are garnished.

His hand has pierced the swift serpent.

14 Behold, these are but the outskirts of his ways.

How small a whisper do we hear of him!

But the thunder of his power who can understand?”

Sheol is the lower world or the grave.

Abaddon means Destroyer.

Job 27

1 Job again took up his parable, and said,

2 “As God lives, who has taken away my right,

the Almighty, who has made my soul bitter

3 (for the length of my life is still in me,

and the spirit of God is in my nostrils);

4 surely my lips shall not speak unrighteousness,

neither shall my tongue utter deceit.

5 Far be it from me that I should justify you.

Until I die I will not put away my integrity from me.

6 I hold fast to my righteousness, and will not let it go.

My heart shall not reproach me so long as I live.

7 “Let my enemy be as the wicked.

Let him who rises up against me be as the unrighteous.

8 For what is the hope of the godless, when he is cut off, when God takes away his life?

9 Will God hear his cry when trouble comes on him?

10 Will he delight himself in the Almighty,

and call on God at all times?

11 I will teach you about the hand of God.

That which is with the Almighty will I not conceal.

12 Behold, all of you have seen it yourselves;

why then have you become altogether vain?

13 “This is the portion of a wicked man with God,

the heritage of oppressors, which they receive from the Almighty.

14 If his children are multiplied, it is for the sword.

His offspring shall not be satisfied with bread.

15 Those who remain of him shall be buried in death.

His widows shall make no lamentation.

16 Though he heap up silver as the dust,

and prepare clothing as the clay;

17 he may prepare it, but the just shall put it on,

and the innocent shall divide the silver.

18 He builds his house as the moth,

as a booth which the watchman makes.

19 He lies down rich, but he shall not do so again.

He opens his eyes, and he is not.

20 Terrors overtake him like waters.

A storm steals him away in the night.

21 The east wind carries him away, and he departs.

It sweeps him out of his place.

22 For it hurls at him, and does not spare,

as he flees away from his hand.

23 Men shall clap their hands at him,

and shall hiss him out of his place.

Job 28

1 “Surely there is a mine for silver,

and a place for gold which they refine.

2 Iron is taken out of the earth,

and copper is smelted out of the ore.

3 Man sets an end to darkness,

and searches out, to the furthest bound,

the stones of obscurity and of thick darkness.

4 He breaks open a shaft away from where people live.

They are forgotten by the foot.

They hang far from men, they swing back and forth.

5 As for the earth, out of it comes bread;

Underneath it is turned up as it were by fire.

6 Sapphires come from its rocks.

It has dust of gold.

7 That path no bird of prey knows,

neither has the falcon’s eye seen it.

8 The proud animals have not trodden it,

nor has the fierce lion passed by there.

9 He puts his hand on the flinty rock,

and he overturns the mountains by the roots.

10 He cuts out channels among the rocks.

His eye sees every precious thing.

11 He binds the streams that they don’t trickle.

The thing that is hidden he brings out to light.

12 “But where shall wisdom be found?

Where is the place of understanding?

13 Man doesn’t know its price;

Neither is it found in the land of the living.

14 The deep says, ‘It isn’t in me.’

The sea says, ‘It isn’t with me.’

15 It can’t be gotten for gold,

neither shall silver be weighed for its price.

16 It can’t be valued with the gold of Ophir,

with the precious onyx, or the sapphire.[*]

17 Gold and glass can’t equal it,

neither shall it be exchanged for jewels of fine gold.

18 No mention shall be made of coral or of crystal.

Yes, the price of wisdom is above rubies.

19 The topaz of Ethiopia shall not equal it,

Neither shall it be valued with pure gold.

20 Where then does wisdom come from?

Where is the place of understanding?

21 Seeing it is hidden from the eyes of all living,

and kept close from the birds of the sky.

22 Destruction and Death say,

‘We have heard a rumor of it with our ears.’

23 “God understands its way,

and he knows its place.

24 For he looks to the ends of the earth,

and sees under the whole sky.

25 He establishes the force of the wind.

Yes, he measures out the waters by measure.

26 When he made a decree for the rain,

and a way for the lightning of the thunder;

27 then he saw it, and declared it.

He established it, yes, and searched it out.

28 To man he said,

‘Behold, the fear of the Lord,[*] that is wisdom.

To depart from evil is understanding.’”

or, lapis lazuli

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Job 29

1 Job again took up his parable, and said,

2 “Oh that I were as in the months of old,

as in the days when God watched over me;

3 when his lamp shone on my head,

and by his light I walked through darkness,

4 as I was in the ripeness of my days,

when the friendship of God was in my tent,

5 when the Almighty was yet with me,

and my children were around me,

6 when my steps were washed with butter,

and the rock poured out streams of oil for me,

7 when I went out to the city gate,

when I prepared my seat in the street.

8 The young men saw me and hid themselves.

The aged rose up and stood.

9 The princes refrained from talking,

and laid their hand on their mouth.

10 The voice of the nobles was hushed,

and their tongue stuck to the roof of their mouth.

11 For when the ear heard me, then it blessed me;

and when the eye saw me, it commended me:

12 Because I delivered the poor who cried,

and the fatherless also, who had no one to help him,

13 the blessing of him who was ready to perish came on me,

and I caused the widow’s heart to sing for joy.

14 I put on righteousness, and it clothed me.

My justice was as a robe and a diadem.

15 I was eyes to the blind,

and feet to the lame.

16 I was a father to the needy.

The cause of him who I didn’t know, I searched out.

17 I broke the jaws of the unrighteous,

and plucked the prey out of his teeth.

18 Then I said, ‘I shall die in my own house,

I shall count my days as the sand.

19 My root is spread out to the waters.

The dew lies all night on my branch.

20 My glory is fresh in me.

My bow is renewed in my hand.’

21 “Men listened to me, waited,

and kept silence for my counsel.

22 After my words they didn’t speak again.

My speech fell on them.

23 They waited for me as for the rain.

Their mouths drank as with the spring rain.

24 I smiled on them when they had no confidence.

They didn’t reject the light of my face.

25 I chose out their way, and sat as chief.

I lived as a king in the army,

as one who comforts the mourners.

Job 30

1 “But now those who are younger than I have me in derision,

whose fathers I would have disdained to put with my sheep dogs.

2 Of what use is the strength of their hands to me,

men in whom ripe age has perished?

3 They are gaunt from lack and famine.

They gnaw the dry ground, in the gloom of waste and desolation.

4 They pluck salt herbs by the bushes.

The roots of the broom are their food.

5 They are driven out from among men.

They cry after them as after a thief;

6 So that they dwell in frightful valleys,

and in holes of the earth and of the rocks.

7 Among the bushes they bray;

and under the nettles they are gathered together.

8 They are children of fools, yes, children of base men.

They were flogged out of the land.

9 “Now I have become their song.

Yes, I am a byword to them.

10 They abhor me, they stand aloof from me,

and don’t hesitate to spit in my face.

11 For he has untied his cord, and afflicted me;

and they have thrown off restraint before me.

12 On my right hand rise the rabble.

They thrust aside my feet,

They cast up against me their ways of destruction.

13 They mar my path,

They set forward my calamity,

without anyone’s help.

14 As through a wide breach they come,

in the middle of the ruin they roll themselves in.

15 Terrors have turned on me.

They chase my honor as the wind.

My welfare has passed away as a cloud.

16 “Now my soul is poured out within me.

Days of affliction have taken hold on me.

17 In the night season my bones are pierced in me,

and the pains that gnaw me take no rest.

18 By great force is my garment disfigured.

It binds me about as the collar of my coat.

19 He has cast me into the mire.

I have become like dust and ashes.

20 I cry to you, and you do not answer me.

I stand up, and you gaze at me.

21 You have turned to be cruel to me.

With the might of your hand you persecute me.

22 You lift me up to the wind, and drive me with it.

You dissolve me in the storm.

23 For I know that you will bring me to death,

To the house appointed for all living.

24 “However doesn’t one stretch out a hand in his fall?

Or in his calamity therefore cry for help?

25 Didn’t I weep for him who was in trouble?

Wasn’t my soul grieved for the needy?

26 When I looked for good, then evil came;

When I waited for light, there came darkness.

27 My heart is troubled, and doesn’t rest.

Days of affliction have come on me.

28 I go mourning without the sun.

I stand up in the assembly, and cry for help.

29 I am a brother to jackals,

and a companion to ostriches.

30 My skin grows black and peels from me.

My bones are burned with heat.

31 Therefore my harp has turned to mourning,

and my pipe into the voice of those who weep.

Job 31

1 “I made a covenant with my eyes,

how then should I look lustfully at a young woman?

2 For what is the portion from God above,

and the heritage from the Almighty on high?

3 Is it not calamity to the unrighteous,

and disaster to the workers of iniquity?

4 Doesn’t he see my ways,

and count all my steps?

5 “If I have walked with falsehood,

and my foot has hurried to deceit

6 (let me be weighed in an even balance,

that God may know my integrity);

7 if my step has turned out of the way,

if my heart walked after my eyes,

if any defilement has stuck to my hands,

8 then let me sow, and let another eat.

Yes, let the produce of my field be rooted out.

9 “If my heart has been enticed to a woman,

and I have laid wait at my neighbor’s door,

10 then let my wife grind for another,

and let others sleep with her.

11 For that would be a heinous crime.

Yes, it would be an iniquity to be punished by the judges:

12 For it is a fire that consumes to destruction,

and would root out all my increase.

13 “If I have despised the cause of my male servant

or of my female servant,

when they contended with me;

14 What then shall I do when God rises up?

When he visits, what shall I answer him?

15 Didn’t he who made me in the womb make him?

Didn’t one fashion us in the womb?

16 “If I have withheld the poor from their desire,

or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail,

17 or have eaten my morsel alone,

and the fatherless has not eaten of it

18 (no, from my youth he grew up with me as with a father,

her I have guided from my mother’s womb);

19 if I have seen any perish for want of clothing,

or that the needy had no covering;

20 if his heart hasn’t blessed me,

if he hasn’t been warmed with my sheep’s fleece;

21 if I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless,

because I saw my help in the gate,

22 then let my shoulder fall from the shoulder blade,

and my arm be broken from the bone.

23 For calamity from God is a terror to me.

Because his majesty, I can do nothing.

24 “If I have made gold my hope,

and have said to the fine gold, ‘You are my confidence;’

25 If I have rejoiced because my wealth was great,

and because my hand had gotten much;

26 if I have seen the sun when it shined,

or the moon moving in splendor,

27 and my heart has been secretly enticed,

and my hand threw a kiss from my mouth,

28 this also would be an iniquity to be punished by the judges;

for I should have denied the God who is above.

29 “If I have rejoiced at the destruction of him who hated me,

or lifted up myself when evil found him

30 (yes, I have not allowed my mouth to sin

by asking his life with a curse);

31 if the men of my tent have not said,

‘Who can find one who has not been filled with his meat?’

32 (the foreigner has not camped in the street,

but I have opened my doors to the traveler);

33 if like Adam I have covered my transgressions,

by hiding my iniquity in my heart,

34 because I feared the great multitude,

and the contempt of families terrified me,

so that I kept silence, and didn’t go out of the door—

35 oh that I had one to hear me!

Behold, here is my signature! Let the Almighty answer me!

Let the accuser write my indictment!

36 Surely I would carry it on my shoulder;

and I would bind it to me as a crown.

37 I would declare to him the number of my steps.

as a prince would I go near to him.

38 If my land cries out against me,

and its furrows weep together;

39 if I have eaten its fruits without money,

or have caused its owners to lose their life,

40 let briers grow instead of wheat,

and stinkweed instead of barley.”

The words of Job are ended.

Job 32

1 So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he was righteous in his own eyes. 2 Then the wrath of Elihu the son of Barachel, the Buzite, of the family of Ram, was kindled against Job. His wrath was kindled because he justified himself rather than God. 3 Also his wrath was kindled against his three friends, because they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job. 4 Now Elihu had waited to speak to Job, because they were elder than he. 5 When Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of these three men, his wrath was kindled.

6 Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered,

“I am young, and you are very old;

Therefore I held back, and didn’t dare show you my opinion.

7 I said, ‘Days should speak,

and multitude of years should teach wisdom.’

8 But there is a spirit in man,

and the breath of the Almighty gives them understanding.

9 It is not the great who are wise,

nor the aged who understand justice.

10 Therefore I said, ‘Listen to me;

I also will show my opinion.’

11 “Behold, I waited for your words,

and I listened for your reasoning,

while you searched out what to say.

12 Yes, I gave you my full attention,

but there was no one who convinced Job,

or who answered his words, among you.

13 Beware lest you say, ‘We have found wisdom,

God may refute him, not man;’

14 for he has not directed his words against me;

neither will I answer him with your speeches.

15 “They are amazed. They answer no more.

They don’t have a word to say.

16 Shall I wait, because they don’t speak,

because they stand still, and answer no more?

17 I also will answer my part,

and I also will show my opinion.

18 For I am full of words.

The spirit within me constrains me.

19 Behold, my breast is as wine which has no vent;

like new wineskins it is ready to burst.

20 I will speak, that I may be refreshed.

I will open my lips and answer.

21 Please don’t let me respect any man’s person,

neither will I give flattering titles to any man.

22 For I don’t know how to give flattering titles;

or else my Maker would soon take me away.

Job 33

1 “However, Job, please hear my speech,

and listen to all my words.

2 See now, I have opened my mouth.

My tongue has spoken in my mouth.

3 My words shall utter the uprightness of my heart.

That which my lips know they shall speak sincerely.

4 The Spirit of God has made me,

and the breath of the Almighty gives me life.

5 If you can, answer me.

Set your words in order before me, and stand up.

6 Behold, I am toward God even as you are.

I am also formed out of the clay.

7 Behold, my terror shall not make you afraid,

neither shall my pressure be heavy on you.

8 “Surely you have spoken in my hearing,

I have heard the voice of your words, saying,

9 ‘I am clean, without disobedience.

I am innocent, neither is there iniquity in me.

10 Behold, he finds occasions against me.

He counts me for his enemy.

11 He puts my feet in the stocks.

He marks all my paths.’

12 “Behold, I will answer you. In this you are not just,

for God is greater than man.

13 Why do you strive against him,

because he doesn’t give account of any of his matters?

14 For God speaks once,

yes twice, though man pays no attention.

15 In a dream, in a vision of the night,

when deep sleep falls on men,

in slumbering on the bed;

16 Then he opens the ears of men,

and seals their instruction,

17 That he may withdraw man from his purpose,

and hide pride from man.

18 He keeps back his soul from the pit,

and his life from perishing by the sword.

19 He is chastened also with pain on his bed,

with continual strife in his bones;

20 So that his life abhors bread,

and his soul dainty food.

21 His flesh is so consumed away, that it can’t be seen.

His bones that were not seen stick out.

22 Yes, his soul draws near to the pit,

and his life to the destroyers.

23 “If there is beside him an angel,

an interpreter, one among a thousand,

to show to man what is right for him;

24 then God is gracious to him, and says,

‘Deliver him from going down to the pit,

I have found a ransom.’

25 His flesh shall be fresher than a child’s.

He returns to the days of his youth.

26 He prays to God, and he is favorable to him,

so that he sees his face with joy.

He restores to man his righteousness.

27 He sings before men, and says,

‘I have sinned, and perverted that which was right,

and it didn’t profit me.

28 He has redeemed my soul from going into the pit.

My life shall see the light.’

29 “Behold, God does all these things,

twice, yes three times, with a man,

30 to bring back his soul from the pit,

that he may be enlightened with the light of the living.

31 Mark well, Job, and listen to me.

Hold your peace, and I will speak.

32 If you have anything to say, answer me.

Speak, for I desire to justify you.

33 If not, listen to me.

Hold your peace, and I will teach you wisdom.”

Job 34

1 Moreover Elihu answered,

2 “Hear my words, you wise men.

Give ear to me, you who have knowledge.

3 For the ear tries words,

as the palate tastes food.

4 Let us choose for us that which is right.

Let us know among ourselves what is good.

5 For Job has said, ‘I am righteous,

God has taken away my right:

6 Notwithstanding my right I am considered a liar.

My wound is incurable, though I am without disobedience.’

7 What man is like Job,

who drinks scorn like water,

8 Who goes in company with the workers of iniquity,

and walks with wicked men?

9 For he has said, ‘It profits a man nothing

that he should delight himself with God.’

10 “Therefore listen to me, you men of understanding:

far be it from God, that he should do wickedness,

from the Almighty, that he should commit iniquity.

11 For the work of a man he will render to him,

and cause every man to find according to his ways.

12 Yes surely, God will not do wickedly,

neither will the Almighty pervert justice.

13 Who put him in charge of the earth?

or who has appointed him over the whole world?

14 If he set his heart on himself,

If he gathered to himself his spirit and his breath,

15 all flesh would perish together,

and man would turn again to dust.

16 “If now you have understanding, hear this.

Listen to the voice of my words.

17 Shall even one who hates justice govern?

Will you condemn him who is righteous and mighty?—

18 Who says to a king, ‘Vile!’

or to nobles, ‘Wicked!’?

19 Who doesn’t respect the persons of princes,

nor respects the rich more than the poor;

for they all are the work of his hands.

20 In a moment they die, even at midnight.

The people are shaken and pass away.

The mighty are taken away without a hand.

21 “For his eyes are on the ways of a man.

He sees all his goings.

22 There is no darkness, nor thick gloom,

where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves.

23 For he doesn’t need to consider a man further,

that he should go before God in judgment.

24 He breaks in pieces mighty men in ways past finding out,

and sets others in their place.

25 Therefore he takes knowledge of their works.

He overturns them in the night, so that they are destroyed.

26 He strikes them as wicked men

in the open sight of others;

27 because they turned aside from following him,

and wouldn’t pay attention to any of his ways,

28 so that they caused the cry of the poor to come to him.

He heard the cry of the afflicted.

29 When he gives quietness, who then can condemn?

When he hides his face, who then can see him?

Alike whether to a nation, or to a man,

30 that the godless man may not reign,

that there be no one to ensnare the people.

31 “For has any said to God,

‘I am guilty, but I will not offend any more.

32 Teach me that which I don’t see.

If I have done iniquity, I will do it no more’?

33 Shall his recompense be as you desire, that you refuse it?

For you must choose, and not I.

Therefore speak what you know.

34 Men of understanding will tell me,

yes, every wise man who hears me:

35 ‘Job speaks without knowledge.

His words are without wisdom.’

36 I wish that Job were tried to the end,

because of his answering like wicked men.

37 For he adds rebellion to his sin.

He claps his hands among us,

and multiplies his words against God.”

Job 35

1 Moreover Elihu answered,

2 “Do you think this to be your right,

or do you say, ‘My righteousness is more than God’s,’

3 That you ask, ‘What advantage will it be to you?

What profit shall I have, more than if I had sinned?’

4 I will answer you,

and your companions with you.

5 Look to the heavens, and see.

See the skies, which are higher than you.

6 If you have sinned, what effect do you have against him?

If your transgressions are multiplied, what do you do to him?

7 If you are righteous, what do you give him?

Or what does he receive from your hand?

8 Your wickedness may hurt a man as you are,

and your righteousness may profit a son of man.

9 “By reason of the multitude of oppressions they cry out.

They cry for help by reason of the arm of the mighty.

10 But no one says, ‘Where is God my Maker,

who gives songs in the night,

11 who teaches us more than the animals of the earth,

and makes us wiser than the birds of the sky?’

12 There they cry, but no one gives answer,

because of the pride of evil men.

13 Surely God will not hear an empty cry,

neither will the Almighty regard it.

14 How much less when you say you don’t see him.

The cause is before him, and you wait for him!

15 But now, because he has not visited in his anger,

neither does he greatly regard arrogance.

16 Therefore Job opens his mouth with empty talk,

and he multiplies words without knowledge.”

Job 36

1 Elihu also continued, and said,

2 “Bear with me a little, and I will show you;

for I still have something to say on God’s behalf.

3 I will get my knowledge from afar,

and will ascribe righteousness to my Maker.

4 For truly my words are not false.

One who is perfect in knowledge is with you.

5 “Behold, God is mighty, and doesn’t despise anyone.

He is mighty in strength of understanding.

6 He doesn’t preserve the life of the wicked,

but gives to the afflicted their right.

7 He doesn’t withdraw his eyes from the righteous,

but with kings on the throne,

he sets them forever, and they are exalted.

8 If they are bound in fetters,

and are taken in the cords of afflictions,

9 then he shows them their work,

and their transgressions, that they have behaved themselves proudly.

10 He also opens their ears to instruction,

and commands that they return from iniquity.

11 If they listen and serve him,

they shall spend their days in prosperity,

and their years in pleasures.

12 But if they don’t listen, they shall perish by the sword;

they shall die without knowledge.

13 “But those who are godless in heart lay up anger.

They don’t cry for help when he binds them.

14 They die in youth.

Their life perishes among the unclean.

15 He delivers the afflicted by their affliction,

and opens their ear in oppression.

16 Yes, he would have allured you out of distress,

into a wide place, where there is no restriction.

That which is set on your table would be full of fatness.

17 “But you are full of the judgment of the wicked.

Judgment and justice take hold of you.

18 Don’t let riches entice you to wrath,

neither let the great size of a bribe turn you aside.

19 Would your wealth sustain you in distress,

or all the might of your strength?

20 Don’t desire the night,

when people are cut off in their place.

21 Take heed, don’t regard iniquity;

for you have chosen this rather than affliction.

22 Behold, God is exalted in his power.

Who is a teacher like him?

23 Who has prescribed his way for him?

Or who can say, ‘You have committed unrighteousness?’

24 “Remember that you magnify his work,

whereof men have sung.

25 All men have looked on it.

Man sees it afar off.

26 Behold, God is great, and we don’t know him.

The number of his years is unsearchable.

27 For he draws up the drops of water,

which distill in rain from his vapor,

28 Which the skies pour down

and which drop on man abundantly.

29 Yes, can any understand the spreading of the clouds,

and the thunderings of his pavilion?

30 Behold, he spreads his light around him.

He covers the bottom of the sea.

31 For by these he judges the people.

He gives food in abundance.

32 He covers his hands with the lightning,

and commands it to strike the mark.

33 Its noise tells about him,

and the livestock also concerning the storm that comes up.

Job 37

1 “Yes, at this my heart trembles,

and is moved out of its place.

2 Hear, oh, hear the noise of his voice,

the sound that goes out of his mouth.

3 He sends it out under the whole sky,

and his lightning to the ends of the earth.

4 After it a voice roars.

He thunders with the voice of his majesty.

He doesn’t hold back anything when his voice is heard.

5 God thunders marvelously with his voice.

He does great things, which we can’t comprehend.

6 For he says to the snow, ‘Fall on the earth;’

likewise to the shower of rain,

and to the showers of his mighty rain.

7 He seals up the hand of every man,

that all men whom he has made may know it.

8 Then the animals take cover,

and remain in their dens.

9 Out of its room comes the storm,

and cold out of the north.

10 By the breath of God, ice is given,

and the width of the waters is frozen.

11 Yes, he loads the thick cloud with moisture.

He spreads abroad the cloud of his lightning.

12 It is turned around by his guidance,

that they may do whatever he commands them

on the surface of the habitable world,

13 Whether it is for correction, or for his land,

or for loving kindness, that he causes it to come.

14 “Listen to this, Job.

Stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God.

15 Do you know how God controls them,

and causes the lightning of his cloud to shine?

16 Do you know the workings of the clouds,

the wondrous works of him who is perfect in knowledge?

17 You whose clothing is warm,

when the earth is still by reason of the south wind?

18 Can you, with him, spread out the sky,

which is strong as a cast metal mirror?

19 Teach us what we shall tell him,

for we can’t make our case by reason of darkness.

20 Will it be told him that I would speak?

Or should a man wish that he were swallowed up?

21 Now men don’t see the light which is bright in the skies,

but the wind passes, and clears them.

22 Out of the north comes golden splendor.

With God is awesome majesty.

23 We can’t reach the Almighty.

He is exalted in power.

In justice and great righteousness, he will not oppress.

24 Therefore men revere him.

He doesn’t regard any who are wise of heart.”

Job 38

1 Then Yahweh answered Job out of the whirlwind,

2 “Who is this who darkens counsel

by words without knowledge?

3 Brace yourself like a man,

for I will question you, then you answer me!

4 “Where were you when I laid the foundations of the earth?

Declare, if you have understanding.

5 Who determined its measures, if you know?

Or who stretched the line on it?

6 Whereupon were its foundations fastened?

Or who laid its cornerstone,

7 when the morning stars sang together,

and all the sons of God shouted for joy?

8 “Or who shut up the sea with doors,

when it broke out of the womb,

9 when I made clouds its garment,

and wrapped it in thick darkness,

10 marked out for it my bound,

set bars and doors,

11 and said, ‘Here you may come, but no further.

Here your proud waves shall be stayed?’

12 “Have you commanded the morning in your days,

and caused the dawn to know its place;

13 that it might take hold of the ends of the earth,

and shake the wicked out of it?

14 It is changed as clay under the seal,

and presented as a garment.

15 From the wicked, their light is withheld.

The high arm is broken.

16 “Have you entered into the springs of the sea?

Or have you walked in the recesses of the deep?

17 Have the gates of death been revealed to you?

Or have you seen the gates of the shadow of death?

18 Have you comprehended the earth in its width?

Declare, if you know it all.

19 “What is the way to the dwelling of light?

As for darkness, where is its place,

20 that you should take it to its bound,

that you should discern the paths to its house?

21 Surely you know, for you were born then,

and the number of your days is great!

22 Have you entered the treasuries of the snow,

or have you seen the treasures of the hail,

23 which I have reserved against the time of trouble,

against the day of battle and war?

24 By what way is the lightning distributed,

or the east wind scattered on the earth?

25 Who has cut a channel for the flood water,

or the path for the thunderstorm;

26 To cause it to rain on a land where no man is;

on the wilderness, in which there is no man;

27 to satisfy the waste and desolate ground,

to cause the tender grass to grow?

28 Does the rain have a father?

Or who fathers the drops of dew?

29 Out of whose womb came the ice?

The gray frost of the sky, who has given birth to it?

30 The waters become hard like stone,

when the surface of the deep is frozen.

31 “Can you bind the cluster of the Pleiades,

or loosen the cords of Orion?

32 Can you lead the constellations out in their season?

Or can you guide the Bear with her cubs?

33 Do you know the laws of the heavens?

Can you establish its dominion over the earth?

34 “Can you lift up your voice to the clouds,

That abundance of waters may cover you?

35 Can you send out lightnings, that they may go?

Do they report to you, ‘Here we are?’

36 Who has put wisdom in the inward parts?

Or who has given understanding to the mind?

37 Who can count the clouds by wisdom?

Or who can pour out the bottles of the sky,

38 when the dust runs into a mass,

and the clods of earth stick together?

39 “Can you hunt the prey for the lioness,

or satisfy the appetite of the young lions,

40 when they crouch in their dens,

and lie in wait in the thicket?

41 Who provides for the raven his prey,

when his young ones cry to God,

and wander for lack of food?

Job 39

1 “Do you know the time when the mountain goats give birth?

Do you watch when the doe bears fawns?

2 Can you count the months that they fulfill?

Or do you know the time when they give birth?

3 They bow themselves, they bear their young.

They end their labor pains.

4 Their young ones become strong.

They grow up in the open field.

They go out, and don’t return again.

5 “Who has set the wild donkey free?

Or who has loosened the bonds of the swift donkey,

6 Whose home I have made the wilderness,

and the salt land his dwelling place?

7 He scorns the tumult of the city,

neither does he hear the shouting of the driver.

8 The range of the mountains is his pasture,

He searches after every green thing.

9 “Will the wild ox be content to serve you?

Or will he stay by your feeding trough?

10 Can you hold the wild ox in the furrow with his harness?

Or will he till the valleys after you?

11 Will you trust him, because his strength is great?

Or will you leave to him your labor?

12 Will you confide in him, that he will bring home your seed,

and gather the grain of your threshing floor?

13 “The wings of the ostrich wave proudly;

but are they the feathers and plumage of love?

14 For she leaves her eggs on the earth,

warms them in the dust,

15 and forgets that the foot may crush them,

or that the wild animal may trample them.

16 She deals harshly with her young ones, as if they were not hers.

Though her labor is in vain, she is without fear,

17 because God has deprived her of wisdom,

neither has he imparted to her understanding.

18 When she lifts up herself on high,

she scorns the horse and his rider.

19 “Have you given the horse might?

Have you clothed his neck with a quivering mane?

20 Have you made him to leap as a locust?

The glory of his snorting is awesome.

21 He paws in the valley, and rejoices in his strength.

He goes out to meet the armed men.

22 He mocks at fear, and is not dismayed,

neither does he turn back from the sword.

23 The quiver rattles against him,

the flashing spear and the javelin.

24 He eats up the ground with fierceness and rage,

neither does he stand still at the sound of the trumpet.

25 As often as the trumpet sounds he snorts, ‘Aha!’

He smells the battle afar off,

the thunder of the captains, and the shouting.

26 “Is it by your wisdom that the hawk soars,

and stretches her wings toward the south?

27 Is it at your command that the eagle mounts up,

and makes his nest on high?

28 On the cliff he dwells, and makes his home,

on the point of the cliff, and the stronghold.

29 From there he spies out the prey.

His eyes see it afar off.

30 His young ones also suck up blood.

Where the slain are, there he is.”

Job 40

1 Moreover Yahweh answered Job,

2 “Shall he who argues contend with the Almighty?

He who argues with God, let him answer it.”

3 Then Job answered Yahweh,

4 “Behold, I am of small account. What shall I answer you?

I lay my hand on my mouth.

5 I have spoken once, and I will not answer;

Yes, twice, but I will proceed no further.”

6 Then Yahweh answered Job out of the whirlwind,

7 “Now brace yourself like a man.

I will question you, and you will answer me.

8 Will you even annul my judgment?

Will you condemn me, that you may be justified?

9 Or do you have an arm like God?

Can you thunder with a voice like him?

10 “Now deck yourself with excellency and dignity.

Array yourself with honor and majesty.

11 Pour out the fury of your anger.

Look at everyone who is proud, and bring him low.

12 Look at everyone who is proud, and humble him.

Crush the wicked in their place.

13 Hide them in the dust together.

Bind their faces in the hidden place.

14 Then I will also admit to you

that your own right hand can save you.

15 “See now, behemoth, which I made as well as you.

He eats grass as an ox.

16 Look now, his strength is in his thighs.

His force is in the muscles of his belly.

17 He moves his tail like a cedar.

The sinews of his thighs are knit together.

18 His bones are like tubes of brass.

His limbs are like bars of iron.

19 He is the chief of the ways of God.

He who made him gives him his sword.

20 Surely the mountains produce food for him,

where all the animals of the field play.

21 He lies under the lotus trees,

in the covert of the reed, and the marsh.

22 The lotuses cover him with their shade.

The willows of the brook surround him.

23 Behold, if a river overflows, he doesn’t tremble.

He is confident, though the Jordan swells even to his mouth.

24 Shall any take him when he is on the watch,

or pierce through his nose with a snare?

Job 41

1 “Can you draw out Leviathan[*] with a fish hook,

or press down his tongue with a cord?

2 Can you put a rope into his nose,

or pierce his jaw through with a hook?

3 Will he make many petitions to you,

or will he speak soft words to you?

4 Will he make a covenant with you,

that you should take him for a servant forever?

5 Will you play with him as with a bird?

Or will you bind him for your girls?

6 Will traders barter for him?

Will they part him among the merchants?

7 Can you fill his skin with barbed irons,

or his head with fish spears?

8 Lay your hand on him.

Remember the battle, and do so no more.

9 Behold, the hope of him is in vain.

Won’t one be cast down even at the sight of him?

10 None is so fierce that he dare stir him up.

Who then is he who can stand before me?

11 Who has first given to me, that I should repay him?

Everything under the heavens is mine.

12 “I will not keep silence concerning his limbs,

nor his mighty strength, nor his goodly frame.

13 Who can strip off his outer garment?

Who shall come within his jaws?

14 Who can open the doors of his face?

Around his teeth is terror.

15 Strong scales are his pride,

shut up together with a close seal.

16 One is so near to another,

that no air can come between them.

17 They are joined to one another.

They stick together, so that they can’t be pulled apart.

18 His sneezing flashes out light.

His eyes are like the eyelids of the morning.

19 Out of his mouth go burning torches.

Sparks of fire leap out.

20 Out of his nostrils a smoke goes,

as of a boiling pot over a fire of reeds.

21 His breath kindles coals.

A flame goes out of his mouth.

22 There is strength in his neck.

Terror dances before him.

23 The flakes of his flesh are joined together.

They are firm on him.

They can’t be moved.

24 His heart is as firm as a stone,

yes, firm as the lower millstone.

25 When he raises himself up, the mighty are afraid.

They retreat before his thrashing.

26 If one attacks him with the sword, it can’t prevail;

nor the spear, the dart, nor the pointed shaft.

27 He counts iron as straw;

and brass as rotten wood.

28 The arrow can’t make him flee.

Sling stones are like chaff to him.

29 Clubs are counted as stubble.

He laughs at the rushing of the javelin.

30 His undersides are like sharp potsherds,

leaving a trail in the mud like a threshing sledge.

31 He makes the deep to boil like a pot.

He makes the sea like a pot of ointment.

32 He makes a path shine after him.

One would think the deep had white hair.

33 On earth there is not his equal,

that is made without fear.

34 He sees everything that is high.

He is king over all the sons of pride.”

Leviathan is a name for a crocodile or similar creature.

Job 42

1 Then Job answered Yahweh,

2 “I know that you can do all things,

and that no purpose of yours can be restrained.

3 You asked, ‘Who is this who hides counsel without knowledge?’

therefore I have uttered that which I did not understand,

things too wonderful for me, which I didn’t know.

4 You said, ‘Listen, now, and I will speak;

I will question you, and you will answer me.’

5 I had heard of you by the hearing of the ear,

but now my eye sees you.

6 Therefore I abhor myself,

and repent in dust and ashes.”

7 It was so, that after Yahweh had spoken these words to Job, Yahweh said to Eliphaz the Temanite, “My wrath is kindled against you, and against your two friends; for you have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job has. 8 Now therefore, take to yourselves seven bulls and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray for you, for I will accept him, that I not deal with you according to your folly. For you have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as my servant Job has.”

9 So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the Naamathite went, and did what Yahweh commanded them, and Yahweh accepted Job.

10 Yahweh turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his friends. Yahweh gave Job twice as much as he had before. 11 Then came there to him all his brothers, and all his sisters, and all those who had been of his acquaintance before, and ate bread with him in his house. They comforted him, and consoled him concerning all the evil that Yahweh had brought on him. Everyone also gave him a piece of money,[*] and everyone a ring of gold.

12 So Yahweh blessed the latter end of Job more than his beginning. He had fourteen thousand sheep, six thousand camels, one thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand female donkeys. 13 He had also seven sons and three daughters. 14 He called the name of the first, Jemimah; and the name of the second, Keziah; and the name of the third, Keren Happuch. 15 In all the land were no women found so beautiful as the daughters of Job. Their father gave them an inheritance among their brothers. 16 After this Job lived one hundred forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons’ sons, to four generations. 17 So Job died, being old and full of days.

literally, kesitah, a unit of money, probably silver

Psalms 2

1 Why do the nations rage,

and the peoples plot a vain thing?

2 The kings of the earth take a stand,

and the rulers take counsel together,

against Yahweh, and against his Anointed,[*] saying,

3 “Let’s break their bonds apart,

and cast their cords from us.”

4 He who sits in the heavens will laugh.

The Lord[*] will have them in derision.

5 Then he will speak to them in his anger,

and terrify them in his wrath:

6 “Yet I have set my King on my holy hill of Zion.”

7 I will tell of the decree.

Yahweh said to me, “You are my son.

Today I have become your father.

8 Ask of me, and I will give the nations for your inheritance,

the uttermost parts of the earth for your possession.

9 You shall break them with a rod of iron.

You shall dash them in pieces like a potter’s vessel.”

10 Now therefore be wise, you kings.

Be instructed, you judges of the earth.

11 Serve Yahweh with fear,

and rejoice with trembling.

12 Give sincere homage to the Son,[*] lest he be angry, and you perish on the way,

for his wrath will soon be kindled.

Blessed are all those who take refuge in him.

The word “Anointed” is the same as the word for “Messiah” or “Christ”

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

or, Kiss the son

Psalms 5

1 Give ear to my words, Yahweh.

Consider my meditation.

2 Listen to the voice of my cry, my King and my God;

for to you do I pray.

3 Yahweh, in the morning you shall hear my voice.

In the morning I will lay my requests before you, and will watch expectantly.

4 For you are not a God who has pleasure in wickedness.

Evil can’t live with you.

5 The arrogant shall not stand in your sight.

You hate all workers of iniquity.

6 You will destroy those who speak lies.

Yahweh abhors the bloodthirsty and deceitful man.

7 But as for me, in the abundance of your loving kindness I will come into your house.

I will bow toward your holy temple in reverence of you.

8 Lead me, Yahweh, in your righteousness because of my enemies.

Make your way straight before my face.

9 For there is no faithfulness in their mouth.

Their heart is destruction.

Their throat is an open tomb.

They flatter with their tongue.

10 Hold them guilty, God.

Let them fall by their own counsels;

Thrust them out in the multitude of their transgressions,

for they have rebelled against you.

11 But let all those who take refuge in you rejoice,

Let them always shout for joy, because you defend them.

Let them also who love your name be joyful in you.

12 For you will bless the righteous.

Yahweh, you will surround him with favor as with a shield.

Psalms 7

1 Yahweh, my God, I take refuge in you.

Save me from all those who pursue me, and deliver me,

2 lest they tear apart my soul like a lion,

ripping it in pieces, while there is no one to deliver.

3 Yahweh, my God, if I have done this,

if there is iniquity in my hands,

4 if I have rewarded evil to him who was at peace with me

(yes, if I have delivered him who without cause was my adversary),

5 let the enemy pursue my soul, and overtake it;

yes, let him tread my life down to the earth,

and lay my glory in the dust. Selah.

6 Arise, Yahweh, in your anger.

Lift up yourself against the rage of my adversaries.

Awake for me. You have commanded judgment.

7 Let the congregation of the peoples surround you.

Rule over them on high.

8 Yahweh administers judgment to the peoples.

Judge me, Yahweh, according to my righteousness,

and to my integrity that is in me.

9 Oh let the wickedness of the wicked come to an end,

but establish the righteous;

their minds and hearts are searched by the righteous God.

10 My shield is with God,

who saves the upright in heart.

11 God is a righteous judge,

yes, a God who has indignation every day.

12 If a man doesn’t relent, he will sharpen his sword;

he has bent and strung his bow.

13 He has also prepared for himself the instruments of death.

He makes ready his flaming arrows.

14 Behold,[*] he travails with iniquity.

Yes, he has conceived mischief,

and brought out falsehood.

15 He has dug a hole,

and has fallen into the pit which he made.

16 The trouble he causes shall return to his own head.

His violence shall come down on the crown of his own head.

17 I will give thanks to Yahweh according to his righteousness,

and will sing praise to the name of Yahweh Most High.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Psalms 9

1 I will give thanks to Yahweh with my whole heart.

I will tell of all your marvelous works.

2 I will be glad and rejoice in you.

I will sing praise to your name, O Most High.

3 When my enemies turn back,

they stumble and perish in your presence.

4 For you have maintained my just cause.

You sit on the throne judging righteously.

5 You have rebuked the nations.

You have destroyed the wicked.

You have blotted out their name forever and ever.

6 The enemy is overtaken by endless ruin.

The very memory of the cities which you have overthrown has perished.

7 But Yahweh reigns forever.

He has prepared his throne for judgment.

8 He will judge the world in righteousness.

He will administer judgment to the peoples in uprightness.

9 Yahweh will also be a high tower for the oppressed;

a high tower in times of trouble.

10 Those who know your name will put their trust in you,

for you, Yahweh, have not forsaken those who seek you.

11 Sing praises to Yahweh, who dwells in Zion,

and declare among the people what he has done.

12 For he who avenges blood remembers them.

He doesn’t forget the cry of the afflicted.

13 Have mercy on me, Yahweh.

See my affliction by those who hate me,

and lift me up from the gates of death;

14 that I may show all of your praise.

In the gates of the daughter of Zion, I will rejoice in your salvation.

15 The nations have sunk down in the pit that they made.

In the net which they hid, their own foot is taken.

16 Yahweh has made himself known.

He has executed judgment.

The wicked is snared by the work of his own hands. Meditation. Selah.

17 The wicked shall be turned back to Sheol,[*]

even all the nations that forget God.

18 For the needy shall not always be forgotten,

nor the hope of the poor perish forever.

19 Arise, Yahweh! Don’t let man prevail.

Let the nations be judged in your sight.

20 Put them in fear, Yahweh.

Let the nations know that they are only men. Selah.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 10

1 Why do you stand far off, Yahweh?

Why do you hide yourself in times of trouble?

2 In arrogance, the wicked hunt down the weak.

They are caught in the schemes that they devise.

3 For the wicked boasts of his heart’s cravings.

He blesses the greedy, and condemns Yahweh.

4 The wicked, in the pride of his face,

has no room in his thoughts for God.

5 His ways are prosperous at all times.

He is haughty, and your laws are far from his sight.

As for all his adversaries, he sneers at them.

6 He says in his heart, “I shall not be shaken.

For generations I shall have no trouble.”

7 His mouth is full of cursing, deceit, and oppression.

Under his tongue is mischief and iniquity.

8 He lies in wait near the villages.

From ambushes, he murders the innocent.

His eyes are secretly set against the helpless.

9 He lurks in secret as a lion in his ambush.

He lies in wait to catch the helpless.

He catches the helpless, when he draws him in his net.

10 The helpless are crushed.

They collapse.

They fall under his strength.

11 He says in his heart, “God has forgotten.

He hides his face.

He will never see it.”

12 Arise, Yahweh!

God, lift up your hand!

Don’t forget the helpless.

13 Why does the wicked person condemn God,

and say in his heart, “God won’t call me into account?”

14 But you do see trouble and grief.

You consider it to take it into your hand.

You help the victim and the fatherless.

15 Break the arm of the wicked.

As for the evil man, seek out his wickedness until you find none.

16 Yahweh is King forever and ever!

The nations will perish out of his land.

17 Yahweh, you have heard the desire of the humble.

You will prepare their heart.

You will cause your ear to hear,

18 to judge the fatherless and the oppressed,

that man who is of the earth may terrify no more.

Psalms 16

1 Preserve me, God, for in you do I take refuge.

2 My soul, you have said to Yahweh, “You are my Lord.

Apart from you I have no good thing.”

3 As for the saints who are in the earth,

they are the excellent ones in whom is all my delight.

4 Their sorrows shall be multiplied who give gifts to another god.

Their drink offerings of blood I will not offer,

nor take their names on my lips.

5 Yahweh assigned my portion and my cup.

You made my lot secure.

6 The lines have fallen to me in pleasant places.

Yes, I have a good inheritance.

7 I will bless Yahweh, who has given me counsel.

Yes, my heart instructs me in the night seasons.

8 I have set Yahweh always before me.

Because he is at my right hand, I shall not be moved.

9 Therefore my heart is glad, and my tongue rejoices.

My body shall also dwell in safety.

10 For you will not leave my soul in Sheol,[*]

neither will you allow your holy one to see corruption.

11 You will show me the path of life.

In your presence is fullness of joy.

In your right hand there are pleasures forever more.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 17

1 Hear, Yahweh, my righteous plea;

Give ear to my prayer, that doesn’t go out of deceitful lips.

2 Let my sentence come out of your presence.

Let your eyes look on equity.

3 You have proved my heart.

You have visited me in the night.

You have tried me, and found nothing.

I have resolved that my mouth shall not disobey.

4 As for the deeds of men, by the word of your lips,

I have kept myself from the ways of the violent.

5 My steps have held fast to your paths.

My feet have not slipped.

6 I have called on you, for you will answer me, God.

Turn your ear to me.

Hear my speech.

7 Show your marvelous loving kindness,

you who save those who take refuge by your right hand from their enemies.

8 Keep me as the apple of your eye.

Hide me under the shadow of your wings,

9 from the wicked who oppress me,

my deadly enemies, who surround me.

10 They close up their callous hearts.

With their mouth they speak proudly.

11 They have now surrounded us in our steps.

They set their eyes to cast us down to the earth.

12 He is like a lion that is greedy of his prey,

as it were a young lion lurking in secret places.

13 Arise, Yahweh, confront him.

Cast him down.

Deliver my soul from the wicked by your sword;

14 from men by your hand, Yahweh,

from men of the world, whose portion is in this life.

You fill the belly of your cherished ones.

Your sons have plenty,

and they store up wealth for their children.

15 As for me, I shall see your face in righteousness.

I shall be satisfied, when I awake, with seeing your form.

Psalms 18

1 I love you, Yahweh, my strength.

2 Yahweh is my rock, my fortress, and my deliverer;

my God, my rock, in whom I take refuge;

my shield, and the horn of my salvation, my high tower.

3 I call on Yahweh, who is worthy to be praised;

and I am saved from my enemies.

4 The cords of death surrounded me.

The floods of ungodliness made me afraid.

5 The cords of Sheol[*] were around me.

The snares of death came on me.

6 In my distress I called on Yahweh,

and cried to my God.

He heard my voice out of his temple.

My cry before him came into his ears.

7 Then the earth shook and trembled.

The foundations also of the mountains quaked and were shaken,

because he was angry.

8 Smoke went out of his nostrils.

Consuming fire came out of his mouth.

Coals were kindled by it.

9 He bowed the heavens also, and came down.

Thick darkness was under his feet.

10 He rode on a cherub, and flew.

Yes, he soared on the wings of the wind.

11 He made darkness his hiding place, his pavilion around him,

darkness of waters, thick clouds of the skies.

12 At the brightness before him his thick clouds passed,

hailstones and coals of fire.

13 Yahweh also thundered in the sky.

The Most High uttered his voice:

hailstones and coals of fire.

14 He sent out his arrows, and scattered them;

Yes, great lightning bolts, and routed them.

15 Then the channels of waters appeared.

The foundations of the world were laid bare at your rebuke, Yahweh,

at the blast of the breath of your nostrils.

16 He sent from on high.

He took me.

He drew me out of many waters.

17 He delivered me from my strong enemy,

from those who hated me; for they were too mighty for me.

18 They came on me in the day of my calamity,

but Yahweh was my support.

19 He brought me out also into a large place.

He delivered me, because he delighted in me.

20 Yahweh has rewarded me according to my righteousness.

According to the cleanness of my hands has he recompensed me.

21 For I have kept the ways of Yahweh,

and have not wickedly departed from my God.

22 For all his ordinances were before me.

I didn’t put away his statutes from me.

23 I was also blameless with him.

I kept myself from my iniquity.

24 Therefore Yahweh has rewarded me according to my righteousness,

according to the cleanness of my hands in his eyesight.

25 With the merciful you will show yourself merciful.

With the perfect man, you will show yourself perfect.

26 With the pure, you will show yourself pure.

With the crooked you will show yourself shrewd.

27 For you will save the afflicted people,

but the haughty eyes you will bring down.

28 For you will light my lamp, Yahweh.

My God will light up my darkness.

29 For by you, I advance through a troop.

By my God, I leap over a wall.

30 As for God, his way is perfect.

Yahweh’s word is tried.

He is a shield to all those who take refuge in him.

31 For who is God, except Yahweh?

Who is a rock, besides our God,

32 the God who arms me with strength, and makes my way perfect?

33 He makes my feet like deer’s feet,

and sets me on my high places.

34 He teaches my hands to war,

so that my arms bend a bow of bronze.

35 You have also given me the shield of your salvation.

Your right hand sustains me.

Your gentleness has made me great.

36 You have enlarged my steps under me,

My feet have not slipped.

37 I will pursue my enemies, and overtake them.

Neither will I turn again until they are consumed.

38 I will strike them through, so that they will not be able to rise.

They shall fall under my feet.

39 For you have armed me with strength to the battle.

You have subdued under me those who rose up against me.

40 You have also made my enemies turn their backs to me,

that I might cut off those who hate me.

41 They cried, but there was no one to save;

even to Yahweh, but he didn’t answer them.

42 Then I beat them small as the dust before the wind.

I cast them out as the mire of the streets.

43 You have delivered me from the strivings of the people.

You have made me the head of the nations.

A people whom I have not known shall serve me.

44 As soon as they hear of me they shall obey me.

The foreigners shall submit themselves to me.

45 The foreigners shall fade away,

and shall come trembling out of their close places.

46 Yahweh lives; and blessed be my rock.

Exalted be the God of my salvation,

47 even the God who executes vengeance for me,

and subdues peoples under me.

48 He rescues me from my enemies.

Yes, you lift me up above those who rise up against me.

You deliver me from the violent man.

49 Therefore I will give thanks to you, Yahweh, among the nations,

and will sing praises to your name.

50 He gives great deliverance to his king,

and shows loving kindness to his anointed,

to David and to his offspring,[*] forever more.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

or, seed

Psalms 19

1 The heavens declare the glory of God.

The expanse shows his handiwork.

2 Day after day they pour out speech,

and night after night they display knowledge.

3 There is no speech nor language,

where their voice is not heard.

4 Their voice has gone out through all the earth,

their words to the end of the world.

In them he has set a tent for the sun,

5 which is as a bridegroom coming out of his room,

like a strong man rejoicing to run his course.

6 His going out is from the end of the heavens,

his circuit to its ends;

There is nothing hidden from its heat.

7 Yahweh’s law is perfect, restoring the soul.

Yahweh’s testimony is sure, making wise the simple.

8 Yahweh’s precepts are right, rejoicing the heart.

Yahweh’s commandment is pure, enlightening the eyes.

9 The fear of Yahweh is clean, enduring forever.

Yahweh’s ordinances are true, and righteous altogether.

10 More to be desired are they than gold, yes, than much fine gold;

sweeter also than honey and the extract of the honeycomb.

11 Moreover by them is your servant warned.

In keeping them there is great reward.

12 Who can discern his errors?

Forgive me from hidden errors.

13 Keep back your servant also from presumptuous sins.

Let them not have dominion over me.

Then I will be upright.

I will be blameless and innocent of great transgression.

14 Let the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart

be acceptable in your sight,

Yahweh, my rock, and my redeemer.

Psalms 21

1 The king rejoices in your strength, Yahweh!

How greatly he rejoices in your salvation!

2 You have given him his heart’s desire,

and have not withheld the request of his lips. Selah.

3 For you meet him with the blessings of goodness.

You set a crown of fine gold on his head.

4 He asked life of you, you gave it to him,

even length of days forever and ever.

5 His glory is great in your salvation.

You lay honor and majesty on him.

6 For you make him most blessed forever.

You make him glad with joy in your presence.

7 For the king trusts in Yahweh.

Through the loving kindness of the Most High, he shall not be moved.

8 Your hand will find out all of your enemies.

Your right hand will find out those who hate you.

9 You will make them as a fiery furnace in the time of your anger.

Yahweh will swallow them up in his wrath.

The fire shall devour them.

10 You will destroy their descendants from the earth,

their posterity from among the children of men.

11 For they intended evil against you.

They plotted evil against you which cannot succeed.

12 For you will make them turn their back,

when you aim drawn bows at their face.

13 Be exalted, Yahweh, in your strength,

so we will sing and praise your power.

Psalms 22

1 My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?

Why are you so far from helping me, and from the words of my groaning?

2 My God, I cry in the daytime, but you don’t answer;

in the night season, and am not silent.

3 But you are holy,

you who inhabit the praises of Israel.

4 Our fathers trusted in you.

They trusted, and you delivered them.

5 They cried to you, and were delivered.

They trusted in you, and were not disappointed.

6 But I am a worm, and no man;

a reproach of men, and despised by the people.

7 All those who see me mock me.

They insult me with their lips. They shake their heads, saying,

8 “He trusts in Yahweh;

let him deliver him.

Let him rescue him, since he delights in him.”

9 But you brought me out of the womb.

You made me trust while at my mother’s breasts.

10 I was thrown on you from my mother’s womb.

You are my God since my mother bore me.

11 Don’t be far from me, for trouble is near.

For there is no one to help.

12 Many bulls have surrounded me.

Strong bulls of Bashan have encircled me.

13 They open their mouths wide against me,

lions tearing prey and roaring.

14 I am poured out like water.

All my bones are out of joint.

My heart is like wax;

it is melted within me.

15 My strength is dried up like a potsherd.

My tongue sticks to the roof of my mouth.

You have brought me into the dust of death.

16 For dogs have surrounded me.

A company of evildoers have enclosed me.

They have pierced my hands and feet.[*]

17 I can count all of my bones.

They look and stare at me.

18 They divide my garments among them.

They cast lots for my clothing.

19 But don’t be far off, Yahweh.

You are my help: hurry to help me.

20 Deliver my soul from the sword,

my precious life from the power of the dog.

21 Save me from the lion’s mouth!

Yes, from the horns of the wild oxen, you have answered me.

22 I will declare your name to my brothers.

Among the assembly, I will praise you.

23 You who fear Yahweh, praise him!

All you descendants of Jacob, glorify him!

Stand in awe of him, all you descendants of Israel!

24 For he has not despised nor abhorred the affliction of the afflicted,

Neither has he hidden his face from him;

but when he cried to him, he heard.

25 Of you comes my praise in the great assembly.

I will pay my vows before those who fear him.

26 The humble shall eat and be satisfied.

They shall praise Yahweh who seek after him.

Let your hearts live forever.

27 All the ends of the earth shall remember and turn to Yahweh.

All the relatives of the nations shall worship before you.

28 For the kingdom is Yahweh’s.

He is the ruler over the nations.

29 All the rich ones of the earth shall eat and worship.

All those who go down to the dust shall bow before him,

even he who can’t keep his soul alive.

30 Posterity shall serve him.

Future generations shall be told about the Lord.

31 They shall come and shall declare his righteousness to a people that shall be born,

for he has done it.

So Dead Sea Scrolls. Masoretic Text reads, “Like a lion, they pin my hands and feet.”

Psalms 25

1 To you, Yahweh, do I lift up my soul.

2 My God, I have trusted in you.

Don’t let me be shamed.

Don’t let my enemies triumph over me.

3 Yes, no one who waits for you shall be shamed.

They shall be shamed who deal treacherously without cause.

4 Show me your ways, Yahweh.

Teach me your paths.

5 Guide me in your truth, and teach me,

For you are the God of my salvation,

I wait for you all day long.

6 Yahweh, remember your tender mercies and your loving kindness,

for they are from old times.

7 Don’t remember the sins of my youth, nor my transgressions.

Remember me according to your loving kindness,

for your goodness’ sake, Yahweh.

8 Good and upright is Yahweh,

therefore he will instruct sinners in the way.

9 He will guide the humble in justice.

He will teach the humble his way.

10 All the paths of Yahweh are loving kindness and truth

to such as keep his covenant and his testimonies.

11 For your name’s sake, Yahweh,

pardon my iniquity, for it is great.

12 What man is he who fears Yahweh?

He shall instruct him in the way that he shall choose.

13 His soul shall dwell at ease.

His offspring[*] shall inherit the land.

14 The friendship of Yahweh is with those who fear him.

He will show them his covenant.

15 My eyes are ever on Yahweh,

for he will pluck my feet out of the net.

16 Turn to me, and have mercy on me,

for I am desolate and afflicted.

17 The troubles of my heart are enlarged.

Oh bring me out of my distresses.

18 Consider my affliction and my travail.

Forgive all my sins.

19 Consider my enemies, for they are many.

They hate me with cruel hatred.

20 Oh keep my soul, and deliver me.

Let me not be disappointed, for I take refuge in you.

21 Let integrity and uprightness preserve me,

for I wait for you.

22 Redeem Israel, God,

out all of his troubles.

or, seed

Psalms 27

1 Yahweh is my light and my salvation.

Whom shall I fear?

Yahweh is the strength of my life.

Of whom shall I be afraid?

2 When evildoers came at me to eat up my flesh,

even my adversaries and my foes, they stumbled and fell.

3 Though an army should encamp against me,

my heart shall not fear.

Though war should rise against me,

even then I will be confident.

4 One thing I have asked of Yahweh, that I will seek after:

that I may dwell in Yahweh’s house all the days of my life,

to see Yahweh’s beauty,

and to inquire in his temple.

5 For in the day of trouble he will keep me secretly in his pavilion.

In the covert of his tabernacle he will hide me.

He will lift me up on a rock.

6 Now my head will be lifted up above my enemies around me;

I will offer sacrifices of joy in his tent.

I will sing, yes, I will sing praises to Yahweh.

7 Hear, Yahweh, when I cry with my voice.

Have mercy also on me, and answer me.

8 When you said, “Seek my face,”

my heart said to you, “I will seek your face, Yahweh.”

9 Don’t hide your face from me.

Don’t put your servant away in anger.

You have been my help.

Don’t abandon me,

neither forsake me, God of my salvation.

10 When my father and my mother forsake me,

then Yahweh will take me up.

11 Teach me your way, Yahweh.

Lead me in a straight path, because of my enemies.

12 Don’t deliver me over to the desire of my adversaries,

for false witnesses have risen up against me,

such as breathe out cruelty.

13 I am still confident of this:

I will see the goodness of Yahweh in the land of the living.

14 Wait for Yahweh.

Be strong, and let your heart take courage.

Yes, wait for Yahweh.

Psalms 28

1 To you, Yahweh, I call.

My rock, don’t be deaf to me;

lest, if you are silent to me,

I would become like those who go down into the pit.

2 Hear the voice of my petitions, when I cry to you,

when I lift up my hands toward your Most Holy Place.

3 Don’t draw me away with the wicked,

with the workers of iniquity who speak peace with their neighbors,

but mischief is in their hearts.

4 Give them according to their work, and according to the wickedness of their doings.

Give them according to the operation of their hands.

Bring back on them what they deserve.

5 Because they don’t respect the works of Yahweh,

nor the operation of his hands,

he will break them down and not build them up.

6 Blessed be Yahweh,

because he has heard the voice of my petitions.

7 Yahweh is my strength and my shield.

My heart has trusted in him, and I am helped.

Therefore my heart greatly rejoices.

With my song I will thank him.

8 Yahweh is their strength.

He is a stronghold of salvation to his anointed.

9 Save your people,

and bless your inheritance.

Be their shepherd also,

and bear them up forever.

Psalms 30

1 I will extol you, Yahweh, for you have raised me up,

and have not made my foes to rejoice over me.

2 Yahweh my God, I cried to you,

and you have healed me.

3 Yahweh, you have brought up my soul from Sheol.[*]

You have kept me alive, that I should not go down to the pit.

4 Sing praise to Yahweh, you saints of his.

Give thanks to his holy name.

5 For his anger is but for a moment.

His favor is for a lifetime.

Weeping may stay for the night,

but joy comes in the morning.

6 As for me, I said in my prosperity,

“I shall never be moved.”

7 You, Yahweh, when you favored me, made my mountain stand strong;

but when you hid your face, I was troubled.

8 I cried to you, Yahweh.

I made supplication to the Lord:

9 “What profit is there in my destruction, if I go down to the pit?

Shall the dust praise you?

Shall it declare your truth?

10 Hear, Yahweh, and have mercy on me.

Yahweh, be my helper.”

11 You have turned my mourning into dancing for me.

You have removed my sackcloth, and clothed me with gladness,

12 To the end that my heart may sing praise to you, and not be silent.

Yahweh my God, I will give thanks to you forever!

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 31

1 In you, Yahweh, I take refuge.

Let me never be disappointed.

Deliver me in your righteousness.

2 Bow down your ear to me.

Deliver me speedily.

Be to me a strong rock,

a house of defense to save me.

3 For you are my rock and my fortress,

therefore for your name’s sake lead me and guide me.

4 Pluck me out of the net that they have laid secretly for me,

for you are my stronghold.

5 Into your hand I commend my spirit.

You redeem me, Yahweh, God of truth.

6 I hate those who regard lying vanities,

but I trust in Yahweh.

7 I will be glad and rejoice in your loving kindness,

for you have seen my affliction.

You have known my soul in adversities.

8 You have not shut me up into the hand of the enemy.

You have set my feet in a large place.

9 Have mercy on me, Yahweh, for I am in distress.

My eye, my soul, and my body waste away with grief.

10 For my life is spent with sorrow,

my years with sighing.

My strength fails because of my iniquity.

My bones are wasted away.

11 Because of all my adversaries I have become utterly contemptible to my neighbors,

A fear to my acquaintances.

Those who saw me on the street fled from me.

12 I am forgotten from their hearts like a dead man.

I am like broken pottery.

13 For I have heard the slander of many, terror on every side,

while they conspire together against me,

they plot to take away my life.

14 But I trust in you, Yahweh.

I said, “You are my God.”

15 My times are in your hand.

Deliver me from the hand of my enemies, and from those who persecute me.

16 Make your face to shine on your servant.

Save me in your loving kindness.

17 Let me not be disappointed, Yahweh, for I have called on you.

Let the wicked be disappointed.

Let them be silent in Sheol.[*]

18 Let the lying lips be mute,

which speak against the righteous insolently, with pride and contempt.

19 Oh how great is your goodness,

which you have laid up for those who fear you,

which you have worked for those who take refuge in you,

before the sons of men!

20 In the shelter of your presence you will hide them from the plotting of man.

You will keep them secretly in a dwelling away from the strife of tongues.

21 Praise be to Yahweh,

for he has shown me his marvelous loving kindness in a strong city.

22 As for me, I said in my haste, “I am cut off from before your eyes.”

Nevertheless you heard the voice of my petitions when I cried to you.

23 Oh love Yahweh, all you his saints!

Yahweh preserves the faithful,

and fully recompenses him who behaves arrogantly.

24 Be strong, and let your heart take courage,

all you who hope in Yahweh.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 32

1 Blessed is he whose disobedience is forgiven,

whose sin is covered.

2 Blessed is the man to whom Yahweh doesn’t impute iniquity,

in whose spirit there is no deceit.

3 When I kept silence, my bones wasted away through my groaning all day long.

4 For day and night your hand was heavy on me.

My strength was sapped in the heat of summer. Selah.

5 I acknowledged my sin to you.

I didn’t hide my iniquity.

I said, I will confess my transgressions to Yahweh,

and you forgave the iniquity of my sin. Selah.

6 For this, let everyone who is godly pray to you in a time when you may be found.

Surely when the great waters overflow, they shall not reach to him.

7 You are my hiding place.

You will preserve me from trouble.

You will surround me with songs of deliverance. Selah.

8 I will instruct you and teach you in the way which you shall go.

I will counsel you with my eye on you.

9 Don’t be like the horse, or like the mule, which have no understanding,

who are controlled by bit and bridle, or else they will not come near to you.

10 Many sorrows come to the wicked,

but loving kindness shall surround him who trusts in Yahweh.

11 Be glad in Yahweh, and rejoice, you righteous!

Shout for joy, all you who are upright in heart!

Psalms 33

1 Rejoice in Yahweh, you righteous!

Praise is fitting for the upright.

2 Give thanks to Yahweh with the lyre.

Sing praises to him with the harp of ten strings.

3 Sing to him a new song.

Play skillfully with a shout of joy!

4 For Yahweh’s word is right.

All his work is done in faithfulness.

5 He loves righteousness and justice.

The earth is full of the loving kindness of Yahweh.

6 By Yahweh’s word, the heavens were made;

all their army by the breath of his mouth.

7 He gathers the waters of the sea together as a heap.

He lays up the deeps in storehouses.

8 Let all the earth fear Yahweh.

Let all the inhabitants of the world stand in awe of him.

9 For he spoke, and it was done.

He commanded, and it stood firm.

10 Yahweh brings the counsel of the nations to nothing.

He makes the thoughts of the peoples to be of no effect.

11 The counsel of Yahweh stands fast forever,

the thoughts of his heart to all generations.

12 Blessed is the nation whose God is Yahweh,

the people whom he has chosen for his own inheritance.

13 Yahweh looks from heaven.

He sees all the sons of men.

14 From the place of his habitation he looks out on all the inhabitants of the earth,

15 he who fashions all of their hearts;

and he considers all of their works.

16 There is no king saved by the multitude of an army.

A mighty man is not delivered by great strength.

17 A horse is a vain thing for safety,

neither does he deliver any by his great power.

18 Behold, Yahweh’s eye is on those who fear him,

on those who hope in his loving kindness;

19 to deliver their soul from death,

to keep them alive in famine.

20 Our soul has waited for Yahweh.

He is our help and our shield.

21 For our heart rejoices in him,

because we have trusted in his holy name.

22 Let your loving kindness be on us, Yahweh,

since we have hoped in you.

Psalms 34

1 [*] I will bless Yahweh at all times.

His praise will always be in my mouth.

2 My soul shall boast in Yahweh.

The humble shall hear of it, and be glad.

3 Oh magnify Yahweh with me.

Let us exalt his name together.

4 I sought Yahweh, and he answered me,

and delivered me from all my fears.

5 They looked to him, and were radiant.

Their faces shall never be covered with shame.

6 This poor man cried, and Yahweh heard him,

and saved him out of all his troubles.

7 Yahweh’s angel encamps around those who fear him,

and delivers them.

8 Oh taste and see that Yahweh is good.

Blessed is the man who takes refuge in him.

9 Oh fear Yahweh, you his saints,

for there is no lack with those who fear him.

10 The young lions do lack, and suffer hunger,

but those who seek Yahweh shall not lack any good thing.

11 Come, you children, listen to me.

I will teach you the fear of Yahweh.

12 Who is someone who desires life,

and loves many days, that he may see good?

13 Keep your tongue from evil,

and your lips from speaking lies.

14 Depart from evil, and do good.

seek peace, and pursue it.

15 Yahweh’s eyes are toward the righteous.

His ears listen to their cry.

16 Yahweh’s face is against those who do evil,

to cut off their memory from the earth.

17 The righteous cry, and Yahweh hears,

and delivers them out of all their troubles.

18 Yahweh is near to those who have a broken heart,

and saves those who have a crushed spirit.

19 Many are the afflictions of the righteous,

but Yahweh delivers him out of them all.

20 He protects all of his bones.

Not one of them is broken.

21 Evil shall kill the wicked.

Those who hate the righteous shall be condemned.

22 Yahweh redeems the soul of his servants.

None of those who take refuge in him shall be condemned.

Psalm 34 is an acrostic poem, with each verse starting with a letter of the alphabet (ordered from Alef to Tav).

Psalms 35

1 Contend, Yahweh, with those who contend with me.

Fight against those who fight against me.

2 Take hold of shield and buckler,

and stand up for my help.

3 Brandish the spear and block those who pursue me.

Tell my soul, “I am your salvation.”

4 Let those who seek after my soul be disappointed and brought to dishonor.

Let those who plot my ruin be turned back and confounded.

5 Let them be as chaff before the wind,

Yahweh’s angel driving them on.

6 Let their way be dark and slippery,

Yahweh’s angel pursuing them.

7 For without cause they have hidden their net in a pit for me.

Without cause they have dug a pit for my soul.

8 Let destruction come on him unawares.

Let his net that he has hidden catch himself.

Let him fall into that destruction.

9 My soul shall be joyful in Yahweh.

It shall rejoice in his salvation.

10 All my bones shall say, “Yahweh, who is like you,

who delivers the poor from him who is too strong for him;

yes, the poor and the needy from him who robs him?”

11 Unrighteous witnesses rise up.

They ask me about things that I don’t know about.

12 They reward me evil for good,

to the bereaving of my soul.

13 But as for me, when they were sick, my clothing was sackcloth.

I afflicted my soul with fasting.

My prayer returned into my own bosom.

14 I behaved myself as though it had been my friend or my brother.

I bowed down mourning, as one who mourns his mother.

15 But in my adversity, they rejoiced, and gathered themselves together.

The attackers gathered themselves together against me, and I didn’t know it.

They tore at me, and didn’t cease.

16 Like the profane mockers in feasts,

they gnashed their teeth at me.

17 Lord, how long will you look on?

Rescue my soul from their destruction,

my precious life from the lions.

18 I will give you thanks in the great assembly.

I will praise you among many people.

19 Don’t let those who are my enemies wrongfully rejoice over me;

neither let those who hate me without a cause wink their eyes.

20 For they don’t speak peace,

but they devise deceitful words against those who are quiet in the land.

21 Yes, they opened their mouth wide against me.

They said, “Aha! Aha! Our eye has seen it!”

22 You have seen it, Yahweh. Don’t keep silent.

Lord, don’t be far from me.

23 Wake up! Rise up to defend me, my God!

My Lord, contend for me!

24 Vindicate me, Yahweh my God, according to your righteousness.

Don’t let them gloat over me.

25 Don’t let them say in their heart, “Aha! That’s the way we want it!”

Don’t let them say, “We have swallowed him up!”

26 Let them be disappointed and confounded together who rejoice at my calamity.

Let them be clothed with shame and dishonor who magnify themselves against me.

27 Let them shout for joy and be glad, who favor my righteous cause.

Yes, let them say continually, “Yahweh be magnified,

who has pleasure in the prosperity of his servant!”

28 My tongue shall talk about your righteousness and about your praise all day long.

Psalms 36

1 An inner sanctuary is within my heart about the disobedience of the wicked:

“There is no fear of God before his eyes.”

2 For he flatters himself in his own eyes,

too much to detect and hate his sin.

3 The words of his mouth are iniquity and deceit.

He has ceased to be wise and to do good.

4 He plots iniquity on his bed.

He sets himself in a way that is not good.

He doesn’t abhor evil.

5 Your loving kindness, Yahweh, is in the heavens.

Your faithfulness reaches to the skies.

6 Your righteousness is like the mountains of God.

Your judgments are like a great deep.

Yahweh, you preserve man and animal.

7 How precious is your loving kindness, God!

The children of men take refuge under the shadow of your wings.

8 They shall be abundantly satisfied with the abundance of your house.

You will make them drink of the river of your pleasures.

9 For with you is the spring of life.

In your light shall we see light.

10 Oh continue your loving kindness to those who know you,

your righteousness to the upright in heart.

11 Don’t let the foot of pride come against me.

Don’t let the hand of the wicked drive me away.

12 There the workers of iniquity are fallen.

They are thrust down, and shall not be able to rise.

Psalms 37

1 Don’t fret because of evildoers,

neither be envious against those who work unrighteousness.

2 For they shall soon be cut down like the grass,

and wither like the green herb.

3 Trust in Yahweh, and do good.

Dwell in the land, and enjoy safe pasture.

4 Also delight yourself in Yahweh,

and he will give you the desires of your heart.

5 Commit your way to Yahweh.

Trust also in him, and he will do this:

6 he will make your righteousness go out as the light,

and your justice as the noon day sun.

7 Rest in Yahweh, and wait patiently for him.

Don’t fret because of him who prospers in his way,

because of the man who makes wicked plots happen.

8 Cease from anger, and forsake wrath.

Don’t fret, it leads only to evildoing.

9 For evildoers shall be cut off,

but those who wait for Yahweh shall inherit the land.

10 For yet a little while, and the wicked will be no more.

Yes, though you look for his place, he isn’t there.

11 But the humble shall inherit the land,

and shall delight themselves in the abundance of peace.

12 The wicked plots against the just,

and gnashes at him with his teeth.

13 The Lord will laugh at him,

for he sees that his day is coming.

14 The wicked have drawn out the sword, and have bent their bow,

to cast down the poor and needy,

to kill those who are upright on the path.

15 Their sword shall enter into their own heart.

Their bows shall be broken.

16 Better is a little that the righteous has,

than the abundance of many wicked.

17 For the arms of the wicked shall be broken,

but Yahweh upholds the righteous.

18 Yahweh knows the days of the perfect.

Their inheritance shall be forever.

19 They shall not be disappointed in the time of evil.

In the days of famine they shall be satisfied.

20 But the wicked shall perish.

The enemies of Yahweh shall be like the beauty of the fields.

They will vanish—

vanish like smoke.

21 The wicked borrow, and don’t pay back,

but the righteous give generously.

22 For such as are blessed by him shall inherit the land.

Those who are cursed by him shall be cut off.

23 A man’s goings are established by Yahweh.

He delights in his way.

24 Though he stumble, he shall not fall,

for Yahweh holds him up with his hand.

25 I have been young, and now am old,

yet I have not seen the righteous forsaken,

nor his children begging for bread.

26 All day long he deals graciously, and lends.

His offspring[*] is blessed.

27 Depart from evil, and do good.

Live securely forever.

28 For Yahweh loves justice,

and doesn’t forsake his saints.

They are preserved forever,

but the children of the wicked shall be cut off.

29 The righteous shall inherit the land,

and live in it forever.

30 The mouth of the righteous talks of wisdom.

His tongue speaks justice.

31 The law of his God is in his heart.

None of his steps shall slide.

32 The wicked watches the righteous,

and seeks to kill him.

33 Yahweh will not leave him in his hand,

nor condemn him when he is judged.

34 Wait for Yahweh, and keep his way,

and he will exalt you to inherit the land.

When the wicked are cut off, you shall see it.

35 I have seen the wicked in great power,

spreading himself like a green tree in its native soil.

36 But he passed away, and behold, he was not.

Yes, I sought him, but he could not be found.

37 Mark the perfect man, and see the upright,

for there is a future for the man of peace.

38 As for transgressors, they shall be destroyed together.

The future of the wicked shall be cut off.

39 But the salvation of the righteous is from Yahweh.

He is their stronghold in the time of trouble.

40 Yahweh helps them, and rescues them.

He rescues them from the wicked, and saves them,

Because they have taken refuge in him.

or, seed

Psalms 38

1 Yahweh, don’t rebuke me in your wrath,

neither chasten me in your hot displeasure.

2 For your arrows have pierced me,

your hand presses hard on me.

3 There is no soundness in my flesh because of your indignation,

neither is there any health in my bones because of my sin.

4 For my iniquities have gone over my head.

As a heavy burden, they are too heavy for me.

5 My wounds are loathsome and corrupt,

because of my foolishness.

6 I am pained and bowed down greatly.

I go mourning all day long.

7 For my waist is filled with burning.

There is no soundness in my flesh.

8 I am faint and severely bruised.

I have groaned by reason of the anguish of my heart.

9 Lord, all my desire is before you.

My groaning is not hidden from you.

10 My heart throbs.

My strength fails me.

As for the light of my eyes, it has also left me.

11 My lovers and my friends stand aloof from my plague.

My kinsmen stand far away.

12 They also who seek after my life lay snares.

Those who seek my hurt speak mischievous things,

and meditate deceits all day long.

13 But I, as a deaf man, don’t hear.

I am as a mute man who doesn’t open his mouth.

14 Yes, I am as a man who doesn’t hear,

in whose mouth are no reproofs.

15 For in you, Yahweh, do I hope.

You will answer, Lord my God.

16 For I said, “Don’t let them gloat over me,

or exalt themselves over me when my foot slips.”

17 For I am ready to fall.

My pain is continually before me.

18 For I will declare my iniquity.

I will be sorry for my sin.

19 But my enemies are vigorous and many.

Those who hate me without reason are numerous.

20 They who also render evil for good are adversaries to me,

because I follow what is good.

21 Don’t forsake me, Yahweh.

My God, don’t be far from me.

22 Hurry to help me,

Lord, my salvation.

Psalms 39

1 I said, “I will watch my ways, so that I don’t sin with my tongue.

I will keep my mouth with a bridle while the wicked is before me.”

2 I was mute with silence.

I held my peace, even from good.

My sorrow was stirred.

3 My heart was hot within me.

While I meditated, the fire burned.

I spoke with my tongue:

4 “Yahweh, show me my end,

what is the measure of my days.

Let me know how frail I am.

5 Behold, you have made my days hand widths.

My lifetime is as nothing before you.

Surely every man stands as a breath.” Selah.

6 “Surely every man walks like a shadow.

Surely they busy themselves in vain.

He heaps up, and doesn’t know who shall gather.

7 Now, Lord, what do I wait for?

My hope is in you.

8 Deliver me from all my transgressions.

Don’t make me the reproach of the foolish.

9 I was mute.

I didn’t open my mouth,

because you did it.

10 Remove your scourge away from me.

I am overcome by the blow of your hand.

11 When you rebuke and correct man for iniquity,

You consume his wealth like a moth.

Surely every man is but a breath.” Selah.

12 “Hear my prayer, Yahweh, and give ear to my cry.

Don’t be silent at my tears.

For I am a stranger with you,

a foreigner, as all my fathers were.

13 Oh spare me, that I may recover strength,

before I go away, and exist no more.”

Psalms 40

1 I waited patiently for Yahweh.

He turned to me, and heard my cry.

2 He brought me up also out of a horrible pit,

out of the miry clay.

He set my feet on a rock,

and gave me a firm place to stand.

3 He has put a new song in my mouth, even praise to our God.

Many shall see it, and fear, and shall trust in Yahweh.

4 Blessed is the man who makes Yahweh his trust,

and doesn’t respect the proud, nor such as turn aside to lies.

5 Many, Yahweh, my God, are the wonderful works which you have done,

and your thoughts which are toward us.

They can’t be declared back to you.

If I would declare and speak of them, they are more than can be counted.

6 Sacrifice and offering you didn’t desire.

You have opened my ears.

You have not required burnt offering and sin offering.

7 Then I said, “Behold, I have come.

It is written about me in the book in the scroll.

8 I delight to do your will, my God.

Yes, your law is within my heart.”

9 I have proclaimed glad news of righteousness in the great assembly.

Behold, I will not seal my lips, Yahweh, you know.

10 I have not hidden your righteousness within my heart.

I have declared your faithfulness and your salvation.

I have not concealed your loving kindness and your truth from the great assembly.

11 Don’t withhold your tender mercies from me, Yahweh.

Let your loving kindness and your truth continually preserve me.

12 For innumerable evils have surrounded me.

My iniquities have overtaken me, so that I am not able to look up.

They are more than the hairs of my head.

My heart has failed me.

13 Be pleased, Yahweh, to deliver me.

Hurry to help me, Yahweh.

14 Let them be disappointed and confounded together who seek after my soul to destroy it.

Let them be turned backward and brought to dishonor who delight in my hurt.

15 Let them be desolate by reason of their shame that tell me, “Aha! Aha!”

16 Let all those who seek you rejoice and be glad in you.

Let such as love your salvation say continually, “Let Yahweh be exalted!”

17 But I am poor and needy.

May the Lord think about me.

You are my help and my deliverer.

Don’t delay, my God.

Psalms 41

1 Blessed is he who considers the poor.

Yahweh will deliver him in the day of evil.

2 Yahweh will preserve him, and keep him alive.

He shall be blessed on the earth,

and he will not surrender him to the will of his enemies.

3 Yahweh will sustain him on his sickbed,

and restore him from his bed of illness.

4 I said, “Yahweh, have mercy on me!

Heal me, for I have sinned against you.”

5 My enemies speak evil against me:

“When will he die, and his name perish?”

6 If he comes to see me, he speaks falsehood.

His heart gathers iniquity to itself.

When he goes abroad, he tells it.

7 All who hate me whisper together against me.

They imagine the worst for me.

8 “An evil disease”, they say, “has afflicted him.

Now that he lies he shall rise up no more.”

9 Yes, my own familiar friend, in whom I trusted,

who ate bread with me,

has lifted up his heel against me.

10 But you, Yahweh, have mercy on me, and raise me up,

that I may repay them.

11 By this I know that you delight in me,

because my enemy doesn’t triumph over me.

12 As for me, you uphold me in my integrity,

and set me in your presence forever.

13 Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel,

from everlasting and to everlasting!

Amen and amen.

Psalms 42

1 As the deer pants for the water brooks,

so my soul pants after you, God.[*]

2 My soul thirsts for God, for the living God.

When shall I come and appear before God?

3 My tears have been my food day and night,

while they continually ask me, “Where is your God?”

4 These things I remember, and pour out my soul within me,

how I used to go with the crowd, and led them to God’s house,

with the voice of joy and praise, a multitude keeping a holy day.

5 Why are you in despair, my soul?

Why are you disturbed within me?

Hope in God!

For I shall still praise him for the saving help of his presence.

6 My God, my soul is in despair within me.

Therefore I remember you from the land of the Jordan,

the heights of Hermon, from the hill Mizar.

7 Deep calls to deep at the noise of your waterfalls.

All your waves and your billows have swept over me.

8 Yahweh[*] will command his loving kindness in the daytime.

In the night his song shall be with me:

a prayer to the God of my life.

9 I will ask God, my rock, “Why have you forgotten me?

Why do I go mourning because of the oppression of the enemy?”

10 As with a sword in my bones, my adversaries reproach me,

while they continually ask me, “Where is your God?”

11 Why are you in despair, my soul?

Why are you disturbed within me?

Hope in God! For I shall still praise him,

the saving help of my countenance, and my God.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

Psalms 44

1 We have heard with our ears, God;

our fathers have told us,

what work you did in their days,

in the days of old.

2 You drove out the nations with your hand,

but you planted them.

You afflicted the peoples,

but you spread them abroad.

3 For they didn’t get the land in possession by their own sword,

neither did their own arm save them;

but your right hand, and your arm, and the light of your face,

because you were favorable to them.

4 You are my King, God.

Command victories for Jacob!

5 Through you, will we push down our adversaries.

Through your name, will we tread them under who rise up against us.

6 For I will not trust in my bow,

neither shall my sword save me.

7 But you have saved us from our adversaries,

and have shamed those who hate us.

8 In God we have made our boast all day long,

we will give thanks to your name forever. Selah.

9 But now you rejected us, and brought us to dishonor,

and don’t go out with our armies.

10 You make us turn back from the adversary.

Those who hate us take plunder for themselves.

11 You have made us like sheep for food,

and have scattered us among the nations.

12 You sell your people for nothing,

and have gained nothing from their sale.

13 You make us a reproach to our neighbors,

a scoffing and a derision to those who are around us.

14 You make us a byword among the nations,

a shaking of the head among the peoples.

15 All day long my dishonor is before me,

and shame covers my face,

16 At the taunt of one who reproaches and verbally abuses,

because of the enemy and the avenger.

17 All this has come on us,

yet have we not forgotten you,

Neither have we been false to your covenant.

18 Our heart has not turned back,

neither have our steps strayed from your path,

19 Though you have crushed us in the haunt of jackals,

and covered us with the shadow of death.

20 If we have forgotten the name of our God,

or spread out our hands to a strange god;

21 won’t God search this out?

For he knows the secrets of the heart.

22 Yes, for your sake we are killed all day long.

We are regarded as sheep for the slaughter.

23 Wake up!

Why do you sleep, Lord?[*]

Arise!

Don’t reject us forever.

24 Why do you hide your face,

and forget our affliction and our oppression?

25 For our soul is bowed down to the dust.

Our body clings to the earth.

26 Rise up to help us.

Redeem us for your loving kindness’ sake.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Psalms 45

1 My heart overflows with a noble theme.

I recite my verses for the king.

My tongue is like the pen of a skillful writer.

2 You are the most excellent of the sons of men.

Grace has anointed your lips,

therefore God has blessed you forever.

3 Strap your sword on your thigh, mighty one:

your splendor and your majesty.

4 In your majesty ride on victoriously on behalf of truth, humility, and righteousness.

Let your right hand display awesome deeds.

5 Your arrows are sharp.

The nations fall under you, with arrows in the heart of the king’s enemies.

6 Your throne, God, is forever and ever.

A scepter of equity is the scepter of your kingdom.

7 You have loved righteousness, and hated wickedness.

Therefore God, your God, has anointed you with the oil of gladness above your fellows.

8 All your garments smell like myrrh, aloes, and cassia.

Out of ivory palaces stringed instruments have made you glad.

9 Kings’ daughters are among your honorable women.

At your right hand the queen stands in gold of Ophir.

10 Listen, daughter, consider, and turn your ear.

Forget your own people, and also your father’s house.

11 So the king will desire your beauty,

honor him, for he is your lord.

12 The daughter of Tyre comes with a gift.

The rich among the people entreat your favor.

13 The princess inside is all glorious.

Her clothing is interwoven with gold.

14 She shall be led to the king in embroidered work.

The virgins, her companions who follow her, shall be brought to you.

15 With gladness and rejoicing they shall be led.

They shall enter into the king’s palace.

16 Your sons will take the place of your fathers.

You shall make them princes in all the earth.

17 I will make your name to be remembered in all generations.

Therefore the peoples shall give you thanks forever and ever.

Psalms 48

1 Great is Yahweh, and greatly to be praised,

in the city of our God, in his holy mountain.

2 Beautiful in elevation, the joy of the whole earth,

is Mount Zion, on the north sides,

the city of the great King.

3 God has shown himself in her citadels as a refuge.

4 For, behold, the kings assembled themselves,

they passed by together.

5 They saw it, then they were amazed.

They were dismayed.

They hurried away.

6 Trembling took hold of them there,

pain, as of a woman in travail.

7 With the east wind, you break the ships of Tarshish.

8 As we have heard, so we have seen,

in the city of Yahweh of Armies, in the city of our God.

God will establish it forever. Selah.

9 We have thought about your loving kindness, God,

in the middle of your temple.

10 As is your name, God,

so is your praise to the ends of the earth.

Your right hand is full of righteousness.

11 Let Mount Zion be glad!

Let the daughters of Judah rejoice,

Because of your judgments.

12 Walk about Zion, and go around her.

Number its towers.

13 Mark well her bulwarks.

Consider her palaces,

that you may tell it to the next generation.

14 For this God is our God forever and ever.

He will be our guide even to death.

Psalms 49

1 Hear this, all you peoples.

Listen, all you inhabitants of the world,

2 both low and high,

rich and poor together.

3 My mouth will speak words of wisdom.

My heart shall utter understanding.

4 I will incline my ear to a proverb.

I will open my riddle on the harp.

5 Why should I fear in the days of evil,

when iniquity at my heels surrounds me?

6 Those who trust in their wealth,

and boast in the multitude of their riches—

7 none of them can by any means redeem his brother,

nor give God a ransom for him.

8 For the redemption of their life is costly,

no payment is ever enough,

9 that he should live on forever,

that he should not see corruption.

10 For he sees that wise men die;

likewise the fool and the senseless perish,

and leave their wealth to others.

11 Their inward thought is that their houses will endure forever,

and their dwelling places to all generations.

They name their lands after themselves.

12 But man, despite his riches, doesn’t endure.

He is like the animals that perish.

13 This is the destiny of those who are foolish,

and of those who approve their sayings. Selah.

14 They are appointed as a flock for Sheol.[*]

Death shall be their shepherd.

The upright shall have dominion over them in the morning.

Their beauty shall decay in Sheol,[*]

far from their mansion.

15 But God will redeem my soul from the power of Sheol,[*]

for he will receive me. Selah.

16 Don’t be afraid when a man is made rich,

when the glory of his house is increased;

17 for when he dies he will carry nothing away.

His glory won’t descend after him.

18 Though while he lived he blessed his soul—

and men praise you when you do well for yourself—

19 he shall go to the generation of his fathers.

They shall never see the light.

20 A man who has riches without understanding,

is like the animals that perish.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 50

1 The Mighty One, God, Yahweh, speaks,

and calls the earth from sunrise to sunset.

2 Out of Zion, the perfection of beauty,

God shines out.

3 Our God comes, and does not keep silent.

A fire devours before him.

It is very stormy around him.

4 He calls to the heavens above,

to the earth, that he may judge his people:

5 “Gather my saints together to me,

those who have made a covenant with me by sacrifice.”

6 The heavens shall declare his righteousness,

for God himself is judge. Selah.

7 “Hear, my people, and I will speak;

Israel, and I will testify against you.

I am God, your God.

8 I don’t rebuke you for your sacrifices.

Your burnt offerings are continually before me.

9 I have no need for a bull from your stall,

nor male goats from your pens.

10 For every animal of the forest is mine,

and the livestock on a thousand hills.

11 I know all the birds of the mountains.

The wild animals of the field are mine.

12 If I were hungry, I would not tell you,

for the world is mine, and all that is in it.

13 Will I eat the meat of bulls,

or drink the blood of goats?

14 Offer to God the sacrifice of thanksgiving.

Pay your vows to the Most High.

15 Call on me in the day of trouble.

I will deliver you, and you will honor me.”

16 But to the wicked God says,

“What right do you have to declare my statutes,

that you have taken my covenant on your lips,

17 since you hate instruction,

and throw my words behind you?

18 When you saw a thief, you consented with him,

and have participated with adulterers.

19 “You give your mouth to evil.

Your tongue frames deceit.

20 You sit and speak against your brother.

You slander your own mother’s son.

21 You have done these things, and I kept silent.

You thought that I was just like you.

I will rebuke you, and accuse you in front of your eyes.

22 “Now consider this, you who forget God,

lest I tear you into pieces, and there be no one to deliver.

23 Whoever offers the sacrifice of thanksgiving glorifies me,

and prepares his way so that I will show God’s salvation to him.”

Psalms 51

1 Have mercy on me, God, according to your loving kindness.

According to the multitude of your tender mercies, blot out my transgressions.

2 Wash me thoroughly from my iniquity.

Cleanse me from my sin.

3 For I know my transgressions.

My sin is constantly before me.

4 Against you, and you only, I have sinned,

and done that which is evil in your sight;

that you may be proved right when you speak,

and justified when you judge.

5 Behold, I was born in iniquity.

In sin my mother conceived me.

6 Behold, you desire truth in the inward parts.

You teach me wisdom in the inmost place.

7 Purify me with hyssop, and I will be clean.

Wash me, and I will be whiter than snow.

8 Let me hear joy and gladness,

That the bones which you have broken may rejoice.

9 Hide your face from my sins,

and blot out all of my iniquities.

10 Create in me a clean heart, O God.

Renew a right spirit within me.

11 Don’t throw me from your presence,

and don’t take your holy Spirit from me.

12 Restore to me the joy of your salvation.

Uphold me with a willing spirit.

13 Then I will teach transgressors your ways.

Sinners shall be converted to you.

14 Deliver me from the guilt of bloodshed, O God, the God of my salvation.

My tongue shall sing aloud of your righteousness.

15 Lord, open my lips.

My mouth shall declare your praise.

16 For you don’t delight in sacrifice, or else I would give it.

You have no pleasure in burnt offering.

17 The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit.

A broken and contrite heart, O God, you will not despise.

18 Do well in your good pleasure to Zion.

Build the walls of Jerusalem.

19 Then you will delight in the sacrifices of righteousness,

in burnt offerings and in whole burnt offerings.

Then they will offer bulls on your altar.

Psalms 55

1 Listen to my prayer, God.

Don’t hide yourself from my supplication.

2 Attend to me, and answer me.

I am restless in my complaint, and moan,

3 Because of the voice of the enemy,

Because of the oppression of the wicked.

For they bring suffering on me.

In anger they hold a grudge against me.

4 My heart is severely pained within me.

The terrors of death have fallen on me.

5 Fearfulness and trembling have come on me.

Horror has overwhelmed me.

6 I said, “Oh that I had wings like a dove!

Then I would fly away, and be at rest.

7 Behold, then I would wander far off.

I would lodge in the wilderness.” Selah.

8 “I would hurry to a shelter from the stormy wind and storm.”

9 Confuse them, Lord, and confound their language,

for I have seen violence and strife in the city.

10 Day and night they prowl around on its walls.

Malice and abuse are also within her.

11 Destructive forces are within her.

Threats and lies don’t depart from her streets.

12 For it was not an enemy who insulted me,

then I could have endured it.

Neither was it he who hated me who raised himself up against me,

then I would have hidden myself from him.

13 But it was you, a man like me,

my companion, and my familiar friend.

14 We took sweet fellowship together.

We walked in God’s house with company.

15 Let death come suddenly on them.

Let them go down alive into Sheol.[*]

For wickedness is among them, in their dwelling.

16 As for me, I will call on God.

Yahweh will save me.

17 Evening, morning, and at noon, I will cry out in distress.

He will hear my voice.

18 He has redeemed my soul in peace from the battle that was against me,

although there are many who oppose me.

19 God, who is enthroned forever,

will hear, and answer them. Selah.

They never change,

who don’t fear God.

20 He raises his hands against his friends.

He has violated his covenant.

21 His mouth was smooth as butter,

but his heart was war.

His words were softer than oil,

yet they were drawn swords.

22 Cast your burden on Yahweh, and he will sustain you.

He will never allow the righteous to be moved.

23 But you, God, will bring them down into the pit of destruction.

Bloodthirsty and deceitful men shall not live out half their days,

but I will trust in you.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 56

1 Be merciful to me, God, for man wants to swallow me up.

All day long, he attacks and oppresses me.

2 My enemies want to swallow me up all day long,

for they are many who fight proudly against me.

3 When I am afraid,

I will put my trust in you.

4 In God, I praise his word.

In God, I put my trust.

I will not be afraid.

What can flesh do to me?

5 All day long they twist my words.

All their thoughts are against me for evil.

6 They conspire and lurk,

watching my steps, they are eager to take my life.

7 Shall they escape by iniquity?

In anger cast down the peoples, God.

8 You count my wanderings.

You put my tears into your bottle.

Aren’t they in your book?

9 Then my enemies shall turn back in the day that I call.

I know this, that God is for me.

10 In God, I will praise his word.

In Yahweh, I will praise his word.

11 I have put my trust in God.

I will not be afraid.

What can man do to me?

12 Your vows are on me, God.

I will give thank offerings to you.

13 For you have delivered my soul from death,

and prevented my feet from falling,

that I may walk before God in the light of the living.

Psalms 57

1 Be merciful to me, God, be merciful to me,

for my soul takes refuge in you.

Yes, in the shadow of your wings, I will take refuge,

until disaster has passed.

2 I cry out to God Most High,

to God who accomplishes my requests for me.

3 He will send from heaven, and save me,

he rebukes the one who is pursuing me. Selah.

God will send out his loving kindness and his truth.

4 My soul is among lions.

I lie among those who are set on fire,

even the sons of men, whose teeth are spears and arrows,

and their tongue a sharp sword.

5 Be exalted, God, above the heavens!

Let your glory be above all the earth!

6 They have prepared a net for my steps.

My soul is bowed down.

They dig a pit before me.

They fall into the middle of it themselves. Selah.

7 My heart is steadfast, God, my heart is steadfast.

I will sing, yes, I will sing praises.

8 Wake up, my glory! Wake up, lute and harp!

I will wake up the dawn.

9 I will give thanks to you, Lord, among the peoples.

I will sing praises to you among the nations.

10 For your great loving kindness reaches to the heavens,

and your truth to the skies.

11 Be exalted, God, above the heavens.

Let your glory be over all the earth.

Psalms 58

1 Do you indeed speak righteousness, silent ones?

Do you judge blamelessly, you sons of men?

2 No, in your heart you plot injustice.

You measure out the violence of your hands in the earth.

3 The wicked go astray from the womb.

They are wayward as soon as they are born, speaking lies.

4 Their poison is like the poison of a snake;

like a deaf cobra that stops its ear,

5 which doesn’t listen to the voice of charmers,

no matter how skillful the charmer may be.

6 Break their teeth, God, in their mouth.

Break out the great teeth of the young lions, Yahweh.

7 Let them vanish like water that flows away.

When they draw the bow, let their arrows be made blunt.

8 Let them be like a snail which melts and passes away,

like the stillborn child, who has not seen the sun.

9 Before your pots can feel the heat of the thorns,

he will sweep away the green and the burning alike.

10 The righteous shall rejoice when he sees the vengeance.

He shall wash his feet in the blood of the wicked;

11 so that men shall say, “Most certainly there is a reward for the righteous.

Most certainly there is a God who judges the earth.”

Psalms 59

1 Deliver me from my enemies, my God.

Set me on high from those who rise up against me.

2 Deliver me from the workers of iniquity.

Save me from the bloodthirsty men.

3 For, behold, they lie in wait for my soul.

The mighty gather themselves together against me,

not for my disobedience, nor for my sin, Yahweh.

4 I have done no wrong, yet they are ready to attack me.

Rise up, behold, and help me!

5 You, Yahweh God of Armies, the God of Israel,

rouse yourself to punish the nations.

Show no mercy to the wicked traitors. Selah.

6 They return at evening, howling like dogs,

and prowl around the city.

7 Behold, they spew with their mouth.

Swords are in their lips,

“For”, they say, “who hears us?”

8 But you, Yahweh, laugh at them.

You scoff at all the nations.

9 Oh, my Strength, I watch for you,

for God is my high tower.

10 My God will go before me with his loving kindness.

God will let me look at my enemies in triumph.

11 Don’t kill them, or my people may forget.

Scatter them by your power, and bring them down, Lord our shield.

12 For the sin of their mouth, and the words of their lips,

let them be caught in their pride,

for the curses and lies which they utter.

13 Consume them in wrath.

Consume them, and they will be no more.

Let them know that God rules in Jacob,

to the ends of the earth. Selah.

14 At evening let them return.

Let them howl like a dog, and go around the city.

15 They shall wander up and down for food,

and wait all night if they aren’t satisfied.

16 But I will sing of your strength.

Yes, I will sing aloud of your loving kindness in the morning.

For you have been my high tower,

a refuge in the day of my distress.

17 To you, my strength, I will sing praises.

For God is my high tower, the God of my mercy.

Psalms 60

1 God, you have rejected us.

You have broken us down.

You have been angry.

Restore us, again.

2 You have made the land tremble.

You have torn it.

Mend its fractures,

for it quakes.

3 You have shown your people hard things.

You have made us drink the wine that makes us stagger.

4 You have given a banner to those who fear you,

that it may be displayed because of the truth. Selah.

5 So that your beloved may be delivered,

save with your right hand, and answer us.

6 God has spoken from his sanctuary:

“I will triumph.

I will divide Shechem,

and measure out the valley of Succoth.

7 Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine.

Ephraim also is the defense of my head.

Judah is my scepter.

8 Moab is my wash basin.

I will throw my shoe on Edom.

I shout in triumph over Philistia.”

9 Who will bring me into the strong city?

Who has led me to Edom?

10 Haven’t you, God, rejected us?

You don’t go out with our armies, God.

11 Give us help against the adversary,

for the help of man is vain.

12 Through God we shall do valiantly,

for it is he who will tread down our adversaries.

Psalms 62

1 My soul rests in God alone.

My salvation is from him.

2 He alone is my rock and my salvation, my fortress—

I will never be greatly shaken.

3 How long will you assault a man,

would all of you throw him down,

Like a leaning wall, like a tottering fence?

4 They fully intend to throw him down from his lofty place.

They delight in lies.

They bless with their mouth, but they curse inwardly. Selah.

5 My soul, wait in silence for God alone,

for my expectation is from him.

6 He alone is my rock and my salvation, my fortress.

I will not be shaken.

7 With God is my salvation and my honor.

The rock of my strength, and my refuge, is in God.

8 Trust in him at all times, you people.

Pour out your heart before him.

God is a refuge for us. Selah.

9 Surely men of low degree are just a breath,

and men of high degree are a lie.

In the balances they will go up.

They are together lighter than a breath.

10 Don’t trust in oppression.

Don’t become vain in robbery.

If riches increase,

don’t set your heart on them.

11 God has spoken once;

twice I have heard this,

that power belongs to God.

12 Also to you, Lord, belongs loving kindness,

for you reward every man according to his work.

Psalms 65

1 Praise waits for you, God, in Zion.

To you shall vows be performed.

2 You who hear prayer,

to you all men will come.

3 Sins overwhelmed me,

but you atoned for our transgressions.

4 Blessed is one whom you choose, and cause to come near,

that he may live in your courts.

We will be filled with the goodness of your house,

your holy temple.

5 By awesome deeds of righteousness, you answer us,

God of our salvation.

You who are the hope of all the ends of the earth,

of those who are far away on the sea;

6 Who by his power forms the mountains,

having armed yourself with strength;

7 who stills the roaring of the seas,

the roaring of their waves,

and the turmoil of the nations.

8 They also who dwell in faraway places are afraid at your wonders.

You call the morning’s dawn and the evening with songs of joy.

9 You visit the earth, and water it.

You greatly enrich it.

The river of God is full of water.

You provide them grain, for so you have ordained it.

10 You drench its furrows.

You level its ridges.

You soften it with showers.

You bless it with a crop.

11 You crown the year with your bounty.

Your carts overflow with abundance.

12 The wilderness grasslands overflow.

The hills are clothed with gladness.

13 The pastures are covered with flocks.

The valleys also are clothed with grain.

They shout for joy!

They also sing.

Psalms 66

1 Make a joyful shout to God, all the earth!

2 Sing to the glory of his name!

Offer glory and praise!

3 Tell God, “How awesome are your deeds!

Through the greatness of your power, your enemies submit themselves to you.

4 All the earth will worship you,

and will sing to you;

they will sing to your name.” Selah.

5 Come, and see God’s deeds—

awesome work on behalf of the children of men.

6 He turned the sea into dry land.

They went through the river on foot.

There, we rejoiced in him.

7 He rules by his might forever.

His eyes watch the nations.

Don’t let the rebellious rise up against him. Selah.

8 Praise our God, you peoples!

Make the sound of his praise heard,

9 who preserves our life among the living,

and doesn’t allow our feet to be moved.

10 For you, God, have tested us.

You have refined us, as silver is refined.

11 You brought us into prison.

You laid a burden on our backs.

12 You allowed men to ride over our heads.

We went through fire and through water,

but you brought us to the place of abundance.

13 I will come into your temple with burnt offerings.

I will pay my vows to you, 14 which my lips promised,

and my mouth spoke, when I was in distress.

15 I will offer to you burnt offerings of fat animals,

with the offering of rams,

I will offer bulls with goats. Selah.

16 Come, and hear, all you who fear God.

I will declare what he has done for my soul.

17 I cried to him with my mouth.

He was extolled with my tongue.

18 If I cherished sin in my heart,

the Lord wouldn’t have listened.

19 But most certainly, God has listened.

He has heard the voice of my prayer.

20 Blessed be God, who has not turned away my prayer,

nor his loving kindness from me.

Psalms 68

1 Let God arise!

Let his enemies be scattered!

Let them who hate him also flee before him.

2 As smoke is driven away,

so drive them away.

As wax melts before the fire,

so let the wicked perish at the presence of God.

3 But let the righteous be glad.

Let them rejoice before God.

Yes, let them rejoice with gladness.

4 Sing to God! Sing praises to his name!

Extol him who rides on the clouds:

to Yah, his name!

Rejoice before him!

5 A father of the fatherless, and a defender of the widows,

is God in his holy habitation.

6 God sets the lonely in families.

He brings out the prisoners with singing,

but the rebellious dwell in a sun-scorched land.

7 God, when you went out before your people,

when you marched through the wilderness... Selah.

8 The earth trembled.

The sky also poured down rain at the presence of the God of Sinai—

at the presence of God, the God of Israel.

9 You, God, sent a plentiful rain.

You confirmed your inheritance, when it was weary.

10 Your congregation lived therein.

You, God, prepared your goodness for the poor.

11 The Lord announced the word.

The ones who proclaim it are a great company.

12 “Kings of armies flee! They flee!”

She who waits at home divides the plunder,

13 while you sleep among the camp fires,

the wings of a dove sheathed with silver,

her feathers with shining gold.

14 When the Almighty scattered kings in her,

it snowed on Zalmon.

15 The mountains of Bashan are majestic mountains.

The mountains of Bashan are rugged.

16 Why do you look in envy, you rugged mountains,

at the mountain where God chooses to reign?

Yes, Yahweh will dwell there forever.

17 The chariots of God are tens of thousands and thousands of thousands.

The Lord is among them, from Sinai, into the sanctuary.

18 You have ascended on high.

You have led away captives.

You have received gifts among men,

yes, among the rebellious also, that Yah God might dwell there.

19 Blessed be the Lord, who daily bears our burdens,

even the God who is our salvation. Selah.

20 God is to us a God of deliverance.

To Yahweh, the Lord, belongs escape from death.

21 But God will strike through the head of his enemies,

the hairy scalp of such a one as still continues in his guiltiness.

22 The Lord said, “I will bring you again from Bashan,

I will bring you again from the depths of the sea;

23 That you may crush them, dipping your foot in blood,

that the tongues of your dogs may have their portion from your enemies.”

24 They have seen your processions, God,

even the processions of my God, my King, into the sanctuary.

25 The singers went before, the minstrels followed after,

among the ladies playing with tambourines,

26 “Bless God in the congregations,

even the Lord in the assembly of Israel!”

27 There is little Benjamin, their ruler,

the princes of Judah, their council,

the princes of Zebulun, and the princes of Naphtali.

28 Your God has commanded your strength.

Strengthen, God, that which you have done for us.

29 Because of your temple at Jerusalem,

kings shall bring presents to you.

30 Rebuke the wild animal of the reeds,

the multitude of the bulls, with the calves of the peoples.

Being humbled, may it bring bars of silver.

Scatter the nations that delight in war.

31 Princes shall come out of Egypt.

Ethiopia shall hurry to stretch out her hands to God.

32 Sing to God, you kingdoms of the earth!

Sing praises to the Lord! Selah.

33 To him who rides on the heaven of heavens, which are of old;

behold, he utters his voice, a mighty voice.

34 Ascribe strength to God!

His excellency is over Israel,

his strength is in the skies.

35 You are awesome, God, in your sanctuaries.

The God of Israel gives strength and power to his people.

Praise be to God!

Psalms 69

1 Save me, God,

for the waters have come up to my neck!

2 I sink in deep mire, where there is no foothold.

I have come into deep waters, where the floods overflow me.

3 I am weary with my crying.

My throat is dry.

My eyes fail, looking for my God.

4 Those who hate me without a cause are more than the hairs of my head.

Those who want to cut me off, being my enemies wrongfully, are mighty.

I have to restore what I didn’t take away.

5 God, you know my foolishness.

My sins aren’t hidden from you.

6 Don’t let those who wait for you be shamed through me, Lord Yahweh of Armies.

Don’t let those who seek you be brought to dishonor through me, God of Israel.

7 Because for your sake, I have borne reproach.

Shame has covered my face.

8 I have become a stranger to my brothers,

an alien to my mother’s children.

9 For the zeal of your house consumes me.

The reproaches of those who reproach you have fallen on me.

10 When I wept and I fasted,

that was to my reproach.

11 When I made sackcloth my clothing,

I became a byword to them.

12 Those who sit in the gate talk about me.

I am the song of the drunkards.

13 But as for me, my prayer is to you, Yahweh, in an acceptable time.

God, in the abundance of your loving kindness, answer me in the truth of your salvation.

14 Deliver me out of the mire, and don’t let me sink.

Let me be delivered from those who hate me, and out of the deep waters.

15 Don’t let the flood waters overwhelm me,

neither let the deep swallow me up.

Don’t let the pit shut its mouth on me.

16 Answer me, Yahweh, for your loving kindness is good.

According to the multitude of your tender mercies, turn to me.

17 Don’t hide your face from your servant,

for I am in distress.

Answer me speedily!

18 Draw near to my soul, and redeem it.

Ransom me because of my enemies.

19 You know my reproach, my shame, and my dishonor.

My adversaries are all before you.

20 Reproach has broken my heart, and I am full of heaviness.

I looked for some to take pity, but there was none;

for comforters, but I found none.

21 They also gave me gall for my food.

In my thirst, they gave me vinegar to drink.

22 Let their table before them become a snare.

May it become a retribution and a trap.

23 Let their eyes be darkened, so that they can’t see.

Let their backs be continually bent.

24 Pour out your indignation on them.

Let the fierceness of your anger overtake them.

25 Let their habitation be desolate.

Let no one dwell in their tents.

26 For they persecute him whom you have wounded.

They tell of the sorrow of those whom you have hurt.

27 Charge them with crime upon crime.

Don’t let them come into your righteousness.

28 Let them be blotted out of the book of life,

and not be written with the righteous.

29 But I am in pain and distress.

Let your salvation, God, protect me.

30 I will praise the name of God with a song,

and will magnify him with thanksgiving.

31 It will please Yahweh better than an ox,

or a bull that has horns and hoofs.

32 The humble have seen it, and are glad.

You who seek after God, let your heart live.

33 For Yahweh hears the needy,

and doesn’t despise his captive people.

34 Let heaven and earth praise him;

the seas, and everything that moves therein!

35 For God will save Zion, and build the cities of Judah.

They shall settle there, and own it.

36 The children also of his servants shall inherit it.

Those who love his name shall dwell therein.

Psalms 71

1 In you, Yahweh, I take refuge.

Never let me be disappointed.

2 Deliver me in your righteousness, and rescue me.

Turn your ear to me, and save me.

3 Be to me a rock of refuge to which I may always go.

Give the command to save me,

for you are my rock and my fortress.

4 Rescue me, my God, from the hand of the wicked,

from the hand of the unrighteous and cruel man.

5 For you are my hope, Lord Yahweh;

my confidence from my youth.

6 I have relied on you from the womb.

You are he who took me out of my mother’s womb.

I will always praise you.

7 I am a marvel to many,

but you are my strong refuge.

8 My mouth shall be filled with your praise,

with your honor all day long.

9 Don’t reject me in my old age.

Don’t forsake me when my strength fails.

10 For my enemies talk about me.

Those who watch for my soul conspire together,

11 saying, “God has forsaken him.

Pursue and take him, for no one will rescue him.”

12 God, don’t be far from me.

My God, hurry to help me.

13 Let my accusers be disappointed and consumed.

Let them be covered with disgrace and scorn who want to harm me.

14 But I will always hope,

and will add to all of your praise.

15 My mouth will tell about your righteousness,

and of your salvation all day,

though I don’t know its full measure.

16 I will come with the mighty acts of the Lord Yahweh.

I will make mention of your righteousness, even of yours alone.

17 God, you have taught me from my youth.

Until now, I have declared your wondrous works.

18 Yes, even when I am old and gray-haired, God, don’t forsake me,

until I have declared your strength to the next generation,

your might to everyone who is to come.

19 Your righteousness also, God, reaches to the heavens;

you have done great things.

God, who is like you?

20 You, who have shown us many and bitter troubles,

you will let me live.

You will bring us up again from the depths of the earth.

21 Increase my honor,

and comfort me again.

22 I will also praise you with the harp for your faithfulness, my God.

I sing praises to you with the lyre, Holy One of Israel.

23 My lips shall shout for joy!

My soul, which you have redeemed, sings praises to you!

24 My tongue will also talk about your righteousness all day long,

for they are disappointed, and they are confounded,

who want to harm me.

Psalms 72

1 God, give the king your justice;

your righteousness to the royal son.

2 He will judge your people with righteousness,

and your poor with justice.

3 The mountains shall bring prosperity to the people.

The hills bring the fruit of righteousness.

4 He will judge the poor of the people.

He will save the children of the needy,

and will break the oppressor in pieces.

5 They shall fear you while the sun endures;

and as long as the moon, throughout all generations.

6 He will come down like rain on the mown grass,

as showers that water the earth.

7 In his days, the righteous shall flourish,

and abundance of peace, until the moon is no more.

8 He shall have dominion also from sea to sea,

from the River to the ends of the earth.

9 Those who dwell in the wilderness shall bow before him.

His enemies shall lick the dust.

10 The kings of Tarshish and of the islands will bring tribute.

The kings of Sheba and Seba shall offer gifts.

11 Yes, all kings shall fall down before him.

All nations shall serve him.

12 For he will deliver the needy when he cries;

the poor, who has no helper.

13 He will have pity on the poor and needy.

He will save the souls of the needy.

14 He will redeem their soul from oppression and violence.

Their blood will be precious in his sight.

15 They shall live, and to him shall be given of the gold of Sheba.

Men shall pray for him continually.

They shall bless him all day long.

16 Abundance of grain shall be throughout the land.

Its fruit sways like Lebanon.

Let it flourish, thriving like the grass of the field.

17 His name endures forever.

His name continues as long as the sun.

Men shall be blessed by him.

All nations will call him blessed.

18 Praise be to Yahweh God, the God of Israel,

who alone does marvelous deeds.

19 Blessed be his glorious name forever!

Let the whole earth be filled with his glory!

Amen and amen.

20 This ends the prayers by David, the son of Jesse.

Psalms 73

1 Surely God[*] is good to Israel,

to those who are pure in heart.

2 But as for me, my feet were almost gone.

My steps had nearly slipped.

3 For I was envious of the arrogant,

when I saw the prosperity of the wicked.

4 For there are no struggles in their death,

but their strength is firm.

5 They are free from burdens of men,

neither are they plagued like other men.

6 Therefore pride is like a chain around their neck.

Violence covers them like a garment.

7 Their eyes bulge with fat.

Their minds pass the limits of conceit.

8 They scoff and speak with malice.

In arrogance, they threaten oppression.

9 They have set their mouth in the heavens.

Their tongue walks through the earth.

10 Therefore their people return to them,

and they drink up waters of abundance.

11 They say, “How does God know?

Is there knowledge in the Most High?”

12 Behold, these are the wicked.

Being always at ease, they increase in riches.

13 Surely I have cleansed my heart in vain,

and washed my hands in innocence,

14 For all day long I have been plagued,

and punished every morning.

15 If I had said, “I will speak thus”;

behold, I would have betrayed the generation of your children.

16 When I tried to understand this,

it was too painful for me;

17 Until I entered God’s sanctuary,

and considered their latter end.

18 Surely you set them in slippery places.

You throw them down to destruction.

19 How they are suddenly destroyed!

They are completely swept away with terrors.

20 As a dream when one wakes up,

so, Lord,[*] when you awake, you will despise their fantasies.

21 For my soul was grieved.

I was embittered in my heart.

22 I was so senseless and ignorant.

I was a brute beast before you.

23 Nevertheless, I am continually with you.

You have held my right hand.

24 You will guide me with your counsel,

and afterward receive me to glory.

25 Whom do I have in heaven?

There is no one on earth whom I desire besides you.

26 My flesh and my heart fails,

but God is the strength of my heart and my portion forever.

27 For, behold, those who are far from you shall perish.

You have destroyed all those who are unfaithful to you.

28 But it is good for me to come close to God.

I have made the Lord Yahweh[*] my refuge,

that I may tell of all your works.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

Psalms 74

1 God, why have you rejected us forever?

Why does your anger smolder against the sheep of your pasture?

2 Remember your congregation, which you purchased of old,

which you have redeemed to be the tribe of your inheritance;

Mount Zion, in which you have lived.

3 Lift up your feet to the perpetual ruins,

all the evil that the enemy has done in the sanctuary.

4 Your adversaries have roared in the middle of your assembly.

They have set up their standards as signs.

5 They behaved like men wielding axes,

cutting through a thicket of trees.

6 Now they break all its carved work down with hatchet and hammers.

7 They have burned your sanctuary to the ground.

They have profaned the dwelling place of your Name.

8 They said in their heart, “We will crush them completely.”

They have burned up all the places in the land where God was worshiped.

9 We see no miraculous signs.

There is no longer any prophet,

neither is there among us anyone who knows how long.

10 How long, God, shall the adversary reproach?

Shall the enemy blaspheme your name forever?

11 Why do you draw back your hand, even your right hand?

Take it out of your pocket and consume them!

12 Yet God is my King of old,

working salvation throughout the earth.

13 You divided the sea by your strength.

You broke the heads of the sea monsters in the waters.

14 You broke the heads of Leviathan in pieces.

You gave him as food to people and desert creatures.

15 You opened up spring and stream.

You dried up mighty rivers.

16 The day is yours, the night is also yours.

You have prepared the light and the sun.

17 You have set all the boundaries of the earth.

You have made summer and winter.

18 Remember this, that the enemy has mocked you, Yahweh.

Foolish people have blasphemed your name.

19 Don’t deliver the soul of your dove to wild beasts.

Don’t forget the life of your poor forever.

20 Honor your covenant,

for haunts of violence fill the dark places of the earth.

21 Don’t let the oppressed return ashamed.

Let the poor and needy praise your name.

22 Arise, God! Plead your own cause.

Remember how the foolish man mocks you all day.

23 Don’t forget the voice of your adversaries.

The tumult of those who rise up against you ascends continually.

Psalms 77

1 My cry goes to God!

Indeed, I cry to God for help,

and for him to listen to me.

2 In the day of my trouble I sought the Lord.

My hand was stretched out in the night, and didn’t get tired.

My soul refused to be comforted.

3 I remember God, and I groan.

I complain, and my spirit is overwhelmed. Selah.

4 You hold my eyelids open.

I am so troubled that I can’t speak.

5 I have considered the days of old,

the years of ancient times.

6 I remember my song in the night.

I consider in my own heart;

my spirit diligently inquires:

7 “Will the Lord reject us forever?

Will he be favorable no more?

8 Has his loving kindness vanished forever?

Does his promise fail for generations?

9 Has God forgotten to be gracious?

Has he, in anger, withheld his compassion?” Selah.

10 Then I thought, “I will appeal to this:

the years of the right hand of the Most High.”

11 I will remember Yah’s deeds;

for I will remember your wonders of old.

12 I will also meditate on all your work,

and consider your doings.

13 Your way, God, is in the sanctuary.

What god is great like God?

14 You are the God who does wonders.

You have made your strength known among the peoples.

15 You have redeemed your people with your arm,

the sons of Jacob and Joseph. Selah.

16 The waters saw you, God.

The waters saw you, and they writhed.

The depths also convulsed.

17 The clouds poured out water.

The skies resounded with thunder.

Your arrows also flashed around.

18 The voice of your thunder was in the whirlwind.

The lightnings lit up the world.

The earth trembled and shook.

19 Your way was through the sea;

your paths through the great waters.

Your footsteps were not known.

20 You led your people like a flock,

by the hand of Moses and Aaron.

Psalms 78

1 Hear my teaching, my people.

Turn your ears to the words of my mouth.

2 I will open my mouth in a parable.

I will utter dark sayings of old,

3 Which we have heard and known,

and our fathers have told us.

4 We will not hide them from their children,

telling to the generation to come the praises of Yahweh,

his strength, and his wondrous deeds that he has done.

5 For he established a testimony in Jacob,

and appointed a teaching in Israel,

which he commanded our fathers,

that they should make them known to their children;

6 that the generation to come might know, even the children who should be born;

who should arise and tell their children,

7 that they might set their hope in God,

and not forget God’s deeds,

but keep his commandments,

8 and might not be as their fathers,

a stubborn and rebellious generation,

a generation that didn’t make their hearts loyal,

whose spirit was not steadfast with God.

9 The children of Ephraim, being armed and carrying bows,

turned back in the day of battle.

10 They didn’t keep God’s covenant,

and refused to walk in his law.

11 They forgot his doings,

his wondrous deeds that he had shown them.

12 He did marvelous things in the sight of their fathers,

in the land of Egypt, in the field of Zoan.

13 He split the sea, and caused them to pass through.

He made the waters stand as a heap.

14 In the daytime he also led them with a cloud,

and all night with a light of fire.

15 He split rocks in the wilderness,

and gave them drink abundantly as out of the depths.

16 He brought streams also out of the rock,

and caused waters to run down like rivers.

17 Yet they still went on to sin against him,

to rebel against the Most High in the desert.

18 They tempted God in their heart

by asking food according to their desire.

19 Yes, they spoke against God.

They said, “Can God prepare a table in the wilderness?

20 Behold, he struck the rock, so that waters gushed out,

and streams overflowed.

Can he give bread also?

Will he provide meat for his people?”

21 Therefore Yahweh heard, and was angry.

A fire was kindled against Jacob,

anger also went up against Israel,

22 because they didn’t believe in God,

and didn’t trust in his salvation.

23 Yet he commanded the skies above,

and opened the doors of heaven.

24 He rained down manna on them to eat,

and gave them food from the sky.

25 Man ate the bread of angels.

He sent them food to the full.

26 He caused the east wind to blow in the sky.

By his power he guided the south wind.

27 He rained also meat on them as the dust;

winged birds as the sand of the seas.

28 He let them fall in the middle of their camp,

around their habitations.

29 So they ate, and were well filled.

He gave them their own desire.

30 They didn’t turn from their cravings.

Their food was yet in their mouths,

31 when the anger of God went up against them,

killed some of their fattest,

and struck down the young men of Israel.

32 For all this they still sinned,

and didn’t believe in his wondrous works.

33 Therefore he consumed their days in vanity,

and their years in terror.

34 When he killed them, then they inquired after him.

They returned and sought God earnestly.

35 They remembered that God was their rock,

the Most High God, their redeemer.

36 But they flattered him with their mouth,

and lied to him with their tongue.

37 For their heart was not right with him,

neither were they faithful in his covenant.

38 But he, being merciful, forgave iniquity, and didn’t destroy them.

Yes, many times he turned his anger away,

and didn’t stir up all his wrath.

39 He remembered that they were but flesh,

a wind that passes away, and doesn’t come again.

40 How often they rebelled against him in the wilderness,

and grieved him in the desert!

41 They turned again and tempted God,

and provoked the Holy One of Israel.

42 They didn’t remember his hand,

nor the day when he redeemed them from the adversary;

43 how he set his signs in Egypt,

his wonders in the field of Zoan,

44 he turned their rivers into blood,

and their streams, so that they could not drink.

45 He sent among them swarms of flies, which devoured them;

and frogs, which destroyed them.

46 He gave also their increase to the caterpillar,

and their labor to the locust.

47 He destroyed their vines with hail,

their sycamore fig trees with frost.

48 He gave over their livestock also to the hail,

and their flocks to hot thunderbolts.

49 He threw on them the fierceness of his anger,

wrath, indignation, and trouble,

and a band of angels of evil.

50 He made a path for his anger.

He didn’t spare their soul from death,

but gave their life over to the pestilence,

51 and struck all the firstborn in Egypt,

the chief of their strength in the tents of Ham.

52 But he led out his own people like sheep,

and guided them in the wilderness like a flock.

53 He led them safely, so that they weren’t afraid,

but the sea overwhelmed their enemies.

54 He brought them to the border of his sanctuary,

to this mountain, which his right hand had taken.

55 He also drove out the nations before them,

allotted them for an inheritance by line,

and made the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tents.

56 Yet they tempted and rebelled against the Most High God,

and didn’t keep his testimonies;

57 but turned back, and dealt treacherously like their fathers.

They were turned aside like a deceitful bow.

58 For they provoked him to anger with their high places,

and moved him to jealousy with their engraved images.

59 When God heard this, he was angry,

and greatly abhorred Israel;

60 So that he abandoned the tent of Shiloh,

the tent which he placed among men;

61 and delivered his strength into captivity,

his glory into the adversary’s hand.

62 He also gave his people over to the sword,

and was angry with his inheritance.

63 Fire devoured their young men.

Their virgins had no wedding song.

64 Their priests fell by the sword,

and their widows couldn’t weep.

65 Then the Lord awakened as one out of sleep,

like a mighty man who shouts by reason of wine.

66 He struck his adversaries backward.

He put them to a perpetual reproach.

67 Moreover he rejected the tent of Joseph,

and didn’t choose the tribe of Ephraim,

68 But chose the tribe of Judah,

Mount Zion which he loved.

69 He built his sanctuary like the heights,

like the earth which he has established forever.

70 He also chose David his servant,

and took him from the sheepfolds;

71 from following the ewes that have their young,

he brought him to be the shepherd of Jacob, his people,

and Israel, his inheritance.

72 So he was their shepherd according to the integrity of his heart,

and guided them by the skillfulness of his hands.

Psalms 79

1 God, the nations have come into your inheritance.

They have defiled your holy temple.

They have laid Jerusalem in heaps.

2 They have given the dead bodies of your servants to be food for the birds of the sky,

the flesh of your saints to the animals of the earth.

3 Their blood they have shed like water around Jerusalem.

There was no one to bury them.

4 We have become a reproach to our neighbors,

a scoffing and derision to those who are around us.

5 How long, Yahweh?

Will you be angry forever?

Will your jealousy burn like fire?

6 Pour out your wrath on the nations that don’t know you;

on the kingdoms that don’t call on your name;

7 For they have devoured Jacob,

and destroyed his homeland.

8 Don’t hold the iniquities of our forefathers against us.

Let your tender mercies speedily meet us,

for we are in desperate need.

9 Help us, God of our salvation, for the glory of your name.

Deliver us, and forgive our sins, for your name’s sake.

10 Why should the nations say, “Where is their God?”

Let it be known among the nations, before our eyes,

that vengeance for your servants’ blood is being poured out.

11 Let the sighing of the prisoner come before you.

According to the greatness of your power, preserve those who are sentenced to death.

12 Pay back to our neighbors seven times into their bosom

their reproach with which they have reproached you, Lord.

13 So we, your people and sheep of your pasture,

will give you thanks forever.

We will praise you forever, to all generations.

Psalms 80

1 Hear us, Shepherd of Israel,

you who lead Joseph like a flock,

you who sit above the cherubim, shine out.

2 Before Ephraim and Benjamin and Manasseh, stir up your might!

Come to save us!

3 Turn us again, God.

Cause your face to shine,

and we will be saved.

4 Yahweh God of Armies,

How long will you be angry against the prayer of your people?

5 You have fed them with the bread of tears,

and given them tears to drink in large measure.

6 You make us a source of contention to our neighbors.

Our enemies laugh among themselves.

7 Turn us again, God of Armies.

Cause your face to shine,

and we will be saved.

8 You brought a vine out of Egypt.

You drove out the nations, and planted it.

9 You cleared the ground for it.

It took deep root, and filled the land.

10 The mountains were covered with its shadow.

Its boughs were like God’s cedars.

11 It sent out its branches to the sea,

Its shoots to the River.

12 Why have you broken down its walls,

so that all those who pass by the way pluck it?

13 The boar out of the wood ravages it.

The wild animals of the field feed on it.

14 Turn again, we beg you, God of Armies.

Look down from heaven, and see, and visit this vine,

15 the stock which your right hand planted,

the branch that you made strong for yourself.

16 It’s burned with fire.

It’s cut down.

They perish at your rebuke.

17 Let your hand be on the man of your right hand,

on the son of man whom you made strong for yourself.

18 So we will not turn away from you.

Revive us, and we will call on your name.

19 Turn us again, Yahweh God of Armies.

Cause your face to shine, and we will be saved.

Psalms 81

1 Sing aloud to God, our strength!

Make a joyful shout to the God of Jacob!

2 Raise a song, and bring here the tambourine,

the pleasant lyre with the harp.

3 Blow the trumpet at the New Moon,

at the full moon, on our feast day.

4 For it is a statute for Israel,

an ordinance of the God of Jacob.

5 He appointed it in Joseph for a testimony,

when he went out over the land of Egypt,

I heard a language that I didn’t know.

6 “I removed his shoulder from the burden.

His hands were freed from the basket.

7 You called in trouble, and I delivered you.

I answered you in the secret place of thunder.

I tested you at the waters of Meribah.” Selah.

8 “Hear, my people, and I will testify to you,

Israel, if you would listen to me!

9 There shall be no strange god in you,

neither shall you worship any foreign god.

10 I am Yahweh, your God,

who brought you up out of the land of Egypt.

Open your mouth wide, and I will fill it.

11 But my people didn’t listen to my voice.

Israel desired none of me.

12 So I let them go after the stubbornness of their hearts,

that they might walk in their own counsels.

13 Oh that my people would listen to me,

that Israel would walk in my ways!

14 I would soon subdue their enemies,

and turn my hand against their adversaries.

15 The haters of Yahweh would cringe before him,

and their punishment would last forever.

16 But he would have also fed them with the finest of the wheat.

I will satisfy you with honey out of the rock.”

Psalms 83

1 God, don’t keep silent.

Don’t keep silent,

and don’t be still, God.

2 For, behold, your enemies are stirred up.

Those who hate you have lifted up their heads.

3 They conspire with cunning against your people.

They plot against your cherished ones.

4 “Come,” they say, “let’s destroy them as a nation,

that the name of Israel may be remembered no more.”

5 For they have conspired together with one mind.

They form an alliance against you.

6 The tents of Edom and the Ishmaelites;

Moab, and the Hagrites;

7 Gebal, Ammon, and Amalek;

Philistia with the inhabitants of Tyre;

8 Assyria also is joined with them.

They have helped the children of Lot. Selah.

9 Do to them as you did to Midian,

as to Sisera, as to Jabin, at the river Kishon;

10 who perished at Endor,

who became as dung for the earth.

11 Make their nobles like Oreb and Zeeb;

yes, all their princes like Zebah and Zalmunna;

12 who said, “Let us take possession of God’s pasture lands.”

13 My God, make them like tumbleweed;

like chaff before the wind.

14 As the fire that burns the forest,

as the flame that sets the mountains on fire,

15 so pursue them with your tempest,

and terrify them with your storm.

16 Fill their faces with confusion,

that they may seek your name, Yahweh.

17 Let them be disappointed and dismayed forever.

Yes, let them be confounded and perish;

18 that they may know that you alone, whose name is Yahweh,

are the Most High over all the earth.

Psalms 84

1 How lovely are your dwellings,

Yahweh of Armies!

2 My soul longs, and even faints for the courts of Yahweh.

My heart and my flesh cry out for the living God.

3 Yes, the sparrow has found a home,

and the swallow a nest for herself, where she may have her young,

near your altars, Yahweh of Armies, my King, and my God.

4 Blessed are those who dwell in your house.

They are always praising you. Selah.

5 Blessed are those whose strength is in you;

who have set their hearts on a pilgrimage.

6 Passing through the valley of Weeping, they make it a place of springs.

Yes, the autumn rain covers it with blessings.

7 They go from strength to strength.

Everyone of them appears before God in Zion.

8 Yahweh, God of Armies, hear my prayer.

Listen, God of Jacob. Selah.

9 Behold, God our shield,

look at the face of your anointed.

10 For a day in your courts is better than a thousand.

I would rather be a doorkeeper in the house of my God,

than to dwell in the tents of wickedness.

11 For Yahweh God is a sun and a shield.

Yahweh will give grace and glory.

He withholds no good thing from those who walk blamelessly.

12 Yahweh of Armies,

blessed is the man who trusts in you.

Psalms 85

1 Yahweh, you have been favorable to your land.

You have restored the fortunes of Jacob.

2 You have forgiven the iniquity of your people.

You have covered all their sin. Selah.

3 You have taken away all your wrath.

You have turned from the fierceness of your anger.

4 Turn us, God of our salvation,

and cause your indignation toward us to cease.

5 Will you be angry with us forever?

Will you draw out your anger to all generations?

6 Won’t you revive us again,

that your people may rejoice in you?

7 Show us your loving kindness, Yahweh.

Grant us your salvation.

8 I will hear what God, Yahweh, will speak,

for he will speak peace to his people, his saints;

but let them not turn again to folly.

9 Surely his salvation is near those who fear him,

that glory may dwell in our land.

10 Mercy and truth meet together.

Righteousness and peace have kissed each other.

11 Truth springs out of the earth.

Righteousness has looked down from heaven.

12 Yes, Yahweh will give that which is good.

Our land will yield its increase.

13 Righteousness goes before him,

And prepares the way for his steps.

Psalms 86

1 Hear, Yahweh, and answer me,

for I am poor and needy.

2 Preserve my soul, for I am godly.

You, my God, save your servant who trusts in you.

3 Be merciful to me, Lord,

for I call to you all day long.

4 Bring joy to the soul of your servant,

for to you, Lord, do I lift up my soul.

5 For you, Lord, are good, and ready to forgive;

abundant in loving kindness to all those who call on you.

6 Hear, Yahweh, my prayer.

Listen to the voice of my petitions.

7 In the day of my trouble I will call on you,

for you will answer me.

8 There is no one like you among the gods, Lord,

nor any deeds like your deeds.

9 All nations you have made will come and worship before you, Lord.

They shall glorify your name.

10 For you are great, and do wondrous things.

You are God alone.

11 Teach me your way, Yahweh.

I will walk in your truth.

Make my heart undivided to fear your name.

12 I will praise you, Lord my God, with my whole heart.

I will glorify your name forever more.

13 For your loving kindness is great toward me.

You have delivered my soul from the lowest Sheol.[*]

14 God, the proud have risen up against me.

A company of violent men have sought after my soul,

and they don’t hold regard for you before them.

15 But you, Lord, are a merciful and gracious God,

slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness and truth.

16 Turn to me, and have mercy on me!

Give your strength to your servant.

Save the son of your servant.

17 Show me a sign of your goodness,

that those who hate me may see it, and be shamed,

because you, Yahweh, have helped me, and comforted me.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 88

1 Yahweh, the God of my salvation,

I have cried day and night before you.

2 Let my prayer enter into your presence.

Turn your ear to my cry.

3 For my soul is full of troubles.

My life draws near to Sheol.[*]

4 I am counted among those who go down into the pit.

I am like a man who has no help,

5 set apart among the dead,

like the slain who lie in the grave,

whom you remember no more.

They are cut off from your hand.

6 You have laid me in the lowest pit,

in the darkest depths.

7 Your wrath lies heavily on me.

You have afflicted me with all your waves. Selah.

8 You have taken my friends from me.

You have made me an abomination to them.

I am confined, and I can’t escape.

9 My eyes are dim from grief.

I have called on you daily, Yahweh.

I have spread out my hands to you.

10 Do you show wonders to the dead?

Do the departed spirits rise up and praise you? Selah.

11 Is your loving kindness declared in the grave?

Or your faithfulness in Destruction?

12 Are your wonders made known in the dark?

Or your righteousness in the land of forgetfulness?

13 But to you, Yahweh, I have cried.

In the morning, my prayer comes before you.

14 Yahweh, why do you reject my soul?

Why do you hide your face from me?

15 I am afflicted and ready to die from my youth up.

While I suffer your terrors, I am distracted.

16 Your fierce wrath has gone over me.

Your terrors have cut me off.

17 They came around me like water all day long.

They completely engulfed me.

18 You have put lover and friend far from me,

and my friends into darkness.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 89

1 I will sing of the loving kindness of Yahweh forever.

With my mouth, I will make known your faithfulness to all generations.

2 I indeed declare, “Love stands firm forever.

You established the heavens.

Your faithfulness is in them.”

3 “I have made a covenant with my chosen one,

I have sworn to David, my servant,

4 ‘I will establish your offspring[*] forever,

and build up your throne to all generations.’” Selah.

5 The heavens will praise your wonders, Yahweh;

your faithfulness also in the assembly of the holy ones.

6 For who in the skies can be compared to Yahweh?

Who among the sons of the heavenly beings is like Yahweh,

7 a very awesome God in the council of the holy ones,

to be feared above all those who are around him?

8 Yahweh, God of Armies, who is a mighty one, like you?

Yah, your faithfulness is around you.

9 You rule the pride of the sea.

When its waves rise up, you calm them.

10 You have broken Rahab in pieces, like one of the slain.

You have scattered your enemies with your mighty arm.

11 The heavens are yours.

The earth also is yours;

the world and its fullness.

You have founded them.

12 The north and the south, you have created them.

Tabor and Hermon rejoice in your name.

13 You have a mighty arm.

Your hand is strong, and your right hand is exalted.

14 Righteousness and justice are the foundation of your throne.

Loving kindness and truth go before your face.

15 Blessed are the people who learn to acclaim you.

They walk in the light of your presence, Yahweh.

16 In your name they rejoice all day.

In your righteousness, they are exalted.

17 For you are the glory of their strength.

In your favor, our horn will be exalted.

18 For our shield belongs to Yahweh;

our king to the Holy One of Israel.

19 Then you spoke in vision to your saints,

and said, “I have given strength to the warrior.

I have exalted a young man from the people.

20 I have found David, my servant.

I have anointed him with my holy oil,

21 with whom my hand shall be established.

My arm will also strengthen him.

22 No enemy will tax him.

No wicked man will oppress him.

23 I will beat down his adversaries before him,

and strike those who hate him.

24 But my faithfulness and my loving kindness will be with him.

In my name, his horn will be exalted.

25 I will set his hand also on the sea,

and his right hand on the rivers.

26 He will call to me, ‘You are my Father,

my God, and the rock of my salvation!’

27 I will also appoint him my firstborn,

the highest of the kings of the earth.

28 I will keep my loving kindness for him forever more.

My covenant will stand firm with him.

29 I will also make his offspring[*] endure forever,

and his throne as the days of heaven.

30 If his children forsake my law,

and don’t walk in my ordinances;

31 if they break my statutes,

and don’t keep my commandments;

32 then I will punish their sin with the rod,

and their iniquity with stripes.

33 But I will not completely take my loving kindness from him,

nor allow my faithfulness to fail.

34 I will not break my covenant,

nor alter what my lips have uttered.

35 Once I have sworn by my holiness,

I will not lie to David.

36 His offspring[*] will endure forever,

his throne like the sun before me.

37 It will be established forever like the moon,

the faithful witness in the sky.” Selah.

38 But you have rejected and spurned.

You have been angry with your anointed.

39 You have renounced the covenant of your servant.

You have defiled his crown in the dust.

40 You have broken down all his hedges.

You have brought his strongholds to ruin.

41 All who pass by the way rob him.

He has become a reproach to his neighbors.

42 You have exalted the right hand of his adversaries.

You have made all of his enemies rejoice.

43 Yes, you turn back the edge of his sword,

and haven’t supported him in battle.

44 You have ended his splendor,

and thrown his throne down to the ground.

45 You have shortened the days of his youth.

You have covered him with shame. Selah.

46 How long, Yahweh?

Will you hide yourself forever?

Will your wrath burn like fire?

47 Remember how short my time is!

For what vanity have you created all the children of men!

48 What man is he who shall live and not see death,

who shall deliver his soul from the power of Sheol?[*] Selah.

49 Lord, where are your former loving kindnesses,

which you swore to David in your faithfulness?

50 Remember, Lord, the reproach of your servants,

how I bear in my heart the taunts of all the mighty peoples,

51 With which your enemies have mocked, Yahweh,

with which they have mocked the footsteps of your anointed one.

52 Blessed be Yahweh forever more.

Amen, and Amen.

or, seed

or, seed

or, seed

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 90

1 Lord,[*] you have been our dwelling place for all generations.

2 Before the mountains were born,

before you had formed the earth and the world,

even from everlasting to everlasting, you are God.

3 You turn man to destruction, saying,

“Return, you children of men.”

4 For a thousand years in your sight are just like yesterday when it is past,

like a watch in the night.

5 You sweep them away as they sleep.

In the morning they sprout like new grass.

6 In the morning it sprouts and springs up.

By evening, it is withered and dry.

7 For we are consumed in your anger.

We are troubled in your wrath.

8 You have set our iniquities before you,

our secret sins in the light of your presence.

9 For all our days have passed away in your wrath.

We bring our years to an end as a sigh.

10 The days of our years are seventy,

or even by reason of strength eighty years;

yet their pride is but labor and sorrow,

for it passes quickly, and we fly away.

11 Who knows the power of your anger,

your wrath according to the fear that is due to you?

12 So teach us to count our days,

that we may gain a heart of wisdom.

13 Relent, Yahweh![*]

How long?

Have compassion on your servants!

14 Satisfy us in the morning with your loving kindness,

that we may rejoice and be glad all our days.

15 Make us glad for as many days as you have afflicted us,

for as many years as we have seen evil.

16 Let your work appear to your servants;

your glory to their children.

17 Let the favor of the Lord our God be on us;

establish the work of our hands for us;

yes, establish the work of our hands.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

Psalms 91

1 He who dwells in the secret place of the Most High

will rest in the shadow of the Almighty.

2 I will say of Yahweh, “He is my refuge and my fortress;

my God, in whom I trust.”

3 For he will deliver you from the snare of the fowler,

and from the deadly pestilence.

4 He will cover you with his feathers.

Under his wings you will take refuge.

His faithfulness is your shield and rampart.

5 You shall not be afraid of the terror by night,

nor of the arrow that flies by day;

6 nor of the pestilence that walks in darkness,

nor of the destruction that wastes at noonday.

7 A thousand may fall at your side,

and ten thousand at your right hand;

but it will not come near you.

8 You will only look with your eyes,

and see the recompense of the wicked.

9 Because you have made Yahweh your refuge,

and the Most High your dwelling place,

10 no evil shall happen to you,

neither shall any plague come near your dwelling.

11 For he will put his angels in charge of you,

to guard you in all your ways.

12 They will bear you up in their hands,

so that you won’t dash your foot against a stone.

13 You will tread on the lion and cobra.

You will trample the young lion and the serpent underfoot.

14 “Because he has set his love on me, therefore I will deliver him.

I will set him on high, because he has known my name.

15 He will call on me, and I will answer him.

I will be with him in trouble.

I will deliver him, and honor him.

16 I will satisfy him with long life,

and show him my salvation.”

Psalms 92

1 It is a good thing to give thanks to Yahweh,

to sing praises to your name, Most High;

2 to proclaim your loving kindness in the morning,

and your faithfulness every night,

3 with the ten-stringed lute, with the harp,

and with the melody of the lyre.

4 For you, Yahweh, have made me glad through your work.

I will triumph in the works of your hands.

5 How great are your works, Yahweh!

Your thoughts are very deep.

6 A senseless man doesn’t know,

neither does a fool understand this:

7 though the wicked spring up as the grass,

and all the evildoers flourish,

they will be destroyed forever.

8 But you, Yahweh, are on high forever more.

9 For, behold, your enemies, Yahweh,

for, behold, your enemies shall perish.

All the evildoers will be scattered.

10 But you have exalted my horn like that of the wild ox.

I am anointed with fresh oil.

11 My eye has also seen my enemies.

My ears have heard of the wicked enemies who rise up against me.

12 The righteous shall flourish like the palm tree.

He will grow like a cedar in Lebanon.

13 They are planted in Yahweh’s house.

They will flourish in our God’s courts.

14 They will still produce fruit in old age.

They will be full of sap and green,

15 to show that Yahweh is upright.

He is my rock,

and there is no unrighteousness in him.

Psalms 94

1 Yahweh, you God to whom vengeance belongs,

you God to whom vengeance belongs, shine out.

2 Rise up, you judge of the earth.

Pay back the proud what they deserve.

3 Yahweh, how long will the wicked,

how long will the wicked triumph?

4 They pour out arrogant words.

All the evildoers boast.

5 They break your people in pieces, Yahweh,

and afflict your heritage.

6 They kill the widow and the alien,

and murder the fatherless.

7 They say, “Yah will not see,

neither will Jacob’s God consider.”

8 Consider, you senseless among the people;

you fools, when will you be wise?

9 He who implanted the ear, won’t he hear?

He who formed the eye, won’t he see?

10 He who disciplines the nations, won’t he punish?

He who teaches man knows.

11 Yahweh knows the thoughts of man,

that they are futile.

12 Blessed is the man whom you discipline, Yah,

and teach out of your law;

13 that you may give him rest from the days of adversity,

until the pit is dug for the wicked.

14 For Yahweh won’t reject his people,

neither will he forsake his inheritance.

15 For judgment will return to righteousness.

All the upright in heart shall follow it.

16 Who will rise up for me against the wicked?

Who will stand up for me against the evildoers?

17 Unless Yahweh had been my help,

my soul would have soon lived in silence.

18 When I said, “My foot is slipping!”

Your loving kindness, Yahweh, held me up.

19 In the multitude of my thoughts within me,

your comforts delight my soul.

20 Shall the throne of wickedness have fellowship with you,

which brings about mischief by statute?

21 They gather themselves together against the soul of the righteous,

and condemn the innocent blood.

22 But Yahweh has been my high tower,

my God, the rock of my refuge.

23 He has brought on them their own iniquity,

and will cut them off in their own wickedness.

Yahweh, our God, will cut them off.

Psalms 96

1 Sing to Yahweh a new song!

Sing to Yahweh, all the earth.

2 Sing to Yahweh!

Bless his name!

Proclaim his salvation from day to day!

3 Declare his glory among the nations,

his marvelous works among all the peoples.

4 For great is Yahweh, and greatly to be praised!

He is to be feared above all gods.

5 For all the gods of the peoples are idols,

but Yahweh made the heavens.

6 Honor and majesty are before him.

Strength and beauty are in his sanctuary.

7 Ascribe to Yahweh, you families of nations,

ascribe to Yahweh glory and strength.

8 Ascribe to Yahweh the glory due to his name.

Bring an offering, and come into his courts.

9 Worship Yahweh in holy array.

Tremble before him, all the earth.

10 Say among the nations, “Yahweh reigns.”

The world is also established.

It can’t be moved.

He will judge the peoples with equity.

11 Let the heavens be glad, and let the earth rejoice.

Let the sea roar, and its fullness!

12 Let the field and all that is in it exult!

Then all the trees of the woods shall sing for joy

13 before Yahweh; for he comes,

for he comes to judge the earth.

He will judge the world with righteousness,

the peoples with his truth.

Psalms 97

1 Yahweh reigns!

Let the earth rejoice!

Let the multitude of islands be glad!

2 Clouds and darkness are around him.

Righteousness and justice are the foundation of his throne.

3 A fire goes before him,

and burns up his adversaries on every side.

4 His lightning lights up the world.

The earth sees, and trembles.

5 The mountains melt like wax at the presence of Yahweh,

at the presence of the Lord of the whole earth.

6 The heavens declare his righteousness.

All the peoples have seen his glory.

7 Let all them be shamed who serve engraved images,

who boast in their idols.

Worship him, all you gods![*]

8 Zion heard and was glad.

The daughters of Judah rejoiced,

because of your judgments, Yahweh.

9 For you, Yahweh, are most high above all the earth.

You are exalted far above all gods.

10 You who love Yahweh, hate evil.

He preserves the souls of his saints.

He delivers them out of the hand of the wicked.

11 Light is sown for the righteous,

and gladness for the upright in heart.

12 Be glad in Yahweh, you righteous people!

Give thanks to his holy Name.

LXX reads “angels” instead of “gods”.

Psalms 102

1 Hear my prayer, Yahweh!

Let my cry come to you.

2 Don’t hide your face from me in the day of my distress.

Turn your ear to me.

Answer me quickly in the day when I call.

3 For my days consume away like smoke.

My bones are burned as a torch.

4 My heart is blighted like grass, and withered,

for I forget to eat my bread.

5 By reason of the voice of my groaning,

my bones stick to my skin.

6 I am like a pelican of the wilderness.

I have become as an owl of the waste places.

7 I watch, and have become like a sparrow that is alone on the housetop.

8 My enemies reproach me all day.

Those who are mad at me use my name as a curse.

9 For I have eaten ashes like bread,

and mixed my drink with tears,

10 Because of your indignation and your wrath,

for you have taken me up, and thrown me away.

11 My days are like a long shadow.

I have withered like grass.

12 But you, Yahweh, will remain forever;

your renown endures to all generations.

13 You will arise and have mercy on Zion;

for it is time to have pity on her.

Yes, the set time has come.

14 For your servants take pleasure in her stones,

and have pity on her dust.

15 So the nations will fear Yahweh’s name;

all the kings of the earth your glory.

16 For Yahweh has built up Zion.

He has appeared in his glory.

17 He has responded to the prayer of the destitute,

and has not despised their prayer.

18 This will be written for the generation to come.

A people which will be created will praise Yah.

19 For he has looked down from the height of his sanctuary.

From heaven, Yahweh saw the earth;

20 to hear the groans of the prisoner;

to free those who are condemned to death;

21 that men may declare Yahweh’s name in Zion,

and his praise in Jerusalem;

22 when the peoples are gathered together,

the kingdoms, to serve Yahweh.

23 He weakened my strength along the course.

He shortened my days.

24 I said, “My God, don’t take me away in the middle of my days.

Your years are throughout all generations.

25 Of old, you laid the foundation of the earth.

The heavens are the work of your hands.

26 They will perish, but you will endure.

Yes, all of them will wear out like a garment.

You will change them like a cloak, and they will be changed.

27 But you are the same.

Your years will have no end.

28 The children of your servants will continue.

Their offspring[*] will be established before you.”

or, seed

Psalms 103

1 Praise Yahweh, my soul!

All that is within me, praise his holy name!

2 Praise Yahweh, my soul,

and don’t forget all his benefits;

3 who forgives all your sins;

who heals all your diseases;

4 who redeems your life from destruction;

who crowns you with loving kindness and tender mercies;

5 who satisfies your desire with good things,

so that your youth is renewed like the eagle’s.

6 Yahweh executes righteous acts,

and justice for all who are oppressed.

7 He made known his ways to Moses,

his deeds to the children of Israel.

8 Yahweh is merciful and gracious,

slow to anger, and abundant in loving kindness.

9 He will not always accuse;

neither will he stay angry forever.

10 He has not dealt with us according to our sins,

nor repaid us for our iniquities.

11 For as the heavens are high above the earth,

so great is his loving kindness toward those who fear him.

12 As far as the east is from the west,

so far has he removed our transgressions from us.

13 Like a father has compassion on his children,

so Yahweh has compassion on those who fear him.

14 For he knows how we are made.

He remembers that we are dust.

15 As for man, his days are like grass.

As a flower of the field, so he flourishes.

16 For the wind passes over it, and it is gone.

Its place remembers it no more.

17 But Yahweh’s loving kindness is from everlasting to everlasting with those who fear him,

his righteousness to children’s children;

18 to those who keep his covenant,

to those who remember to obey his precepts.

19 Yahweh has established his throne in the heavens.

His kingdom rules over all.

20 Praise Yahweh, you angels of his,

who are mighty in strength, who fulfill his word,

obeying the voice of his word.

21 Praise Yahweh, all you armies of his,

you servants of his, who do his pleasure.

22 Praise Yahweh, all you works of his,

in all places of his dominion.

Praise Yahweh, my soul!

Psalms 104

1 Bless Yahweh, my soul.

Yahweh, my God, you are very great.

You are clothed with honor and majesty.

2 He covers himself with light as with a garment.

He stretches out the heavens like a curtain.

3 He lays the beams of his rooms in the waters.

He makes the clouds his chariot.

He walks on the wings of the wind.

4 He makes his messengers[*] winds;

his servants flames of fire.

5 He laid the foundations of the earth,

that it should not be moved forever.

6 You covered it with the deep as with a cloak.

The waters stood above the mountains.

7 At your rebuke they fled.

At the voice of your thunder they hurried away.

8 The mountains rose,

the valleys sank down,

to the place which you had assigned to them.

9 You have set a boundary that they may not pass over;

that they don’t turn again to cover the earth.

10 He sends springs into the valleys.

They run among the mountains.

11 They give drink to every animal of the field.

The wild donkeys quench their thirst.

12 The birds of the sky nest by them.

They sing among the branches.

13 He waters the mountains from his rooms.

The earth is filled with the fruit of your works.

14 He causes the grass to grow for the livestock,

and plants for man to cultivate,

that he may produce food out of the earth:

15 wine that makes glad the heart of man,

oil to make his face to shine,

and bread that strengthens man’s heart.

16 Yahweh’s trees are well watered,

the cedars of Lebanon, which he has planted;

17 where the birds make their nests.

The stork makes its home in the cypress trees.

18 The high mountains are for the wild goats.

The rocks are a refuge for the rock badgers.

19 He appointed the moon for seasons.

The sun knows when to set.

20 You make darkness, and it is night,

in which all the animals of the forest prowl.

21 The young lions roar after their prey,

and seek their food from God.

22 The sun rises, and they steal away,

and lay down in their dens.

23 Man goes out to his work,

to his labor until the evening.

24 Yahweh, how many are your works!

In wisdom have you made them all.

The earth is full of your riches.

25 There is the sea, great and wide,

in which are innumerable living things,

both small and large animals.

26 There the ships go,

and leviathan, whom you formed to play there.

27 These all wait for you,

that you may give them their food in due season.

28 You give to them; they gather.

You open your hand; they are satisfied with good.

29 You hide your face: they are troubled;

you take away their breath: they die, and return to the dust.

30 You send out your Spirit and they are created.

You renew the face of the ground.

31 Let Yahweh’s glory endure forever.

Let Yahweh rejoice in his works.

32 He looks at the earth, and it trembles.

He touches the mountains, and they smoke.

33 I will sing to Yahweh as long as I live.

I will sing praise to my God while I have any being.

34 Let my meditation be sweet to him.

I will rejoice in Yahweh.

35 Let sinners be consumed out of the earth.

Let the wicked be no more.

Bless Yahweh, my soul.

Praise Yah!

or, angels

Psalms 105

1 Give thanks to Yahweh! Call on his name!

Make his doings known among the peoples.

2 Sing to him, sing praises to him!

Tell of all his marvelous works.

3 Glory in his holy name.

Let the heart of those who seek Yahweh rejoice.

4 Seek Yahweh and his strength.

Seek his face forever more.

5 Remember his marvelous works that he has done;

his wonders, and the judgments of his mouth,

6 you offspring[*] of Abraham, his servant,

you children of Jacob, his chosen ones.

7 He is Yahweh, our God.

His judgments are in all the earth.

8 He has remembered his covenant forever,

the word which he commanded to a thousand generations,

9 the covenant which he made with Abraham,

his oath to Isaac,

10 and confirmed the same to Jacob for a statute;

to Israel for an everlasting covenant,

11 saying, “To you I will give the land of Canaan,

the lot of your inheritance”;

12 when they were but a few men in number,

yes, very few, and foreigners in it.

13 They went about from nation to nation,

from one kingdom to another people.

14 He allowed no one to do them wrong.

Yes, he reproved kings for their sakes,

15 “Don’t touch my anointed ones!

Do my prophets no harm!”

16 He called for a famine on the land.

He destroyed the food supplies.

17 He sent a man before them.

Joseph was sold for a slave.

18 They bruised his feet with shackles.

His neck was locked in irons,

19 until the time that his word happened,

and Yahweh’s word proved him true.

20 The king sent and freed him;

even the ruler of peoples, and let him go free.

21 He made him lord of his house,

and ruler of all of his possessions;

22 to discipline his princes at his pleasure,

and to teach his elders wisdom.

23 Israel also came into Egypt.

Jacob lived in the land of Ham.

24 He increased his people greatly,

and made them stronger than their adversaries.

25 He turned their heart to hate his people,

to conspire against his servants.

26 He sent Moses, his servant,

and Aaron, whom he had chosen.

27 They performed miracles among them,

and wonders in the land of Ham.

28 He sent darkness, and made it dark.

They didn’t rebel against his words.

29 He turned their waters into blood,

and killed their fish.

30 Their land swarmed with frogs,

even in the rooms of their kings.

31 He spoke, and swarms of flies came,

and lice in all their borders.

32 He gave them hail for rain,

with lightning in their land.

33 He struck their vines and also their fig trees,

and shattered the trees of their country.

34 He spoke, and the locusts came,

and the grasshoppers, without number,

35 ate up every plant in their land;

and ate up the fruit of their ground.

36 He struck also all the firstborn in their land,

the first fruits of all their manhood.

37 He brought them out with silver and gold.

There was not one feeble person among his tribes.

38 Egypt was glad when they departed,

for the fear of them had fallen on them.

39 He spread a cloud for a covering,

fire to give light in the night.

40 They asked, and he brought quails,

and satisfied them with the bread of the sky.

41 He opened the rock, and waters gushed out.

They ran as a river in the dry places.

42 For he remembered his holy word,

and Abraham, his servant.

43 He brought his people out with joy,

his chosen with singing.

44 He gave them the lands of the nations.

They took the labor of the peoples in possession,

45 that they might keep his statutes,

and observe his laws.

Praise Yah!

or, seed

Psalms 106

1 Praise Yahweh!

Give thanks to Yahweh, for he is good,

for his loving kindness endures forever.

2 Who can utter the mighty acts of Yahweh,

or fully declare all his praise?

3 Blessed are those who keep justice.

Blessed is one who does what is right at all times.

4 Remember me, Yahweh, with the favor that you show to your people.

Visit me with your salvation,

5 that I may see the prosperity of your chosen,

that I may rejoice in the gladness of your nation,

that I may glory with your inheritance.

6 We have sinned with our fathers.

We have committed iniquity.

We have done wickedly.

7 Our fathers didn’t understand your wonders in Egypt.

They didn’t remember the multitude of your loving kindnesses,

but were rebellious at the sea, even at the Red Sea.

8 Nevertheless he saved them for his name’s sake,

that he might make his mighty power known.

9 He rebuked the Red Sea also, and it was dried up;

so he led them through the depths, as through a desert.

10 He saved them from the hand of him who hated them,

and redeemed them from the hand of the enemy.

11 The waters covered their adversaries.

There was not one of them left.

12 Then they believed his words.

They sang his praise.

13 They soon forgot his works.

They didn’t wait for his counsel,

14 but gave in to craving in the desert,

and tested God in the wasteland.

15 He gave them their request,

but sent leanness into their soul.

16 They envied Moses also in the camp,

and Aaron, Yahweh’s saint.

17 The earth opened and swallowed up Dathan,

and covered the company of Abiram.

18 A fire was kindled in their company.

The flame burned up the wicked.

19 They made a calf in Horeb,

and worshiped a molten image.

20 Thus they exchanged their glory

for an image of a bull that eats grass.

21 They forgot God, their Savior,

who had done great things in Egypt,

22 Wondrous works in the land of Ham,

and awesome things by the Red Sea.

23 Therefore he said that he would destroy them,

had Moses, his chosen, not stood before him in the breach,

to turn away his wrath, so that he wouldn’t destroy them.

24 Yes, they despised the pleasant land.

They didn’t believe his word,

25 but murmured in their tents,

and didn’t listen to Yahweh’s voice.

26 Therefore he swore to them

that he would overthrow them in the wilderness,

27 that he would overthrow their offspring[*] among the nations,

and scatter them in the lands.

28 They joined themselves also to Baal Peor,

and ate the sacrifices of the dead.

29 Thus they provoked him to anger with their deeds.

The plague broke in on them.

30 Then Phinehas stood up, and executed judgment,

so the plague was stopped.

31 That was credited to him for righteousness,

for all generations to come.

32 They angered him also at the waters of Meribah,

so that Moses was troubled for their sakes;

33 because they were rebellious against his spirit,

he spoke rashly with his lips.

34 They didn’t destroy the peoples,

as Yahweh commanded them,

35 but mixed themselves with the nations,

and learned their works.

36 They served their idols,

which became a snare to them.

37 Yes, they sacrificed their sons and their daughters to demons.

38 They shed innocent blood,

even the blood of their sons and of their daughters,

whom they sacrificed to the idols of Canaan.

The land was polluted with blood.

39 Thus were they defiled with their works,

and prostituted themselves in their deeds.

40 Therefore Yahweh burned with anger against his people.

He abhorred his inheritance.

41 He gave them into the hand of the nations.

Those who hated them ruled over them.

42 Their enemies also oppressed them.

They were brought into subjection under their hand.

43 He rescued them many times,

but they were rebellious in their counsel,

and were brought low in their iniquity.

44 Nevertheless he regarded their distress,

when he heard their cry.

45 He remembered for them his covenant,

and repented according to the multitude of his loving kindnesses.

46 He made them also to be pitied

by all those who carried them captive.

47 Save us, Yahweh, our God,

gather us from among the nations,

to give thanks to your holy name,

to triumph in your praise!

48 Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel,

from everlasting even to everlasting!

Let all the people say, “Amen.”

Praise Yah!

or, seed

Psalms 107

1 Give thanks to Yahweh,[*] for he is good,

for his loving kindness endures forever.

2 Let the redeemed by Yahweh say so,

whom he has redeemed from the hand of the adversary,

3 And gathered out of the lands,

from the east and from the west,

from the north and from the south.

4 They wandered in the wilderness in a desert way.

They found no city to live in.

5 Hungry and thirsty,

their soul fainted in them.

6 Then they cried to Yahweh in their trouble,

and he delivered them out of their distresses,

7 he led them also by a straight way,

that they might go to a city to live in.

8 Let them praise Yahweh for his loving kindness,

for his wonderful deeds to the children of men!

9 For he satisfies the longing soul.

He fills the hungry soul with good.

10 Some sat in darkness and in the shadow of death,

being bound in affliction and iron,

11 because they rebelled against the words of God,[*]

and condemned the counsel of the Most High.

12 Therefore he brought down their heart with labor.

They fell down, and there was no one to help.

13 Then they cried to Yahweh in their trouble,

and he saved them out of their distresses.

14 He brought them out of darkness and the shadow of death,

and broke away their chains.

15 Let them praise Yahweh for his loving kindness,

for his wonderful deeds to the children of men!

16 For he has broken the gates of brass,

and cut through bars of iron.

17 Fools are afflicted because of their disobedience,

and because of their iniquities.

18 Their soul abhors all kinds of food.

They draw near to the gates of death.

19 Then they cry to Yahweh in their trouble,

he saves them out of their distresses.

20 He sends his word, and heals them,

and delivers them from their graves.

21 Let them praise Yahweh for his loving kindness,

for his wonderful deeds to the children of men!

22 Let them offer the sacrifices of thanksgiving,

and declare his deeds with singing.

23 Those who go down to the sea in ships,

who do business in great waters;

24 These see Yahweh’s deeds,

and his wonders in the deep.

25 For he commands, and raises the stormy wind,

which lifts up its waves.

26 They mount up to the sky; they go down again to the depths.

Their soul melts away because of trouble.

27 They reel back and forth, and stagger like a drunken man,

and are at their wits’ end.

28 Then they cry to Yahweh in their trouble,

and he brings them out of their distress.

29 He makes the storm a calm,

so that its waves are still.

30 Then they are glad because it is calm,

so he brings them to their desired haven.

31 Let them praise Yahweh for his loving kindness,

for his wonderful deeds for the children of men!

32 Let them exalt him also in the assembly of the people,

and praise him in the seat of the elders.

33 He turns rivers into a desert,

water springs into a thirsty ground,

34 and a fruitful land into a salt waste,

for the wickedness of those who dwell in it.

35 He turns a desert into a pool of water,

and a dry land into water springs.

36 There he makes the hungry live,

that they may prepare a city to live in,

37 sow fields, plant vineyards,

and reap the fruits of increase.

38 He blesses them also, so that they are multiplied greatly.

He doesn’t allow their livestock to decrease.

39 Again, they are diminished and bowed down

through oppression, trouble, and sorrow.

40 He pours contempt on princes,

and causes them to wander in a trackless waste.

41 Yet he lifts the needy out of their affliction,

and increases their families like a flock.

42 The upright will see it, and be glad.

All the wicked will shut their mouths.

43 Whoever is wise will pay attention to these things.

They will consider the loving kindnesses of Yahweh.

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Psalms 109

1 God of my praise, don’t remain silent,

2 for they have opened the mouth of the wicked and the mouth of deceit against me.

They have spoken to me with a lying tongue.

3 They have also surrounded me with words of hatred,

and fought against me without a cause.

4 In return for my love, they are my adversaries;

but I am in prayer.

5 They have rewarded me evil for good,

and hatred for my love.

6 Set a wicked man over him.

Let an adversary stand at his right hand.

7 When he is judged, let him come out guilty.

Let his prayer be turned into sin.

8 Let his days be few.

Let another take his office.

9 Let his children be fatherless,

and his wife a widow.

10 Let his children be wandering beggars.

Let them be sought from their ruins.

11 Let the creditor seize all that he has.

Let strangers plunder the fruit of his labor.

12 Let there be no one to extend kindness to him,

neither let there be anyone to have pity on his fatherless children.

13 Let his posterity be cut off.

In the generation following let their name be blotted out.

14 Let the iniquity of his fathers be remembered by Yahweh.

Don’t let the sin of his mother be blotted out.

15 Let them be before Yahweh continually,

that he may cut off their memory from the earth;

16 because he didn’t remember to show kindness,

but persecuted the poor and needy man,

the broken in heart, to kill them.

17 Yes, he loved cursing, and it came to him.

He didn’t delight in blessing, and it was far from him.

18 He clothed himself also with cursing as with his garment.

It came into his inward parts like water,

like oil into his bones.

19 Let it be to him as the clothing with which he covers himself,

for the belt that is always around him.

20 This is the reward of my adversaries from Yahweh,

of those who speak evil against my soul.

21 But deal with me, Yahweh the Lord,[*] for your name’s sake,

because your loving kindness is good, deliver me;

22 for I am poor and needy.

My heart is wounded within me.

23 I fade away like an evening shadow.

I am shaken off like a locust.

24 My knees are weak through fasting.

My body is thin and lacks fat.

25 I have also become a reproach to them.

When they see me, they shake their head.

26 Help me, Yahweh, my God.

Save me according to your loving kindness;

27 that they may know that this is your hand;

that you, Yahweh, have done it.

28 They may curse, but you bless.

When they arise, they will be shamed,

but your servant shall rejoice.

29 Let my adversaries be clothed with dishonor.

Let them cover themselves with their own shame as with a robe.

30 I will give great thanks to Yahweh with my mouth.

Yes, I will praise him among the multitude.

31 For he will stand at the right hand of the needy,

to save him from those who judge his soul.

The word translated “Lord” is “Adonai.”

Psalms 111

1 Praise Yah![*]

I will give thanks to Yahweh with my whole heart,

in the council of the upright, and in the congregation.

2 Yahweh’s works are great,

pondered by all those who delight in them.

3 His work is honor and majesty.

His righteousness endures forever.

4 He has caused his wonderful works to be remembered.

Yahweh is gracious and merciful.

5 He has given food to those who fear him.

He always remembers his covenant.

6 He has shown his people the power of his works,

in giving them the heritage of the nations.

7 The works of his hands are truth and justice.

All his precepts are sure.

8 They are established forever and ever.

They are done in truth and uprightness.

9 He has sent redemption to his people.

He has ordained his covenant forever.

His name is holy and awesome!

10 The fear of Yahweh is the beginning of wisdom.

All those who do his work have a good understanding.

His praise endures forever!

Psalm 111 is an acrostic poem, with each verse after the initial “Praise Yah!” starting with a letter of the alphabet (ordered from Alef to Tav).

Psalms 112

1 Praise Yah![*]

Blessed is the man who fears Yahweh,

who delights greatly in his commandments.

2 His offspring[*] will be mighty in the land.

The generation of the upright will be blessed.

3 Wealth and riches are in his house.

His righteousness endures forever.

4 Light dawns in the darkness for the upright,

gracious, merciful, and righteous.

5 It is well with the man who deals graciously and lends.

He will maintain his cause in judgment.

6 For he will never be shaken.

The righteous will be remembered forever.

7 He will not be afraid of evil news.

His heart is steadfast, trusting in Yahweh.

8 His heart is established.

He will not be afraid in the end when he sees his adversaries.

9 He has dispersed, he has given to the poor.

His righteousness endures forever.

His horn will be exalted with honor.

10 The wicked will see it, and be grieved.

He shall gnash with his teeth, and melt away.

The desire of the wicked will perish.

Psalm 112 is an acrostic poem, with each verse after the initial “Praise Yah!” starting with a letter of the alphabet (ordered from Alef to Tav).

or, seed

Psalms 115

1 Not to us, Yahweh, not to us,

but to your name give glory,

for your loving kindness, and for your truth’s sake.

2 Why should the nations say,

“Where is their God, now?”

3 But our God is in the heavens.

He does whatever he pleases.

4 Their idols are silver and gold,

the work of men’s hands.

5 They have mouths, but they don’t speak.

They have eyes, but they don’t see.

6 They have ears, but they don’t hear.

They have noses, but they don’t smell.

7 They have hands, but they don’t feel.

They have feet, but they don’t walk,

neither do they speak through their throat.

8 Those who make them will be like them;

yes, everyone who trusts in them.

9 Israel, trust in Yahweh!

He is their help and their shield.

10 House of Aaron, trust in Yahweh!

He is their help and their shield.

11 You who fear Yahweh, trust in Yahweh!

He is their help and their shield.

12 Yahweh remembers us. He will bless us.

He will bless the house of Israel.

He will bless the house of Aaron.

13 He will bless those who fear Yahweh,

both small and great.

14 May Yahweh increase you more and more,

you and your children.

15 Blessed are you by Yahweh,

who made heaven and earth.

16 The heavens are the heavens of Yahweh;

but the earth has he given to the children of men.

17 The dead don’t praise Yah,

neither any who go down into silence;

18 But we will bless Yah,

from this time forward and forever more.

Praise Yah!

Psalms 116

1 I love Yahweh, because he listens to my voice,

and my cries for mercy.

2 Because he has turned his ear to me,

therefore I will call on him as long as I live.

3 The cords of death surrounded me,

the pains of Sheol[*] got a hold of me.

I found trouble and sorrow.

4 Then I called on Yahweh’s name:

“Yahweh, I beg you, deliver my soul.”

5 Yahweh is Gracious and righteous.

Yes, our God is merciful.

6 Yahweh preserves the simple.

I was brought low, and he saved me.

7 Return to your rest, my soul,

for Yahweh has dealt bountifully with you.

8 For you have delivered my soul from death,

my eyes from tears,

and my feet from falling.

9 I will walk before Yahweh in the land of the living.

10 I believed, therefore I said,

“I was greatly afflicted.”

11 I said in my haste,

“All men are liars.”

12 What will I give to Yahweh for all his benefits toward me?

13 I will take the cup of salvation, and call on Yahweh’s name.

14 I will pay my vows to Yahweh,

yes, in the presence of all his people.

15 Precious in Yahweh’s sight is the death of his saints.

16 Yahweh, truly I am your servant.

I am your servant, the son of your servant.

You have freed me from my chains.

17 I will offer to you the sacrifice of thanksgiving,

and will call on Yahweh’s name.

18 I will pay my vows to Yahweh,

yes, in the presence of all his people,

19 in the courts of Yahweh’s house,

in the middle of you, Jerusalem.

Praise Yah!

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 118

1 Give thanks to Yahweh, for he is good,

for his loving kindness endures forever.

2 Let Israel now say

that his loving kindness endures forever.

3 Let the house of Aaron now say

that his loving kindness endures forever.

4 Now let those who fear Yahweh say

that his loving kindness endures forever.

5 Out of my distress, I called on Yah.

Yah answered me with freedom.

6 Yahweh is on my side. I will not be afraid.

What can man do to me?

7 Yahweh is on my side among those who help me.

Therefore I will look in triumph at those who hate me.

8 It is better to take refuge in Yahweh,

than to put confidence in man.

9 It is better to take refuge in Yahweh,

than to put confidence in princes.

10 All the nations surrounded me,

but in Yahweh’s name, I cut them off.

11 They surrounded me, yes, they surrounded me.

In Yahweh’s name I indeed cut them off.

12 They surrounded me like bees.

They are quenched like the burning thorns.

In Yahweh’s name I cut them off.

13 You pushed me back hard, to make me fall,

but Yahweh helped me.

14 Yah is my strength and song.

He has become my salvation.

15 The voice of rejoicing and salvation is in the tents of the righteous.

“The right hand of Yahweh does valiantly.

16 The right hand of Yahweh is exalted!

The right hand of Yahweh does valiantly!”

17 I will not die, but live,

and declare Yah’s works.

18 Yah has punished me severely,

but he has not given me over to death.

19 Open to me the gates of righteousness.

I will enter into them.

I will give thanks to Yah.

20 This is the gate of Yahweh;

the righteous will enter into it.

21 I will give thanks to you, for you have answered me,

and have become my salvation.

22 The stone which the builders rejected

has become the cornerstone.[*]

23 This is Yahweh’s doing.

It is marvelous in our eyes.

24 This is the day that Yahweh has made.

We will rejoice and be glad in it!

25 Save us now, we beg you, Yahweh!

Yahweh, we beg you, send prosperity now.

26 Blessed is he who comes in Yahweh’s name!

We have blessed you out of Yahweh’s house.

27 Yahweh is God, and he has given us light.

Bind the sacrifice with cords, even to the horns of the altar.

28 You are my God, and I will give thanks to you.

You are my God, I will exalt you.

29 Oh give thanks to Yahweh, for he is good,

for his loving kindness endures forever.

Literally, head of the corner

Psalms 119

1 Blessed are those whose ways are blameless,

who walk according to Yahweh’s law.

2 Blessed are those who keep his statutes,

who seek him with their whole heart.

3 Yes, they do nothing wrong.

They walk in his ways.

4 You have commanded your precepts,

that we should fully obey them.

5 Oh that my ways were steadfast

to obey your statutes!

6 Then I wouldn’t be disappointed,

when I consider all of your commandments.

7 I will give thanks to you with uprightness of heart,

when I learn your righteous judgments.

8 I will observe your statutes.

Don’t utterly forsake me.

BET

9 How can a young man keep his way pure?

By living according to your word.

10 With my whole heart, I have sought you.

Don’t let me wander from your commandments.

11 I have hidden your word in my heart,

that I might not sin against you.

12 Blessed are you, Yahweh.

Teach me your statutes.

13 With my lips,

I have declared all the ordinances of your mouth.

14 I have rejoiced in the way of your testimonies,

as much as in all riches.

15 I will meditate on your precepts,

and consider your ways.

16 I will delight myself in your statutes.

I will not forget your word.

GIMEL

17 Do good to your servant.

I will live and I will obey your word.

18 Open my eyes,

that I may see wondrous things out of your law.

19 I am a stranger on the earth.

Don’t hide your commandments from me.

20 My soul is consumed with longing for your ordinances at all times.

21 You have rebuked the proud who are cursed,

who wander from your commandments.

22 Take reproach and contempt away from me,

for I have kept your statutes.

23 Though princes sit and slander me,

your servant will meditate on your statutes.

24 Indeed your statutes are my delight,

and my counselors.

DALED

25 My soul is laid low in the dust.

Revive me according to your word!

26 I declared my ways, and you answered me.

Teach me your statutes.

27 Let me understand the teaching of your precepts!

Then I will meditate on your wondrous works.

28 My soul is weary with sorrow:

strengthen me according to your word.

29 Keep me from the way of deceit.

Grant me your law graciously!

30 I have chosen the way of truth.

I have set your ordinances before me.

31 I cling to your statutes, Yahweh.

Don’t let me be disappointed.

32 I run in the path of your commandments,

for you have set my heart free.

HEY

33 Teach me, Yahweh, the way of your statutes.

I will keep them to the end.

34 Give me understanding, and I will keep your law.

Yes, I will obey it with my whole heart.

35 Direct me in the path of your commandments,

for I delight in them.

36 Turn my heart toward your statutes,

not toward selfish gain.

37 Turn my eyes away from looking at worthless things.

Revive me in your ways.

38 Fulfill your promise to your servant,

that you may be feared.

39 Take away my disgrace that I dread,

for your ordinances are good.

40 Behold, I long for your precepts!

Revive me in your righteousness.

WAW

41 Let your loving kindness also come to me, Yahweh,

your salvation, according to your word.

42 So I will have an answer for him who reproaches me,

for I trust in your word.

43 Don’t snatch the word of truth out of my mouth,

for I put my hope in your ordinances.

44 So I will obey your law continually,

forever and ever.

45 I will walk in liberty,

for I have sought your precepts.

46 I will also speak of your statutes before kings,

and will not be disappointed.

47 I will delight myself in your commandments,

because I love them.

48 I reach out my hands for your commandments, which I love.

I will meditate on your statutes.

ZAYIN

49 Remember your word to your servant,

because you gave me hope.

50 This is my comfort in my affliction,

for your word has revived me.

51 The arrogant mock me excessively,

but I don’t swerve from your law.

52 I remember your ordinances of old, Yahweh,

and have comforted myself.

53 Indignation has taken hold on me,

because of the wicked who forsake your law.

54 Your statutes have been my songs,

in the house where I live.

55 I have remembered your name, Yahweh, in the night,

and I obey your law.

56 This is my way,

that I keep your precepts.

CHET

57 Yahweh is my portion.

I promised to obey your words.

58 I sought your favor with my whole heart.

Be merciful to me according to your word.

59 I considered my ways,

and turned my steps to your statutes.

60 I will hurry, and not delay,

to obey your commandments.

61 The ropes of the wicked bind me,

but I won’t forget your law.

62 At midnight I will rise to give thanks to you,

because of your righteous ordinances.

63 I am a friend of all those who fear you,

of those who observe your precepts.

64 The earth is full of your loving kindness, Yahweh.

Teach me your statutes.

TET

65 Do good to your servant,

according to your word, Yahweh.

66 Teach me good judgment and knowledge,

for I believe in your commandments.

67 Before I was afflicted, I went astray;

but now I observe your word.

68 You are good, and do good.

Teach me your statutes.

69 The proud have smeared a lie upon me.

With my whole heart, I will keep your precepts.

70 Their heart is as callous as the fat,

but I delight in your law.

71 It is good for me that I have been afflicted,

that I may learn your statutes.

72 The law of your mouth is better to me than thousands of pieces of gold and silver.

YUD

73 Your hands have made me and formed me.

Give me understanding, that I may learn your commandments.

74 Those who fear you will see me and be glad,

because I have put my hope in your word.

75 Yahweh, I know that your judgments are righteous,

that in faithfulness you have afflicted me.

76 Please let your loving kindness be for my comfort,

according to your word to your servant.

77 Let your tender mercies come to me, that I may live;

for your law is my delight.

78 Let the proud be disappointed, for they have overthrown me wrongfully.

I will meditate on your precepts.

79 Let those who fear you turn to me.

They will know your statutes.

80 Let my heart be blameless toward your decrees,

that I may not be disappointed.

KAF

81 My soul faints for your salvation.

I hope in your word.

82 My eyes fail for your word.

I say, “When will you comfort me?”

83 For I have become like a wineskin in the smoke.

I don’t forget your statutes.

84 How many are the days of your servant?

When will you execute judgment on those who persecute me?

85 The proud have dug pits for me,

contrary to your law.

86 All of your commandments are faithful.

They persecute me wrongfully.

Help me!

87 They had almost wiped me from the earth,

but I didn’t forsake your precepts.

88 Preserve my life according to your loving kindness,

so I will obey the statutes of your mouth.

LAMED

89 Yahweh, your word is settled in heaven forever.

90 Your faithfulness is to all generations.

You have established the earth, and it remains.

91 Your laws remain to this day,

for all things serve you.

92 Unless your law had been my delight,

I would have perished in my affliction.

93 I will never forget your precepts,

for with them, you have revived me.

94 I am yours.

Save me, for I have sought your precepts.

95 The wicked have waited for me, to destroy me.

I will consider your statutes.

96 I have seen a limit to all perfection,

but your commands are boundless.

MEM

97 How I love your law!

It is my meditation all day.

98 Your commandments make me wiser than my enemies,

for your commandments are always with me.

99 I have more understanding than all my teachers,

for your testimonies are my meditation.

100 I understand more than the aged,

because I have kept your precepts.

101 I have kept my feet from every evil way,

that I might observe your word.

102 I have not turned aside from your ordinances,

for you have taught me.

103 How sweet are your promises to my taste,

more than honey to my mouth!

104 Through your precepts, I get understanding;

therefore I hate every false way.

NUN

105 Your word is a lamp to my feet,

and a light for my path.

106 I have sworn, and have confirmed it,

that I will obey your righteous ordinances.

107 I am afflicted very much.

Revive me, Yahweh, according to your word.

108 Accept, I beg you, the willing offerings of my mouth.

Yahweh, teach me your ordinances.

109 My soul is continually in my hand,

yet I won’t forget your law.

110 The wicked have laid a snare for me,

yet I haven’t gone astray from your precepts.

111 I have taken your testimonies as a heritage forever,

for they are the joy of my heart.

112 I have set my heart to perform your statutes forever,

even to the end.

SAMEKH

113 I hate double-minded men,

but I love your law.

114 You are my hiding place and my shield.

I hope in your word.

115 Depart from me, you evildoers,

that I may keep the commandments of my God.

116 Uphold me according to your word, that I may live.

Let me not be ashamed of my hope.

117 Hold me up, and I will be safe,

and will have respect for your statutes continually.

118 You reject all those who stray from your statutes,

for their deceit is in vain.

119 You put away all the wicked of the earth like dross.

Therefore I love your testimonies.

120 My flesh trembles for fear of you.

I am afraid of your judgments.

AYIN

121 I have done what is just and righteous.

Don’t leave me to my oppressors.

122 Ensure your servant’s well-being.

Don’t let the proud oppress me.

123 My eyes fail looking for your salvation,

for your righteous word.

124 Deal with your servant according to your loving kindness.

Teach me your statutes.

125 I am your servant. Give me understanding,

that I may know your testimonies.

126 It is time to act, Yahweh,

for they break your law.

127 Therefore I love your commandments more than gold,

yes, more than pure gold.

128 Therefore I consider all of your precepts to be right.

I hate every false way.

PEY

129 Your testimonies are wonderful,

therefore my soul keeps them.

130 The entrance of your words gives light.

It gives understanding to the simple.

131 I opened my mouth wide and panted,

for I longed for your commandments.

132 Turn to me, and have mercy on me,

as you always do to those who love your name.

133 Establish my footsteps in your word.

Don’t let any iniquity have dominion over me.

134 Redeem me from the oppression of man,

so I will observe your precepts.

135 Make your face shine on your servant.

Teach me your statutes.

136 Streams of tears run down my eyes,

because they don’t observe your law.

TZADI

137 You are righteous, Yahweh.

Your judgments are upright.

138 You have commanded your statutes in righteousness.

They are fully trustworthy.

139 My zeal wears me out,

because my enemies ignore your words.

140 Your promises have been thoroughly tested,

and your servant loves them.

141 I am small and despised.

I don’t forget your precepts.

142 Your righteousness is an everlasting righteousness.

Your law is truth.

143 Trouble and anguish have taken hold of me.

Your commandments are my delight.

144 Your testimonies are righteous forever.

Give me understanding, that I may live.

KUF

145 I have called with my whole heart.

Answer me, Yahweh!

I will keep your statutes.

146 I have called to you. Save me!

I will obey your statutes.

147 I rise before dawn and cry for help.

I put my hope in your words.

148 My eyes stay open through the night watches,

that I might meditate on your word.

149 Hear my voice according to your loving kindness.

Revive me, Yahweh, according to your ordinances.

150 They draw near who follow after wickedness.

They are far from your law.

151 You are near, Yahweh.

All your commandments are truth.

152 Of old I have known from your testimonies,

that you have founded them forever.

RESH

153 Consider my affliction, and deliver me,

for I don’t forget your law.

154 Plead my cause, and redeem me!

Revive me according to your promise.

155 Salvation is far from the wicked,

for they don’t seek your statutes.

156 Great are your tender mercies, Yahweh.

Revive me according to your ordinances.

157 Many are my persecutors and my adversaries.

I haven’t swerved from your testimonies.

158 I look at the faithless with loathing,

because they don’t observe your word.

159 Consider how I love your precepts.

Revive me, Yahweh, according to your loving kindness.

160 All of your words are truth.

Every one of your righteous ordinances endures forever.

SIN AND SHIN

161 Princes have persecuted me without a cause,

but my heart stands in awe of your words.

162 I rejoice at your word,

as one who finds great plunder.

163 I hate and abhor falsehood.

I love your law.

164 Seven times a day, I praise you,

because of your righteous ordinances.

165 Those who love your law have great peace.

Nothing causes them to stumble.

166 I have hoped for your salvation, Yahweh.

I have done your commandments.

167 My soul has observed your testimonies.

I love them exceedingly.

168 I have obeyed your precepts and your testimonies,

for all my ways are before you.

TAV

169 Let my cry come before you, Yahweh.

Give me understanding according to your word.

170 Let my supplication come before you.

Deliver me according to your word.

171 Let my lips utter praise,

for you teach me your statutes.

172 Let my tongue sing of your word,

for all your commandments are righteousness.

173 Let your hand be ready to help me,

for I have chosen your precepts.

174 I have longed for your salvation, Yahweh.

Your law is my delight.

175 Let my soul live, that I may praise you.

Let your ordinances help me.

176 I have gone astray like a lost sheep.

Seek your servant, for I don’t forget your commandments.

Psalms 132

1 Yahweh, remember David and all his affliction,

2 how he swore to Yahweh,

and vowed to the Mighty One of Jacob:

3 “Surely I will not come into the structure of my house,

nor go up into my bed;

4 I will not give sleep to my eyes,

or slumber to my eyelids;

5 until I find out a place for Yahweh,

a dwelling for the Mighty One of Jacob.”

6 Behold, we heard of it in Ephrathah.

We found it in the field of Jaar:

7 “We will go into his dwelling place.

We will worship at his footstool.

8 Arise, Yahweh, into your resting place;

you, and the ark of your strength.

9 Let your priests be clothed with righteousness.

Let your saints shout for joy!”

10 For your servant David’s sake,

don’t turn away the face of your anointed one.

11 Yahweh has sworn to David in truth.

He will not turn from it:

“I will set the fruit of your body on your throne.

12 If your children will keep my covenant,

my testimony that I will teach them,

their children also will sit on your throne forever more.”

13 For Yahweh has chosen Zion.

He has desired it for his habitation.

14 “This is my resting place forever.

Here I will live, for I have desired it.

15 I will abundantly bless her provision.

I will satisfy her poor with bread.

16 Her priests I will also clothe with salvation.

Her saints will shout aloud for joy.

17 There I will make the horn of David to bud.

I have ordained a lamp for my anointed.

18 I will clothe his enemies with shame,

but on himself, his crown will be resplendent.”

Psalms 135

1 Praise Yah!

Praise Yahweh’s name!

Praise him, you servants of Yahweh,

2 you who stand in Yahweh’s house,

in the courts of our God’s house.

3 Praise Yah, for Yahweh is good.

Sing praises to his name, for that is pleasant.

4 For Yah has chosen Jacob for himself;

Israel for his own possession.

5 For I know that Yahweh is great,

that our Lord is above all gods.

6 Whatever Yahweh pleased, that he has done,

in heaven and in earth, in the seas and in all deeps;

7 who causes the clouds to rise from the ends of the earth;

who makes lightnings with the rain;

who brings the wind out of his treasuries;

8 Who struck the firstborn of Egypt,

both of man and animal;

9 Who sent signs and wonders into the middle of you, Egypt,

on Pharaoh, and on all his servants;

10 who struck many nations,

and killed mighty kings,

11 Sihon king of the Amorites,

Og king of Bashan,

and all the kingdoms of Canaan,

12 and gave their land for a heritage,

a heritage to Israel, his people.

13 Your name, Yahweh, endures forever;

your renown, Yahweh, throughout all generations.

14 For Yahweh will judge his people,

and have compassion on his servants.

15 The idols of the nations are silver and gold,

the work of men’s hands.

16 They have mouths, but they can’t speak.

They have eyes, but they can’t see.

17 They have ears, but they can’t hear;

neither is there any breath in their mouths.

18 Those who make them will be like them;

yes, everyone who trusts in them.

19 House of Israel, praise Yahweh!

House of Aaron, praise Yahweh!

20 House of Levi, praise Yahweh!

You who fear Yahweh, praise Yahweh!

21 Blessed be Yahweh from Zion,

Who dwells at Jerusalem.

Praise Yah!

Psalms 139

1 Yahweh, you have searched me,

and you know me.

2 You know my sitting down and my rising up.

You perceive my thoughts from afar.

3 You search out my path and my lying down,

and are acquainted with all my ways.

4 For there is not a word on my tongue,

but, behold, Yahweh, you know it altogether.

5 You hem me in behind and before.

You laid your hand on me.

6 This knowledge is beyond me.

It’s lofty.

I can’t attain it.

7 Where could I go from your Spirit?

Or where could I flee from your presence?

8 If I ascend up into heaven, you are there.

If I make my bed in Sheol,[*] behold, you are there!

9 If I take the wings of the dawn,

and settle in the uttermost parts of the sea;

10 Even there your hand will lead me,

and your right hand will hold me.

11 If I say, “Surely the darkness will overwhelm me;

the light around me will be night”;

12 even the darkness doesn’t hide from you,

but the night shines as the day.

The darkness is like light to you.

13 For you formed my inmost being.

You knit me together in my mother’s womb.

14 I will give thanks to you,

for I am fearfully and wonderfully made.

Your works are wonderful.

My soul knows that very well.

15 My frame wasn’t hidden from you,

when I was made in secret,

woven together in the depths of the earth.

16 Your eyes saw my body.

In your book they were all written,

the days that were ordained for me,

when as yet there were none of them.

17 How precious to me are your thoughts, God!

How vast is their sum!

18 If I would count them, they are more in number than the sand.

When I wake up, I am still with you.

19 If only you, God, would kill the wicked.

Get away from me, you bloodthirsty men!

20 For they speak against you wickedly.

Your enemies take your name in vain.

21 Yahweh, don’t I hate those who hate you?

Am I not grieved with those who rise up against you?

22 I hate them with perfect hatred.

They have become my enemies.

23 Search me, God, and know my heart.

Try me, and know my thoughts.

24 See if there is any wicked way in me,

and lead me in the everlasting way.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 140

1 Deliver me, Yahweh, from the evil man.

Preserve me from the violent man;

2 those who devise mischief in their hearts.

They continually gather themselves together for war.

3 They have sharpened their tongues like a serpent.

Viper’s poison is under their lips. Selah.

4 Yahweh, keep me from the hands of the wicked.

Preserve me from the violent men who have determined to trip my feet.

5 The proud have hidden a snare for me,

they have spread the cords of a net by the path.

They have set traps for me. Selah.

6 I said to Yahweh, “You are my God.”

Listen to the cry of my petitions, Yahweh.

7 Yahweh, the Lord, the strength of my salvation,

you have covered my head in the day of battle.

8 Yahweh, don’t grant the desires of the wicked.

Don’t let their evil plans succeed, or they will become proud. Selah.

9 As for the head of those who surround me,

let the mischief of their own lips cover them.

10 Let burning coals fall on them.

Let them be thrown into the fire,

into miry pits, from where they never rise.

11 An evil speaker won’t be established in the earth.

Evil will hunt the violent man to overthrow him.

12 I know that Yahweh will maintain the cause of the afflicted,

and justice for the needy.

13 Surely the righteous will give thanks to your name.

The upright will dwell in your presence.

Psalms 141

1 Yahweh, I have called on you.

Come to me quickly!

Listen to my voice when I call to you.

2 Let my prayer be set before you like incense;

the lifting up of my hands like the evening sacrifice.

3 Set a watch, Yahweh, before my mouth.

Keep the door of my lips.

4 Don’t incline my heart to any evil thing,

to practice deeds of wickedness with men who work iniquity.

Don’t let me eat of their delicacies.

5 Let the righteous strike me, it is kindness;

let him reprove me, it is like oil on the head;

don’t let my head refuse it;

Yet my prayer is always against evil deeds.

6 Their judges are thrown down by the sides of the rock.

They will hear my words, for they are well spoken.

7 “As when one plows and breaks up the earth,

our bones are scattered at the mouth of Sheol.”[*]

8 For my eyes are on you, Yahweh, the Lord.

In you, I take refuge.

Don’t leave my soul destitute.

9 Keep me from the snare which they have laid for me,

from the traps of the workers of iniquity.

10 Let the wicked fall together into their own nets,

while I pass by.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Psalms 143

1 Hear my prayer, Yahweh.

Listen to my petitions.

In your faithfulness and righteousness, relieve me.

2 Don’t enter into judgment with your servant,

for in your sight no man living is righteous.

3 For the enemy pursues my soul.

He has struck my life down to the ground.

He has made me live in dark places, as those who have been long dead.

4 Therefore my spirit is overwhelmed within me.

My heart within me is desolate.

5 I remember the days of old.

I meditate on all your doings.

I contemplate the work of your hands.

6 I spread out my hands to you.

My soul thirsts for you, like a parched land. Selah.

7 Hurry to answer me, Yahweh.

My spirit fails.

Don’t hide your face from me,

so that I don’t become like those who go down into the pit.

8 Cause me to hear your loving kindness in the morning,

for I trust in you.

Cause me to know the way in which I should walk,

for I lift up my soul to you.

9 Deliver me, Yahweh, from my enemies.

I flee to you to hide me.

10 Teach me to do your will,

for you are my God.

Your Spirit is good.

Lead me in the land of uprightness.

11 Revive me, Yahweh, for your name’s sake.

In your righteousness, bring my soul out of trouble.

12 In your loving kindness, cut off my enemies,

and destroy all those who afflict my soul,

For I am your servant.

Psalms 144

1 Blessed be Yahweh, my rock,

who teaches my hands to war,

and my fingers to battle:

2 my loving kindness, my fortress,

my high tower, my deliverer,

my shield, and he in whom I take refuge;

who subdues my people under me.

3 Yahweh, what is man, that you care for him?

Or the son of man, that you think of him?

4 Man is like a breath.

His days are like a shadow that passes away.

5 Part your heavens, Yahweh, and come down.

Touch the mountains, and they will smoke.

6 Throw out lightning, and scatter them.

Send out your arrows, and rout them.

7 Stretch out your hand from above,

rescue me, and deliver me out of great waters,

out of the hands of foreigners;

8 whose mouths speak deceit,

Whose right hand is a right hand of falsehood.

9 I will sing a new song to you, God.

On a ten-stringed lyre, I will sing praises to you.

10 You are he who gives salvation to kings,

who rescues David, his servant, from the deadly sword.

11 Rescue me, and deliver me out of the hands of foreigners,

whose mouths speak deceit,

whose right hand is a right hand of falsehood.

12 Then our sons will be like well-nurtured plants,

our daughters like pillars carved to adorn a palace.

13 Our barns are full, filled with all kinds of provision.

Our sheep produce thousands and ten thousands in our fields.

14 Our oxen will pull heavy loads.

There is no breaking in, and no going away,

and no outcry in our streets.

15 Happy are the people who are in such a situation.

Happy are the people whose God is Yahweh.

Psalms 145

1 I will exalt you, my God, the King.

I will praise your name forever and ever.

2 Every day I will praise you.

I will extol your name forever and ever.

3 Great is Yahweh, and greatly to be praised!

His greatness is unsearchable.

4 One generation will commend your works to another,

and will declare your mighty acts.

5 Of the glorious majesty of your honor,

of your wondrous works, I will meditate.

6 Men will speak of the might of your awesome acts.

I will declare your greatness.

7 They will utter the memory of your great goodness,

and will sing of your righteousness.

8 Yahweh is gracious, merciful,

slow to anger, and of great loving kindness.

9 Yahweh is good to all.

His tender mercies are over all his works.

10 All your works will give thanks to you, Yahweh.

Your saints will extol you.

11 They will speak of the glory of your kingdom,

and talk about your power;

12 to make known to the sons of men his mighty acts,

the glory of the majesty of his kingdom.

13 Your kingdom is an everlasting kingdom.

Your dominion endures throughout all generations.

Yahweh is faithful in all his words,

and loving in all his deeds.[*]

14 Yahweh upholds all who fall,

and raises up all those who are bowed down.

15 The eyes of all wait for you.

You give them their food in due season.

16 You open your hand,

and satisfy the desire of every living thing.

17 Yahweh is righteous in all his ways,

and gracious in all his works.

18 Yahweh is near to all those who call on him,

to all who call on him in truth.

19 He will fulfill the desire of those who fear him.

He also will hear their cry, and will save them.

20 Yahweh preserves all those who love him,

but all the wicked he will destroy.

21 My mouth will speak the praise of Yahweh.

Let all flesh bless his holy name forever and ever.

Some manuscripts omit these last two lines.

Psalms 147

1 Praise Yah,

for it is good to sing praises to our God;

for it is pleasant and fitting to praise him.

2 Yahweh builds up Jerusalem.

He gathers together the outcasts of Israel.

3 He heals the broken in heart,

and binds up their wounds.

4 He counts the number of the stars.

He calls them all by their names.

5 Great is our Lord, and mighty in power.

His understanding is infinite.

6 Yahweh upholds the humble.

He brings the wicked down to the ground.

7 Sing to Yahweh with thanksgiving.

Sing praises on the harp to our God,

8 who covers the sky with clouds,

who prepares rain for the earth,

who makes grass grow on the mountains.

9 He provides food for the livestock,

and for the young ravens when they call.

10 He doesn’t delight in the strength of the horse.

He takes no pleasure in the legs of a man.

11 Yahweh takes pleasure in those who fear him,

in those who hope in his loving kindness.

12 Praise Yahweh, Jerusalem!

Praise your God, Zion!

13 For he has strengthened the bars of your gates.

He has blessed your children within you.

14 He makes peace in your borders.

He fills you with the finest of the wheat.

15 He sends out his commandment to the earth.

His word runs very swiftly.

16 He gives snow like wool,

and scatters frost like ashes.

17 He hurls down his hail like pebbles.

Who can stand before his cold?

18 He sends out his word, and melts them.

He causes his wind to blow, and the waters flow.

19 He shows his word to Jacob;

his statutes and his ordinances to Israel.

20 He has not done this for just any nation.

They don’t know his ordinances.

Praise Yah!

Psalms 148

1 Praise Yah!

Praise Yahweh from the heavens!

Praise him in the heights!

2 Praise him, all his angels!

Praise him, all his army!

3 Praise him, sun and moon!

Praise him, all you shining stars!

4 Praise him, you heavens of heavens,

You waters that are above the heavens.

5 Let them praise Yahweh’s name,

For he commanded, and they were created.

6 He has also established them forever and ever.

He has made a decree which will not pass away.

7 Praise Yahweh from the earth,

you great sea creatures, and all depths;

8 lightning and hail, snow and clouds;

stormy wind, fulfilling his word;

9 mountains and all hills;

fruit trees and all cedars;

10 wild animals and all livestock;

small creatures and flying birds;

11 kings of the earth and all peoples;

princes and all judges of the earth;

12 both young men and maidens;

old men and children:

13 let them praise Yahweh’s name,

for his name alone is exalted.

His glory is above the earth and the heavens.

14 He has lifted up the horn of his people,

the praise of all his saints;

even of the children of Israel, a people near to him.

Praise Yah!

Proverbs 1

1 The proverbs of Solomon, the son of David, king of Israel:

2 to know wisdom and instruction;

to discern the words of understanding;

3 to receive instruction in wise dealing,

in righteousness, justice, and equity;

4 to give prudence to the simple,

knowledge and discretion to the young man:

5 that the wise man may hear, and increase in learning;

that the man of understanding may attain to sound counsel:

6 to understand a proverb, and parables,

the words and riddles of the wise.

7 The fear of Yahweh[*] is the beginning of knowledge;

but the foolish despise wisdom and instruction.

8 My son, listen to your father’s instruction,

and don’t forsake your mother’s teaching:

9 for they will be a garland to grace your head,

and chains around your neck.

10 My son, if sinners entice you,

don’t consent.

11 If they say, “Come with us.

Let’s lay in wait for blood.

Let’s lurk secretly for the innocent without cause.

12 Let’s swallow them up alive like Sheol,[*]

and whole, like those who go down into the pit.

13 We’ll find all valuable wealth.

We’ll fill our houses with plunder.

14 You shall cast your lot among us.

We’ll all have one purse.”

15 My son, don’t walk on the path with them.

Keep your foot from their path,

16 for their feet run to evil.

They hurry to shed blood.

17 For in vain is the net spread in the sight of any bird:

18 but these lay wait for their own blood.

They lurk secretly for their own lives.

19 So are the ways of everyone who is greedy for gain.

It takes away the life of its owners.

20 Wisdom calls aloud in the street.

She utters her voice in the public squares.

21 She calls at the head of noisy places.

At the entrance of the city gates, she utters her words:

22 “How long, you simple ones, will you love simplicity?

How long will mockers delight themselves in mockery,

and fools hate knowledge?

23 Turn at my reproof.

Behold,[*] I will pour out my spirit on you.

I will make known my words to you.

24 Because I have called, and you have refused;

I have stretched out my hand, and no one has paid attention;

25 but you have ignored all my counsel,

and wanted none of my reproof;

26 I also will laugh at your disaster.

I will mock when calamity overtakes you;

27 when calamity overtakes you like a storm,

when your disaster comes on like a whirlwind;

when distress and anguish come on you.

28 Then will they call on me, but I will not answer.

They will seek me diligently, but they will not find me;

29 because they hated knowledge,

and didn’t choose the fear of Yahweh.

30 They wanted none of my counsel.

They despised all my reproof.

31 Therefore they will eat of the fruit of their own way,

and be filled with their own schemes.

32 For the backsliding of the simple will kill them.

The careless ease of fools will destroy them.

33 But whoever listens to me will dwell securely,

and will be at ease, without fear of harm.”

“Yahweh” is God’s proper Name, sometimes rendered “LORD” (all caps) in other translations.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

“Behold”, from “הִנֵּה”, means look at, take notice, observe, see, or gaze at. It is often used as an interjection.

Proverbs 2

1 My son, if you will receive my words,

and store up my commandments within you;

2 So as to turn your ear to wisdom,

and apply your heart to understanding;

3 Yes, if you call out for discernment,

and lift up your voice for understanding;

4 If you seek her as silver,

and search for her as for hidden treasures:

5 then you will understand the fear of Yahweh,

and find the knowledge of God.[*]

6 For Yahweh gives wisdom.

Out of his mouth comes knowledge and understanding.

7 He lays up sound wisdom for the upright.

He is a shield to those who walk in integrity;

8 that he may guard the paths of justice,

and preserve the way of his saints.

9 Then you will understand righteousness and justice,

equity and every good path.

10 For wisdom will enter into your heart.

Knowledge will be pleasant to your soul.

11 Discretion will watch over you.

Understanding will keep you,

12 to deliver you from the way of evil,

from the men who speak perverse things;

13 who forsake the paths of uprightness,

to walk in the ways of darkness;

14 who rejoice to do evil,

and delight in the perverseness of evil;

15 who are crooked in their ways,

and wayward in their paths:

16 To deliver you from the strange woman,

even from the foreigner who flatters with her words;

17 who forsakes the friend of her youth,

and forgets the covenant of her God:

18 for her house leads down to death,

her paths to the departed spirits.

19 None who go to her return again,

neither do they attain to the paths of life:

20 that you may walk in the way of good men,

and keep the paths of the righteous.

21 For the upright will dwell in the land.

The perfect will remain in it.

22 But the wicked will be cut off from the land.

The treacherous will be rooted out of it.

The Hebrew word rendered “God” is “אֱלֹהִ֑ים” (Elohim).

Proverbs 3

1 My son, don’t forget my teaching;

but let your heart keep my commandments:

2 for length of days, and years of life,

and peace, will they add to you.

3 Don’t let kindness and truth forsake you.

Bind them around your neck.

Write them on the tablet of your heart.

4 So you will find favor,

and good understanding in the sight of God and man.

5 Trust in Yahweh with all your heart,

and don’t lean on your own understanding.

6 In all your ways acknowledge him,

and he will make your paths straight.

7 Don’t be wise in your own eyes.

Fear Yahweh, and depart from evil.

8 It will be health to your body,

and nourishment to your bones.

9 Honor Yahweh with your substance,

with the first fruits of all your increase:

10 so your barns will be filled with plenty,

and your vats will overflow with new wine.

11 My son, don’t despise Yahweh’s discipline,

neither be weary of his reproof:

12 for whom Yahweh loves, he reproves;

even as a father reproves the son in whom he delights.

13 Happy is the man who finds wisdom,

the man who gets understanding.

14 For her good profit is better than getting silver,

and her return is better than fine gold.

15 She is more precious than rubies.

None of the things you can desire are to be compared to her.

16 Length of days is in her right hand.

In her left hand are riches and honor.

17 Her ways are ways of pleasantness.

All her paths are peace.

18 She is a tree of life to those who lay hold of her.

Happy is everyone who retains her.

19 By wisdom Yahweh founded the earth.

By understanding, he established the heavens.

20 By his knowledge, the depths were broken up,

and the skies drop down the dew.

21 My son, let them not depart from your eyes.

Keep sound wisdom and discretion:

22 so they will be life to your soul,

and grace for your neck.

23 Then you shall walk in your way securely.

Your foot won’t stumble.

24 When you lie down, you will not be afraid.

Yes, you will lie down, and your sleep will be sweet.

25 Don’t be afraid of sudden fear,

neither of the desolation of the wicked, when it comes:

26 for Yahweh will be your confidence,

and will keep your foot from being taken.

27 Don’t withhold good from those to whom it is due,

when it is in the power of your hand to do it.

28 Don’t say to your neighbor, “Go, and come again;

tomorrow I will give it to you,”

when you have it by you.

29 Don’t devise evil against your neighbor,

since he dwells securely by you.

30 Don’t strive with a man without cause,

if he has done you no harm.

31 Don’t envy the man of violence.

Choose none of his ways.

32 For the perverse is an abomination to Yahweh,

but his friendship is with the upright.

33 Yahweh’s curse is in the house of the wicked,

but he blesses the habitation of the righteous.

34 Surely he mocks the mockers,

but he gives grace to the humble.

35 The wise will inherit glory,

but shame will be the promotion of fools.

Proverbs 4

1 Listen, sons, to a father’s instruction.

Pay attention and know understanding;

2 for I give you sound learning.

Don’t forsake my law.

3 For I was a son to my father,

tender and an only child in the sight of my mother.

4 He taught me, and said to me:

“Let your heart retain my words.

Keep my commandments, and live.

5 Get wisdom.

Get understanding.

Don’t forget, neither swerve from the words of my mouth.

6 Don’t forsake her, and she will preserve you.

Love her, and she will keep you.

7 Wisdom is supreme.

Get wisdom.

Yes, though it costs all your possessions, get understanding.

8 Esteem her, and she will exalt you.

She will bring you to honor, when you embrace her.

9 She will give to your head a garland of grace.

She will deliver a crown of splendor to you.”

10 Listen, my son, and receive my sayings.

The years of your life will be many.

11 I have taught you in the way of wisdom.

I have led you in straight paths.

12 When you go, your steps will not be hampered.

When you run, you will not stumble.

13 Take firm hold of instruction.

Don’t let her go.

Keep her, for she is your life.

14 Don’t enter into the path of the wicked.

Don’t walk in the way of evil men.

15 Avoid it, and don’t pass by it.

Turn from it, and pass on.

16 For they don’t sleep, unless they do evil.

Their sleep is taken away, unless they make someone fall.

17 For they eat the bread of wickedness,

and drink the wine of violence.

18 But the path of the righteous is like the dawning light,

that shines more and more until the perfect day.

19 The way of the wicked is like darkness.

They don’t know what they stumble over.

20 My son, attend to my words.

Turn your ear to my sayings.

21 Let them not depart from your eyes.

Keep them in the center of your heart.

22 For they are life to those who find them,

and health to their whole body.

23 Keep your heart with all diligence,

for out of it is the wellspring of life.

24 Put away from yourself a perverse mouth.

Put corrupt lips far from you.

25 Let your eyes look straight ahead.

Fix your gaze directly before you.

26 Make the path of your feet level.

Let all of your ways be established.

27 Don’t turn to the right hand nor to the left.

Remove your foot from evil.

Proverbs 5

1 My son, pay attention to my wisdom.

Turn your ear to my understanding:

2 that you may maintain discretion,

that your lips may preserve knowledge.

3 For the lips of an adulteress drip honey.

Her mouth is smoother than oil,

4 but in the end she is as bitter as wormwood,

and as sharp as a two-edged sword.

5 Her feet go down to death.

Her steps lead straight to Sheol.[*]

6 She gives no thought to the way of life.

Her ways are crooked, and she doesn’t know it.

7 Now therefore, my sons, listen to me.

Don’t depart from the words of my mouth.

8 Remove your way far from her.

Don’t come near the door of her house,

9 lest you give your honor to others,

and your years to the cruel one;

10 lest strangers feast on your wealth,

and your labors enrich another man’s house.

11 You will groan at your latter end,

when your flesh and your body are consumed,

12 and say, “How I have hated instruction,

and my heart despised reproof;

13 neither have I obeyed the voice of my teachers,

nor turned my ear to those who instructed me!

14 I have come to the brink of utter ruin,

among the gathered assembly.”

15 Drink water out of your own cistern,

running water out of your own well.

16 Should your springs overflow in the streets,

streams of water in the public squares?

17 Let them be for yourself alone,

not for strangers with you.

18 Let your spring be blessed.

Rejoice in the wife of your youth.

19 A loving doe and a graceful deer—

let her breasts satisfy you at all times.

Be captivated always with her love.

20 For why should you, my son, be captivated with an adulteress?

Why embrace the bosom of another?

21 For the ways of man are before Yahweh’s eyes.

He examines all his paths.

22 The evil deeds of the wicked ensnare him.

The cords of his sin hold him firmly.

23 He will die for lack of instruction.

In the greatness of his folly, he will go astray.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 6

1 My son, if you have become collateral for your neighbor,

if you have struck your hands in pledge for a stranger;

2 You are trapped by the words of your mouth.

You are ensnared with the words of your mouth.

3 Do this now, my son, and deliver yourself,

since you have come into the hand of your neighbor.

Go, humble yourself.

Press your plea with your neighbor.

4 Give no sleep to your eyes,

nor slumber to your eyelids.

5 Free yourself, like a gazelle from the hand of the hunter,

like a bird from the snare of the fowler.

6 Go to the ant, you sluggard.

Consider her ways, and be wise;

7 which having no chief, overseer, or ruler,

8 provides her bread in the summer,

and gathers her food in the harvest.

9 How long will you sleep, sluggard?

When will you arise out of your sleep?

10 A little sleep, a little slumber,

a little folding of the hands to sleep:

11 so your poverty will come as a robber,

and your scarcity as an armed man.

12 A worthless person, a man of iniquity,

is he who walks with a perverse mouth;

13 who winks with his eyes, who signals with his feet,

who motions with his fingers;

14 in whose heart is perverseness,

who devises evil continually,

who always sows discord.

15 Therefore his calamity will come suddenly.

He will be broken suddenly, and that without remedy.

16 There are six things which Yahweh hates;

yes, seven which are an abomination to him:

17 haughty eyes, a lying tongue,

hands that shed innocent blood;

18 a heart that devises wicked schemes,

feet that are swift in running to mischief,

19 a false witness who utters lies,

and he who sows discord among brothers.

20 My son, keep your father’s commandment,

and don’t forsake your mother’s teaching.

21 Bind them continually on your heart.

Tie them around your neck.

22 When you walk, it will lead you.

When you sleep, it will watch over you.

When you awake, it will talk with you.

23 For the commandment is a lamp,

and the law is light.

Reproofs of instruction are the way of life,

24 to keep you from the immoral woman,

from the flattery of the wayward wife’s tongue.

25 Don’t lust after her beauty in your heart,

neither let her captivate you with her eyelids.

26 For a prostitute reduces you to a piece of bread.

The adulteress hunts for your precious life.

27 Can a man scoop fire into his lap,

and his clothes not be burned?

28 Or can one walk on hot coals,

and his feet not be scorched?

29 So is he who goes in to his neighbor’s wife.

Whoever touches her will not be unpunished.

30 Men don’t despise a thief,

if he steals to satisfy himself when he is hungry:

31 but if he is found, he shall restore seven times.

He shall give all the wealth of his house.

32 He who commits adultery with a woman is void of understanding.

He who does it destroys his own soul.

33 He will get wounds and dishonor.

His reproach will not be wiped away.

34 For jealousy arouses the fury of the husband.

He won’t spare in the day of vengeance.

35 He won’t regard any ransom,

neither will he rest content, though you give many gifts.

Proverbs 7

1 My son, keep my words.

Lay up my commandments within you.

2 Keep my commandments and live!

Guard my teaching as the apple of your eye.

3 Bind them on your fingers.

Write them on the tablet of your heart.

4 Tell wisdom, “You are my sister.”

Call understanding your relative,

5 that they may keep you from the strange woman,

from the foreigner who flatters with her words.

6 For at the window of my house,

I looked out through my lattice.

7 I saw among the simple ones.

I discerned among the youths a young man void of understanding,

8 passing through the street near her corner,

he went the way to her house,

9 in the twilight, in the evening of the day,

in the middle of the night and in the darkness.

10 Behold, there a woman met him with the attire of a prostitute,

and with crafty intent.

11 She is loud and defiant.

Her feet don’t stay in her house.

12 Now she is in the streets, now in the squares,

and lurking at every corner.

13 So she caught him, and kissed him.

With an impudent face she said to him:

14 “Sacrifices of peace offerings are with me.

Today I have paid my vows.

15 Therefore I came out to meet you,

to diligently seek your face,

and I have found you.

16 I have spread my couch with carpets of tapestry,

with striped cloths of the yarn of Egypt.

17 I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

18 Come, let’s take our fill of loving until the morning.

Let’s solace ourselves with loving.

19 For my husband isn’t at home.

He has gone on a long journey.

20 He has taken a bag of money with him.

He will come home at the full moon.”

21 With persuasive words, she led him astray.

With the flattering of her lips, she seduced him.

22 He followed her immediately,

as an ox goes to the slaughter,

as a fool stepping into a noose.

23 Until an arrow strikes through his liver,

as a bird hurries to the snare,

and doesn’t know that it will cost his life.

24 Now therefore, sons, listen to me.

Pay attention to the words of my mouth.

25 Don’t let your heart turn to her ways.

Don’t go astray in her paths,

26 for she has thrown down many wounded.

Yes, all her slain are a mighty army.

27 Her house is the way to Sheol,[*]

going down to the rooms of death.

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 8

1 Doesn’t wisdom cry out?

Doesn’t understanding raise her voice?

2 On the top of high places by the way,

where the paths meet, she stands.

3 Beside the gates, at the entry of the city,

at the entry doors, she cries aloud:

4 “To you men, I call!

I send my voice to the sons of mankind.

5 You simple, understand prudence.

You fools, be of an understanding heart.

6 Hear, for I will speak excellent things.

The opening of my lips is for right things.

7 For my mouth speaks truth.

Wickedness is an abomination to my lips.

8 All the words of my mouth are in righteousness.

There is nothing crooked or perverse in them.

9 They are all plain to him who understands,

right to those who find knowledge.

10 Receive my instruction rather than silver;

knowledge rather than choice gold.

11 For wisdom is better than rubies.

All the things that may be desired can’t be compared to it.

12 “I, wisdom, have made prudence my dwelling.

Find out knowledge and discretion.

13 The fear of Yahweh is to hate evil.

I hate pride, arrogance, the evil way, and the perverse mouth.

14 Counsel and sound knowledge are mine.

I have understanding and power.

15 By me kings reign,

and princes decree justice.

16 By me princes rule;

nobles, and all the righteous rulers of the earth.

17 I love those who love me.

Those who seek me diligently will find me.

18 With me are riches, honor,

enduring wealth, and prosperity.

19 My fruit is better than gold, yes, than fine gold;

my yield than choice silver.

20 I walk in the way of righteousness,

in the middle of the paths of justice;

21 That I may give wealth to those who love me.

I fill their treasuries.

22 “Yahweh possessed me in the beginning of his work,

before his deeds of old.

23 I was set up from everlasting, from the beginning,

before the earth existed.

24 When there were no depths, I was born,

when there were no springs abounding with water.

25 Before the mountains were settled in place,

before the hills, I was born;

26 while as yet he had not made the earth, nor the fields,

nor the beginning of the dust of the world.

27 When he established the heavens, I was there;

when he set a circle on the surface of the deep,

28 when he established the clouds above,

when the springs of the deep became strong,

29 when he gave to the sea its boundary,

that the waters should not violate his commandment,

when he marked out the foundations of the earth;

30 then I was the craftsman by his side.

I was a delight day by day,

always rejoicing before him,

31 Rejoicing in his whole world.

My delight was with the sons of men.

32 “Now therefore, my sons, listen to me,

for blessed are those who keep my ways.

33 Hear instruction, and be wise.

Don’t refuse it.

34 Blessed is the man who hears me,

watching daily at my gates,

waiting at my door posts.

35 For whoever finds me, finds life,

and will obtain favor from Yahweh.

36 But he who sins against me wrongs his own soul.

All those who hate me love death.”

Proverbs 9

1 Wisdom has built her house.

She has carved out her seven pillars.

2 She has prepared her meat.

She has mixed her wine.

She has also set her table.

3 She has sent out her maidens.

She cries from the highest places of the city:

4 “Whoever is simple, let him turn in here!”

As for him who is void of understanding, she says to him,

5 “Come, eat some of my bread,

Drink some of the wine which I have mixed!

6 Leave your simple ways, and live.

Walk in the way of understanding.”

7 He who corrects a mocker invites insult.

He who reproves a wicked man invites abuse.

8 Don’t reprove a scoffer, lest he hate you.

Reprove a wise man, and he will love you.

9 Instruct a wise man, and he will be still wiser.

Teach a righteous man, and he will increase in learning.

10 The fear of Yahweh is the beginning of wisdom.

The knowledge of the Holy One is understanding.

11 For by me your days will be multiplied.

The years of your life will be increased.

12 If you are wise, you are wise for yourself.

If you mock, you alone will bear it.

13 The foolish woman is loud,

undisciplined, and knows nothing.

14 She sits at the door of her house,

on a seat in the high places of the city,

15 To call to those who pass by,

who go straight on their ways,

16 “Whoever is simple, let him turn in here.”

as for him who is void of understanding, she says to him,

17 “Stolen water is sweet.

Food eaten in secret is pleasant.”

18 But he doesn’t know that the departed spirits are there,

that her guests are in the depths of Sheol.[*]

Sheol is the place of the dead.

Proverbs 10

1 The proverbs of Solomon.

A wise son makes a glad father;

but a foolish son brings grief to his mother.

2 Treasures of wickedness profit nothing,

but righteousness delivers from death.

3 Yahweh will not allow the soul of the righteous to go hungry,

but he thrusts away the desire of the wicked.

4 He becomes poor who works with a lazy hand,

but the hand of the diligent brings wealth.

5 He who gathers in summer is a wise son,

but he who sleeps during the harvest is a son who causes shame.

6 Blessings are on the head of the righteous,

but violence covers the mouth of the wicked.

7 The memory of the righteous is blessed,

but the name of the wicked will rot.

8 The wise in heart accept commandments,

but a chattering fool will fall.

9 He who walks blamelessly walks surely,

but he who perverts his ways will be found out.

10 One winking with the eye causes sorrow,

but a chattering fool will fall.

11 The mouth of the righteous is a spring of life,

but violence covers the mouth of the wicked.

12 Hatred stirs up strife,

but love covers all wrongs.

13 Wisdom is found on the lips of him who has discernment,

but a rod is for the back of him who is void of understanding.

14 Wise men lay up knowledge,

but the mouth of the foolish is near ruin.

15 The rich man’s wealth is his strong city.

The destruction of the poor is their poverty.

16 The labor of the righteous leads to life.

The increase of the wicked leads to sin.

17 He is in the way of life who heeds correction,

but he who forsakes reproof leads others astray.

18 He who hides hatred has lying lips.

He who utters a slander is a fool.

19 In the multitude of words there is no lack of disobedience,

but he who restrains his lips does wisely.

20 The tongue of the righteous is like choice silver.

The heart of the wicked is of little worth.

21 The lips of the righteous feed many,

but the foolish die for lack of understanding.

22 Yahweh’s blessing brings wealth,

and he adds no trouble to it.

23 It is a fool’s pleasure to do wickedness,

but wisdom is a man of understanding’s pleasure.

24 What the wicked fear, will overtake them,

but the desire of the righteous will be granted.

25 When the whirlwind passes, the wicked is no more;

but the righteous stand firm forever.

26 As vinegar to the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes,

so is the sluggard to those who send him.

27 The fear of Yahweh prolongs days,

but the years of the wicked shall be shortened.

28 The prospect of the righteous is joy,

but the hope of the wicked will perish.

29 The way of Yahweh is a stronghold to the upright,

but it is a destruction to the workers of iniquity.

30 The righteous will never be removed,

but the wicked will not dwell in the land.

31 The mouth of the righteous produces wisdom,

but the perverse tongue will be cut off.

32 The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable,

but the mouth of the wicked is perverse.

Proverbs 11

1 A false balance is an abomination to Yahweh,

but accurate weights are his delight.

2 When pride comes, then comes shame,

but with humility comes wisdom.

3 The integrity of the upright shall guide them,

but the perverseness of the treacherous shall destroy them.

4 Riches don’t profit in the day of wrath,

but righteousness delivers from death.

5 The righteousness of the blameless will direct his way,

but the wicked shall fall by his own wickedness.

6 The righteousness of the upright shall deliver them,

but the unfaithful will be trapped by evil desires.

7 When a wicked man dies, hope perishes,

and expectation of power comes to nothing.

8 A righteous person is delivered out of trouble,

and the wicked takes his place.

9 With his mouth the godless man destroys his neighbor,

but the righteous will be delivered through knowledge.

10 When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices.

When the wicked perish, there is shouting.

11 By the blessing of the upright, the city is exalted,

but it is overthrown by the mouth of the wicked.

12 One who despises his neighbor is void of wisdom,

but a man of understanding holds his peace.

13 One who brings gossip betrays a confidence,

but one who is of a trustworthy spirit is one who keeps a secret.

14 Where there is no wise guidance, the nation falls,

but in the multitude of counselors there is victory.

15 He who is collateral for a stranger will suffer for it,

but he who refuses pledges of collateral is secure.

16 A gracious woman obtains honor,

but violent men obtain riches.

17 The merciful man does good to his own soul,

but he who is cruel troubles his own flesh.

18 Wicked people earn deceitful wages,

but one who sows righteousness reaps a sure reward.

19 He who is truly righteous gets life.

He who pursues evil gets death.

20 Those who are perverse in heart are an abomination to Yahweh,

but those whose ways are blameless are his delight.

21 Most certainly, the evil man will not be unpunished,

but the offspring[*] of the righteous will be delivered.

22 Like a gold ring in a pig’s snout,

is a beautiful woman who lacks discretion.

23 The desire of the righteous is only good.

The expectation of the wicked is wrath.

24 There is one who scatters, and increases yet more.

There is one who withholds more than is appropriate, but gains poverty.

25 The liberal soul shall be made fat.

He who waters shall be watered also himself.

26 People curse someone who withholds grain,

but blessing will be on the head of him who sells it.

27 He who diligently seeks good seeks favor,

but he who searches after evil, it shall come to him.

28 He who trusts in his riches will fall,

but the righteous shall flourish as the green leaf.

29 He who troubles his own house shall inherit the wind.

The foolish shall be servant to the wise of heart.

30 The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life.

He who is wise wins souls.

31 Behold, the righteous shall be repaid in the earth;

how much more the wicked and the sinner!

or, seed